<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0008" label="8"><title>8. The Depths of Regret</title><sect1 id="ch0008s0011"><title>8. The Depths of Regret</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_8</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0008">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Regret, Imposter syndrome</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0008s0001"><title>8. The Depths of Regret</title><sidebar id="ch0008s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explain how regret negatively impacts the bullied nurse who decides not to report their workplace experience with incivility targeted at them.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the implications of regret for onlookers of nurse bullying—further violence or nurse suicide.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Consider how a reset can positively impact a regret.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0002" role="Heading"><title>Regret Defined</title><para role="Para">Regret is defined by the Merriam-Webster Dictionary as both a noun and verb. Regret defined as a verb is to be very sorry for mistakes made, to experience a regret, to mourn the death or loss of someone or something, and to miss very much. The word regret used as a noun recognizes a distressing emotion such as a sorrow or a deep sorrow that was aroused by life circumstances that were beyond the affected person’s power or control to repair (Merriam-Webster Dictionary Online, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib09">2024</link></emphasis>). Regret can bring to affected persons, loneliness, frustration, and sadness.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0003" role="Heading"><title>The Hollow</title><para role="Para">For nurses who experience The Hollow in the workplace, the perception that their being mobbed by co-workers in a meeting, a co-worker is attempting to belittle their skills or perpetuate lies, is not serious enough to report to managers, directors, or Human Resources Department. The nurses’ concern may be that there is no proof of bullying. A later report of these incidences in the setting of the bully or bullies presenting with a significant lie leading to an attack on character of the affected nurse is then considered a new investigation of a first act of uncivil conduct. Hence, though difficult, it is important that someone is made aware of these acts of incivility by the affected nurse (or someone who has witnessed the incident such as a co-worker), the first time these behaviors present as an issue.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0004" role="Heading"><title>The Targets</title><para role="Para">Bullies target nurses who tend to be focused on their jobs, have potential for promotion, introduce cultural innovation or change, are culturally (e.g., religion, linguistics, etc.) and racially different, show no interest in joining their clicks, and present as free thinkers. Bullies tend to be stagnant in their approach to change and prefer to maintain the status quo. Typically, underperformer bullies target those who they perceive may threaten their (the bully’s) personal or professional success(es) by exposing who they really are and the knowledge they have or do not have. While the target may not understand this and only sees the meanness, lies, and covert actions of the bully or bullies at work, many bullies are very insecure people who hide behind a pompous personality façade.</para><para role="Para">Targets tend to suffer from imposter syndrome. <emphasis role="bold">Imposter syndrome</emphasis> occurs when, persons, despite their intellectual accomplishments (e.g., education level attainment, career success, etc.) and personal and professional successes, feel undeserving and that their successes may have occurred for other reasons outside of their own work and determination. Nursing is a profession that involves emotional and physical connectiveness to patients (families and significant others) that are known for very short or long periods of time by the nurse. Hence, because nurses are providing healthcare to others, a level of vulnerability occurs, whether the nurse positively or negatively connects with patients in their care. For nurses, their care of patients and their loved ones on a routine basis can contribute to the development of burnout, compassion satisfaction, or compassion fatigue (Cetrano et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib04">2017</link></emphasis>; Clark et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">The vulnerability of the nurse experiencing The Hollow, because of being targeted by a bully or bullies, can cause nurses to consider leaving the profession of nursing and or resigning from their job. Needless to say, becoming the target of another when striving to maintain health and well-being in the workplace is fatiguing. However, consequentially, bullying, reframed, is a workplace occurrence that is a nuisance. And that which is a nuisance is an annoyance that may or may not cause a person harm. It is the decision to approach bullying as illogical foolishness that is a waste of time and emotional and physical energy that can help affected persons survive incidences of bullying.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0005" role="Heading"><title>The Broken Bully</title><para role="Para">Persons who bully are usually psychologically vulnerable themselves. Negative childhood events or early adulthood trauma may lead to persons who bully being angry, saddened, and lacking trust. Their psychological vulnerability becomes a defense mechanism that causes them to strike out at others not to protect themselves but to relive their own fantasies of vengeance on those that hurt them in the past. Bullies’ trauma is often cyclic and has nothing to do with their current situation. It is the bully’s anger, sadness, and lack of trust that causes them to distort seemingly harmless interactions and perceive them as threat. An example of a scenario demonstrating the overreaction of the bully is provided below.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0006" role="Heading"><title>Scenario 1: Bully Overreaction</title><para role="Para">Richard hated to be questioned about any decision he made. He had been a nurse manager for 8 years and felt that he had more than enough experience to manage the two units that he oversaw for the last 2 years. Michael, a nurse manager for 23 years of four units noticed that Richard had a significant turnover of nursing staff on his two units occurring over the last 3 months. Michael offered to help Richard investigate why his nursing staff was leaving his units. Richard shared, “Michael, I am here to support and mentor you whenever you need me. I was a young manager once myself.”</para><para role="Para">Richard was angry and offended that Michael would have the audacity to question his ability to manage his own unit. Thereafter, Richard would gossip and spread negative lies about Michael without reason. Richard’s own insecurities about being perceived as an ineffective manager drove him to undermine a colleague who had merely offered to help him investigate the cause of his nursing staff’s turnover intentions.</para><para role="Para">Insecurities in the person or persons who bully other people lead to their own demise because they ensnare themselves in the imaginary world they create in order to justify their deception. For persons experiencing The Hollow, understanding that the person who bullies is actually weak and vulnerable themselves helps to bring awareness to the frivolousness of the actions of others that have to basis in the truth. The bully shares their own manufactured distortions about how they want others to perceive you.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0007" role="Heading"><title>The Emotional Voice</title><para role="Para">The emotional voice (EV) is either a voice of reason and sound rationale or of confusion and intentionally remiss of truth versus evil. Be it the voice of a co-worker, boss, supervisor, president, chief officer, manager, a family member, close friend, spouse, or significant other, the speech with emotional expressions and vocalizations (Pell et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib10">2022</link></emphasis>) brings context to the communication being shared between people. For example, if a person is raising the tone of their voice and crying uncontrollably, they may be perceived as being weak and vulnerable by onlookers. The face of the crying person is sad and remorseful and can appear indecisive.</para><para role="Para">Within the context of bullying and persons experiencing The Hollow, the person who bullies will use their observation of EV to determine how, when, and what words and situations they can use to manipulate the person or persons they are targeting. According to Giordano et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib07">2021</link></emphasis>), affective science theories have examined continuous dimensional attributes such as negative vocal emotions and intense vocalizations and perceptions of emotional stimuli such as a voice that sounds angry. Perceptions of emotions are not always based on reality. Emotional perceptions observed or heard by different persons may produce varied thoughts of personal threat—harm to self or harm to others.</para><para role="Para">An example of the perception of the emotional voice as angry has been linked to different people groups. For example, some ethnic groups have been perceived to be louder or more emotional than others (Cowen et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib06">2019</link></emphasis>). The angry Black woman or the loud Italian. While these perceptions are not 100% accurate, they breed racism and misunderstanding. While, acoustically, there are some variations among different people from varied cultural backgrounds, this does not account for individual personalities and life experiences.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0008" role="Heading"><title>Regret in the Workplace: Why Is This Unhealthy Behavior Tolerated Anyway</title><para role="Para">Unhealthy workplaces are unfortunately a common occurrence. A workplace survey taken by the American Psychological Association entitled <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib03">2024</link></emphasis><emphasis>Work in America Survey</emphasis>, noted that 59% of employees think that their employers believe their workplace to be healthier than it actually is in reality. The APA survey found that 39% of employees believe that if they shared with their employer that they were experiencing a mental health condition, this would not have a positive impact on their career.</para><para role="Para">Resignations can occur in the workplace for a variety of reasons including that of employee relocation, corporate restructuring, job instability, promotion to a higher-level position, or general unhappiness with the type of work the employee is doing. Sull et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib12">2022</link></emphasis>) in an article written within the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) Sloan Management Review implemented research that investigated why people leave their jobs and analyzed over 170 organizational cultural issues that can impact employee attrition. Sull et al.’s (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib12">2022</link></emphasis>) research occurred during the months of April through September 2021, during the global pandemic of the coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19). Culture 500 companies were included in the study. Culture 500 companies are companies that excel in these nine areas: performance, innovation, respect, integrity, customer orientation, agility, diversity, and collaboration (Sull &amp; Sull, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib11">2020</link></emphasis>). The five top predictors of attrition identified were:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Poor response to COVID-19:</emphasis> 1.8</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Failure to recognize employee performance</emphasis>: 2.9</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">High levels of innovation</emphasis>: 3.2</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Job insecurity and reorganization</emphasis>: 3.5</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Toxic corporate culture</emphasis>: 10.4</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para role="Para">Interestingly, despite having otherwise healthy cultures, these top-performing Culture 500 companies shared in common the existence of toxic corporate cultures. Hence, toxic work environments can exist anywhere and are by no means a reflection of company failure. Instead, companies can take the approach of maintaining or establishing healthy work environments, by acknowledging the need for their existence and then actively and unashamedly, pursuing change.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0009" role="Heading"><title>Navigating Workplace Change in Real Time</title><para role="Para">Work cultures are complex and not easily changed. On average, it can take 3–5 years to change a workplace culture. Within the profession of nursing, healthy workplace cultures are imperative for the maintenance of patient safety in healthcare environments. Classically, the view that a <emphasis>just culture</emphasis> can contribute to increased patient safety in healthcare promotes the ideology of systems thinking. In just <emphasis>cultures</emphasis>, emphasis is placed on the systems’ failures to address dysfunction and promote healthy and sustained organizational change, rather than the errors of individuals working within the system (Alashram et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib01">2024</link></emphasis>). While the latter is true and applicable to nurse bullying if the system has intentionally ignored malfunctioning unit cultures for years that have bullying problems, the responsibility must also be placed on the bullies themselves as well.</para><para role="Para">The allowance of The Hollow to remain active on known clinical units and in departments within healthcare organizations is often a failure of systems to openly address incivility and take a stance for zero tolerance of workplace bullying. Imboden (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib08">2024</link></emphasis>) explored the value and health benefits of people having a sense of belonging in organizations. Belonging is an essential human need in order to function in social situations. Absence of connectivity to others leads to isolation, impacts well-being and trust, and affects employees’ health (Imboden, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib08">2024</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">In order to change workplace cultures, systems have to change. In order for systems to change, administration has to acknowledge problems that exist within their organization. In order for problems to be discovered, directors and managers have to ask for and receive openly the feedback from their direct patient care staff. For nurses, united, they must reach out for support to one another and to their American Nurses Association so that they have a clear understanding of the Code of Ethics for Nurses (American Nurses Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0010bib02">n.d.</link></emphasis>) and how these codes apply to their daily nursing practice.</para><para role="Para">Nurses must realize that they have the unique gift as healthcare professionals working directly with patients and spending the greatest amount of direct clinical practice hours with patients daily and are best positioned to promote organizational change. No longer can bedside nurse leaders say, “I am just the nurse.” Know that your critical thinking and clinical judgment saves the lives of human beings that you interface with as you practice each day you enter the workplace. You have more power than you think. Discover your power, own it, share it, and do not let others attempt to take what is yours on their terms.</para><sidebar id="ch0008s0009ad02"><title>Activity</title><bridgehead>Change</bridgehead><bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each scenario and identify if change is needed in the workplace. Write down the steps you would take to make this change happen.</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #1 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A new night nurse is abrupt and curses at her co-workers when they are not “immediately” ready to provide handoff report to so she can “go home.”</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #2 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A manager announces that they have selected two nurses to attend a research conference to represent the hospital.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #3 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A director announces that nurses on a 40-bed medical-surgical unit will be penalized via a new point system if they do not take their required 30-min break each time they work. A cumulation of a total of five points will lead to a negative write up related to the affected nurses poor time management. The unit is currently hiring for six full-time registered nurse positions.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #4 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse observes one of her nurse colleagues being screamed at by a fellow co-worker. The altercation occurs outside of a patient’s hospital room.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #5 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A patient throws a picture of water on a Latino nurse. The patient yells, “Go back to your country and take care of people that look like you, not me!”</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #6 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse manager informs an African American nurse that she “may not fit in” on the new hospital campus that she has transferred to and recommends she returns to her former “inner city hospital.”</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #7 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse is walking into the hospital garage when he is approached by three other nurses. The nurses begin to push and shove the nurse. One of the three nurses proceeds to spit in the nurse’s face. You are sitting in your car preparing to leave work when you observe this situation.</para><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Consider this:</emphasis></para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is the nurse in a safe situation?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is the nurse able to safely leave the situation.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #8 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse receives an award for providing life-saving care to a fellow hospital employee in the parking lot.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #9 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Two nurses have been known bullies on a unit for the past 8 years. A newly hired nurse observes these nurses’ bullying behaviors and immediately reports them to the manager and Human Resources. The new nurse is now being bullied each time she enters the workplace. The nurse has become depressed and withdrawn.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #10 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse confides in you that as a result of being bullied for 9 months, she has recently contemplated suicide.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sidebar><sidebar id="ch0008s0009ad03"><title>A Contemplation Activity</title><bridgehead>Regret</bridgehead><bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each statement or question and discuss how regret likely impacted the outcome.</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>A nurse informs their nurse manager that they are resigning from their career of 20 years sharing, “I just cannot take this toxic environment anymore.” The nurse is 2 months away from retirement.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>A manager is hospitalized after a severe emotional break following an argument with her director. The manager’s director had been sarcastic and belittling to him for the last 4 years.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Lonely, a nurse contemplates self-harm after an incident of bullying with a night shift nurse. A co-worker observes the nurse taking pills out of her locker and quietly placing them in a small plastic bag. The co-worker stops the nurse and asks if everything is o.k.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>A nursing professor presenting a research project to a group of colleagues is questioned harshly post presentation as to the credibility of the research findings. The professor leaves the room in silence and returns to their office, closes the door, and cries.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>A nurse, after being bullied on their clinical unit for 9 months, obtains the new position of unit educator. Very much aware of the bullying problem on the unit, the nurse initiates a series of lectures and activities on the unit that address bullying and the consequences for retaliation.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0008s0010" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0008s0010bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib01">Alashram, H. M., Hamouda, G. M., &amp; Yaseen, M. (2024). Nurses’ perception toward the relationship between just culture and patient safety activities: A literature review. Journal of Health, Medicine &amp; Nursing, 10(2), 18–33. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.47604/jhmn.2499"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.47604/jhmn.2499</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.47604/jhmn.2499">https://doi.org/10.47604/jhmn.2499</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib02">American Nurses Association. (n.d.). View the Code of Ethics for nurses. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nursingworld.org/practice-policy/nursing-excellence/ethics/code-of-ethics-for-nurses/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nursingworld.org/practice-policy/nursing-excellence/ethics/code-of-ethics-for-nurses/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib03">American Psychological Association. (2024). 2024 Work in America Survey: Psychological safety in the changing workplace. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.apa.org/pubs/reports/work-in-america/2024/2024-work-in-america-report.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.apa.org/pubs/reports/work-in-america/2024/2024-work-in-america-report.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib04">Cetrano, G., Tedeschi, F., Rabbi, L., Gosetti, G., Lora, A., Lamonaca, D., Manthorpe, J., &amp; Amaddeo, F. (2017). How are compassion fatigue, burnout, and compassion satisfaction affected by quality of working life? Findings from a survey of mental health staff in Italy. BMC Health Services Research, 17(1), 755. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-017-2726-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-017-2726-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-017-2726-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-017-2726-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29162095">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5696765">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib05">Clark, P., Holden, C., Russell, M., &amp; Downs, H. (2022). The impostor phenomenon in mental health professionals: Relationships among compassion fatigue, burnout, and compassion satisfaction. Contemporary Family Therapy, 44(2), 185–197. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-021-09580-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-021-09580-y</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-021-09580-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-021-09580-y</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33948046">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib06">Cowen, A. S., Laukka, P., Elfenbein, H. A., Liu, R., &amp; Keltner, D. (2019). The primacy of categories in the recognition of 12 emotions in speech prosody across two cultures. Nature Human Behavior, 3(4), 369–382. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0533-6">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0533-6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0533-6">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-019-0533-6</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib07">Giordano, B. L., Whiting, C., Kriegeskorte, N., Kotz, S. A., Gross, J., &amp; Belin, P. (2021). The representational dynamics of perceived voice emotions evolve from categories to dimensions. Nature Human Behavior, 5(9), 1203–1213. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01073-0">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01073-0</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01073-0">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01073-0</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib08">Imboden, M. T. (2024). Belonging: An essential human and organizational need. American Journal of Health Promotion, 38(6), 883–897. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/08901171241255204"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/08901171241255204</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/08901171241255204a">https://doi.org/10.1177/08901171241255204a</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=39113175">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib09">Merriam-Webster Dictionary. (2024). Regret. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/regret"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/regret</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib10">Pell, M. D., Sethi, S., Rigoulot, S., Rothermich, K., Liu, P., &amp; Jiang, X. (2022). Emotional voices modulate perception and predictions about an upcoming face. Cortex, 149, 148–164. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2021.12.017">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2021.12.017</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2021.12.017">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cortex.2021.12.017</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35231722">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib11">Sull, D., &amp; Sull, C. (2020, October 13). Cultural excellence. MIT Sloan Management Review. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://sloanreview.mit.edu/projects/culture-500-introducing-the-2020-culture-champions/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://sloanreview.mit.edu/projects/culture-500-introducing-the-2020-culture-champions/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0008s0010bib12">Sull, D., Sull, C., &amp; Zweig, B. (2022, January 11). Toxic culture is driving the greatest resignation. MIT Sloan Management Review. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://sloanreview.mit.edu/article/toxic-culture-is-driving-the-great-resignation/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://sloanreview.mit.edu/article/toxic-culture-is-driving-the-great-resignation/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
