<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0002" label="2"><title>2. Origins of The Hollow</title><sect1 id="ch0002s0007"><title>2. Origins of The Hollow</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_2">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_2</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0002">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Bullying, The Hollow, Nursing theory, Nursing profession</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0002s0001"><title>2. Origins of The Hollow</title><sidebar id="ch0002s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explain The Hollow Theory and the physical and emotional manifestations within nurses affected by workplace bullying.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Describe the potential for physiological and psychological decline of the nurse affected by sustained bullying in the workplace.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Decipher ways in which nurses affected by The Hollow can successfully recover with support.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0002" role="Heading"><title>Introduction</title><sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0001" role="Heading"><title>Bullying Characteristics</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Bullying</emphasis> is the action(s) taken by a person or group of people toward another person(s) with the intent of producing physical or emotional harm. In the study of different ways that nurses bully one another, the literature identifies behaviors such as cyberbullying (Park &amp; Choi, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib04">2019</link></emphasis>), with bullying occurring on Internet platforms. Additionally, nurse-to-nurse bullying can consist of mobbing (groups of individuals who are jealous of another person’s skill level in the workplace bully and attempt to intimidate the person; Valclavikova &amp; Kozakova, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib08">2022</link></emphasis>), rudeness, lying, gossip, singling out (not being invited to work events fellow employees are all participating within), attempting to attack one’s character, name-calling, sabotaging of another’s work, and joy-stealing (Heinrich, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib03">2007</link></emphasis>).</para><sect3 id="ch0002s0002s0001s01" role="Heading"><title>Rude Boy, Rude Girl</title><para role="Para">In the West Indian culture, a “rude boy or rude girl” was someone within the subculture that was involved in gangster activities or spent time on street corners attempting to make a living, as they were unable to secure work. The rude boy and rude girl were usually unemployed and had difficulty surviving because of their financial and social isolation. Historically, the terms rude boy and rude girl originated in shanty towns within the West Indies. Shanty towns are lower-income areas on the island (The Guardian, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib06">2014</link></emphasis>; Underground, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib07">2021</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">Changes in cultures arise in difficult life situations. In organizations, organizational cultures can shift with changes in employees that bring either negative or positive behaviors to the workplace based upon their own life experiences. Rude boys and rude girls were in fact poor persons who had difficulty finding employment during the 1960s. However, with pride intact, they dressed nicely and moved in the music scene but yet maintained a gangster element.</para><para role="Para">With regard to “The Hollow,” the bully or bullies inflate their own value due to their own insecurities that they make a distinct point of hiding from others. Instead, the bully or bullies project their own frustrations with themselves and their life situations on others. Like the rude boy or rude girl, the bully emerges from complicated life circumstances but makes the wrong decisions in how they view and interact with others who they interact with in “their world” (the world of the bully).</para></sect3></sect2><sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0002" role="Heading"><title>Bullying Target Types</title><para role="Para">There are approximately four bullying target types. The bullying target types include <emphasis>downward, horizontal, upward, and mixed</emphasis>. Downward bullying involves persons in organizational leadership positions whereby they directly supervise and have employees to whom they provide oversight of their work. Bullying that occurs horizontally is lateral, and typically involves coworkers or peers. Upward bullying within the workplace involves subordinates, while mixed bullying usually consists of a workplace clique comprised of subordinates and supervisors. With mixed bullying, the bully or bullies approach their targets directionally, using any of the targeting types of bullying (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0003" role="Heading"><title>Personal Losses Endured by Bullied Persons</title><para role="Para">The losses that persons affected by bully endure can be devastating to their mental and physical health. All areas of their lives are affected. Psychologically, persons may experience posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), loss of confidence, nightmares, anxiety, suicidal ideation, insomnia, and depression. Persons may experience a decline in their physical health and have several different physiological problems such as gastrointestinal issues, palpitations, or severe headaches. Additionally, persons with physical health changes may experience burnout and disability with worsening illnesses associated with stress such as an elevated blood pressure or the overuse of drugs or alcohol to self-medicate their trauma (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link></emphasis>; Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">Socially, persons affected by bullying may lose their professional networks as bullies lie and attempt to attack their character. Friendships are impacted and some persons may experience a loss in their reputation. The person affected by bullying may decide to leave their job, and income or promotion may be given up in order to maintain physical and mental health (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link></emphasis>; Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0003" role="Heading"><title>What Is The Hollow Theory?</title><para role="Para">The <emphasis role="bold">Hollow Theory</emphasis> is the manifestation of emotional and physical symptomatology related to stress that nurses encounter in workplace settings whereby bullying and incivility are permitted to flourish unabated. Feelings associated with The Hollow include sadness, embittered, feeling hurt, and misunderstood by others. Additionally, affected persons perseverate on incidences of negative behaviors experienced by them from the perpetrator of the act(s) of bullying. Sustained, persons experiencing The Hollow can become physically and mentally ill. Lack of energy, focus, and enthusiasm emerge as part of the perseveration component of The Hollow, whereby affected persons play and replay incidences of bullying. For nurses, and other affected persons, the replaying of incidences of bullying in their minds makes them feel vulnerable, frustrated, and anxious. Accompanied by intermittent tearfulness, productivity in the workplace can ultimately be impacted (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link></emphasis>; Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib02">2020</link></emphasis>).</para><sidebar id="ch0002s0003ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Nursing Profession Nursing is a profession whereby the ability to think analytically, think critically, and exercise clinical judgment in the care of acute and chronically ill patients is a daily expectation. For nurses who experience The Hollow, their ability to concentrate can be affected. Hence, patient safety and the quality in the delivery of nursing care may be compromised.</title><para role="Para">Nurses that are impacted by The Hollow may make the decision to seek mediation from a nurse manager or a Human Resources representative. Counseling support can be beneficial in helping nurses cope with their anxiety, worry, and perseveration on recalled events of bullying. Counseling can be accessed through the Employee Assistance Program (EAP) through their employer or nurses may seek a private therapist. Licensed mental health professionals can be helpful in helping affected nurses process their bullying experience and maintain their emotional health as affected nurses decide on their next actions in dealing with their unhealthy work situation.</para></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0004" role="Heading"><title>Survival Unimagined</title><para role="Para">According to the Workplace Bullying Institute, in the United States, 79.3 million employees report being affected by bullying in the workplace (WBI, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib09">2021</link></emphasis>). Remote workers experience bullying at the rate of 43%; sources of remote workers’ bullying include 9% email and 50% via online meetings. Employees are not immune to workplace bullying within leadership positions. Nonmanagement employees who are bullied in the workplace represent 52%, while 40% of managers are bullied, with 30% of employees having experienced bullying within the workplace (WBI, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib09">2021</link></emphasis>).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0005" role="Heading"><title>Organizational Impact of Bullying</title><para role="Para">Organizations are impacted by bullying as well. Employees will leave an organization that does not have a healthy work environment (WBI, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0006bib09">2021</link></emphasis>). Hence, turnover intentions are likely to be higher and employee absences from the workplace increase. The reputation of the organization will be impacted over time and lawsuits may occur. As a result of poor branding and reputation, the organization will be unable to attract nor sustain talented workers. Because employees experience a disruption in their work as a result of the bullying and also a lack of confidence, productivity is impacted. Ultimately, the quality of customer service declines as costs to manage the organization and product(s) increase.</para><figure id="ch0002s0005fg01" role="Figure"><title>Cold</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="Ch0002f01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><sidebar id="ch0002s0005ad03"><title>Cold Communications</title><bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">For many people, responding to a rude or demeaning comment can be uncomfortable. However, at times, unaddressed untrue or negative behaviors can affect the health of the person being bullied. Additionally, addressing the unprofessional behaviors of a coworker(s) can help in the unit-based and organizational initiatives to create healthy work environments for all people. Read each statement and decide if you will respond, not respond, or be undecided. Answers will vary and depend upon an individual’s personality and personal life experiences. Hence, below the questions are possible considerations only when responding.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 1.</emphasis> “Sometimes I wonder if you really have a brain.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 1.</emphasis> “I am certain that I do. I met the qualifications to work here just like you.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis></para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(a) Respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(b) Not respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(c) Undecided.</para></listitem></orderedlist></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. It is important to set clear boundaries as to who you are and do not allow the bully to define you or your abilities.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 2.</emphasis> “Let me explain how this works to ensure you understand.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 2.</emphasis> No response.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis></para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(a) Respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(b) Not respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(c) Undecided.</para></listitem></orderedlist></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Not respond. This statement does not warrant a response. Some comments by people attempting to be rude or belittling to you are just not worth your energy. Maintain direct eye contact for a few moments with a neutral expression and drop your gaze. The latter demonstrates that their statement was meaningless to you and that you have already moved on to the next best thing.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 3.</emphasis> (Insert name) “It looks like ______ is the last pick for project teams again. Anyone interested in ________ joining your team? What? Afraid of having to do “extra” work?”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 2.</emphasis> “I enjoy working in teams and will do my best to help my team succeed. My work ethic is to arrive early and stay late.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis></para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(a) Respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(b) Not respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(c) Undecided.</para></listitem></orderedlist></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. Reframe the negative statement with a positive one.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 4.</emphasis> “That hairstyle you are wearing is very unprofessional. Braids and afros do not belong in the workplace.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 4.</emphasis> “Have you ever heard of the Crown Act. You may want to read about this Act before you decide to make any more comments about my hair. Not appropriate.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis></para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(a) Respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(b) Not respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(c) Undecided.</para></listitem></orderedlist></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. It is important to recognize your own uniqueness and beauty as being valuable. No one has the right to disrespect who you are and how you choose to present yourself.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 5.</emphasis> “Do you really think they will believe you… that all this was your idea. Look at me and then look at you?”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 5.</emphasis> No response.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis></para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(a) Respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(b) Not respond.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>(c) Undecided.</para></listitem></orderedlist></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Not respond. No response is necessary to the bully; instead follow up with substantiating the origins of your work. It is your work and no one has the right to take credit for it but you.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sidebar><sidebar id="ch0002s0005ad04"><title>Activity: Poof!</title><bridgehead>Meditation for Contemplation.</bridgehead><bridgehead>Poof!</bridgehead><para role="Para">Quietly lying in bed again but wide awake, I meditate on the failures of my own interventions to stop the bullying.</para><para role="Para">Tossing and turning. Repetition of words said and words I wish I could unsay; the determination of assigned fault seems relentless.</para><para role="Para">Scarred more than I care to admit I ruminate.</para><para role="Para">I ruminate over words said to me and words said about me.</para><para role="Para">The strength now emerging is not one of fantasy but of reality. This is my reality.</para><para role="Para">Mood uplifted and strength renewed, I awake to peace. What happened?</para><para role="Para">Poof!</para><para role="Para">I awoke from my toil. Tired of the endless and relentless nonsense of the bullies, I arose.</para><para role="Para">Stronger and unscathed.</para><para role="Para">Poof!</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Meditation and Contemplation </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">After reading the poetic meditation entitled “Poof!,” consider how it made you feel. Answer the questions below.</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What is the meaning of the title “Poof!”?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Why does the person in the poem have sleepless nights?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What made the person in the poem meditate on their own failures?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What causes a person to ruminate?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What causes a person to have their strength renewed?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0006" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0002s0006bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib01">Green, C. (2019). Incivility among nursing professionals in clinical and academic environments: Emerging research and opportunities. IGI Global. ISBN 13: 9781522573418.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8">https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8">https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib02">Green, C. (2020). The hollow: A theory on workplace bullying in nursing practice. Nursing Forum, 56(1). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/nuf.12539">https://doi.org/10.1111/nuf.12539</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib03">Heinrich, K. (2007). Joy stealing: 10 mean games faculty play and how to stop the gaming. Nurse Educator, 32(1), 34–38. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/nurseeducatoronline/Abstract/2007/01000/Joy_Stealing__10_Mean_Games_Faculty_Play_and_How.10.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/nurseeducatoronline/Abstract/2007/01000/Joy_Stealing__10_Mean_Games_Faculty_Play_and_How.10.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/00006223-200701000-00010">https://doi.org/10.1097/00006223-200701000-00010</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=17220766">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib04">Park, M., &amp; Choi, J. S. (2019). Effects of workplace cyberbullying on nurses’ symptom experience and turnover intention. Journal of Nursing Management, 27(6), 1108–1115. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12779">https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12779</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12779">https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12779</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30951229">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib05">Praslova, L. N., Carucci, R., &amp; Stokes, C. (2022). How bullying manifests at work–and how to stop it. Harvard Business Review. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib06">The Guardian. (2014). Rude boys: Shanty Town to Savile Row. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2014/may/24/rude-boys-jamaican-subculture-photography-exhibition"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2014/may/24/rude-boys-jamaican-subculture-photography-exhibition</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib07">Underground Music, Art, &amp; Subculculture (2021, March 1). The story of subculture: The rude boy (and rude girl). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://underground-england.com/the-story-of-subculture-the-rude-boy-rude-girl/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://underground-england.com/the-story-of-subculture-the-rude-boy-rude-girl/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib08">Valclavikova, K., &amp; Kozakova, R. (2022). Mobbing and its effects on the health of a selected sample of nurses in The Czech Republic. Nursing in the 21st Century, 21(1), 29–33. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2478/pielxxiw-2022-0008">https://doi.org/10.2478/pielxxiw-2022-0008</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2478/pielxxiw-2022-0008">https://doi.org/10.2478/pielxxiw-2022-0008</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0002s0006bib09">Workplace Bullying Institute. (2021). 2021 WBI workplace bullying survey. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://workplacebullying.org/2021-wbi-survey/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://workplacebullying.org/2021-wbi-survey/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
