<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0010" label="10"><title>10. A Coverage of Eyes and Ears</title><sect1 id="ch0010s0006"><title>10. A Coverage of Eyes and Ears</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_10">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_10</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0010">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Eyes and ears, Secondary trauma</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0010s0001"><title>10. A Coverage of Eyes and Ears</title><sidebar id="ch0010s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Consider the implications of choosing not to advocate for a person heard and or observed being bullied.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explain how ignoring bullying in the workplace impacts not only the affected person but the observer as well.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0010s0002" role="Heading"><title>Eyes and Ears</title><para role="Para">The <emphasis role="bold">eyes and ears</emphasis> reveal a multitude of sins. For persons targeted by bullies in the workplace and experiencing The Hollow, the hope for a witness who observed and or heard the bully or bullies being offensive is important to the substantiation of their complaint. However, when persons observing and hearing incidences of workplace bullying choose to be silent, the toxicity of the workplace remains. Over longer periods of time in workplaces, the silence of standby observers and hearers serves to empower the bullies so that bullying persists and more targets are identified.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0010s0003" role="Heading"><title>Secondary Trauma</title><para role="Para">For nurses experiencing The Hollow in the context of workplace bullying, they can feel isolated, helpless, and hopeless. Interestingly, for nurses or other persons observing and hearing workplace bullying, whether they choose to report the bullying or do not, secondary trauma can occur. <emphasis role="bold">Secondary trauma</emphasis> can occur when a person is exposed to another person who is involved in a traumatizing event such as workplace bullying (e.g., yelling, harassment, belittlement, lying, mobbing, social exclusion, etc.).</para><para role="Para">Jiao et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0010s0005bib02">2023</link></emphasis>) noted that persons who were bullied over long periods of time were more likely to report post-traumatic stress disorder, helplessness, anger, sleep disruption, silence, depression, powerlessness, and anger. Ongoing exposure led to digestive problems, stress, decreased immunity, high blood pressure, and headaches.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0010s0004" role="Heading"><title>Summary</title><para role="Para">Observers and hearers of bullying can help to end the bully or bullies’ negative behavior and actions by acknowledging what they saw and reporting the negative behavior to their manager, director, and Human Resources Department. It is important that it be emphasized within healthcare organizations experiencing bullying, particularly bullying that is nurse-to-nurse, that a zero tolerance for bullying being adopted to maintain a healthy workplace environment (ANA, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0010s0005bib01">2015</link></emphasis>; Knight et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0010s0005bib03">2024</link></emphasis>) is necessary for the health and well-being of employees. Policies adhering to zero tolerance should be developed and require employee signature sign off annually to hold perpetrators accountable. Organizations that ignore bullying and that condone employees who ignore bullying are placing the lives of nurses at risk and, ultimately, endangering the lives of patients treated by nurses who are the walking wounded victims of The Hollow.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0010s0005" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0010s0005bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0010s0005bib01">American Nurses Association. (2015). Incivility, bullying, and workplace violence. ANA position statement. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nursingworld.org/practice-policy/nursing-excellence/official-position-statements/id/incivility-bullying-and-workplace-violence/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nursingworld.org/practice-policy/nursing-excellence/official-position-statements/id/incivility-bullying-and-workplace-violence/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0010s0005bib02">Jiao, R., Li, J., Cheng, N., Liu, X., &amp; Tan, Y. (2023). The mediating role of coping styles between nurses’ workplace bullying and professional quality of life. BMC Nursing, 22(1), 1–10. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1186/s12912-023-01624-y"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1186/s12912-023-01624-y</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12912-023-01624-y">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12912-023-01624-y</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0010s0005bib03">Knight, K. E., Ellis, C., Miller, T., Neu, J., &amp; Helfrich, L. (2024). Does where you work and what you do matter? Testing the role of organizational context and job type for future study of occupation-based secondary trauma intervention development. Journal of Interpersonal Violence, 39(7–8), 1623–1648. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/08862605231211927"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1177/08862605231211927</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/08862605231211927">https://doi.org/10.1177/08862605231211927</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38014684">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
