<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0009" label="9"><title>9. Simplifying Life</title><sect1 id="ch0009s0011"><title>9. Simplifying Life</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_9">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_9</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0009">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Work-life balance, Simplifying life</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0009s0001"><title>9. Simplifying Life</title><sidebar id="ch0009s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Consider how simplifying one’s life can benefit their overall health and well-being.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the implications of not prioritizing work-life balance within the context of experiencing workplace bullying.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Learning the importance of rest is important to restorative sleep, relaxation, and renewal of energy.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0002" role="Heading"><title>Work-Life Balance</title><para role="Para">To maintain a <emphasis role="bold">work-life balance is to ensure that your work and home life seldom intermingle</emphasis>. For example, a work-related problem may be discussed within the home or within a personal situation with a friend or colleague, but the problem is not the predominant factor nor focus. When work-life balance is managed, care of one’s self is prioritized, health and well-being is important, and time and energy is balanced. Often, it is when a person does not balance their time and energy toward their home life being one of contentment that toxic work environments can strangulate the mind and body causing mental fatigue and physical strain (Gragnano et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib03">2020</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">An unhealthy work-life balance, according to Cook-Campbell (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib01">2023</link></emphasis>) includes burnout, constant overwork, lack of self-care, strained relationships, and neglected personal life. Persons who overwork, tend to have higher incidences of physical illness and depression and anxiety (el Batawi, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib02">1984</link></emphasis>; Kivimäki et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib04">2015</link></emphasis>; Virtanen et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib06">2011</link></emphasis>). Symptomatology suggestive of a poor work-life balance according to Cook-Campbell (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib01">2023</link></emphasis>) is lack of energy, constantly thinking about work, unexplained aches and pains, restlessness when not at work, struggling to take time off or a vacation, and money that is spent trying to outsource home chores (e.g., laundry, house cleaning, etc.) due to lack of time at home.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0003" role="Heading"><title>Simplifying Life</title><para role="Para">The <emphasis role="bold">simplification of one’s life involves the recognition of the brevity of life and that the circumstantiality of negative behaviors and outcomes persist for a season only</emphasis>. In other words, change, no matter how difficult the situation, can occur. It is the realization that it is the moment-to-moment glimpses of peace and tranquility that can bring about hope for the future.</para><para role="Para">Below are ten tips for simplifying one’s life:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Kiss a person you love each day and tell them you appreciate them.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Make healthy food selections to nourish your body and mind, and prepare your body to conquer stress and disease.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Remove yourself from toxic situations both at work and at home. If a person is physically or verbally abusive toward you, even if you love the person, give yourself permission to set limits and depart from the situation.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Take short vacations to regroup throughout the year and designate time for a longer vacation during the year.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Avoid patterns of volatile arguments from persons who are preoccupied with their own emotions and peace, and not yours.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Exercise daily. Even a short walk around the block or in nature, lifting weights, or stretching can help build balance and strength.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Have faith that you are not alone in this world or universe. Explore spirituality and your belief in God.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Understand that your beauty is both inward and outward. If you are content with a new hairstyle or outfit and others do not like your outfit or hairstyle, own what you like and love it. Consciously decide to just be you.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Leave work on time.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Let no one define your worth both at work or home.</para></listitem></orderedlist><para role="Para">While this is by no means an exhaustive list of ways to simplify one’s life, it is a start. The tips are free and most can be completed with minimal to no monetary amounts. Remember, taking a vacation at home with time off from work can be gratifying. Or taking a day off to explore the beach or experiment with new hairstyles or clothing or obtaining a massage can be relaxing. The key is to find something that is relaxing and people who bring “life to your life” through positivity and genuine care that is unconditional.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0004" role="Heading"><title>Here Is an Idea: Just Go to the Workplace to Work</title><para role="Para">If healthcare environments are to be therapeutic and intellectually stimulating with innovation being the ultimate goal for the healthcare team’s achievement of individual patients’ optimal wellness, workplace health must be prioritized. When workplace environments in healthcare are driven by therapeutics, quiet, respect, peace, and the subjective and objective focus on states of health, both patients and employees can thrive. The loneliness, isolation, and vulnerability experienced by patients, must not be overshadowed by the trust, expertise, and genuine care for humanity that healthcare workers offer patients as workers within healthcare settings.</para><para role="Para">The trivialness of The Hollow with senseless acts of targeted bullying is not appropriate to environments cultivating health and wellness. Hence The Hollow is not conducive to the workplace, let alone those, particularly those persons caring for vulnerable populations diagnosed with physical and mental illness. The practical approach to protection from The Hollow is to simply establish workplace policies whereby bullying is not tolerated. Demonstrations of uncivil conduct toward others is viewed as unprofessional and grounds for a progressive plan of action up to and including termination.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0005" role="Heading"><title>Why Do I Suffer at Work?</title><para role="Para">Therapeutic work with persons who experience workplace incivility can be disheartening. Hearing their pain and the injustices they have experienced on a frequent basis, often at no fault of their own, warrants organizational investigation, support, and resolution. It is also important for organizations to understand that unhealthy workplaces are an international phenomenon. The United Nations, in a global survey, found that one in five employees (23%) have been harassed and or experienced violence in the workplace that was sexual, psychological, or physical in nature. Of concern, according to the United Nations’ International Labour Organization (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0010bib05">2022</link></emphasis>) is the lack of disclosure by affected persons. With more women (60.7%) than men (50.1%), reporting their workplace incivility experiences because of their desire to protect their reputation, leaving persons who have been abusive to them in the workplace environment, or thinking disclosure to be a waste of their time, there is underreporting of uncivil conduct.</para><para role="Para">No matter the color of persons skin, the language they speak, the religion(s) they choose to practice, or the culture of which they originate, discrimination is illogical and unsettling and propagates disunity. Unity and healing must be the focus in order to disarm The Hollow and disempower bullies. In order for this to happen in the workplace, policies must be put in place that do not tolerate the wrongful treatment of employees by employees and employees with clients. Respect, not in word alone but indeed and action and without contingency plans, is what communicates care.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0006" role="Heading"><title>Workplace Norms</title><para role="Para">The Hollow challenges workplace norms that perpetuate self-destruction and the destruction of others. The nurturing workplace is one that seeks to resolve conflict, bring forth solutions, and sustain healthy work environments. Workplace norms that set forth the expectation of gratitude, supporting one another, and the importance of truth-telling are not representative of an idealistic Utopia but can easily be made a reality. Examples of workplace norms include the following:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Zero tolerance for defamation of character in writing or orally.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Affected parties and non-affected parties of bullying are provided the opportunity to confidentially express their experiences working within a toxic work environment.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Ambiguous platitudes of others’ character are thoroughly investigated to substantiate accuracy.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Patterns of possible discrimination are investigated thoroughly by the organization.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Annually, classes are provided on bullying prevention and reporting of toxic workplace experiences at identified system levels; employees to managers to directors to administrators and administrative teams and board members are treated as equal occurrences by the organizations, because all employees and persons that work, receive care, or interface with the organization have value.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Progressive disciplinary action will be taken against repeat offenders and will include termination if no change in behaviors or actions occurs.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Policies are reviewed annually to determine if an update is required for continual support and protection of all employees against The Hollow.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para role="Para">By upholding workplace norms, employees and employers have a contractual dialogue and agreement to maintain healthy workplace environments.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0007" role="Heading"><title>Who Says “No” Is Such a Bad Word in the Workplace?</title><para role="Para">The word “no” can be the most difficult words to say in the workplace, especially for the workaholic and dedicated employee. However, setting of limits creates work-life balance and job satisfaction. This same ability to set limits by saying “no” to workaholism and over dedication to the workplace for one’s health and well-being must be applied to saying “no” to behaviors and actions representative of The Hollow in the workplace.</para><para role="Para">The word “no” brings clarity and focus as well as a well-defined understanding that the preservation of one’s mental and physical health is a priority. It is the clear communication from the individual needing to say “no” that they value their own peace and will not allow anyone to disrupt their peace using disrespectful or dishonest approaches in the work environment. Individuals experiencing The Hollow in the workplace must make the conscious decision to never place their health in the hands of another person who has blatantly disrespected them.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0008" role="Heading"><title>Common Sense</title><para role="Para">Common sense is the basic sensibility applied in the recognition that a wrong or a right has occurred. The hierarchy of that which is civil and representative of truth is the absence of common sense necessity and a humane courtesy to be respectful. Having a mindset of unity is the only way to bring conflict resolution to a bullying situation.</para><para role="Para">Individuals who observe a gap of unification of employees within their organization would do well for themselves and their fellow employees to acknowledge the existence of dysfunction. The acknowledgment of the existence of The Hollow can help employees to assist their organization in changing the culture. A healthy work culture incorporates respect and unity of employees despite their differences.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0009" role="Heading"><title>And So, I Recall: Learning from the Past</title><para role="Para">If your organizational culture was affected by The Hollow in the past, this does not mean that there cannot be a reoccurrence of workplace bullying. A reoccurrence of bullying is always one employee hire away of a person with anger, integrity, manipulation, insecurity, or prior bullying issues. Hence, it is important that managers learn to ask questions and explore work history indicative of bullying behaviors. For example, a hiring manager could inquire about team-building skills and approaches to resolutions of conflict in the workplace and create scenarios whereby in writing, future employees must address a challenging fellow employee or client. Also, include a scenario, whereby the employee is a witness to an actual incident of bullying in the workplace, and ask the employee to explain how they would react and why they chose to react the way they did.</para><para role="Para">Pre-employment Screening: Two Scenario Examples:</para><sidebar id="ch0009s0009ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Scenario 1: Addressing a Challenging PatientThe nurse enters the hospital room of a patient the nurse has been providing care to for the last 8 h of a 12-h shift. The nurse who answered the patient’s call bell asks, “How may I help you.” The patient shares, “I’ve decided that I want to change hospitals. I am not pleased with my care you provided me today. You are not a very good nurse, and you have a horrible bedside manner. I have already notified Patient Relations and your Manager. I am calling to ask you to pack my belongings and complete my discharge. I am ready to go!”</title><para role="Para">Answer the following questions:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What would be your first response?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Do you need to contact anyone?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is there a need for follow-up with patient relations and the manager?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What education, if any, is necessary for the patient?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What education, if any, is necessary for you?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What is your greatest fear or concern after this verbal interaction with your patient?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Have you ever experienced a situation similar to the scenario? If yes, how did you handle it?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is it common for patients to have complaints?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What is your motto in the care of patients that have shared that they are not pleased with their healthcare?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What would be your tone of voice, physical approach, proximity, and comfort level in engaging this patient in determining what could be done differently to ensure continuity of care and that they complete their healthcare treatment?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar><sidebar id="ch0009s0009ad03" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Scenario 2: Observing an Employee Being BulliedAt 7:45 p.m., you have just completed your 12-h day to evening shift and begin walking toward the fifth level of the garage where you parked earlier. As you walk toward your car, you hear arguing, and someone whispering, “If you tell anyone, I will deny it and you’ll look like the fool. They will believe me over you any day.” Standing quietly behind a truck in a darkened area of the garage, you observe that it is the female assistant nurse manager and a male nurse from your unit. You hear the male nurse say, “I am back with my wife and our child. I am ending this relationship that should have never begun in the first place. I made a mistake. My wife forgives me and I am moving on.”</title><para role="Para">The female assist nurse manager slaps the male nurse on his left cheek and begins to walk away stating, “I will get you fired. If I have to lie about your character, I will get you fired.”</para><para role="Para">Answer the following questions:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What would you do?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Should you make your presence known to your two co-workers in the garage?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is it necessary to approach either party to explain what you heard them discuss?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Would you disclose what you heard to another employee you work with?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Whom should the information you heard be shared with within the organization?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is employee confidentiality important in this situation?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What is your role here, if any?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Who are you advocating for in this situation?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What type of situation is this?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Have you ever participated within or observed workplace bullying before? If yes, what was the outcome?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar><para role="Para">Hiring managers should review the scenario and responses with the future employee to provide an opportunity for him or her to explain their thought processes in answering the questions and also to determine how they interpreted the scenario itself. Include their feedback and your discussion with the future employee as part of their scenario write-up. The latter is an opportunity to provide future hires with insight on the importance of healthy workplace environments. With regard to whether the individual is hired or not, an opportunity to promote healthy workplace ideals has been provided.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0009s0010" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0009s0010bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib01">Cook-Campbell, A. (2023). How to have a good work-life balance. Betterup. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.betterup.com/blog/how-to-have-good-work-life-balance#what-does-work-life-balance-mean?"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.betterup.com/blog/how-to-have-good-work-life-balance#what-does-work-life-balance-mean?</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib02">el Batawi, M. A. (1984). Work-related diseases. A new program of the World Health Organization. Scandinavian Journal of Work Environmental Health, 10(6 Spec No), 341–346. doi:<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.5271/sjweh.2309">https://doi.org/10.5271/sjweh.2309</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib03">Gragnano, A., Simbula, S., &amp; Miglioretti, M. (2020). Work-life balance: Weighing the importance of work-family and work-health balance. International Journal of Environmental Research &amp; Public Health, 17(3), 907. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17030907">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17030907</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17030907">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph17030907</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib04">Kivimäki, M., Jokela, M., Nyberg, S. T., Singh-Manoux, A., Fransson, E. I., Alfredsson, L., Bjorner, J. B., Borritz, M., Burr, H., Casini, A., Clays, E., De Bacquer, D., Dragano, N., Erbel, R., Geuskens, G. A., Hamer, M., Hooftman, W. E., Houtman, I. L., Jöckel, K. H., Kittel, F., Knutsson, A., Koskenvuo, M., Lunau, T., Madsen, I. E., Nielsen, M. L., Nordin, M., Oksanen, T., Pejtersen, J. H., Pentti, J., Rugulies, R., Salo, P., Shipley, M. J., Siegrist, J., Steptoe, A., Suominen, S. B., Theorell, T., Vahtera, J., Westerholm, P. J., Westerlund, H., O'Reilly, D., Kumari, M., Batty, G. D., Ferrie, J. E., &amp; Virtanen, M. (2015). IPD-work consortium. Long working hours and risk of coronary heart disease and stroke: A systematic review and meta-analysis of published and unpublished data for 603,838 individuals. Lancet, 386(10005), 1739–1746. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60295-1">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60295-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60295-1">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(15)60295-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=26298822">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib05">United Nations. (2022, December 5). More than 1 in 5 worldwide suffering from violence at work: ILO. United Nations International Labour Organization. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://news.un.org/en/story/2022/12/1131372"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://news.un.org/en/story/2022/12/1131372</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0009s0010bib06">Virtanen, M., Ferrie, J. E., Singh-Manoux, A., Shipley, M. J., Stansfeld, S. A., Marmot, M. G., Ahola, K., Vahtera, J., &amp; Kivimäki, M. (2011). Long working hours and symptoms of anxiety and depression: A 5-year follow-up of the Whitehall II study. Psychological Medicine, 41(12), 2485–2494. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291711000171">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291711000171</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291711000171">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291711000171</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=21329557">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
