<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0017" label="17">
  <title>17. People of Haitian Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0017s0004">
    <title>17. People of Haitian Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_17">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_17</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Jessie M. Colin</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0017">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">College of Health and Wellness, Barry University, Miami, FL, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Jessie M. Colin</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:jcolin@barry.edu">jcolin@barry.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Family roles, Workforce issues, Nutrition, Pregnancy, Spirituality</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0017s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Haiti, with a population of 11.4 million, is located in the Caribbean on the island of Hispaniola, which it shares with the Dominican Republic. The per capita annual income as of 2022 is $1743. Only 13% of the people have access to potable water. Haiti defines itself as a black, republic, consisting of 95% of the population, nation. In Haiti, the concept of color differs from the concept of race. The Haitian system has been described as one in which there are no tight racial categories but in which skin color and other phenotypic demarcations are significant variables. When Duvalier was elected president-for-life in 1964, many Haitians covertly immigrated to the United States in small sailboats, resulting in their being labeled “ <emphasis role="bold">boat people</emphasis>,” a term that is associated with extreme poverty.</para>
    <para role="Para">Migration from Haiti to the United States since the mid-twentieth century has occurred in response to persistent political instability, persecution, frequent economic crises, and natural disasters including a devastating 2010 earthquake that killed over 300,000 people, injured another 300,000, and left over 1.5 million homeless.</para>
    <para role="Para">The recent collapse of basic governmental functions and widespread gang violence followed the 2021 assassination of President Jovenel Moïse. As of 2022, nearly 731,000 Haitian immigrants resided in the United States, making them the country’s 15th-largest foreign-born population.</para>
    <para role="Para">The Haitian population in the United States is not well documented because many are undocumented immigrants. The top 10 metro areas with the most Haitians are within or close to the six states into which the majority of immigrants arrive—Florida, New York, New Jersey, Illinois, California, and Texas. The Haitian immigrant population has more than tripled in the United States, which is the top global destination.</para>
    <para role="Para">The year 2023 offered more opportunities than ever before for Haitians to come into the United States legally. President Joe Biden’s extensions of Temporary Protected Status (<emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="https://www.uscis.gov/humanitarian/temporary-protected-status/temporary-protected-status-designated-country-haiti"><emphasis role="RefSource">TPS</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>) have allowed Haitian immigrants to stay and work legally. They participate in the labor force at a similar rate as all immigrants. About 69 percent of Haitian immigrants and 67% of all immigrants aged 16 and over were in the civilian labor force in 2022, compared to 62% of the native-born. Haitians are more likely than all immigrants in the United States to work in service occupations.</para>
    <para role="Para">Even though Haitians value education, only 15% are privileged enough to obtain a formal education. The illiteracy rate of 61% continues to be a major concern in Haiti. Like other ethnic groups, Haitians are very diverse according to the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para>
    <para role="Para">Haitians are more likely to be naturalized US citizens, have obtained legal permanent residence (also known as getting a green card) through family-based categories, and work in service occupations. They are also less likely to have a college degree and tend to report lower household incomes.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haiti has two official languages: French and Creole. French is the dominant language of the educated and the elite, whereas Creole is the language of the lower socioeconomic classes. Creole, a rich, expressive language, is spoken by everyone. <emphasis role="bold">Develop video programs, audiocassettes, and picture brochures in Creole to provide health education.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most are very expressive with their emotions, including loud animated speech. Pain and sorrow are very obvious in facial expressions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians are affectionate, polite, and shy. The under-educated generally hide their lack of knowledge by keeping to themselves, avoiding conflict, and sometimes projecting a timid air or attitude. They smile frequently and often respond in this manner when they do not understand what is being said.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals pretend to understand by nodding; this sign of approval is given to hide their limitations. <emphasis role="bold">Because Haitians are very private, especially in health matters, it is inappropriate to share information with friends.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many patients may prefer to use professional interpreters, who will give an accurate interpretation of their concerns. Most important, the interpreter should be someone with whom they have no relationship and will likely never see again. <emphasis role="bold">Use simple and clear instructions. Ask family members to assist with interpretation only if an interpreter is not available.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When conversations are really animated, the conversants speak in close proximity and ignore territorial space. Sometimes the conversation is at such a high pitch and speed that to an outsider the conversation may appear disorganized or angry. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret loud conversations as anger.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, Haitians do not maintain eye contact when speaking with those in a position of authority. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret lack of eye contact as not listening or not caring.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians touch frequently when speaking with friends. They may touch you to make you aware that they are speaking to you. <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense from a casual touch on the arm or shoulder.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians greet each other by kissing and embracing in informal situations. In formal encounters, they shake hands and appear composed and stern. Men usually do not kiss women unless they are old friends or relatives. Children greet everyone by kissing them on the cheek. Children refer to adult friends as uncle or auntie.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Temporal orientation is a balance among the past, present, and future. The past is important because it lays the historical foundation from which one must learn. The present is cherished and savored. The future is predetermined and God is the only Supreme Being who can redirect it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians have a fatalistic but serene view of life. Some believe that destiny or spiritual forces are in control of life events such as health and death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">To achieve acceptance, build trust, and ensure compliance, be clear, honest, and open when assessing individuals’ perceptions and how they perceive the forces that have an influence over life, health, and illness.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most do not respect clock time; flexibility with time is the norm, and punctuality is not valued. Arriving late, even for medical appointments, is not considered impolite. <emphasis role="bold">Make reminder calls for appointments and encourage the patient about the importance of timeliness if it is important.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians have a first, middle, and last name; sometimes the first two names are hyphenated as in Marie-Maude. The family name is very important in middle- and upper-class society, promoting and communicating tradition and prestige. Families usually have an affectionate name or nickname for individuals.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When a woman marries, she takes her husband’s full name. She loses her name except on paper. Most names are of French origin, although many Arabic names are also heard. Most are formal and respectful. <emphasis role="bold">Address patients by their title: Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., Doctor, or other title until given permission to do otherwise.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, the head of the household has been the man, but today most families are matriarchal. The man is generally considered the primary income provider for the family, and daily decision-making is considered his province. Women are expected to be faithful, honest, and respectable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are valued among Haitians because they are key to the family’s progeny, cultural beliefs, and values. Children are expected to be high achievers. Children are expected to be obedient and respectful to parents and older people. They are not allowed to express anger to older people.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Physical punishment, often used as a way of disciplining children, is sometimes considered child abuse by US standards. Fear of having their children taken away from them because of their methods of discipline can cause parents to withdraw or not follow through on health-care appointments if such abuse is evident (e.g., bruises or belt marks). <emphasis role="bold">Educate parents about other methods of discipline and laws so they can learn new ways of disciplining their children without compromising their beliefs or violating US laws.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the summer, parents engage their children in health promotion activities such as giving them <emphasis>lok</emphasis> (a laxative), a mixture of bitter tea leaves, juice, sugarcane syrup, and oil. Children are also given <emphasis>lavman</emphasis> (enemas) to ensure cleanliness. This rids the bowel of impurities and refreshes it, prevents acne, and rejuvenates the body.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Boys are given more freedom than girls and are even expected to receive outside initiation in social and sexual life. Girls are educated toward marriage and respectability. Even when they are 16 or 17 years of age, girls cannot go out alone because any mishap can be a threat to her future and bring shame to her family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assist children and family members to work through cultural differences related to the proper age for dating while conveying respect for family and cultural beliefs.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The expression “blood is thicker than water” reflects family connectedness. An important unit for decision-making is the family council, which is composed of influential members of the family. Any action taken by one family member has repercussions for the entire family; consequently, all share prestige and shame. <emphasis role="bold">Include the extended nuclear family in health-care decision-making.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family system includes the nuclear, consanguine, and affinal relatives, some or all of whom may live under the same roof. <emphasis role="bold">Include family members in the care of loved ones to achieve trusting relationships and compliance with treatment regimens.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When family members are ill and in the hospital, there is an obligation to be there for them; all family members try to visit. <emphasis role="bold">Suggest alternative locations for family members to gather. Ask a family spokesperson to help regulate the number of visitors at any one time.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When grandparents are no longer able to function independently, they move in with their children. Older people are highly respected and are often addressed by an affectionate title such as aunt, uncle, grandma, or grandpa, even if they are not related. Their children are expected to care for and provide for them when self-care becomes a concern. Older people are family advisers, babysitters, historians, and consultants.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians are reluctant to place family members in nursing homes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Homosexuality is taboo; gay and lesbian individuals usually remain closeted. If a family member discloses homosexuality, everyone keeps it quiet; there is total denial. Gay and lesbian relationships are not talked about; they remain buried. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose lesbian and gay relationships to family members.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although divorce is common, family members, friends, the church, and elders try to counsel the couple before the divorce becomes final.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Single parenting, widespread in Haiti, is well accepted. It is a well-accepted practice for men to have both a wife and a mistress. Both women bear children. The mistress usually raises her children alone and with minimal support from the father. Haitian women in general know that their husbands are involved in extramarital relationships but pretend not to know. <emphasis role="bold">Approach health education, birth control, and safe-sex issues with sensitivity and acceptance within cultural boundaries. Provide educational brochures in French, Creole, and English.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Haitians in the United States work two jobs to provide for their family while sending money to Haiti for those left behind. Most readily conform to the rules and regulations of the workplace. Haitians tend to settle in clusters with other Haitians. When people live and work primarily in an ethnic enclave, the native culture becomes a barrier to assimilation and acculturation into the dominant society. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage Haitian employees to socialize with other cultural groups.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sometimes Haitians in the workplace greet each other in their native tongue because it is easier to articulate ideas and feelings and to express support in their native language. This may be irritating to non-Haitians who consider it rude. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the rules for speaking a foreign language when at work.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals pretend to understand by nodding; this sign of approval is given to hide their limitations. <emphasis role="bold">Because Haitians are very private, especially in health matters, it is inappropriate to share any information with friends.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When conversations are really animated, the conversants speak in close proximity and ignore territorial space. Sometimes the conversation is at such a high pitch and speed. To an outsider, the conversation may appear disorganized or angry. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret loud conversations as anger or take offense at spatial distancing closer than what you are accustomed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, Haitians generally do not maintain eye contact when speaking with those in a position of authority. Maintaining direct eye contact can be considered rude and insolent, especially when speaking with superiors. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret lack of eye contact as not listening or not caring.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians touch frequently when speaking with friends. They may touch you to make you aware that they are speaking to you. <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense from a casual touch on the arm or shoulder.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Different assessment techniques are required when assessing dark-skinned people for anemia and jaundice. <emphasis role="bold">Examine the sclera, oral mucosa, conjunctiva, lips, nail beds, palms of the hands, and soles of the feet when assessing for cyanosis and low blood hemoglobin levels. To assess for jaundice, examine the conjunctiva and oral mucosa for patches of bilirubin pigment because dark skin has natural underlying tones of red and yellow.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0017s0001ta01">17.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Haitians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assess newer immigrants for signs of malaria, hepatitis, and infectious diseases that are common in Haiti.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0017s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 17.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Haitians</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cholera</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cerebrovascular disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Behaviors that may be considered high-risk in American society are generally viewed as recreational or unimportant among Haitians.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Alcohol plays an important part in society and is culturally approved for men. Women drink socially and in moderation. Cigarette smoking is practiced by men, whereas Haitian women have a very low rate of tobacco use. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation and start educational programs in elementary school.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Other high-risk behaviors include non-use of seat belts and helmets when driving or using a motorcycle or bicycle because these safety measures are not normally used in Haiti. <emphasis role="bold">Educate patients about seat belt use, car seats for youngsters, and the need for helmets on bicycles.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Use graphic videos or skits when instructing patients about these safety practices.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Use Haitian radio stations for educational purposes when they are available.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Promote behavioral changes using church and community group activities.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For many, food means survival; however, food is also relished as a cultural treasure and most Haitians retain their food habits and practices after emigrating. They prefer eating at home, take pride in promoting their culture through their food choices to their children, and discourage fast food. When hospitalized, many individuals would rather fast than eat non-Haitian food. They do not eat yogurt, cottage cheese, or “runny” egg yolks. They drink a lot of water, homemade fruit juices, and cold fruity sodas.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Encourage family members to bring food from home for the hospitalized patient if necessary.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The typical breakfast consists of bread, butter, bananas, and coffee. Children are allowed to drink coffee that is not as strong as that consumed by adults.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The largest meal is eaten at lunch and includes rice and beans, boiled plantains, a salad made of watercress and tomatoes, and stewed vegetables and beef or cornmeal cooked as polenta.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">“Hot and cold,” “acid and non-acid,” and “heavy and light” are the major categories of contrast when discussing food. Illness is caused when the body is exposed to an imbalance of <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">fret</emphasis></emphasis> (cold) or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">cho</emphasis></emphasis> (hot) factors. For example, soursop, is a large green prickly fruit with a white pulp that is used in juice and ice cream, is considered a cold food and is avoided when a woman is menstruating; eating white beans after childbirth are believed to induce hemorrhage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Foods that are considered heavy, such as plantain, cornmeal mush, rice, and meat, are to be eaten during the day because they provide energy. Light foods, such as hot chocolate milk, bread, and soup, are eaten for dinner because they are more easily digested.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">To treat a person in the hot-and-cold system, a potent drink or herbal medicine of the class opposite to the disease is administered. For example, cough medicines are considered to be in the hot category, and laxatives are in the cold category.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Teenagers are advised to avoid drinking citrus fruit juices such as lemonade to prevent the development of acne.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After performing strenuous activities or any activity that causes the body to become hot, one should not eat cold food because that will create an imbalance causing a condition called <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">chofret</emphasis></emphasis>. A woman who has just straightened her hair by using a hot comb and then opens a refrigerator may become a victim of <emphasis>chofret</emphasis>. This means she may catch a cold and/or possibly develop pneumonia.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When ill, pumpkin soup, bouillon, or a special soup made with green vegetables, meat, plantains, dumplings, and yams is consumed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Eating right entails eating sufficient food to feel full and maintain a constant body weight, which is often higher than the weight standards medically recommended in the United States. Men like to see “plump” women. <emphasis role="bold">Negotiate a desirable weight with patients.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Weight loss is considered one of the most important signs of illness. A healthy diet includes tonics to stimulate the appetite and the use of high-calorie supplements such as <emphasis>Akasan</emphasis>, which is either prepared plain or made as a special drink with cream of cornmeal, evaporated milk, cinnamon, vanilla extract, sugar, and a pinch of salt. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients about food rituals when designing individualized dietary plans to facilitate compliance with dietary regimens that promote a healthier lifestyle. Include family in the counseling process.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many women and children who come from rural areas have significant protein deficiencies. A cultural factor that contributes to this problem is the uneven distribution of protein among family members. The problem is not one of net protein deficiency in the community but rather the distribution of the available protein among family members. Whenever meat is served, the major portion goes to the men on the assumption that they must be well-fed to provide for the household. <emphasis role="bold">Being aware that men receive the largest protein servings enables health-care providers to prepare nutritional plans that meet patients’ dietary needs.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pregnancy and fertility practices are not readily used. Most Haitians are Catholic and are unwilling to overtly engage in conversation about birth control or abortion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Abortion is viewed as a woman’s issue and is left to her and her significant other to decide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be cautious in assessing and gathering information related to fertility control.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because pregnancy is not a disease or illness, many women do not seek prenatal care. Pregnancy does not relieve a woman from her work.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pregnant women are restricted from eating spices that may irritate the fetus. They eat vegetables and red fruits because these are believed to improve the fetus’s blood. They are encouraged to eat large quantities of food because they are eating for two.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pregnant women who experience increased salivation may rid themselves of the excess at places that may seem inappropriate in the United States. They may even carry a “spit” cup in order to rid themselves of the excess saliva. They are not embarrassed by this behavior because they believe it is perfectly normal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During labor, the woman may walk, squat, pace, sit, or rub her belly. Generally, women practice natural childbirth and do not ask for analgesia. Some may scream or cry and become hysterical, whereas others are stoic, only moaning and grunting. <emphasis role="bold">Women in labor need support and reassurance. Applying a cold compress on the woman’s forehead demonstrates caring and sensitivity.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cesarean birth is feared because it is abdominal surgery.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fathers do not generally participate in labor and delivery believing that this is a private event that is best handled by women. The woman is not coached; female members of the family provide assistance as needed. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make men feel guilty if they do not want to participate in the delivery.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Postpartum, the woman takes an active role in her own care. She dresses warmly after birth as a way to become healthy and clean.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many believe that the bones are “open” after birth and that a woman should stay in bed during the first 2–3 days postpartum to allow the bones to close. Wearing an abdominal binder is another way to facilitate closing the bones.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The postpartum woman also engages in “the three baths.” For the first 3 days, the mother bathes in hot water boiled with special leaves that are either bought or picked from the field. She also drinks tea boiled from these leaves. For the next 3 days, the mother bathes in water prepared with leaves that are warmed by the sun. At this point, the mother takes only water or tea warmed by the sun. Another practice is to take a vapor bath with boiled orange leaves to enhance cleanliness and tighten the internal muscles. At the end of the third to fourth week, she takes the third bath, which is the cold bath.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A cathartic may be administered to cleanse her intestinal tract. When the process is completed, she may drink cold water again and resume her normal activities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the postpartum period, women avoid white foods such as lima beans, okra, mushrooms, and tomatoes because they are believed to increase vaginal discharge. Strength foods include porridge, rice, and red beans, plantains boiled or grated with the skins and prepared as porridge (the skin is high in iron), carrot juice, and carrot juice mixed with red beet juice.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Breast-feeding is encouraged for up to 9 months postpartum. Breast milk can become detrimental to both mother and child if it becomes too thick or too thin. If it is too thin, it is believed that the milk has “turned,” which may cause diarrhea and headaches in the child and, possibly, postpartum depression in the mother. If milk is too “thick,” it is believed to cause <emphasis>bouton</emphasis> (impetigo).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information and dispel myths related to breast-feeding.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Breast-feeding and bottle feeding are accepted practices. If the child develops diarrhea, breast-feeding is immediately discontinued. <emphasis>Lok</emphasis>, a laxative similar to the one administered to the older children in the summer, is given to infants to hasten the expulsion of meconium. <emphasis role="bold">Stress the risks associated with lok and the need to prevent dehydration.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Generally, Haitians prefer to die at home rather than in the hospital.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When death is imminent, the family may pray and cry uncontrollably, sometimes even hysterically. <emphasis role="bold">Meet the person’s spiritual needs by encouraging family members to bring religious medallions, pictures of saints, or fetishes.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When the person dies, all family members try to be at the bedside and have a prayer service. <emphasis role="bold">If possible and if it is not too disturbing to other patients, encourage a family member to assist with postmortem care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The preburial activity is called <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">veye</emphasis></emphasis>, a gathering of family and friends who come to the house of the deceased to cry, tell stories about the deceased’s life, and laugh. Food, tea, coffee, and rum are in abundant supply. The intent is to show support and to join the family in sharing this painful loss.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Another religious ritual is the <emphasis>dernie priye</emphasis>, a prayer service consisting of 7 consecutive days of prayer, which facilitates the passage of the soul from this world to the next.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">On the seventh day, there is a mass called <emphasis>prise de deuil</emphasis>, which officially begins the mourning process. After each of these prayers, there is a reception/celebration in memory of the deceased.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians have a very strong belief in resurrection and paradise; thus, cremation is not usually an option.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians are very cautious about autopsies. If foul play is suspected, they may request an autopsy to ensure the patient is really dead. This alleviates their fear that their loved one is being zombified. According to the belief, this can occur when the person appears to have died of natural causes but is still alive. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain the legalities of autopsy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Catholic religious beliefs are combined with voodooism. Voodooism involves communication by trance between the believer and ancestors, saints, or animistic deities. Participants gather to worship the <emphasis>loa</emphasis>, deities, or spirits, who are believed to have received their powers from God and are capable of expressing themselves through the possession of a chosen believer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Believers in voodooism attribute their ailments or medical problems to the doings of evil spirits. In such cases, they prefer to confirm their suspicions through the <emphasis>loa</emphasis> before accepting natural causes as the problem, which would lead to seeking Western medical care. Belief in the power of the supernatural can have a great influence on the psychological and medical concerns of patients.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Recognizing and accepting patients’ beliefs alleviates barriers and may make patients feel more at ease to discuss their beliefs and needs.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Good health is the ability to achieve internal equilibrium between <emphasis>cho</emphasis> and <emphasis>fret</emphasis>. To become balanced, one must eat well, give attention to personal hygiene, pray, and have good spiritual habits. To promote good health, one must be strong, have good color, be plump, and be free of pain. To maintain this state, one must eat right, sleep right, keep warm, exercise, and keep clean.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Illness is perceived as punishment, considered an assault on the body, and may have two different causes: natural illnesses, known as <emphasis>maladi Bondye</emphasis> (disease of the Lord), and supernatural illnesses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Natural illnesses are of short duration and are caused by environmental factors such as food, air, cold, heat, and gas.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Supernatural illnesses are caused by angry spirits. To placate these spirits, patients must offer feasts called <emphasis>manger morts</emphasis>. If individuals do not partake in these rituals, misfortunes are likely to befall them. Illnesses of supernatural origin are fundamentally a breach in the rapport between the individual and his or her protector. Health can be recovered if the patient takes the first step in determining the nature of the illness. This can be accomplished by eliciting the help of a voodoo priest and following the advice given by the spirit itself. <emphasis role="bold">To accurately prescribe treatment options, differentiate between natural and supernatural causes of illness and disease.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most individuals believe that gas may provoke pain and anemia. Gas can occur in the head, where it enters through the ears; in the stomach, where it enters through the mouth; and in the shoulders, back, legs, or appendix where it travels from the stomach. When gas is in the stomach, the patient is said to suffer <emphasis>kolik</emphasis> (stomach pain). Gas in the head is called <emphasis>van nan tet</emphasis> or <emphasis>van nan zorey</emphasis>, which literally means “gas in one’s ears” and is believed to be a cause of headaches.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Gas moving from one part of the body to another produces pain. Thus, the movement of gas from the stomach to the legs produces rheumatism, to the back causes back pain, and to the shoulder causes shoulder pain. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients what they think is causing their pain.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Foods that help dispel gas include tea made from garlic, cloves, and mint; plantain; and corn. To deter the entry of gas into the body, one must be careful about eating leftovers, especially beans.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians engage in self-treatment and consider these activities as a way of preventing disease or promoting health, trying home remedies as a first resort for treating illness. If they know someone who has had a particular illness, they may take the prescribed medicine from that person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Haitians tend to keep numerous topical and oral medicines on hand. In Haiti, many medications can be purchased without a prescription, a potentially dangerous practice.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Admonishing patients may cause them to withdraw and not listen to instructions. Be very discreet in assessing, teaching, and guiding the patient toward safer health practices. Inquire if the patient has been taking medication that was prescribed for someone else.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Haitians in America ask friends or relatives to send medications from Haiti. Such medications may consist of roots, leaves, and European-manufactured products that are more familiar to them. <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain what the patient is taking at home to avoid serious complications.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A primary respiratory ailment is <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">oppression</emphasis></emphasis>, which is a term used to describe asthma. However, the term really describes a state of anxiety and hyperventilation rather than the condition. <emphasis>Oppression</emphasis> is considered a “cold” state, as are many respiratory conditions. A home remedy for oppression is to take a dry coconut and cut it open, fill it half with sugarcane syrup and half honey, grate one full nutmeg and add it to the syrup mix, reseal the coconut, and then bury it in the ground for a month. The coconut is reopened, the content is stirred and mixed, and one tablespoon is administered twice a day until it is finished. By the end of this treatment, the child is supposed to be cured of the respiratory problem.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Haitians have low-paying jobs that do not provide health insurance and they cannot afford to purchase it themselves. Thus, economics acts as a barrier to health promotion. Those who do not speak English well have difficulty accessing the health-care system, explaining their needs fully, or understanding prescriptions and treatments. <emphasis role="bold">Obtain an interpreter when necessary.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Diabetes is considered a natural illness; however, most do not seek immediate medical assistance when they detect the symptoms of polyuria, excessive thirst, and weight loss. Instead, they attempt symptom management by making dietary changes on their own by drinking potions or herbal remedies. When the person finally seeks medical attention, he or she may be very sick. <emphasis role="bold">Dispel myths and explain the medical regimen, diet, and medications for diabetes. Reinforce at every opportunity.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pain is commonly referred to as <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">doule</emphasis></emphasis>. Many Haitians have a low pain threshold. They are verbal about the cause of their pain and sometimes moan. They are vague about the location of the pain because they believe that it is not important; they believe that the whole body is affected because disease travels, making it very difficult to assess pain accurately. Injections are the preferred method for medication administration, followed by elixirs, tablets, and capsules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Chest pain is <emphasis>doule nan ke mwen</emphasis>, abdominal pain is <emphasis>doule nan vent</emphasis>, and stomach pain is <emphasis>doule nan ke mwen</emphasis> or <emphasis>doule nan lestomak mwen</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nausea is expressed as <emphasis>lestomak/mwen ap roule, M santi m anwi vomi, lestomak/mwen chaje</emphasis>, or <emphasis>ke mwen tounin</emphasis>. Because of modesty, they may discard vomitus immediately so as not to upset others. <emphasis role="bold">Specific instructions should be given regarding keeping the specimen until the health-care provider has had a chance to see it.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Oxygen should be offered only when absolutely necessary because the use of oxygen is perceived as an indicator of the seriousness of the illness.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fatigue and physical weakness are interpreted as signs of anemia or insufficient blood. Various external and internal environmental factors are believed to cause <emphasis>sezisman</emphasis> ( <emphasis>fright</emphasis>), thereby disrupting normal blood flow. <emphasis>Sezisman</emphasis> may occur when someone receives bad news, is involved in a frightful situation, or suffers from indignation after being treated unjustly.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The stigma attached to mental illness is strong; most do not readily admit to being depressed. Depression can be viewed as a hex placed by a jealous or an envious individual.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients what they think is causing their depression. Negotiate treatment accordingly.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In an unnatural illness, the person’s poor health is attributed to magical causes such as a hex, a curse, or a spell, which has been cast by someone as a result of family or interpersonal disagreement. Symptoms include burning skin, rashes, pruritus, nausea, vomiting, and headaches and often coincide with psychological problems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most are extremely afraid of diseases associated with blood irregularities. Patients and their families become emotional about blood transfusions. Thus, they are received with much apprehension. Additionally, blood transfusions are feared because of the potential for HIV transmission.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Factually explain the need for a blood transfusion, and carefully explain the procedure along with the involved risks. Involve patients and their families in the care as much as possible. Explain precautionary measures that have been taken to prevent blood contamination.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The body must remain intact for burial. Thus, organ donation and transplantation are not generally discussed or practiced. <emphasis role="bold">Assess patients’ beliefs about organ donation and involve a religious leader to provide support and help facilitate a decision regarding organ donation or transplantation.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0017s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Haitians resort to symptom management with self-care first and then spiritual care. They commonly use traditional and Western health-care providers simultaneously.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Physicians and nurses are well respected. Physicians are men, and nurses are women. Nurses are referred to as “Miss.” <emphasis role="bold">Explain and re-explain relevant points to compensate for patients’ knowledge deficits or language limitations.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0017s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">17.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>In what languages would you prepare educational brochures for general health education for Haitians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the primary roles of traditional Haitian men and Women?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the principles of <emphasis>fret</emphasis> and <emphasis>cho</emphasis>. How are these principles applied in dietary practices? In health conditions?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the primary health conditions common with Haitians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explaining breast-feeding practices common with Haitian mothers. Which practices are potentially dangerous and how would you address them with the mother?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the tenets of <emphasis>voodism</emphasis>. How is <emphasis>voodism</emphasis> seen in health-care practices?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Distinguish natural versus supernatural illness among Haitians.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is <emphasis>oppression</emphasis>? What education would you include in a patient who has <emphasis>oppression?</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What infectious diseases would you look for in recent immigrants from Haiti?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are traditional Haitian verbal and nonverbal communication practices?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0017s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0017s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib01">CIA (2024) World Factbook: Haiti. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/haiti/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/haiti/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib02">Cultural Competency and Haitian Immigrants: Death rituals (2003). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nj.gov/humanservices/emergency/HaitiCultural_ClinicalCarePresentation.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://nj.gov/humanservices/emergency/Haiti Cultural_Clinical Care Presentation.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib03">Dain B, Batalova (2023). Haitian Immigrants in the United States. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/haitian-immigrants-united-states#income-poverty"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/haitian-immigrants-united-states#income-poverty</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib04">Death and Funeral Rituals in the Haitian Culture (2013) Haiti Observer. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.haitiobserver.com/blog/death-and-funeral-rituals-in-haitian-culture.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.haitiobserver.com/blog/death-and-funeral-rituals-in-haitian-culture.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib05">Finnegan N (2023) Haitian Immigrants' information needs and behaviors: libraries, information professionals and Haitians in the United States. Student Res J 12(2):3. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://scholarworks.sjsu.edu/ischoolsrj/vol12/iss2/3/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://scholarworks.sjsu.edu/ischoolsrj/vol12/iss 2/3/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.31979/2575-2499.120203">https://doi.org/10.31979/2575-2499.120203</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib06">Haiti: Global Health (2016) USAID. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.usaid.gov/haiti/global-health"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.usaid.gov/haiti/global-health</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib07">Hasalhoef JO (2023) Haitian immigration to the Americas as of 2023, by the numbers. Haitian Times. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://haitiantimes.com/2023/12/19/haitian-immigration-to-america-as-of-2023-by-the-numbers/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://haitiantimes.com/2023/12/19/haitian-immigration-to-america-as-of-2023-by-the-numbers/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib08">Pardo C, Brutus N, Labatte D, Saint-Jean F, Tribié S, Joseph I, Clare CA, Su J, Sánchez JP (2021) An introduction to structural Competency for Haitian-identified patients: history, culture, and access to care. MedEdPORTAL 17:11207. PMID: 35018304; PMCID: PMC8710435. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.15766/mep_2374-8265.11207">https://doi.org/10.15766/mep_2374-8265.11207</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8710435/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8710435/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.15766/mep_2374-8265.11207">https://doi.org/10.15766/mep_2374-8265.11207</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35018304">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8710435">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0017s0003bib09">World Bank in Haiti. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.worldbank.org/en/country/haiti/overview"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.worldbank.org/en/country/haiti/overview</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
