<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0035" label="35">
  <title>35. People of Vietnamese Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0035s0004">
    <title>35. People of Vietnamese Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_35">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_35</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Carol O. Long</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0035">1</link></superscript>, </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tracy Tram Tran</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0035">2</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Timothy Minh Tran</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0035">3</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Transcultural and Palliative Care Consultant, Fredericksburg, VA, USA</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Banner Desert Medical Center, Mesa, AZ, USA</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Gila River Health Care, Sacaton, AZ, USA</para>
    <para role="keywords">Dominant language Vietnamese with mountain dialects, Cultural communication patterns, Format for names, Biocultural ecology, Diseases and health conditions, Variations is drug metabolism, Maternity practices, Death rituals, Spirituality, Dietary practices: am and duong, Folk and traditional practices</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0035s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese living in the United States have arrived since 1975. Their departures from Vietnam were often precipitous and tragic. Escape attempts were long, harrowing, and, for many, fatal. Survivors were often placed in squalid refugee camps for years. Many departed Vietnam in small, often unseaworthy and overcrowded vessels in hopes of reaching a non-Communist port. Half died during their journey. Many were forcibly repatriated to Vietnam or eventually returned voluntarily; others continued to languish in camps. The 1979 Orderly Departure Program provided safe and legal exit for the Vietnamese to reunite with family members already in the United States (referring specifically to the United States and not North, South, or Central America). In 1987, The Amerasian Homecoming Act provided for the entry of former South Vietnamese military officers, other political detainees, children of American servicemen, and Vietnamese women and their close relatives. The Vietnamese in America differ substantially, depending on acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>. Vietnamese place a high value on education and accord scholars an honored place in society. The teacher is highly respected as a symbol of learning and culture.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.1 </emphasis> Communication</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Vietnamese is a single distinctive language with northern, central, and southern dialects, all of which can be understood by individuals speaking any one of these dialects. Vietnamese is the only language of the Asian mainland that is regularly written in the Roman alphabet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">All words in Vietnamese consist of a single syllable, although two words are commonly joined with a hyphen to form a new word. Each vowel can be spoken in five or six tones that may completely change the meaning of the word. Vietnamese language also tends to be more descriptive. For example, if you say <emphasis>mau xanh</emphasis>, it could either be “blue” or “green.” However, Vietnamese would describe it as <emphasis>mau xanh da troi</emphasis> which means “color of the sky” for blue, whereas <emphasis>mau xanh la cay</emphasis> which means “color of a leaf.” <emphasis role="bold">To avoid misunderstandings, do not give directions such as take one “blue” pill at a specified time. Instead, provide the name and dosage of the medication.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the same context, Vietnamese tend to pretend to understand the instructions given or what was told to them to avoid creating disharmony. Ask the patient to repeat the instruction or their understanding of what was said back to you. <emphasis role="bold">Ask open-ended questions, and have the patients demonstrate rather than verbalize their understanding of treatments.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Am</emphasis> and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> translate to <emphasis>yin</emphasis> and <emphasis>yang</emphasis>. This is used in a different context such as when you are talking about the effect (hot or cold) ( <emphasis>duong</emphasis> or <emphasis>am</emphasis>) certain types of food have on the body. Whereas <emphasis>nong</emphasis> (hot) or <emphasis>lanh</emphasis> (cold) are used to express physical feelings associated with fever and chills. <emphasis role="bold">See Sect.</emphasis><emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0035s0001s0006"><emphasis role="bold">35.1.6</emphasis></link></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">in this chapter for a fuller understanding about hot and cold.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">English skills may not be sufficient to communicate in psychiatric interviews, which are usually carried out at a highly abstract level. <emphasis role="bold">Observe patients for behavioral cues, use simple sentences, paraphrase words that may have multiple meanings, and avoid metaphors and idiomatic expressions. Explain all points carefully. Approach patients in a quiet, unhurried manner. Provide an interpreter as needed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Self-control, another traditional value, encourages keeping to oneself. Expressions of disagreement that may irritate or offend another person are avoided. Individuals may be in pain, distraught, or unhappy, yet rarely complain to health-care providers. Some Vietnamese tend to not like to impose on other people for health care. Thus, they tend to use the self-care method to take care of themselves. Going to see a health-care provider is usually a last resort.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Expressions of emotion are considered a weakness that may interfere with self-control. Negative emotions and expressions may be conveyed by silence or a reluctant smile. A smile may express joy or convey stoicism in the face of difficulty or may indicate an apology for a minor social offense. A smile may also be a response to a scolding, as a way to show sincere acknowledgment for the wrongdoing. <emphasis role="bold">Clarify the meaning of a smile.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The head is a sacred part of the body that should not be touched. To place one’s feet on a desk is considered offensive. <emphasis role="bold">If it is medically necessary to touch the head, provide an explanation and ask permission. Do not place feet on a table or desk.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Looking another person directly in the eyes may be deemed disrespectful.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">To signal for someone to come closer using an upturned finger is considered a provocation, usually used to call a dog. Waving the hand is considered more proper. <emphasis role="bold">Do not point when beckoning patients; call them by name.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Hugging and kissing are not seen outside the privacy of the home. Men greet each other with a handshake, but they do not shake hands with a woman unless she offers her hand first. <emphasis role="bold">Greet men with a handshake. Men should wait for the woman to extend her hand for a greeting.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Two men or two women can walk hand in hand without implying sexual connotations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women may be reluctant to discuss sex, childbearing, or contraception when men are present.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional Vietnamese prefer more distance during personal and social relationships than the European American culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Not keeping appointments may relate to not understanding oral or written instructions or not knowing how to use the telephone. More acculturated patients understand the significance of punctuality.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Little attention is given to one’s precise age. Birth dates may pass unnoticed, with everyone celebrating birthdays together during the Lunar New Year ( <emphasis>Tet</emphasis>) in January or February. A person’s age is calculated from the time of conception; children are considered to be a year old at birth and gain a year each <emphasis>Tet</emphasis>. A child born just before <emphasis>Tet</emphasis> could be regarded as 2 years old when only a few days old. Because of the difficulty in determining age, many immigrants use January 1 as a date of birth for official records.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most names consist of a family name, a middle name, and a given name of one or two words, always written in that order. There are relatively few family names, with Nguyen (pronounced “nwin”) and Tran accounting for more than half of all Vietnamese names. Other common family names are Cao, Dinh, Hoang, Le, Ly, Ngo, Phan, and Pho. There are relatively few middle names, with Van being used regularly for men and Thi (pronounced “tee”) for women. A typical woman’s name is Tran Thi Thu. That is how she would write or give her name if requested. She would expect to be called simply Thu or sometimes <emphasis>Chi</emphasis> (sister) Thu by friends and family. In other situations, she would expect to be addressed as <emphasis>Cô</emphasis> (Miss) or <emphasis>Ba</emphasis> (Mrs.) Thu. If married to a man named Nguyen Van Kha, the proper way to address her would be as Mrs. Kha, but she would retain her full three-part maiden name for formal purposes. The man would always be known as <emphasis>Kha</emphasis> or <emphasis>Ong</emphasis> (Mr.) Kha. Some Vietnamese American women have adopted their husband’s family name. Children always take the father’s family name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Vietnamese are very hierarchical. Depending on where they are in age, you would use a certain term to denote where they are in the hierarchy as a form of respect. For example, if they are similar in age to your parents but a little younger, you would call them <emphasis>Co</emphasis> or <emphasis>Chu</emphasis> as in <emphasis>Co Thu</emphasis> or <emphasis>Chu Kha</emphasis>. If they are older than your parents, you would call them <emphasis>Bac Thu</emphasis> or <emphasis>Bac Kha</emphasis>. If they are similar in age as you, you would call them either <emphasis>Em</emphasis> if they are younger or <emphasis>Anh</emphasis> if they are older and male or <emphasis>Chi</emphasis> if they are older and female. If you don’t know their age, out of respect always assume they are older than you. If they are similar to your children age, you would call them either <emphasis>Chau</emphasis> or <emphasis>Con</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">Ask women their preferred name as well as their legal name.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family is the main reference point for the individual throughout life, superseding obligations to country, religion, and self. The traditional family is patriarchal with an extended family structure. Men deal with matters outside the home. A wife is expected to be dutiful and respectful toward her husband and his parents. Women often make family health-care decisions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are expected to be obedient and devoted to their parents and to worship their memory after death. The eldest son is usually responsible for rituals honoring the memory and invoking the blessings of departed ancestors. A son’s obligations and duties to his parents may assume a higher value than those to his wife or children.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For the first 2 years of life, mothers primarily care for their children; thereafter, grandmothers and others take on much of this responsibility.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Exposure of the younger generation to American culture can become a source of conflict with considerable family strain when adolescents are influenced by the perceived American values of individuality, independence, self-assertion, and egalitarian relationships. <emphasis role="bold">Counsel with parents and children together and discuss cultural values to help them reach satisfactory outcomes.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Unattached male refugees may join <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">pseudofamilies</emphasis></emphasis>, households made up of close and distant relatives and friends who share accommodations, finances, and companionship.</para>
          <para role="Para">
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="bold">Pseudofamilies</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">form an important source of social support in the refugee communities.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Differing sexual orientation is difficult for Vietnamese to face because of the shame it can bring to the family. When questioning a lesbian, gay, bisexual or transgender (a more inclusive LGBT initialism), queer or questioning, intersex or asexual individuals, as well as those who identify beyond these commonly used sexuality and gender expressions their sexual orientation, an interpreter unknown to the family is an absolute requirement. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose these conversations or relationships to family members</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional Vietnamese are class-conscious and rarely associate with individuals at different levels of society. Respect is accorded to people in authoritative positions who are well educated or otherwise successful or who have professional titles.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Priority is given to the concerns of the family, rather than to those of the employer.</para>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of punctuality in the workforce.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Vietnamese are highly adaptable and adjust their work habits to meet requirements.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese respect authority figures with impressive titles, achievements, education, and a harmonious work environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Confucian cultural background results in conformity and reluctance to undertake independent action.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many fear losing their job if they speak out about inequities; they are likely to be taken advantage of by some more unscrupulous employers. <emphasis role="bold">Allow extra time, provide visually oriented instructions, and provide programs that enhance communications to promote increased harmony in the workplace.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals cannot easily give a blunt “no” as an answer because they feel that such an answer may create disharmony. A “yes” response, rather than expressing a positive answer or agreement, may simply reflect an avoidance of confrontation or a desire to please the other person. <emphasis role="bold">Ask open-ended questions and have employees demonstrate rather than verbalize their understanding of procedures.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Looking another person directly in the eyes may be deemed disrespectful. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that lack of eye contact means the person is not listening, does not care, or is being less than truthful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense if the Vietnamese employee stands at a greater distance away from how you are accustomed.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Skin color ranges from pale ivory to dark brown. Mongolian spots, bluish discolorations on the lower back of a newborn child, are normal hyperpigmented areas in many Asians. <emphasis role="bold">Assess for oxygenation and cyanosis in dark-skinned Vietnamese by examining the sclera, conjunctiva, buccal mucosa, tongue, lips, nail beds, palms of the hands, and soles of the feet. Assess for patches of melanin in the buccal mucosa and the conjunctiva for petechiae and rashes. Assess for jaundice by observing for yellow discoloration of the conjunctiva.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese are small in physical stature. Adult women average 5 ft tall and weigh 80–100 lb. Men average a few inches taller and weigh 110–130 lb.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Typical physical features include inner eye folds that make the eyes look almond shaped, sparse body hair, and coarse head hair. They also have dry earwax, which is gray and brittle. People with dry earwax have few apocrine glands, especially in the underarm area, and thus produce less sweat and associated body odor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are small by US standards. American growth charts do not provide adequate assessments for evaluating the physical development of Vietnamese children. Standing, walking, and language skills begin at a slightly later age in Vietnamese children, but they rapidly catch up with European American norms by the age of 1½–2 years.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0035s0001ta01">35.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Vietnamese in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. See Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0002#ch0002"><emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Betel-nut pigmentation may be found in some adults, resulting from the practice of chewing <emphasis>chau</emphasis> (betel leaves) that is common among older women for its narcotic effect on diseased gums. Some elderly women lacquer their teeth, believing that it strengthens the teeth and symbolizes beauty and wealth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cancer and other problems common to this group may be associated with the widespread application of chemical agents during the Vietnam War. Explain the importance of cancer screening. <emphasis role="bold">For recent immigrants or older adults, assess patients for tuberculosis, parasitism, anemia, malaria, and hepatitis B.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Melioidosis and paragonimiasis may mimic tuberculosis. Microcytosis may be misdiagnosed as iron deficiency. Inappropriate treatment with iron may be initiated. Erythrocytic microcytosis is a reflection of the presence of thalassemia or of hemoglobin E trait. <emphasis role="bold">Screen for these disorders in people with findings consistent with tuberculosis but with a negative purified protein derivative response.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese people are slow metabolizers of alcohol, making them more sensitive to the adverse effects of alcohol as expressed by facial flushing, palpitation, and tachycardia. They are twice as sensitive to the effects of propranolol on blood pressure and heart rate, experience a greater increase in heart rate from atropine, and require lower doses of benzodiazepines, diazepam, and alprazolam. Because of their increased sensitivity to the sedative effects of these drugs, many require lower doses of imipramine, desipramine, amitriptyline, and clomipramine. They are less sensitive to cardiovascular and respiratory side effects of analgesics (for example, morphine) but are more sensitive to their gastrointestinal side effects.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Most Asians require lower doses of neuroleptics. Because Vietnamese people are considerably smaller than most European Americans and many other groups, medication dosages may need to be reduced.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0035s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 35.1</emphasis> Vietnamese health conditions</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cervical cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Depression and post-traumatic stress syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Trichinosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Nasopharyngeal cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Leprosy</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some newer immigrants have never heard of cancer; among those who have heard of it, some believe it is contagious. Many women have never heard of or had a Pap test. Many have never performed breast self-examination or had a mammogram. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of Pap tests, mammograms, and breast self-exams.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Vietnamese drink a lot of alcohol, mainly beer, wine, and cognac, especially at parties and weddings. Consider screening for liver diseases such as fatty liver and cirrhosis.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">High rates of gastrointestinal cancer may be due to asbestos that, in some parts of the world, is used in the process of “polishing” rice. <emphasis role="bold">Remind patients that polished, imported rice should always be washed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many do not know that cigarette smoking can cause cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the adverse effects of cigarette smoking and encourage cessation, starting as early as in elementary school.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Trichinosis risk is 25 times greater in Southeast Asian refugees than in the general population. This increased risk is related to undercooking pork and purchasing pigs directly from farms. <emphasis role="bold">Screen newer immigrants for the possibility of trichinosis if symptomatology warrants.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Meal preparation is precise and may occupy much of the day. Celebrations and holidays involve elaborately prepared meals.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The normal daily caloric intake of the Vietnamese is approximately two-thirds that of average Americans. White or polished rice is the main staple in the diet, providing up to 80% of daily calories. Other common foods are fish (including shellfish), pork, chicken, soybean curd (tofu), noodles, various soups, and green vegetables. Preferred fruits are bananas, mangoes, papayas, oranges, coconuts, pineapples, and grapefruit. Soy sauce, garlic, onions, ginger root, lemon, and chili peppers are used as seasoning. Rice and other foods are commonly served with <emphasis>nuoc mam</emphasis> (a salty, marinated fish sauce). A meal typically consists of rice, <emphasis>nuoc mam</emphasis>, and a variety of other seasonings, green vegetables, and sometimes meat cut into slivers. Chicken and duck eggs may be used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese prefer white bread, particularly French loaves and rolls, and pastry. A regular dish is <emphasis>pho</emphasis>, a soup containing rice noodles, thinly sliced beef or chicken.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food preparation includes <emphasis>com chien</emphasis> (fried rice) and <emphasis>thit bo xao ca chua</emphasis> (beef fried with tomatoes). <emphasis>Cha gio</emphasis> (pronounced “cha-yuh”) is a combination of finely chopped vegetables, mushrooms, meat, or bean curd that is rolled into delicate rice paper and deep-fried. Stir-frying, steaming, roasting, and boiling are the preferred methods of cooking. Hot tea is the usual beverage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A predominant aspect of the traditional Asian system of health maintenance is the principle of balance between two opposing natural forces, known as <emphasis>am</emphasis> (cold) and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> (hot) in Vietnamese. The terms have nothing to do with temperature and are only partly associated with seasoning. Rice, flour, potatoes, most fruits and vegetables, fish, duck, and other things that grow in water are considered cold. Most other meats, fish sauce, eggs, spices, peppers, onions, candies, and sweets are hot. Tea is cold, coffee is hot, water is cold, and ice is hot.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Illness or trauma may require therapeutic adjustment of hot–cold balance to restore equilibrium. Hot foods and beverages, used to replace and strengthen the blood, are preferred after surgery or childbirth. During illness, certain foods, such as <emphasis>chao</emphasis> (light rice gruel or porridge) and a few pieces of salty pork cooked with fish sauce, are consumed in greater quantity. Chao is the preferred food because it is easy on the palette, requires minimal effort to chew, and is easy to digest when you don’t feel good and tired. Fresh fruits and vegetables are usually avoided, being considered too cold. Water, juices, and other cold drinks are restricted. <emphasis role="bold">Nutritional counseling should take into consideration these factors and other aspects of the usual Vietnamese diet because professional advice to eat certain kinds of American foods may be ignored.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most adults and many children suffer from lactose intolerance, which may cause problems in schools, other institutional settings, and adoptive families. <emphasis role="bold">Consider the use of substitute milk products that use soybeans for those who are lactose intolerant.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women have high fertility rates (average of six pregnancies, with four live births) and commonly have children until their early to middle 40s. Many know little about contraception. Abortions are commonly performed in their homeland because pregnancy outside of marriage is considered a disgrace to the family. More acculturated individuals practice some form of birth control. <emphasis role="bold">Avoid family planning issues on the first encounter; but such information is usually well received on subsequent visits.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prescriptive food practices for a healthy pregnancy include noodles, sweets, sour foods, and fruit and exclude fish, salty foods, and rice. After birth, to restore equilibrium and provide adequate warmth to the breast milk, women consume soups with chili peppers, salty fish and meat dishes, and wine steeped with herbs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Foods are also classified as <emphasis>tonic</emphasis> and <emphasis>wind</emphasis>. Tonic foods include animal protein, fat, sugar, and carbohydrates; they are usually also hot and sweet. Sour and sometimes raw and cold foods are classified as <emphasis>antitonic</emphasis>. Wind foods, often classified as cold, include leafy vegetables, fruit, beef, mutton, fowl, fish, and glutinous rice. It is considered critical to increase or decrease foods in various categories to restore bodily balances upset by unusual or stressful conditions such as pregnancy. While the balance of foods may be followed, the terminology is not used consistently.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Until now, older generations such as grandmothers, mothers, and aunties will restrict certain foods for pregnant women such as watermelon (red inside/green outside is considered not good for the baby). A lot of the restrictions are based on superstitions rather than health based. For example: “don’t drink coffee because it will give baby dark skin.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During the first trimester, the expectant mother is considered to be in a weak, cold, and antitonic state. Therefore, she should correct the imbalance by eating and drinking hot foods, such as ripe mangoes, grapes, ginger, peppers, alcohol, and coffee. To provide energy and food for the fetus, she is prescribed tonic foods, including a basic diet of steamed rice and pork.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cold foods, including mung beans, green coconut, spinach, and melon, and antitonic foods, such as vinegar, pineapple, and lemon, are avoided during the first trimester. In the second trimester, the pregnant woman is considered to be in a neutral state. Cold foods are introduced, and the tonic diet is continued.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During the third trimester, when the woman may feel hot and suffer from indigestion and constipation, cold foods are prescribed, and hot foods are avoided or strictly limited. Tonic foods, which are believed to increase birth weight, are restricted to reduce the chances of a large baby. Wind foods are generally avoided throughout pregnancy, as they are associated with convulsions, allergic reactions, asthma, and other problems. This regimen may appear more complex and restrictive than it actually is in practice. Most women use it only as a general guide, commonly restricting, rather than totally abstaining from the restricted foods. A great variety of foods, including rice, many kinds of vegetables and fruits, various seasonings, and certain meats and fish are generally permissible throughout pregnancy. <emphasis role="bold">Ask women at each stage of their pregnancy about preferred foods before initiating dietary recommendations. Dispel any myths and recommend foods that are congruent with beliefs.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many women do not seek medical attention until the third trimester because of cost, fear, or lack of perceived need. Women who are generally better educated seek early prenatal care. For obstetric and gynecologic matters, they tend to feel more comfortable with a female physician or midwife.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women maintain physical activity to keep the fetus moving and to prevent edema, miscarriage, or premature delivery. It is believed that prolonged labor may result from idleness, and an undesirably large baby may result from afternoon napping.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Restrictive beliefs include avoiding heavy lifting and strenuous work and raising the arms above the head, which pulls on the placenta causing it to break. Sexual relations late in pregnancy may cause respiratory stress in the infant.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many consider it taboo for pregnant women to attend weddings or funerals.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some pregnant women look at pictures of happy families and healthy children, believing that it helps give birth to healthy babies.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Anesthesia during labor and delivery is usually accepted. Once in labor, the woman tries to maintain self-control and may even smile continuously. Her period of labor may be usually short, and there may be no warning of impending delivery.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Because the head is considered sacred, neither the mother nor the infant’s head should be touched or stroked. Removal of vernix from the infant’s head can cause distress. If it is necessary to touch the head for medical treatment, an explanation is essential. Stress the importance and necessity of any invasive procedures that are required.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because body heat is lost during delivery, women avoid cold foods and beverages and increase the consumption of hot foods to replace and strengthen their blood. Ice water and other cold drinks are usually not welcome, and most raw vegetables, fruits, and sour items are consumed in lesser amounts. Prescriptive foods include steamed rice, fish sauce, pork, chicken, eggs, soups with chili or black peppers, other highly seasoned and salty items, wine, and sweets.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because water is <emphasis>am</emphasis> (cold), women traditionally do not fully bathe, shower, or wash their hair for a month after delivery. This is still in practice, even for Vietnamese Americans and is totally opposite of Western medicine, which is moving and showering right after birth. Some women have complained that they were adversely affected by showering shortly after delivery in American hospitals; others however welcomed the opportunity to shower and seemed willing to give up some traditional practices. Be mindful of individual choice with these decisions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Postpartum women avoid drafts and strenuous activity; wear warm clothing; stay in bed, indoors, or both for about a month; and some avoid sexual intercourse for months. Many use hot water bottles or electric blankets to combat the cold forces of childbirth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Other women in the family assume responsibility for the baby’s care. In Vietnam, husbands would never be present at their child’s delivery; this may also occur in the United States and elsewhere. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret the mother’s inactivity and dependence on others as apathy or depression. Do not praise the baby, lest jealous spirits steal the infant. Do not cut the child’s hair or nails for fear that this might cause illness.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The infant is generally maintained on a diet of milk for the first year, with the introduction of rice gruel at around 6 months.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some women discard colostrum and feed the baby rice paste or boiled sugar water for several days. This does not indicate a decision against breast-feeding. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the immune properties of colostrum.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After the milk comes in, the mother and baby benefit from the hot foods consumed by the mother for the first month. Then, however, a conflict arises: the mother believes that hot foods benefit her health, but that cold foods ensure healthy breast milk. Having the mother change from breast-feeding to formula can easily solve this dilemma. However, if the mother cannot afford formula, she may use fresh milk or rice boiled with water, which may result in anemia and growth retardation. <emphasis role="bold">Reinforce the benefits of colostrum.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Vietnamese accept death as a normal part of life. Ancestors are commonly honored and worshipped and are believed to bestow protection on the living.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most individuals have an aversion to hospitals and prefer to die at home. Some believe that a person who dies outside the home becomes a wandering soul.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many do not want to artificially prolong life and suffering, but it may still be difficult for relatives to consent to terminating active intervention, which might be considered contributing to the death of an ancestor who shapes the fate of the living. <emphasis role="bold">Having a family conference and providing factual information is appreciated.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Clergy visitation is usually associated with Sacrament of the Sick; rites influenced by Catholicism can actually be upsetting to hospitalized patients. Sending flowers may be startling, as flowers are usually reserved for the rites of the dead. <emphasis role="bold">Do not place flowers in the patient’s room until getting permission from the patient or family. Contact religious leaders only with the permission or request of the patient or family.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Families gather around the body of a deceased relative and express great emotion. Traditional mourning practices include the wearing of white clothes for 14 days, the subsequent wearing of black armbands by men and white headbands by women, and the yearly celebration of the anniversary of a person’s death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Few families consent to autopsy unless they know and agree with the reasons for it. Cremation is an acceptable practice to some families. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the legalities of an autopsy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most practice Buddhism, either solely or combined with other religions. Other major religions practiced are Confucianism and Taoism; a few are Christians, most of whom are Catholic. Animism is found mainly among people from the highland tribes. Many believe that deities and spirits control the universe and that the spirits of dead relatives continue to dwell in the home.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spirituality is also gained by participating in ethnic community activities. <emphasis role="bold">Learn more about individual spiritual practices as a means to gain trust.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Good health is achieved by having harmony and balance with the two basic opposing forces, <emphasis>am</emphasis> (cold, dark, female) and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> (hot, light, male). An excess of either force may lead to discomfort or illness. <emphasis>Am</emphasis> (cold) represents factors that are considered negative, feminine, dark, and empty, whereas <emphasis>duong</emphasis> (hot) represents those that are positive, masculine, light, and full. Proper balance of these two life forces ensures the correct circulation of blood and good health. If the balance is not proper, life is short.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Diseases and debilitating conditions result from either cold or hot influences. For example, diarrhea and some febrile diseases are due to an excess of cold, whereas pimples and other skin problems result from an excess of hot. Countermeasures involve using foods, medications, and treatments that have properties opposite those of the problem and avoiding foods that would intensify the problem. Asian herbs are cold, and Western medicines are hot. <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate traditional practices into allopathic or Western care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common Vietnamese medical practices are discussed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0035s0001ta02">35.2</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Vietnamese try home remedies, allowing the condition to become serious before seeking professional assistance. Once a physician or nurse has been consulted, the Vietnamese are usually quite cooperative and respect the wisdom and experience of health-care providers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The belief that life is predetermined is a deterrent to seeking health care. Diagnostic tests may be baffling, and invasive procedures are frightening. The prospect of surgery can be terrifying. <emphasis role="bold">Explain procedures in simple, realistic terms, and reinforce information as necessary.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Hospitalization is considered a last resort and is acceptable only in case of emergency when everything else has failed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Naturalistic explanations for poor health include eating spoiled food and exposure to inclement weather. Natural elements are associated with bad weather and cold drafts and cause problems such as the common cold, mild fever, and headache. Countermeasures involve dietary, herbal, hygienic, and simple medical practices. Collectively, these measures are categorized as <emphasis>thuoc nam</emphasis>, the traditional southern medicine of Vietnam, and <emphasis>thuoc bac</emphasis>, the more formal northern medicine of Vietnam or Chinese medicine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Supernaturalistic causes, such as gods, spirits, or demons, may cause illness. Illness may be considered a punishment for offending such an entity or violating some religious or moral code.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A “weak heart” may refer to palpitations or dizziness, a “weak kidney” to sexual dysfunction, a “weak nervous system” to headaches, and a “weak stomach or liver” to indigestion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Loss of blood from any route is feared, and some may refuse to have blood drawn for laboratory tests. The patient may complain, although not to the health-care provider, of feeling weak for months. A patient may fear that any body tissue or fluid removed cannot be replaced and that the body suffers the loss in this life as well as into the next life. <emphasis role="bold">Explain that blood is naturally replenished with good nutrition.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many believe that Western medicine is very powerful and cures quickly, but few understand the risks of over- or underdosages. The concept of long-term medication for chronic illnesses and the acceptance of unpleasant side effects and increased autonomic symptoms are not congruent with the traditional notions of safe and effective treatment of illnesses. Some people politely accept a prescription but may not fill it. Even if they have filled it, they may not take the medicine: they may adjust the dosage without telling the health-care provider. <emphasis role="bold">Extensive education, the repetition of instructions, and home visitations are necessary to promote adherence.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Persistent reminding, as part of an overall effort to improve communication and information dissemination, has been suggested as the best way to encourage Vietnamese women to undergo regular cancer screening and follow-up treatment.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include family members in all major treatment decisions regarding physical and mental health.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common problems that pose barriers to health care are discussed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0035s0001ta03">35.3</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fatalistic attitudes and the belief that problems are punishment may reduce the amount of complaining and expression of pain among those who view endurance as an indicator of strong character. Many Vietnamese accept pain as part of life and attempt to maintain self-control as a means of relief. <emphasis role="bold">Explain that accepting pain medication will hasten the healing process.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In times of distress or loss, they often complain of physical discomforts such as headaches, backaches, or insomnia.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mental illness is believed to result from offending a deity and brings disgrace to the family. A shaman may be enlisted to help: additional therapy is sought only with the greatest discretion and often after a dangerous delay. <emphasis role="bold">Partner with traditional healers to refer patients early in the diagnostic or treatment stages.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Emotional disturbance is usually attributed to the possession by malicious spirits, bad luck of familial inheritance, or, for Buddhists, bad karma accumulated by misdeeds in past lives.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The term <emphasis>psychiatrist</emphasis> has no direct translation in Vietnamese and may be interpreted to mean nerve physician or specialist who treats crazy people. The nervous system is sometimes considered the source of mental problems, with neurosis being thought of as “weakness of the nerves” and psychosis as “turmoil of the nerves.” A person with a mental disability may be stigmatized by the family and society, which can jeopardize the ability of relatives to find marriage partners. People with mental disabilities are usually harbored within their families unless they become destructive: then they may be admitted to a hospital. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose mental health conditions outside the family.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">People with a physical disability are commonly accepted and are treated well and cared for by their families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many women who have abnormal Pap smears fail to return for follow-up care, thereby contributing to the shockingly high incidence of cervical cancer among Vietnamese women. Many women fail to comprehend the severity of the situation and the potential for recovery if regular treatment begins early enough. <emphasis role="bold">To increase follow-up visits and care, carefully explain the problems that may result if they do not follow up after an abnormal Pap smear. Explain that lack of symptoms or pain may be only temporary. Persistent reminding, as part of an overall effort to improve communication and information dissemination, has been suggested as the best way to encourage Vietnamese women to undergo regular cancer screening and follow-up treatment.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because many believe that the body must be kept intact even after death, they are averse to blood transfusions and organ donation. Those who prefer cremation will donate body parts under certain circumstances.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women may not want to discuss sexual problems, reproductive matters, and birth control techniques until after an initial visit and confidence has been established in the health-care provider. <emphasis role="bold">Pelvic examinations on unmarried women should not be conducted on the first visit or without careful advance explanation and preparation. When such an examination is necessary, the woman may want her husband present. If possible, the health-care provider and an interpreter should both be female.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0035s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 35.2</emphasis> Traditional Vietnamese medicine</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Cao gio</emphasis></emphasis> (literally, “rubbing out the wind”) is used for treating colds, sore throats, flu, sinusitis, and similar ailments. An ointment or hot balm oil is spread across the back, chest, or shoulders and rubbed with the edge of a coin (preferably silver) in short, firm strokes. This technique brings blood under the skin, resulting in dark ecchymotic stripes, so the offending wind can escape. Dermabrasion may provide a portal for infection. Do not interpret these ecchymotic areas as evidence of abuse</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Be bao</emphasis></emphasis> or <emphasis>bar gio</emphasis> (skin pinching) is a treatment for headache or sore throat. The skin of the affected area is repeatedly squeezed between the thumb and forefinger of both hands, as the hands converge toward the center of the face. The objective is to produce ecchymoses or petechiae. Do not interpret these ecchymotic areas as evidence of abuse</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Giac</emphasis></emphasis> (cup suctioning), another dermabrasive procedure, is used to relieve stress, headaches, and joint and muscle pain. A small cup is heated and placed on the skin with the open side down. As the cup cools, it contracts the skin and draws unwanted hot energy into the cup. This treatment leaves marks that may appear as large bruises. Do not interpret these ecchymotic areas as evidence of abuse</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Xong</emphasis></emphasis> (an herbal preparation) relieves motion sickness or cold-related problems. Herbs or an agent such as Vicks VapoRub is put into boiling water, and the vapor is inhaled. Small containers of aromatic oils or liniments are sometimes carried and inhaled directly</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis role="bold">Moxibustion</emphasis> is used to counter conditions associated with excess cold, including labor and delivery. Pulverized wormwood or incense is heated and placed directly on the skin at certain meridians</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Acupuncture, acupressure, and acumassage relieve symptomatic stress and pain (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0010#ch0010"><emphasis role="RefSource">10</emphasis></ulink></emphasis> for a description of these healing practices)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Balms and oils, such as Red Tiger Balm, available in Asian shops, are applied to affected areas for relief of bone and muscle ailments</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Herbal teas, soups, and other concoctions are taken for various problems, generally in the sense of using cold measures to overcome hot illnesses. Eating organ meats such as liver, kidneys, testes, brains, and bones of an animal is said to increase the strength of the corresponding human part. Two additional practices are consuming gelatinized tiger bones to gain strength and taking powdered rhinoceros horn to reduce fever</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table id="ch0035s0001ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 35.3</emphasis> Barriers to health care for Vietnamese people</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Subjective beliefs and the cost of health care</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Lack of a primary care provider</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Differences between Western and Asian health-care practices</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Caregivers’ judgment of Vietnamese as deviant and unmotivated because of noncompliance with medication schedules, diagnostic tests, follow-up care, and failure to keep appointments</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Inability to communicate effectively in the English language with recent immigrants, who lack confidence in their ability to communicate their needs; failure of providers to communicate</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Avoidance of Western practitioners out of fear that traditional methods will be criticized</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Fear of conflicts and ridicule, resulting in loss of face</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Lack of knowledge of the available resources</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Fear of stigmatization, difficulty in locating agencies that can provide assistance without distorted professional and cultural communication, and unwillingness to express inner feelings</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0035s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Four kinds of traditional and folk healers exist in Vietnam, as shown in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0035s0001ta04">35.4</link></emphasis>. Many consult one or more of these healers in an attempt to find a cure. <emphasis role="bold">Partner with traditional healers as a means for social support and treatment adherence.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The acknowledgment and support of traditional belief systems are important in building a trusting relationship. Traditional healers often provide Vietnamese people with necessary social support.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Adults, particularly young and unmarried women, are more comfortable with health-care providers of the same gender, especially for obstetrical and gynecological conditions. <emphasis role="bold">Provide female healthcare providers whenever possible for gynecological care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Vietnamese are not accustomed to female authority figures and may have difficulty relating to women as professional health-care providers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While many individuals have great respect for professional well-educated people, they may be distrustful of outside authority figures. Most have come to the United States and elsewhere to escape oppressive authority. A common suspicion is that divulging personal information for a medical history may jeopardize their legal rights. Respect and mistrust are not mutually exclusive concepts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0035s0001ta04">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 35.4</emphasis> Folk practitioners</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Asian physicians who are learned individuals who use herbal medication and acupuncture</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Informal folk healers who use special herbs and diets as cures based on natural or pragmatic approaches. The secrets of folk medicine are passed down through the generations</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Spiritual healers, some of whom have a specific religious outlook, and others who have powers to drive away malevolent spirits</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Magicians or sorcerers who have magical, curative powers but no communication with the spirits</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0035s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">35.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the naming format for Vietnamese men and women.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>When does a traditional Vietnamese have a birthday? What might this mean for child development in accordance with the US standards and expectations?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are traditional Vietnamese family roles and decision-making?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe two high-risk health behaviors that may require additional screening during a health care intervention.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>List five ideologies or ideals that Vietnamese people value as part of the culture.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the <emphasis>am</emphasis> and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> concepts of nutrition.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How do <emphasis>am</emphasis> and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> practices vary with pregnancy and postpartum practices?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How are the principles of <emphasis>am</emphasis> and <emphasis>duong</emphasis> displayed in illnesses?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How are mental illnesses seen among the Vietnamese? As a health-care provider, what can you do to improve Vietnamese’s’ access to mental health professionals?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the five different traditional Vietnamese medical practices.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0035s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0035s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib01">Budiman A (2021) Vietnamese in the US fact sheet. Pew Research Center. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/fact-sheet/asian-americans-vietnamese-in-the-u-s-fact-sheet/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/fact-sheet/asian-americans-vietnamese-in-the-u-s-fact-sheet/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib02">CIA (2024) World Factbook—Vietnam. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/vietnam/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/vietnam/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib03">Global Health: Vietnam (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cdc.gov/globalhealth/countries/vietnam/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cdc.gov/globalhealth/countries/vietnam/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib04">Gordon S, Bernadett M, Evans D, Shapiro NB, Dang L (2006) Vietnamese culture: influences and implications for health care. Molina Institute for Cultural Competency. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.molinahealthcare.com/~/media/Molina/PublicWebsite/PDF/providers/nm/medicaid/resource/health_nm_vietnameseculture-influencesandimplicationsforhealthcare_materialandtest.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.molinahealthcare.com/~/media/Molina/Public Website/PDF/providers/nm/medicaid/resource/health_nm_vietnameseculture-influencesandimplicationsforhealthcare_materialandtest.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib05">Harjanto L, Batalova J (2021) Vietnamese immigrants in the United States. Migration Policy Institute. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/vietnamese-immigrants-united-states"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.migrationpolicy.org/article/vietnamese-immigrants-united-states</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib06">La Borde P, Duong B (2010) Vietnamese cultural profile. EthnoMed. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://ethnomed.org/culture/vietnamese/vietnamese-cultural-profile"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://ethnomed.org/culture/vietnamese/vietnamese-cultural-profile</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib07">Long CO (2021) People of Vietnamese heritage. In: Purnell L, Fenkl EA (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib08">Nguyen DS, Giap N (2019) Death and dying: belief, fear and ritual in Vietnamese culture. In: Selin H, Rakoff RM (eds) Death across cultures. Death and dying in non-western cultures. Springer, Cham. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-18826-9_5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-18826-9_5</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-18826-9_5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-18826-9_5</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib09">Nguyen VVT, Zheng MY, Liu SM, Kallen MA, Kay K, Ivey SL (2022) Prevalence of traditional Asian postpartum practices at a federally qualified health center. J Immig Minor Health 24(5):1251–1260. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-021-01299-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-021-01299-0</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-021-01299-0">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-021-01299-0</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib10">Thai C (2003) Traditional Vietnamese medicine: historical perspective and current usage. EthnoMed. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://ethnomed.org/clinical/traditional-medicine/traditional-vietnamese-medicine-historical-perspective-and-current-usage"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://ethnomed.org/clinical/traditional-medicine/traditional-vietnamese-medicine-historical-perspective-and-current-usage</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib11">Vietnam—Culture, etiquette and business practice (2022) Commisceo Global. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/vietnam-guide"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/vietnam-guide</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0035s0003bib12">Vietnamese pregnancy and birth practices (2024) <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.vietnam-culture.com/zones-28-1/Pregnancy-and-Birth-Customs.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.vietnam-culture.com/zones-28-1/Pregnancy-and-Birth-Customs.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
