<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0003" label="3"><title>3. Barriers to Culturally Competent Health Care</title><sect1 id="ch0003s0017"><title>3. Barriers to Culturally Competent Health Care</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_3">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_3</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0003">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0003">2</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">College of Health and Nursing Sciences, Excelsior University, Albany, NY, USA</para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:lpurnell@udel.edu">lpurnell@udel.edu</ulink></para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:efenkl@fiu.edu">efenkl@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Language and health literacy, Accessibility, Affordability, Awareness, Alternative Practices</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.1 </emphasis> Introduction</title><para role="Para">Barriers to culturally competent health care are defined as obstacles or hindrances that make it difficult to obtain or access good health or health care. Despite efforts and goals in the United States and many other countries around the world to reduce or eliminate obstacles, significant disparities continue, especially with what the professional literature refers to as vulnerable populations. Vulnerable populations include the following:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">the economically disadvantaged</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">racial and ethnic minorities (including those of mixed race or ethnicities)</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">the uninsured and underinsured</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">older adults</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">children</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">the homeless</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">people with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">people who are stigmatized for whatever reason, which includes substance misuse</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">people with chronic health conditions and severe mental illness</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">rural populations</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">people with low acculturation and low levels of education</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">gender disparities</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">refugees and undocumented immigrants</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">distance to a health-care facility</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">language difficulties, and an interpreter is not available.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para role="Para">Overall, these disparities are due to environmental, psychological, and social factors; maldistribution or shortage of human and fiscal resources; and lack of access to health-care systems. From this list, it seems clear that under the right set of circumstances, any group or individual can be vulnerable.</para><para role="Para">Barriers can be categorized in several domains that are presented in this chapter: language and health literacy, availability, accessibility, affordability, appropriateness, accountability, adaptability, acceptability, awareness, attitudes, approachability, alternative practices, and additional services. It should be noted that these domains are not categorically imperative or perfectly distinct categories; they can overlap.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.2 </emphasis> Language and Health Literacy</title><para role="Para">Language and health literacy barriers include the medical jargon used by health-care providers, inadequate reading level of the patient, or lack of fluency in English or in the patient’s mother tongue. Several studies in the United States have identified that a lack of fluency in language is the primary barrier to receiving adequate health care, and not just for people for whom English is a second language.</para><para role="Para">Language barriers may involve both oral and written language. Interpretation refers to oral communication, while translation refers to written communication. Interpretation requires more than word-for-word substitution. Professional interpreters must not only demonstrate bilingual proficiency, but they must also be knowledgeable of idioms, slang, and colloquialisms as well as medical terminology. Sign language may be a concern for some because there is no standard worldwide sign language. Besides American Sign Language, there are multiple Arabic sign languages. Language and literacy barriers may result in the following:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Language barriers can negatively affect perceptions of patient and provider care, resulting in patients not returning for follow-up care.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Language barriers may result in a patient leaving against medical advice. A patient who perceives that he or she is not understood by the health-care provider or who does not understand a provider who is using medical technology may simply leave.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Limited English proficiency (LEP) can result in unsafe situations caused by poor patient comprehension of their medical condition, treatment plan, or discharge instructions; an inaccurate and incomplete medical history being obtained by the health-care provider; ineffective or improper use of medications or serious medication errors; improper preparation for tests and procedures; and poor or inadequate informed consent.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Be alert to comments and behaviors from patients and family members that might mean they do not understand the provider. Such cues include “Can I take these forms home to complete?” or “I forgot my glasses. I’ll wait until (friend or family member) comes to help me.”</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">LEP patients who do not receive professional interpretation services at admission and discharge have longer lengths of stay and higher readmission rates compared with patients who receive professional interpretation services.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Just because someone speaks the language does not necessarily mean he or she has the skills to be successful at interpretation.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Improper interpretation is prone to additions, substitutions, omissions, volunteer opinions, and sematic errors.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Compared with professional medical interpreters, ad hoc interpreters such as patients’ family members or house staff frequently make medical interpretation errors. These errors are significantly more likely to have clinical consequences.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Use only certified interpreters when at all possible.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Use dialect specific interpreters whenever possible.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Create a system for interpretation and translation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Compile a list of commonly used words in the dominant languages of the patients using the facility. This list does not replace the need for an interpreter but may be helpful if a professional interpreter is not available.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Allow time for interpretation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Be aware that social class differences can affect interpretation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Maintain eye contact with both the patient and the interpreter.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Non-professional interpretation and using children or other family members can lead to a breach of confidentiality. Also, patients might not speak freely, especially regarding issues such as sexuality, drug and alcohol misuse, and domestic violence.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not place the patient in a precarious situation by asking the patient in front of the family if it is acceptable for a family member or friend to interpret.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not use family members except in nonconfidential situations such as obtaining demographic and admitting data and teaching about medication administration and dietary requirements.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not use individuals known to the family as interpreters due to confidentiality issues.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Language barriers may involve written as well as oral communication. It is therefore important to provide written materials in the patient’s native language.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Translate satisfaction surveys into the languages of the population served.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Translate treatment plans and medication requirements into the languages of the patients who come to the facility.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Translate pamphlets on common illnesses and diseases into the languages of the patients who come to the facility.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Ensure that translated material is at a grade 6 reading level.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Create pamphlets on high-risk behaviors and occupations that are high risk.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.3 </emphasis> Availability</title><para role="Para">Availability is defined as a health-related system offering a needed service and doing so at a time that is reasonable. Patients are routinely referred to Emergency Departments for care when health-care providers’ offices and clinics are closed, adding to patient dissatisfaction and increased cost to the patient and health-care system. Pharmacy hours can be severely restricted in the evening and at night, especially in high crime unsafe neighborhoods, making their services unavailable.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Create fast-track systems with expanded hours of services in Emergency Departments that can be staffed by advanced practice nurses.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Open satellite urgent care centers making services more readily available and taking some of the workload off the Emergency Department.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide patients with a temporary supply of medications until the local pharmacy is open.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0004" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.4 </emphasis> Accessibility</title><para role="Para">Accessibility is defined as the ability of the patient to actually get to a service when needed. Transportation services may not be available, or challenging road conditions and rivers and mountains may make it difficult for people to obtain needed health-care services when no health-care provider is available in their immediate region. Although federal law requires public facilities to be accessible to people with disabilities, there are still private clinics where accessibility may be a problem. Extremely rural hospitals have critical access facilities receive cost-based reimbursement but access can still be a concern when the closest facility is 50+ miles away.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Make vans available at convenient locations and at specified times to transport patients to clinics.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide guidance for accessing services and navigating the health-care delivery system by advertising in local newspapers, in newsletters, and on public transportation systems. Local convenience stores and restaurants are additional sites to advertising services.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide telephone triage systems where patients and families can talk with a nurse to determine the acuity of a health concern.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0005" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.5 </emphasis> Affordability</title><para role="Para">Affordability is defined as having the financial resources to access and use health-care services. The service might be available, but if patients do not have financial resources, they may wait until their health condition is more severe, resulting in longer recovery times and an increase in cost.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Partner with local philanthropic agencies to provide financial services.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Involve social workers to get patients funds on a temporary basis.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0006" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.6 </emphasis> Appropriateness</title><para role="Para">Appropriateness is defined as having a service that is needed and congruent with the patient’s and family’s cultural belief system. Maternal and child services might be available, but there might be a greater need for geriatric and psychiatric services. Perhaps the critical access hospital does not have an infectious disease specialist.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Partner with larger organizations that have full-service capabilities to offer hours in rural areas on a regular basis.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Offer full-service health promotion and wellness services, testing, and education a few days each week on a regular basis.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0007" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.7 </emphasis> Organizational Accountability</title><para role="Para">Organizational accountability is defined as health-care providers’ seeking resources for their own education and learning about the cultures of the people they serve.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide cultural competence in orientation programs.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Obtain local, regional, or national organizations and personnel to provide cultural competence workshops.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Update staff annually on the practices, values, and health beliefs of the populations the organization serves.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide staff with assessment forms and guides for culturally competent assessment and interventions.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Incorporate cultural data on intake assessment forms.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide print and online resources for staff.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0008" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.8 </emphasis> Adaptability</title><para role="Para">Adaptability is defined as the health-care environment being able to change and to offer additional services when needed. For example, a mother brings her child to the clinic for an immunization. Can she get a mammogram at the same time or must she make another appointment?</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide several times during the week when full-service health promotion and wellness, services, testing, and education are available. Advertise these hours in local stores such as grocery stores, houses of worship, banks, post offices, and restaurants—including fast food restaurants.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0009" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.9 </emphasis> Acceptability</title><para role="Para">Acceptability is defined as being able to meet the requirements and provide satisfaction to a patient or family needing a health-care service. Are services and patient education offered in a language preferred by the patient?</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Match sex of the patient and health-care provider whenever requested and if available.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide ethnic concordant providers if requested whenever possible.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0010" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.10 </emphasis> Awareness</title><para role="Para">Awareness is defined as the patient and family being cognizant of needed health-care services. Is the patient aware that needed services exist in the community? The service may be available, but if patients are not aware of it, the service will not be used.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Advertise in local newspapers, in newsletters, and on public transportation systems services that are available in the community. Include convenient stores, grocery stores, houses of worship, libraries, and restaurants. Include advertisements in foreign languages where appropriate.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Partner with local and regional radio and television stations (including foreign-language stations) that advertise the services that are available to patients in the community.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0011" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.11 </emphasis> Attitudes</title><para role="Para">Attitude is defined as a state of mind or feeling about a patient’s or family’s health beliefs and values. Adverse subjective beliefs and attitudes from caregivers increase the chance that the patient will not return for needed services until the condition is more severe. Do health-care providers have negative attitudes about patients’ home-based traditional practices?</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not tell patients that they are wrong for using home-based treatments. Explain problems that might occur.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not let judgmental attitudes interfere with acceptance of patients and families.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0012" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.12 </emphasis> Approachability</title><para role="Para">Approachability is defined as the patient or family feeling it is easy to talk or deal with health-care providers. Do patients feel welcomed? Do health-care providers and receptionists greet patients in the manner in which they prefer?</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Greet patients formally until told to do otherwise.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Introduce yourself by name and position.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Maintain eye contact without staring when greeting patients and families. Note that in some cultures, people do not maintain eye contact with people in higher social positions.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0013" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.13 </emphasis> Alternative Practices</title><para role="Para">Alternative practices are defined as complementary and alternative health-care practices and traditional and folk practices. While some practices are not harmful and may be helpful, some patients may overuse folk practices and folk practitioners before seeking allopathic care.</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Incorporate nonharmful alternative practices into treatment plans.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Partner with local folk healers and educate them on when referral to allopathic care is advisable.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Refer patients to alternative folk practitioners when the condition (for example: evil eye) warrants it.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0014" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.14 </emphasis> Additional Services</title><para role="Para">Additional services are defined as value-added benefits that improve health-care access and adaptability. For example, are child- and adult-care services available if a parent must bring children or an aging parent with them for an appointment?</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Network with local organizations and churches that can volunteer sitter services with professional oversight.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Assist patients with navigating the intricacies of the health-care system.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Assist patients and families with completing bureaucratic forms.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Conduct focus groups to determine community needs.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0015" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.15 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What barriers do you see to culturally competent care in your organization? School, work, etc.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What language barriers to you see in your community such as English as a second language, educational levels, health literacy, etc.?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What affordability concerns for health care do you see in your community?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What complementary/alternative health-care practices do you use?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What complementary/alternative health-care practices are available in your community?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How do you want to be addressed? First name, last name with a title?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How do you address older people in your community? First name, last name with a title?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is public transportation readily available to health-care services in your community? What might be done to improve them?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What does your organization do when a patient needs an interpreter?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>In addition to English, what other languages are health-care instructions provided in your organization?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0003s0016" role="bibliography"><title>Bibliography</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0003s0016bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib01">Agency for Healthcare Quality and Research (2016) TeamSTEPPS enhancing safety for patients with limited English proficiency module. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ahrq.gov/teamsteppstools/"><emphasis role="RefSource">www.ahrq.gov/teamsteppstools/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib02">Betancourt J, Green A, Carrillo JE, Ananeh-Firempong A (2003) Defining cultural competence: a practical framework for addressing racial/ethnic disparities in health and health care. Public Health Rep 118:293–302<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0033-3549(04)50253-4">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0033-3549(04)50253-4</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12815076">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1497553">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib03">Center for Health Care Strategies (2016) Reducing barriers to health care: practical strategies for local organizations. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.chcs.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">www.chcs.org</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib04">Flores G (2005) The impact of medical interpreter services on the quality of health care: a systematic review. Med Care Res Rev 62(3):255–299<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1077558705275416">https://doi.org/10.1177/1077558705275416</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=15894705">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib05">Flores G, Laws MB, Mayo SJ, Zuckerman B, Abreu M, Medina L, Hardt EJ (2003) Errors in medical interpretation and their potential clinical consequences in pediatric encounters. Pediatrics 111(1):6–14<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.111.1.6">https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.111.1.6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=12509547">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib06">Giger J, Davidhizar R, Purnell L, Harden J, Phillips J, Strickland O (2007) American Academy of Nursing Expert Panel Report: developing cultural competence to eliminate health disparities in ethnic minorities and other vulnerable populations. J Transcult Nurs 18(2):95–102<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659606298618">https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659606298618</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=17416710">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib07">Institute of Medicine of the National Academies (2016) Crossing the quality chasm. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://nationalacademies.org/hmd/reports/2001/crossing-the-quality-chasm-a-new-health-system-for-the-21st-century.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://nationalacademies.org/hmd/reports/2001/crossing-the-quality-chasm-a-new-health-system-for-the-21st-century.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib08">Jacobs EA, Agger-Gupta N, Hm Chin A, Piorowski A, Hardt A (2016) Language barriers in healthcare settings. California Endowment. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.calendow.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">www.calendow.org</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib09">Office of Minority Health (2016) National Standards on Culturally and Linguistically Appropriate Services (CLAS). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/cultural-and-linguistic-competency"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/cultural-and-linguistic-competency</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib10">Purnell L (2013) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach. F. A. Davis, Philadelphia</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib11">Purnell L, Davidhizar R, Fishman D, Strickland O, Allison D (2011) A guide to developing a culturally competent organization. J Transcult Nurs 22(1):5–14<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659610387147">https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659610387147</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib12">The Joint Commission (2010) Advancing effective communication, cultural competence, and family centered care: a roadmap for hospitals. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.jointcommission.org/-/media/tjc/documents/resources/patient-safety-topics/health-equity/aroadmapforhospitalsfinalversion727pdf.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.jointcommission.org/-/media/tjc/documents/resources/patient-safety-topics/health-equity/aroadmapforhospitalsfinalversion727pdf.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0003s0016bib13">The Joint Commission (2011) Patient-centered communication standards and EPs. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.imiaweb.org/uploads/pages/275.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.imiaweb.org/uploads/pages/275.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
