<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0007" label="7">
  <title>7. People of Appalachian Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0007s0004">
    <title>7. People of Appalachian Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_7">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_7</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Mary Lou Clark Fornehed</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0007">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Whitson-Hester School of Nursing, Tennessee Technological University, Cookeville, TN, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Mary Lou Clark Fornehed</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:mcfornehed@tntech.edu">mcfornehed@tntech.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Diversity in Appalachia, Communication and dialects, Family roles and priorities, Death rituals, Alternative life styles, Diseases and health conditions, Spirituality, Substance misuse, Neonatal abstinence syndrome</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0007s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">The term <emphasis>Appalachian</emphasis> describes people born in the Appalachian mountain range and their descendants who live in or near Appalachia. Appalachia comprises 25 million people in 423 counties in 13 states—Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, Virginia, West Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Kentucky, Tennessee, Ohio, Maryland, New York, and Pennsylvania. Thus, one can see the tremendous diversity that exists is such a large region. Most of the region is rugged, mountainous terrain that is partially responsible for its residents’ values and traditions. Substandard secondary and tertiary roads as well as limited public bus, rail, and airport facilities prevent easy access to much of the area.</para>
    <para role="Para">Most Appalachians have always been a racially and ethnically diverse population with strong family ties to Native American Indians, as well as the Spanish, French, and Eastern European people. Many of those who live in Appalachia can trace their family roots back 200 years or more and it is common to find whole communities comprising of extended, related families.</para>
    <para role="Para">Appalachians are loyal, caring, family-oriented, religious, hardy, independent, honest, patriotic, and resourceful. The concept of “home” is associated with the land and the family, not a physical structure. Although many are well educated, for some education beyond elementary levels is not considered important because it is not viewed as necessary to earning a living in their traditional occupations. High unemployment and low wages necessitate that many Appalachians migrate throughout the region for better economic opportunities.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The dominant language among Appalachians is English, with many words derived from the sixteenth-century Elizabethan English. A small population may still speak Elizabethan English in their home environment. This can cause communication difficulties with health-care providers who are not familiar with the dialect. Many drop the <emphasis>g</emphasis> on words ending in <emphasis>ing</emphasis>. For example, <emphasis>writing</emphasis> becomes <emphasis>writin’</emphasis>, <emphasis>reading</emphasis> becomes <emphasis>readin’</emphasis>, and <emphasis>spelling</emphasis> becomes <emphasis>spellin’</emphasis>. Consonants may be added, and vowels may be pronounced with a diphthong that can cause difficulty to one unfamiliar with this dialect; hence, <emphasis>poosh</emphasis> for <emphasis>push</emphasis>, <emphasis>boosh</emphasis> for <emphasis>bush</emphasis>, <emphasis>warsh</emphasis> for <emphasis>wash</emphasis>, <emphasis>hiegen</emphasis> for <emphasis>hygiene</emphasis>, <emphasis>deef</emphasis> for <emphasis>deaf</emphasis>, <emphasis>welks</emphasis> for <emphasis>welts</emphasis>, <emphasis>whar</emphasis> for <emphasis>where</emphasis>, <emphasis>hit</emphasis> for <emphasis>it</emphasis>, <emphasis>hurd</emphasis> for <emphasis>heard</emphasis>, and <emphasis>your’n</emphasis> for <emphasis>your</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">If unfamiliar with the exact meaning of a word, ask the patient to elaborate.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Appalachians practice the <emphasis>ethic of neutrality</emphasis>, which helps shape communication styles, their worldview, and other aspects of the culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Appalachians may be less precise in describing emotions and are more concrete in conversations; many answer questions in a direct manner. <emphasis role="bold">Use more open-ended questions when obtaining health information and eliciting opinions and beliefs about health-care practices.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Appalachians do not easily trust or share their thoughts and feelings with <emphasis role="bold">outsiders</emphasis> and are sensitive to direct questions about personal issues. <emphasis role="bold">Sensitive topics are best approached with indirect questions and suggestions. Establish trust before asking questions that are sensitive in nature if possible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because of past experiences with large mining and timber companies, many dislike authority figures and institutions that attempt to control behavior. <emphasis role="bold">If time permits, “sit a spell” and “chat” before getting down to the business of collecting health information. To establish trust, it is necessary to demonstrate an interest in the patient’s family and other personal matters, drop hints instead of giving orders, and solicit patients’ opinions and advice.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">More traditional individuals may stand at a distance when talking with people in health-care situations. Direct eye contact from strangers may be considered as aggression or hostility.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Appalachians are comfortable with silence and when talking are likely to speak without emotion, facial expression, or gestures.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Calling a person by his or her first name with the title Miss</emphasis> (pronounced “miz,” similar to “Ms.,” when referring to women, whether single or married) <emphasis role="bold">or Mr. (for example, Miss Brenda or Mr. Erbie) denotes familiarity with respect.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Some individuals may respond better to verbal instructions and education, with reinforcement from videos rather than from printed communications.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Based on fatalistic views, some individuals believe they have little or no control over nature and that the time of death is “predetermined by God.” Thus, one frequently hears expressions such as “I’ll be there, God willing, or if the crick (creek) don’t rise.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nonverbal behaviors should be assessed when speaking with Appalachians, considering the context with which they are communicating.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When individuals are not seen because they are late for an appointment and are asked to reschedule, they may not return because of difficult transportation or feelings of rejection. <emphasis role="bold">Be flexible with appointments.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Appalachians are comfortable with silence. <emphasis role="bold">Allow a modicum of silence before initiating conversations.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rural Appalachian persons often refer to their family as “kin.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The traditional household continues to be patriarchal, however, gender roles are usually well defined.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Grandparents becoming the head of a household is a rapidly growing part of the family unit.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many of the people who live in Appalachia can trace their family roots back 200 years or more and it is common to find whole communities comprising extended, related families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Young children and adolescents in Appalachia and across the United States do experience adverse childhood experiences (ACEs) (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One’s obligation to extended family outweighs the obligations to school or work.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children, single or married, may return to their parents’ home where they are readily accepted whenever the need arises.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">The family network can be a rich resource when health teaching and assistance with personalized care are needed. The family rather than the individual must be considered as the basic treatment unit.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although alternative lifestyles are usually readily accepted in the Appalachian culture, <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to others.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.3 </emphasis> Family Decision Making at End of Life</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Caring for persons with life-limiting illness has changed in the last 20 years, creating complex situations when families must make decisions at end of life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In rural Appalachia, family plays an integral role in these decisions. <emphasis role="bold">Supporting family care at home is very important.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Communication is essential to rural Appalachians when making decisions at end of life. <emphasis role="bold">Maintaining a trusting and caring nurse practice with families and persons dying is vital.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Knowledge and economics play a large role in decision making at end of life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rural appalachians value combining folk care with traditional medicine at end of life. <emphasis role="bold">Preserving their folk care practices are vital.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rural Appalachian families may choose <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> to receive hospice care based on the desire to continue curative care. <emphasis role="bold">Becoming active with your state legislator to propose both adult and pediatric palliative and hospice care is provided in your area is important.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pediatric palliative and hospice care is very limited in rural Appalachia.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rural Appalachian families may only decide to use hospice when caregivers are exhausted or when pain and symptom management is no longer possible using folk care methods. <emphasis role="bold">Negotiations with community resources (family church) to support families in their homes at end of life can be helpful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.4 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because many Appalachians value family above all else, reporting to work may become less of a priority when a family member is ill or other family obligations are pressing. For some, the preferred work pattern is to work for an extended period of time, take some time off, and then return to work. <emphasis role="bold">Liberal leave policies for funerals and family emergencies are a necessary part of the work environment.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">More traditional individuals may stand at a distance when talking with people in the workforce. <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense if Appalachians stand at a greater distance than to what you are accustomed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A harmonious environment that fosters cooperation and agreement in decision making is valued. Health-care workers who come from outside the area may have some difficulty establishing rapport in the workplace if they lack an understanding and appreciation for Appalachian workplace etiquette. <emphasis role="bold">Familiarize yourself with the Appalachian culture of neutrality when working with Appalachian staff.</emphasis> (See Sect. <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0001s0001">7.1.1</link></emphasis>.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Appalachians are comfortable with silence, and when talking are likely to speak without emotion, facial expression, or gestures. <emphasis role="bold">Do not mistake silence and lack of facial expressions as not caring or not listening.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Appalachian ethic of neutrality and the values of individualism and non-assertiveness, with a strong people orientation, may pose a dichotomous perception at work for outsiders who may not be familiar with the Appalachian way of life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because many Appalachians align themselves more closely with horizontal rather than hierarchical relationships, they are sometimes reluctant to take on management and leadership roles. Many Appalachians prefer to work at their own pace, devising their own work rules and methods for getting the job done.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.5 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sometimes, the influence of American Indians can be observed in olive-toned skin.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Those of Scots-Irish background and others with light skin tones are at increased risk for skin cancer. Take precautions and teach patients to protect themselves from the harmful effects of the sun.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Predominant occupations, particularly farming, textile manufacturing, mining, furniture-making, and logging, place residents at increased risk for accidents and respiratory diseases such as black lung, brown lung, and emphysema.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are at greater risk for sudden infant death syndrome, congenital malformations, and infections. Only 70% of children are immunized, compared with 90% for the nation as a whole. The area also has an incidence of childhood injuries due to burns, trauma, poisoning, child neglect, and abuse that is higher than the national average. Poor oral hygiene has high rates in Appalachia.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Work with community organizations and schools to promote immunizations, oral hygiene, and prevention of childhood injuries.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Dental care is challenging, with rural Appalachians experiencing the worst oral in health in the United States.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0001ta01">7.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Appalachians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0007s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 7.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to people of Appalachian heritage</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Black lung, brown lung</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Emphysema</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hypochromic anemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Sudden infant death syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Otitis media</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitic infections</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Suicide</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.6 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">High smoking rates continue throughout Appalachia. Underage use of alcohol is widespread among teens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rural Appalachians have a disproportionately higher rate of substance misuse disorder.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Suffer from reduced mental health care.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Initiate anti-smoking campaigns in elementary schools and promote the benefits of not being overweight.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.7 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common foods are sweet potato pie; molasses candy; apple beer; gooseberry pie; pumpkin cake; and pickled beans, fruit, corn, beets, and cabbage, usually high in sodium.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Bone marrow is used to make sauces, and stomach, intestines (chitlins or chitterlings), pigs’ feet, tail, and ribs are also commonly eaten.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many recipes contain lard, and meats are commonly preserved with salt. Low-fat game meat is usually breaded and fried with lard or animal fat, negating the overall gains from these low-fat meat sources.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most diets include sweet pre-packaged drinks, Kool-Aid with added sugar, very sweet iced tea, and soda.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the benefits of low-fat preparation practices and the potential harmful effects of excess salt and refined sugar.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many children replace meals with snacks. The most common snacks are candy, salty foods, desserts, and carbonated beverages. Many adolescents skip breakfast and lunch entirely, preferring to eat snack foods. This pattern of snacking can result in deficiencies in vitamin A, iron, and calcium. <emphasis role="bold">Educate students on healthy eating and food preparation practices beginning in elementary school.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.8 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fertility control methods include birth control pills, condoms, and tubal ligation; abortion is an individual choice.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A disproportionate number of teenage pregnancies occur at a younger age among Appalachians when compared with non-Appalachians. <emphasis role="bold">Fertility practices and sexual activity, both sensitive topics for many teenagers, are areas in which outsiders unknown to the family may be more effective than health-care providers who are known.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Beliefs about pregnancy are given in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0001ta02">7.2</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The birthing mother is expected to accept childbirth as a short, intense, natural process that will bring her closer to the Earth and must be endured. <emphasis role="bold">Let the birthing mother know that pain medicine is available if she desires.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0007s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 7.2</emphasis> Beliefs about pregnancy</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Boys are carried higher and the mother’s belly appears pointy, whereas girls are carried low</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Picture-taking can cause a stillbirth</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Reaching over one’s head can cause the cord to strangle the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wearing an opal ring during pregnancy may harm the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Being frightened by a snake or eating strawberries or citrus fruit can cause birthmarks</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• If the mother experiences a tragedy, a congenital anomaly may occur</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• If the mother craves a particular food during her pregnancy, then she should eat that food or the baby will have a birthmark similar to the craved food</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.9 </emphasis> Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">With the disproportionate misuse of opioids, babies are born suffering from neonatal abstinence syndrome (NAS).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Approximately every 15 min a baby is born addicted to opioids or alcohol.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">In rural Appalachia, these women have limited access to medication assisted treatment for opioid addiction.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.10 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When death is expected, family and friends may stay through the night. <emphasis role="bold">Make accommodations for some family members to stay in the health-care facility.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Diversity in these practices can also include accepting death by some family while others continue to pray for a miracle.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Funeral services can last for 3 h. The amount of time for a service varies according to the age of the deceased. For example, the service for an elderly person is usually longer than for a younger person. The body is displayed for hours, either in the home or at the church, so that all those who wish to view the body may do so.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">At the end of the service, all who wish to view the body again may do so, with the closest relative being the last to view the body.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The deceased is usually buried in his or her best clothes. A common practice is to bury the deceased with personal possessions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Burial sites can vary. For example, the author’s “daddy” was buried in a cemetary less than a mile from his home where family and community have been buried for over 200 years. Cremation is becoming more popular, however, with the movement or outmigration of children and other family members.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After the funeral services are completed, elaborate meals are served either in the home or at the church. Services are accompanied by singing before, during, and after the service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Clergy help families through the grieving process by providing counseling and support to family members. <emphasis role="bold">Ask family if they wish to see a chaplain and help them with contacting one.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.11 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prayer for many Appalachians is a primary source of strength. Prayer is personally designed around specific church and religious beliefs and practices, which vary widely throughout the region and between and among churches of similar faith.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There is a great diversity of religious practices throughout Appalachia, such as Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, Luthern, Jehovah’s Winess, Jewish, Muslim, Mornon, Episcopalian, Mennonite, Quaker, Hindu, and Unitarian as well as people of other faiths all live and worship in Appalachia. Do not make assumptions regarding religious practices.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Churches in many parts of Appalachia serve as the social centers of the community and are a good location for health teaching.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many small churches have lay preachers instead of trained ministers. Most believe that to be a preacher, a person must have a divine calling.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some free-will churches (for example, The Holiness Church) preach against attending movies, ball games, and social functions where dancing occurs. Other sects believe in handling poisonous snakes, although this is rare, the practice continues; it is believed that the snake will not bite those who have faith.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Religious beliefs may also be of a spiritual nature, not tied to the tenets of any singular faith, and reflect the harmony of the mountains and being at one with life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some free-will churches—for example, the Holiness Church—preach against attending movies, ball games, and social functions where dancing occurs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Another practice, the ingestion of strychnine in small doses during religious services, is believed to increase sensory stimuli. Needless to say, this practice can precipitate convulsions if ingested in large enough amounts.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Meaning in life comes from the family and “living right,” which is defined by each person and usually means living right with God and in the beliefs of a chosen church.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Forming partnerships between health-care providers and faith-related organizations for health promotion and wellness, and illness and disease prevention has strong potential for improving the health of Appalachians. Respect the spiritual beliefs of Appalachians without expressing negative comments.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0012" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.12 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because self-reliance activities and nature predominate over people, many believe that it is best to let nature heal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For some who do not believe in owing money, seeing a health-care provider may be postponed until the condition is severe.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many may not see formal biomedical health-care providers until self-medicating and folk remedies have been exhausted. When they finally seek formal health care, the condition has become severe, takes longer to treat, and has a less favorable outcome.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Individuals may feel powerless regarding their own health and abdicate self-responsibility in favor of high expectations and unrealistic dependence on the health-care system, with the physician taking charge of their care completely.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Folk Medicine is a traditional part of the Appalachian culture with a wide variation in use of folk remedies that honor their elders.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When older people see a health-care provider, many expect immediate help. Physicians who dispense medications in their offices are considered helpful.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A strong belief in folk medicine is a traditional part of the culture. Using herbal medicines, poultices, and teas is common practice among individuals of all socioeconomic levels. Although many of these home remedies are not harmful, some may have deleterious effects when used to the exclusion of, or in combination with, prescription medications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain if individuals intend to use folk medicines simultaneously with prescription medications and treatment regimens so that these remedies can be incorporated into the plan of care and dialog can be undertaken to prevent adverse effects.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Integrating folk medicine into allopathic prescriptions has a greater chance of improving patients’ compliance with health prescriptions and interventions.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Bureaucratic forms foster fear and suspicion of health-care providers. <emphasis role="bold">Help patients complete bureaucratic forms if needed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be aware that patients may be especially sensitive to criticism. If the provider uses language that the patient does not understand, the provider may be perceived as “stuck up.” Decrease language barriers by decoding the jargon of the health-care environment.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Individuals with mental impairments or physical handicaps are readily accepted and not turned away. Those with a mental handicap are not perceived as crazy but rather as having “bad nerves” or being “quite turned” or “odd turned.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The traditional belief is that disability is a natural and inevitable part of the aging process. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about disability and explain that it is not an inevitable part of the aging process.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For many, pain is something that is to be endured and accepted stoically. When a person becomes ill or has pain, personal space collapses inward and the person expects to be waited on and cared for by others. <emphasis role="bold">Explain that self-care activities and taking pain medicine will hasten the healing process.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Rural children with life-limiting illness continue to follow with their primary care and nonhospice providers for symptom relief at end of life.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A 10-step pattern of health-seeking behaviors was identified see Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0001ta03">7.3</link></emphasis>:</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0007s0001ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 7.3</emphasis> Health-seeking behaviors of rural Appalachian</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">1. At the onset of symptoms, self-care practices that are usually learned from mothers are implemented</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2. When the symptoms persist, they call their mother, if she is available</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">3. If the mother is unavailable, they call the female in their kin network that is perceived as knowledgeable regarding health. If a nurse is available, they may seek the nurse’s advice</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4. If relief is not achieved, they use over-the-counter (OTC) medicine they have seen advertised on television for symptoms that most closely match their own</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">5. If that is ineffective, they use some of a neighbor’s medicine</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6. Next, they ask the local pharmacist for a recommendation; this usually marks the first encounter with a professional health-care provider. (Of course, they usually do not tell the pharmacist that they tried the neighbor’s medicine.) The pharmacist may strongly suggest that they see a health-care provider; however, on their insistence, the pharmacist may recommend another OTC medication</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">7. When no relief is achieved, they seek a local health-care provider. The provider treats them to the best of his or her ability</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">8. If the condition does not resolve, the local health-care provider refers them to a specialist in the area</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9. The specialist treats the condition to the best of his or her ability</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10. If unsuccessful, the specialist refers them to the closest tertiary medical center. These ten steps may not always follow the sequence presented here; some steps may be skipped, and not all steps are always completed. The time around these ten steps may be several years. Often by the time they are referred for definitive treatment, compensatory reserves have been depleted, and they die at large medical centers. It is essential to inquire in a nonjudgmental way about all treatments used for an illness</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0007s0001s0013" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.1.13 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Folk practitioners are primarily older women but may be men. Grannies and herb doctors are trusted and known to individuals and the community for giving more personalized care.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">For patients to become more accepting of biomedical care, it is important for health-care providers to approach individuals in an unhurried manner and engage patients in decision making and care planning.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Generally, there is no problem providing care to opposite-gender patients.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There are significant shortages of specialty providers throughout Appalachia. Barriers to seeing these specialty providers in larger urban areas include economics, long distances, lack of family or community resources for travel.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">As a large area of Appalachia is medically and health-care provider underserved, “outsider health-care providers” may be seen as disrespectful of the Appalachian culture and therefore not trusted to provide care. Trust is gained slowly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0007s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">7.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>A patient wants to incorporate ginseng with prescriptive medication. What is your advice?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What evidence do you see with the “ethic of neutrality” among Appalachians or any other group or person?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify at least three health conditions common among Appalachians. What might you do to help decrease these conditions?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What tactics might you use to help decrease the high smoking rates among Appalachians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How might you work with local community churches to teach health food practices and prevention of sexually transmitted infections?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How is <emphasis>fatalism</emphasis> displayed among Appalachians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>An overweight teenager is drinking 8–10 glasses of “sweet tea” on a daily basis. How might you encourage her to decrease the amount of “sweet tea” she drinks on a daily basis?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>A close family friend whose spouse is dying of metastatic breast cancer tells you “I am wore out and don’t know how much more I can do.” What might you do to help your friend get some respite from this situation?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0007s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0007s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib01">Appalachian Regional Commission (2023) About the Appalachian region. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.arc.gov/about-the-appalachian-region/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.arc.gov/about-the-appalachian-region/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib02">Center for Oral Health Research in Appalachia (2020) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.dental.pitt.edu/research/center-oral-health-research-appalachia"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.dental.pitt.edu/research/center-oral-health-research-appalachia</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib03">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2019a) Adverse childhood experiences (ACEs). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cdc.gov/aces/about/index.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cdc.gov/aces/about/index.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib04">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2019b) Preventing adverse childhood experiences. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/82316"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://stacks.cdc.gov/view/cdc/82316</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib05">Fornehed MLC, Mixer SJ, Lindley LC (2020) Families’ decision making at end of life in rural Appalachia. J Hosp Palliat Nurs 22(3):188–195<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000642">https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000642</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32168088">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib06">Fornehed M, Svynarenko R, Keim-Malpass J, Cozad M, Qualls K, Stone W, Lindley L (2022) Comparison between rural and urban Appalachian children in hospice care. South Med J 115(3):192–197. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.14423/SMJ.0000000000001365">https://doi.org/10.14423/SMJ.0000000000001365</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.14423/SMJ.0000000000001365">https://doi.org/10.14423/SMJ.0000000000001365</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35237837">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8908896">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib07">Hatcher J, Voigts K, Culp-Roche A, Adegboyega A, Scott T (2018) Rural grandparent headed households: a qualitative description. Online J Rural Nurs Health Care 18(1):40–62<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.14574/ojrnhc.v18i1.486">https://doi.org/10.14574/ojrnhc.v18i1.486</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=34079430">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8168369">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib08">Hufford M (2006) Folklore and folklife. In: Abramson R, Haskell J (eds) Encyclopedia of Appapachia. The University of Tennessee Press, Knoxville, pp 844–909</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib09">March of Dimes (2020) Neonatal abstinence syndrome (NAS) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.marchofdimes.org/complications/neonatal-abstinence-syndrome-(nas).aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.marchofdimes.org/complications/neonatal-abstinence-syndrome-(nas).aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib10">Mixer SJ, Fornehed MLC (2021) People of Appalachian heritage. In: Purnell LD, Fenkyl EA (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach. Cultural competence concepts in nursing care, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib11">Mixer SJ, Fornehed ML, Varney J, Lindley LC (2014) Culturally congruent end-of-life care for rural Appalachian people and their families. J Hosp Palliat Nurs 16(8):526–535. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000114">https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000114</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000114">https://doi.org/10.1097/NJH.0000000000000114</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=25544833">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4275656">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib12">National Alliance on Mental Illness [NAMI] (2018) Mental health by the numbers. Accessed 20 Jun 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nami.org/Learn-More/Mental-Health-By-the-Numbers"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nami.org/Learn-More/Mental-Health-By-the-Numbers</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib13">National Institute on Drug Abuse [NIDA] (2018a) Drugs, brains, and behavior: the science of addiction. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.drugabuse.gov/publications/drugs-brains-behavior-science-addiction/drug-misuse-addiction"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.drugabuse.gov/publications/drugs-brains-behavior-science-addiction/drug-misuse-addiction</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib14">National Institute on Drug Abuse [NIDA] (2018b) Pregnant women in Appalachia face barriers to opiod treatment. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29949454/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29949454/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib15">Tennessee Department of Health (2021) Neonatal abstinence syndrome surveillance summary week 35: August 29–September 04, 2021. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.tn.gov/health/health-program-areas/fhw/neonatal-abstinence-syndrome-/data-and-reports.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.tn.gov/health/health-program-areas/fhw/neonatal-abstinence-syndrome-/data-and-reports.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib16">U. S. Department of Health and Human Services (USDHHS) (2020a) Administration shortage designation advisor. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://datawarehouse.hrsa.gov/tools/analyzers/hpsafind.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://datawarehouse.hrsa.gov/tools/analyzers/hpsafind.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib17">U. S. Department of Health and Human Services (USDHHS) (2020b) Loan repayment. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nhsc.hrsa.gov/loan-repayment/nhsc-loan-repayment-program"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://nhsc.hrsa.gov/loan-repayment/nhsc-loan-repayment-program</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib18">Webb A (2013) African Americans in Appalachia. Accessed 26 Jan 2020<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://oxfordaasc.com/page/2527"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://oxfordaasc.com/page/2527</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0007s0003bib19">Yao N, Hector EA, Anderson R, Balkrishnan R (2017) Cancer dispartities in rural Appalachia: incidence, early detection and survivorship. J Rural Health 33:375–381<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jrh.12213">https://doi.org/10.1111/jrh.12213</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=27602545">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
