<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0009" label="9">
  <title>9. People of Brazilian Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0009s0004">
    <title>9. People of Brazilian Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_9">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_9</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Thaís Moreira São João</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0009">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">College of Nursing, University of Rhode Island, Kingston, RI, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Thaís Moreira São João</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:thais_sao-joao@uri.edu">thais_sao-joao@uri.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Family roles, Workforce issues, Death rituals, Health-care providers</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0009s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Brazil, the largest country in South America, borders all South American countries except Chile and Ecuador. Brazilians are not a homogeneous group given the diversity of the size and topography of the country as well as individuality and the variant characteristics of the culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para>
    <para role="Para">There is significant literature on Brazilian health conditions, practices, and beliefs depicting the culture of the various groups in Brazil, including arts, music, dance, and cuisine. Brazilian heritage is rich in its mixture of Portuguese, French, Dutch, German, Italian, Japanese, Chinese, African, Arab, and indigenous Brazilian Indians. Brazilians are not considered Hispanics, despite some similarities between their ethnic features and some Hispanic countries. Because Brazil is located in Latin America, they are also considered Latinxs.</para>
    <para role="Para">Most Brazilians in the United States are concentrated in communities around Boston; New York; Newark, New Jersey; and Miami. Smaller groups exist in Los Angeles, Detroit, and other locales. Larger Brazilian settlements in the United States have their churches, spiritualists, beauty shops, travel services, and support services. The exact number of Brazilians living in the United States is unknown. Approximately, 550,000 Brazilians are living in the United States, according to the most recent U. S. Census Bureau Data. Many Brazilians subsist in urban slums without privacy and hope to earn enough money to return home. Alternative lifestyles are also typical. They frequently leave children, partners, and family behind to become slaves of work in any type of situation. There are relatively few second- and third-generation Brazilians where both the mother and father have immigrated to the United States. Like other immigrants, many Brazilians are underemployed after immigrating, often giving up their professions to earn money as domestic workers, waiters, cab drivers, and other undervalued positions. Immigrants often move to large cities where many networks help find informal occupations.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilian Portuguese is the official language of Brazil and continues to dominate Brazilian communities. Dialects vary among Brazilians according to region. Dialects from Rio de Janeiro, São Paulo, and Northeast are the most frequent. Language is commonly a barrier for Brazilians to have access to culturally competent health care in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Obtain an interpreter for Brazilians when necessary.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Brazilians continue to be of “proper” old-world orientation in which true feelings are not divulged for fear of hurting the communication receiver. Everything is said to be “ <emphasis>tudo bem”</emphasis> (“fine”), almost in a stoic sense. However, in the intimate circle of family and compatriots, sharing thoughts and feelings is common. <emphasis role="bold">Establish trust before attempting to obtain sensitive information in the health history.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Young adult and adolescent Brazilians in the United States are generally more acculturated because of their desire and need to assimilate into the new culture. Sharing thoughts and feelings is more common among intragenerational groups rather than intergenerational groups.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Brazilians use touch and direct eye contact. They frequently kiss each other on the cheek when they meet and say good-bye. Men shake each other’s hands and slap each other on the back with the other hand. This gesture frequently ends in an embrace. Children are kissed, and there is much touching. The kissing of a child frequently includes the combination of a “kiss and smell.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spatial distancing is close. Facial expressions and symbolic gestures are commonplace.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para role="Para">
        <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense if Brazilians stand closer than you are accustomed.</emphasis>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Brazilians in the United States are future-oriented. In general, some are not punctual and tend to arrive “a bit” late—from minutes to hours—especially for social occasions. Everyone seems to know the behavior of tardiness and plans around it. However, those in professional circles are punctual. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain the importance of being on time for health-care appointments.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilian names are lengthy, but the common trend is to use only the first and last names. Traditionally, names appear as first name, mother’s family name, and father’s family name. “Junior” is added to a name if the son has been named after the father and “ <emphasis>Neto</emphasis>” if the son has been named after the grandfather (third generation). When one marries, they may opt to add the partner’s last name, drop their mother’s maiden name or their father’s name, or keep them both. At times “ <emphasis>de,</emphasis>” “ <emphasis>da/do,</emphasis>” or “ <emphasis>das/dos</emphasis>” is added to a name to denote “of” and seems to be done out of tradition. No rigid protocol is apparent.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There is a growing trend of single-parent families, with a prevalence of female-headed families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask the patient his or her full name and the name that is used for legal purposes.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In day-to-day relationships, people are called by their first name or <emphasis>Seu, Senhor</emphasis> (more respectful, equivalent to Sir or Mr.) preceding the first name of a man, or <emphasis>Dona</emphasis> preceding the first name of a woman (equivalent to Ms. or Madam). Mothers, grandmothers, or respected strangers are referred to as <emphasis>A Senhora,</emphasis> and fathers, grandfathers, and respected men are called <emphasis>O Senhor</emphasis>. Clinicians are addressed as <emphasis>Doutor</emphasis> or <emphasis>Doutora,</emphasis> and professors are addressed as <emphasis>Professor</emphasis> or <emphasis>Professora</emphasis>. The latter two are followed by the first name.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Address Brazilian patients formally with Mr., Mrs., Ms., or an appropriate title until told to do otherwise.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilian society is mostly sexist<emphasis>,</emphasis> with the middle and upper classes being patriarchal in structure. However, as women assert their equality, more egalitarian relationships are becoming evident. Lower socioeconomic households tend to be more matriarchal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be sure to identify the family decision-maker for health concerns.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are important to Brazilian families. If a mother and child face deportation from the United States, the baby is generally accepted into the family and often raised by the maternal grandmother. Wealthier family members may raise the child of a poorer relative, if needed. However, these children often enter the family in a second-class capacity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people live with one of their children when self-care is a concern, and nursing home placement is rare. Older people are respected, seen as family counselors, and are always addressed as <emphasis>O Senhor</emphasis> or <emphasis>A Senhora</emphasis>. They are included in family activities and usually accompany their children’s families on vacation. The extended family is also very important.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include the older members of the family and extended family in health-care decision-making.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Brazilian families are catholic. Godparents are derived from this religious view and considered an important family extension. Poor families frequently ask their <emphasis>patron</emphasis> and <emphasis>patrona</emphasis> (employer and spouse) to be godparents to their children. Godparent may support caring for the child’s clothing, schooling, and others. The godmother is called <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">comadre</emphasis></emphasis> by the mother. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Compadre</emphasis></emphasis> is used in reference to the godfather.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although historically common in the lower socioeconomic classes, middle-class households with a single-female parent are becoming increasingly common among Brazilians in the United States. Birth certificates may contain one or both names of parents If the father is absent at the birth or denies to recognize the child, the enfant will mostly receive the mother’s last name only.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Social status is very important in Brazilian society, demonstrated in the titles that people use with each other and the practice of listing both parents’ surnames. Class separation is maintained discretely by literacy status.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians, especially from the south and southeast of Brazil, have become more accepting of LGBTQIA+ relationships. However, for many, same-sex relationships carry a stigma. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to family members or others.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians value diplomacy over honesty even when they promise to attend to something the next day, knowing that it will be impossible.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask for specific dates and times for when work is to be completed.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Professional Brazilians show up for work on time. Less educated Brazilians may find it difficult to adhere to time schedules in the American workplace.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the value of punctuality in the American workforce.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The English intonation and the pronunciation of certain words are particularly difficult for some Brazilians. Brazilians generally respect authority and are frequently more comfortable in employment situations where rules and job specifications are well defined.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Speak clearly and slowly with work directions and ask for clarification to ensure the employee understands the job requirements.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many undocumented Brazilians find employment within the Brazilian community where they may never have to learn the new language. The categorization of Brazilians in the United States under the general category of “Hispanics” adds to their discomfort. <emphasis role="bold">Do not refer to Brazilians as Hispanics.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The “typical” Brazilian is a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">moreno</emphasis></emphasis> with brown skin and eyes and black or brown hair. However, individuals particularly from the southern states of Brazil may have blond hair and blue eyes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0009s0001ta01">9.1</link></emphasis> lists health conditions commonly occurring for Brazilians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. Because intestinal worms are common in Brazilian immigrants, parasitic diseases should be considered during health assessments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Interviews have substantiated that the incidence of gastrointestinal diseases increases when Brazilians first move to the United States. Changes in eating habits from the Brazilian long and ample midday dinner to American fast foods have left Brazilians in the United Stateswith gastric complaints. A genetic tendency toward lactose intolerance can contribute to some of these gastric problems. An increased incidence of allergies, especially in children of Brazilian immigrants, has also been reported.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazil represents the largest number of people living with HIV in Latin America, an endemic infection following Brazilians to the United States, and for which documentation is found. Since 2010, HIV is no longer considered grounds for inadmissibility to the United Statesand since 2013, Brazil has had much success in rolling out a program of highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) as well as pre- and post-exposer therapy (PrEP/PEP) for its citizens. Nevertheless, due to socioeconomic constraints and lack of medical insurance in the United States, many Brazilians living in the United States, and particularly those who migrate between the United Statesand Brazil, may be at greater risk for non-treatment of HIV infection or HIV treatment nonadherence.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0009s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 9.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Brazilians</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health condition</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cause</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Chagas disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Dengue fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Meningitis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Rabies</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Yellow fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Schistosomiasis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Typhoid fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hansen’s disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitic skin infections</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cholera</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactose intolerance</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
        <emphasis role="bold">Refer patients as needed to social services to help them obtain needed services.</emphasis>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because Brazilian immigrants frequently settle in Brazilian enclaves in large cities, they are subject to the same risk factors as any socially vulnerable urban subpopulation. The greatest risks are violence, drugs, and crime. Adolescents run the risk of resolving their adolescent identity crises by either banding together or joining gangs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">School officials can help decrease violence and crime among Brazilians by instituting after-school programs such as dance, music, sports, and other programs for teens.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Smoking is a high-risk behavior among Brazilians living in the United States. Among men, drinking hard liquor is also prevalent. Accessibility and use of street drugs and an individual’s desperate search for quick money are other identifiable high-risk behaviors and often involve living in crowded urban conditions where rent is inexpensive. Although many immigrants are aware of the ill effects of smoking and recreational drugs, loneliness and frustration are deterrents to stopping these habits.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation and moderation in alcohol consumption. Help patients find community support groups to decrease loneliness and smoking cessation programs in elementary school.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food is important in the celebration of all rites among Brazilians. Food and its counterpart, hunger, are often viewed as symbols that determine social relations. Food has symbolic content, is used as a reward or punishment, and establishes and maintains social relations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The mainstay of the Brazilian American’s diet continues to be rice, beans, and farina. Roast beef, fresh chicken, and seafood are sought when they are not too expensive.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Cafe de manha</emphasis> (breakfast) typically consists of bread with <emphasis>cafe com leite</emphasis> (half coffee and half hot milk). Sometimes <emphasis>cuscus</emphasis> (dry cornmeal mush) is served with milk. Fruit, fruit juices, and scrambled eggs, with or without sliced hot dogs, are common special breakfast fares among middle-class families. Sometimes sweet potatoes and yams grace the breakfast table.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>O almoco</emphasis> (dinner) is eaten at noon. This heavy meal, consisting of beans, rice, and farina, often includes <emphasis>puree</emphasis> (mashed potatoes) and <emphasis>macarrao</emphasis> (pasta). Desserts such as <emphasis>pudim de leite</emphasis> (custard), various cornmeal pastries, fruit, and <emphasis>doce</emphasis> (a sweet paste made by boiling sugar and fruit or fruit pulp) are common. A typical vegetable salad consists of finely cubed carrots, potatoes, and <emphasis>shushu</emphasis> (summer squash-like plant). A fruit salad with finely cubed fruits is also common.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians living in the U. S. are tipycally vitamin- and health-food conscious. Although this luxury is often not available to those who have immigrated for fast money, documented residents generally become health-food consumers. The preference, especially among young Brazilian women, is to rely on vitamins instead of food consumption to help them remain thin.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fruit juices are expensive, and special foods that are common to the Brazilian diet are hard to procure in the United States. Food limitations are imposed by expense and inaccessibility of Brazilian mainstay foods. However, many Brazilian communities in the United States have ethnic markets and restaurants. Large-chain supermarkets often carry a section of ethnic foods, some of which are reasonably priced.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Help patients identify low-cost nutritious, culturally acceptable foods.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although Brazil is predominantly a Catholic country, birth control is taught and used. Women are encouraged by their physicians or clinic personnel to have tubal ligations to prevent unwanted pregnancies. Immigrants in the United Statesgenerally practice birth control. Abortions of unwanted pregnancies occur as a matter of personal choice if needed. Thus, fertility practices among immigrant Brazilians are a matter of convenience with a traditional fatalistic overtone.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Help women identify acceptable methods of fertility control.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Herbal teas are used for bringing on late menstrual periods and for stimulating natural abortions. At times, single women try to become pregnant to facilitate their chance of remaining permanently in the United States. This opportunity is greatly enhanced if the child is born here and has been able to attend school.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pregnant women are encouraged not to do heavy work and not to swim. Taboos also warn against having sexual relations during pregnancy.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about sexual relations during pregnancy.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some foods are to be avoided, and specific foods are recommended during pregnancy. Taboos generally vary according to geographic region, socioeconomic status, and ethnic background. <emphasis role="bold">Determine taboo and acceptable food choices for pregnant women on an individual basis.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many mothers prefer to give their babies powdered dry milk in place of breastfeeding. Many women wish to regain their pre-pregnancy weight as soon as possible. Some women often feel that their milk is <emphasis>fraca</emphasis> (weak). Breastfeeding is linked to a social stigma that a mother who breastfeeds may often be thought of as abandoned or sexually unattractive.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information on the nutritious effects and immune properties of breastfeeding.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A postpartum woman eats chicken soup to help her body return to normal. She is also advised not to eat spicy foods or <emphasis>repadura</emphasis> (a molasses candy) and not to drink <emphasis>garapa</emphasis> (sugar water) or <emphasis>caldo de cana</emphasis> (sugar cane juice) if she breastfeeds her infant.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Support postpartum women’s nonharmful food choices and practices.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The cultural response to the death of a baby can vary widely among Brazilians, as cultural practices and beliefs are influenced by factors such as religion, regional customs, and personal beliefs. In general, Brazilians may experience profound grief and mourning following the loss of a baby, regardless of the circumstances.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">If financially possible, the families of Brazilians who die in the United Statespersonally accompany the body to Brazil for burial in the family vault. If family members cannot come to the United States, relatives meet at the airport upon the body’s arrival in Brazil.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Refer to social services and funeral homes if needed to assist with sending the body to Brazil.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Responses to death and grief depend on the family. The fatalistic expression, “It was God’s will,” helps the grieving process among the rich and the poor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people wear black for various amounts of time depending on their relationship with the family member. Frequently, the final portrait is hung in the family <emphasis>chaper</emphasis> or near the family altar, and prayers are recited. An eternal light burns.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Relatives are honored on the anniversaries of their death, both at home and at masses. Often, the family places an obituary of remembrance with or without a picture of the deceased in the local newspaper on the anniversary of the death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Support bereavement practices within their cultural context.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although 90% of Brazilians are Catholic, various Protestant sects exist. A few, including Catholics, incorporate Indian animism, African cults, Afro-Catholic syncretism, and Kardecism, a spiritualist religion embracing Eastern mysticism.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Aside from the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">curandeiros</emphasis></emphasis> (folk healers), special healers exorcise and pray for the wellness of their patients. Saints are asked for help, and people wear medals or little pouches of special powders around their necks.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Accept a wide range of religious practices among Brazilians. Integrate nonharmful religious practices into health prescriptions.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The meaning of life is found in religion, economy, fatalism, and reality. For some, life is <emphasis>uma luta</emphasis> (a battle). For others, life has an almost hedonistic attitude.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The greatest source of strength for Brazilians is their immediate and extended families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include nuclear and extended family in health-care decisions.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove medals or pouches without asking permission.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Brazilians do not talk about their illnesses unless the illnesses are very serious. Generally, illness is discussed only within the family. Many Brazilians feel that talking about an illness such as cancer negatively influences their condition.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose the patient’s health condition to others. Accept that some patients may not want to talk about their illness.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because many Brazilians tend to shun hospitals, when they are hospitalized their families accompany them and stay around the clock. The patient is often brought food from home. The family is the nucleus of responsibility for health care and is eager to participate in care. <emphasis role="bold">Include the family in the care of the patient whether in the hospital, long-term-care facility, or at home.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians residing in the United Statesare legally required to have health insurance. However, many cannot afford to pay for medical care and thereby revert to self-care.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians are known for their self-medication practices. Antibiotic, neuroleptic, antiemetic, and most other prescription drugs are easily obtained over the counter in Brazilian pharmacies. Once in the United States, it becomes difficult to obtain the many drugs readily available in Brazil. Eventually, incoming Brazilians bring medicines requested by their friends and thus maintain the circulation of medications not available to Brazilians living in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients to fully disclose the use of all medications and treatments so they do not conflict with prescription medicines.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because Brazilians tend to self-medicate, the procurement of necessary health care is often avoided or delayed. Consulting with someone who has the same condition or with friends who know someone who has a similar condition may be the first step taken. A trip to the local pharmacist may be the second. A third response may be a telephone call to Brazil asking for a particular medicine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Brazilian culture is rich in folk practices and depends on geographic region, ethnic background, socioeconomic factors, and generation. Many Brazilians prefer to use homeopathic medicines and herbs. Traditional and homeopathic pharmacies are supplemented by <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">remedios populares</emphasis></emphasis> (folk medicines) and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">remedios caseiros</emphasis></emphasis> (home medicines). <emphasis role="bold">Ask about the use of herbal remedies.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Folk remedies and traditional health-care practices are intermeshed when a serious illness may be best treated by traditional caretakers. Some take homeopathic <emphasis>“glóbulos”</emphasis>(little white balls) prepared specifically for certain ailments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">At times, support services for documented and undocumented Brazilians are hard to find for those who do not have language skills or the self-esteem to become assimilated into the culture of their newly found environments. Language is a major problem for these immigrants. They neglect to learn English and prefer to get by in their enclave community, which may be detrimental to health assessment. <emphasis role="bold">Help patients find legal assistance through social services. Obtain an interpreter when necessary.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Another barrier to health care for Brazilians in the United Statesis cost. This, combined with lack of knowledge about the health-care system and facilities. <emphasis role="bold">Refer patients in financial need to social services departments.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians generally do not like to talk about pain. However, once the emotional barrier is removed, they feel relieved to be able to discuss their discomfort. Many pain-relieving medicines are available without a prescription in Brazil. Frequently, a person requiring these on a regular basis can request that friends or friends of friends bring a supply from Brazil.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the facts about pain medicine, and encourage disclosure of all pain medicine and treatments being used.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Brazilians do not work if they are seriously ill. Sickness is a neutral role and is considered socially exempt. This role is free of guilt, blame, and responsibility. Sickness is often seen as something that just happens.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Better-educated Brazilians accept blood transfusions, organ donation, and organ transplantation. As in the United Statesand other parts of the world, acceptance depends on religious credence and individual preference.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0009s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The folk-health field has many types of health-care providers. <emphasis>Curandeiros</emphasis> are divinely gifted, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">rezadeiras</emphasis></emphasis> (praying women) help exorcise illnesses, card readers can predict fortunes, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">espiritualistas</emphasis></emphasis> are able to summon souls and spirits, <emphasis>conselheiros</emphasis> are counselors or advisors, and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">catimbozeiros</emphasis></emphasis> are sorcerers. Additionally, the <emphasis>mae</emphasis> or <emphasis>pai de santo</emphasis> are head priestesses or priests from the African-Brazilian Umbanda or Xango religion. All have the power to heal their believers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients to disclose the use of folk healers and treatments prescribed. Incorporate nonharmful practices into prescriptions.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Brazilians in the United Statestend to respect physicians and nurses. Medical education is prestigious and highly sought by aspiring university students.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0009s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">9.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the extensive name format for Brazilians? How would you address a woman and a man?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are some common health conditions of Brazilians in the United States?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Under what conditions can Brazilians with AIDS come to the United States?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify at least three barriers to health care for Brazilians in the United States.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify at least three high-risk health behaviors common among Brazilians. What might you do to help decrease these barriers?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify three Brazilian fold practitioners. What are the tenets of each?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify taboo practices for pregnant Brazilian women.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe communication practices of Brazilians with intimates. With non-intimates.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are <emphasis>comadres</emphasis> and what are their roles?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is the greatest source of strength among Brazilians?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0009s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0009s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib01">Boccolini CS, Lacerda EMA, Bertoni N, et al. (2023). Trends of breastfeeding indicators in Brazil from 1996 to 2019 and the gaps to achieve the WHO/UNICEF 2030 targets. BMJ global health, 8(9), e012529.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2023-012529">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjgh-2023-012529</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib02">Coler MS, Coler MA (2013) People of Brazilian heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach, 4th edn. F. A Davis, Philadelphia</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib03">Garcia-Cerde R, de Medeiros PFP, Silva LF, et al (2023) Use of integrative and complementary health practices by Brazilian population: results from the 2019 National Health Survey. BMC Public Health 23, 1153 <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-16083-y">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-16083-y</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib04">Gomes MR, da Cunha MS, de Souza SCI et al (2023) Reproduction of parental occupations, income and poverty in Brazil. Soc Indic Res 167:339–362. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-023-03103-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-023-03103-y</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-023-03103-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11205-023-03103-y</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib05">Roman A (2023) A Closer Look Into Brazil’s Healthcare System: What Can We Learn? Cureus, 15(5), e38390. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.38390">https://doi.org/10.7759/cureus.38390</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0009s0003bib06">Silva DFD, Paiva CE, Paiva BSR (2022) Cross-cultural adaptation and translation of the pediatric intensive care unit-quality of dying and death into Brazilian Portuguese. Adaptação transcultural Para o português brasileiro do questionário pediatric intensive care unit-quality of dying and death. Rev Bras Ter Intensiva 33(4):592–599. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.5935/0103-507X.20210086">https://doi.org/10.5935/0103-507X.20210086</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.5935/0103-507X.20210086">https://doi.org/10.5935/0103-507X.20210086</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
