<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0002" label="2"><title>2. The Purnell Model for Cultural Competence</title><sect1 id="ch0002s0004"><title>2. The Purnell Model for Cultural Competence</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_2">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_2</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0002">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">College of Health and Nursing Sciences, Excelsior University, Albany, NY, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:lpurnell@udel.edu">lpurnell@udel.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Cultural diversity, Core similarities, Caregiver, Awareness, Biases</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1 </emphasis> The Purnell Model</title><para role="Para">The Purnell Model for Cultural Competence and its organizing framework can be used in all practice settings and by all health-care providers. Moreover, it has been classified a holographic and complexity grand theory. In fact, even mediators with the American Bar Association have found the model valuable. The model is a circle, with an outlying rim representing global society, a second rim representing community, a third rim representing family, and an inner rim representing the person (Fig. <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0002s0001fg01">2.1</link></emphasis>). The interior of the circle is divided into 12 pie-shaped wedges depicting cultural domains (constructs) and their associated concepts. The dark center of the circle represents unknown phenomena. Along the bottom of the model is a jagged line representing the nonlinear concept of cultural consciousness. The 12 cultural domains and their concepts provide the organizing framework. Each domain includes concepts that need to be addressed when assessing patients in various settings. Moreover, health-care providers can use these same concepts to better understand their own cultural beliefs, attitudes, values, practices, and behaviors. An important concept to understand is that no single domain stands alone; they are all interconnected. The 12 domains are overview/heritage, communications, family roles and organization, workforce issues, biocultural ecology, high-risk health behaviors, nutrition, pregnancy and the childbearing family, death rituals, spirituality, health-care practices, and health-care practitioners.</para><figure id="ch0002s0001fg01" role="Figure"><title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Fig. 2.1</emphasis> The Purnell model for cultural competence</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="Ch0002f01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><sect2 id="ch0002s0001s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.1 </emphasis> Assessment Guide</title><para role="Para">Following each of the domains and concepts is a box that includes suggested questions to ask and observations to make when assessing patients from a cultural perspective. It is recognized that clinicians are not able to complete a thorough cultural assessment for every patient. The list of questions is extensive; thus, the clinician must determine which questions to ask according to the patient’s presenting symptoms, teaching needs, and the potential impact of culture. Furthermore, cultural values and beliefs might change over time.</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0002s0001s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2 </emphasis> Domains and Concepts</title><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s01" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title><para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the country of origin and current residence; the effects of the topography of the country of origin and the current residence on health, economics, politics, reasons for migration, educational status, and occupations both present and past. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s02" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.2 </emphasis> Communications</title><para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the dominant language, dialects, and the contextual use of the language; paralanguage variations such as voice volume, tone, intonations, inflections, and willingness to share thoughts and feelings; nonverbal communications such as eye contact, gesturing and facial expressions, use of touch, body language, spatial distancing practices, and acceptable greetings; temporality in terms of past, present, and future orientation of worldview; clock versus social time; and the amount of formality in use of names. Differences between the language spoken by the health-care provider and the patient, educational level, and health literacy are additional communication add to the communication difficulties. Effective communication is the first and probably the most important aspect of obtaining an accurate assessment. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s03" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.3 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title><para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the head of the household, gender roles (a product of biology and culture), family goals and priorities, developmental tasks of children and adolescents, roles of the aged and extended family, individual and family social status in the community, and acceptance of alternative lifestyles such as single parenting, same sex partnerships and marriage, childless marriages, and divorce. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s04" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.4 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title><para role="Para">Includes concepts related to autonomy, acculturation, assimilation, gender roles, ethnic communication styles, and health-care practices of the country of origin. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s05" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.5 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title><para role="Para">Includes physical, biological, and physiological variations among ethnic and racial groups such as skin color (the most evident) and physical differences in body habitus; genetic, hereditary, endemic, and topographical diseases; psychological makeup of individuals; and the physiological differences that affect the way drugs are metabolized by the body. In general, most diseases and illnesses can be divided into three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para><para role="Para"><emphasis>Lifestyle</emphasis> causes include cultural practices and behaviors that can generally be controlled: for example, smoking, diet, and stress.</para><para role="Para"><emphasis>Environment</emphasis> causes refer to the external environment (e.g., air and water pollution) and situations over which the individual has little or no control (e.g., presence of malarial mosquitos, exposure to chemicals and pesticides, access to care, and associated diseases and illnesses). See table below.</para><para role="Para"><emphasis>Genetic</emphasis> conditions are caused by genes.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s06" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.6 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title><para role="Para">Includes substance use and misuse of tobacco, alcohol, and recreational drugs; lack of physical activity; increased calorie consumption; nonuse of safety measures such as seat belts, helmets, and safe driving practices; and not taking safety measures to prevent contracting HIV and sexually transmitted infections. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s07" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.7 </emphasis> Nutrition</title><para role="Para">Includes the meaning of food, common foods and rituals, nutritional deficiencies and food limitations, and the use of food for health promotion and wellness, and illness and disease prevention. Multiple diseases and illnesses are a consequence of this major cultural component. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s08" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.8 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title><para role="Para">Includes culturally sanctioned and unsanctioned fertility practices; views on pregnancy; and prescriptive, restrictive, and taboo practices related to pregnancy, birthing, the postpartum period, and family involvement. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s09" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.9 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title><para role="Para">Includes how the individual and the society view death and euthanasia, rituals to prepare for death, burial practices, and bereavement behaviors. Death rituals are slow to change. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s10" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.10 </emphasis> Spirituality</title><para role="Para">Includes formal religious beliefs related to faith and affiliation and the use of prayer; behavior practices that give meaning to life; and individual sources of strength. See the following table.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s11" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title><para role="Para">Includes the focus of health care (acute versus preventive); traditional, magico-religious, and biomedical beliefs and practices; individual responsibility for health; self-medicating practices; views on mental illness, chronicity, and rehabilitation; acceptance of blood and blood products; and organ donation and transplantation. See table below.</para></sect3><sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s12" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.12 </emphasis> Health-Care Practitioners</title><para role="Para">Includes the status, use, and perceptions of traditional; magico-religious, and biomedical health-care providers; and the gender of the health-care provider. See table below.</para></sect3></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.2 </emphasis> Purnell Cultural Assessment Tool</title><para role="Para">An extensive cultural assessment is rarely completed in the clinical setting because of time and other circumstances. A seasoned clinical practitioner will know when further assessment is required. Thus, this tool should be used as a guide. Furthermore, cultures change over time. <emphasis>Shaded items in italics are part of any standard assessment. Other items may also be part of a standard assessment, depending on the organization, setting, and clinical area.</emphasis></para><table id="ch0002s0002ta01"><title>Table 1</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/><colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/><tbody><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cultural assessment tool</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Comments</para></entry></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Overview, inhabited localities, and topography</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Where do you currently live</emphasis>?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your ancestry?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Where were you born?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How many years have you lived in the United States (or other country, as appropriate)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Were your parents born in the United States (or other country, as appropriate)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What brought you (your parents/ancestors) to the United States (or other country, as appropriate)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Describe the land or countryside where you live. Is it mountainous, swampy, etc.?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Have you lived in other places in the United States/world?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What was the land or countryside like when you lived there?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your income level?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Does your income allow you to afford the essentials of life?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you have health insurance?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are you able to afford health insurance on your salary?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your educational level (formal/informal/self-taught)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What is your current occupation? If retired, ask about previous occupations</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Have you worked in other occupations? What were they?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are there (were there) any health hazards associated with your job(s)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Have you been in the military? If so, in what foreign countries were you stationed?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Communications</emphasis></para><para role="SimplePara">How do you wish to be greeted?</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What is your full name?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What is your legal name?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>By what name do you wish to be called?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What is your primary language?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you speak a specific dialect?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What other languages do you speak?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you find it difficult to share your thoughts, feelings, and ideas with family? Friends? Health-care providers?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you mind being touched by friends? Strangers? Health-care workers?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do wish to be greeted? Handshake? Nod of the head, verbal greeting only etc.?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are you usually on time for appointments?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are you usually on time for social engagements?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Observe the patient’s speech pattern. Is the speech pattern high- or low-context? Note: Patients from highly contexted cultures place greater value on silence</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Observe the patient when physical contact is made. Does he/she withdraw from the touch or become tense?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How close does the patient stand when talking with family members? With health-care providers?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Does the patient maintain eye contact when talking with the nurse/physician/etc.?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Family roles and organization</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your <emphasis>marital</emphasis>/partner status?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>How many children do you have?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who makes most of the decisions in your family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What types of decisions do(es) the female(s) in your family make?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What types of decisions do(es) the male(s) in your family make?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the duties of the women in the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the duties of the men in the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What should children do to make a good impression for themselves and for the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What should children <emphasis>not</emphasis> do to make a good impression for themselves and for the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are children forbidden to do?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What should adolescents do to make a good impression for themselves and for the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What should adolescents <emphasis>not</emphasis> do to make a good impression for themselves and for the family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are adolescents forbidden to do?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the priorities for your family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the roles of the older people in your family? Are they sought for their advice?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are there extended family members in your household? Who else lives in your household?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the roles of extended family members in this household? What gives you and your family status?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Is it acceptable to you for people to have children out of wedlock?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Is it acceptable to you for people to live together and not be married?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Is it acceptable to you for people to admit being gay or lesbian?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your sexual preference/orientation? (ask only if appropriate and later in the assessment after a modicum of trust has been established)</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Workforce issues</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you usually report to work on time?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you usually report to meetings on time?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What concerns do you have about working with someone of the opposite gender?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you consider yourself a “loyal” employee?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How long do you expect to remain in your position?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you do when you do not know how to do something related to your job?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you consider yourself to be assertive in your job?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulty does English (or another language) give you in the workforce?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulties do you have working with people older (younger) than you?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulty do you have in taking directions from someone younger/older than you?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulty do you have working with people whose religions are different from yours?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulty do you have working with people whose sexual orientation is different from yours?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What difficulty do you have working with someone whose race or ethnicity is different from yours?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you consider yourself to be an independent decision maker?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Biocultural ecology</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are you allergic to any medications?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What problems did you have when you took over-the-counter medications?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What problems did you have when you took prescription medications?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What are the major illnesses and diseases in your family?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are you aware of any genetic diseases in your family?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are the major health problems in the country from which you come (if appropriate)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>With what races and ethnic groups(s) do you identify?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Observe and document skin coloration and physical characteristics</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Observe for and document physical handicaps and disabilities</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">High-risk health behaviors</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How many cigarettes a day do you smoke?</para><para role="SimplePara">Do you smoke a pipe (or cigars)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you chew tobacco?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>For how many years have you smoked/chewed tobacco?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>How much alcohol do you drink each day? Ask about wine, beer, spirits?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How many energy drinks do you consume each day</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What recreational drugs do you use?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>How often do you use recreational drugs?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What type of exercise do you do each day?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you use seat belts?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What precautions do you take to prevent getting a sexually transmitted infections or HIV/AIDS?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Nutrition</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are you on a special diet?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are you satisfied with your weight?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Which foods do you eat to maintain your health?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Do you avoid certain foods to maintain your health?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Why do you avoid these foods?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat when you are ill?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you avoid when you are ill?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Why do you avoid these foods (if appropriate)?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">For what illnesses do you eat certain foods?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat to balance your diet?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat every day?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat every week?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat that are part of your cultural heritage?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods are high-status foods in your family/culture?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods are eaten only by men? Women? Children? Teenagers? Elderly?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How many meals do you eat each day?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What time do you eat each meal?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Do you snack between meals?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What foods do you eat when you snack?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What holidays do you celebrate?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Which foods do you eat on particular holidays?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who is present at each meal? Is the entire family present?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you primarily eat the same foods as the rest of your family?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Where do you usually buy your food?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who usually buys the food in your household?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who does the cooking in your household?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How frequently do you eat at a restaurant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">When you eat at a restaurant, in what type of restaurant do you eat?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you eat foods left from previous meals?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Where do you keep your food?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you have a refrigerator?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do you cook your food?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do you prepare meat?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do you prepare vegetables?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What type of spices do you use?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you drink with your meals?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you drink special teas?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Do you have any food allergies?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are there certain foods that cause you problems when you eat them?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How does your diet change with each season?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are your food habits different on days you work versus when you are not working?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Pregnancy and childbearing practices</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>How many children do you have?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you use for birth control?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What does it mean to you and your family when you are pregnant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What special foods do you eat when you are pregnant? Looking for pica</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What foods do you avoid when you are pregnant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What activities do you avoid when you are pregnant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you do anything special when you are pregnant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you eat non-food substances when you are pregnant?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Who do you want with you when you deliver your baby?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">In what position do you want to be when you deliver your baby?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What special foods do you eat after delivery?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What foods do you avoid after delivery?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What activities do you avoid after you deliver?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you do anything special after delivery?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who will help you with the baby after delivery?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What bathing restrictions do you have after you deliver?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you want to keep the placenta?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you do to care for the baby’s umbilical cord?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Death rituals</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What special activities need to be performed to prepare for death?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What special activities need to be performed after death?</para><para role="SimplePara">Who do you want to be with you when dying?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Would you want to know about your impending death?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What is your preferred burial practice? Interment, cremation?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How soon after death does burial occur?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do men grieve?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do women grieve?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What does death mean to you?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you believe in an afterlife?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are children included in death rituals?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Spirituality</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What is your religion?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you consider yourself deeply religious?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How many times a day do you pray?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you need in order to say your prayers?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you practice meditation such as TM, mindfulness, meditation?</para><para role="SimplePara">What gives strength and meaning to your life?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">In what spiritual practices do engage for your physical and emotional status?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Health-care practices</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>In what prevention activities do you engage to maintain your health?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who in your family takes responsibility for your health?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Who takes care of family members when they are sick?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>What over-the-counter medicines do you use?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What herbal teas and folk medicines do you use?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">For what conditions do you use herbal medicines?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you usually do when you are in pain?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How do you express your pain?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How are people in your culture viewed or treated when they have a mental illness?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How are people with physical disabilities treated in your culture?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What do you do when you are sick? Stay in bed, continue your normal activities, etc.?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What are your beliefs about rehabilitation?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">How are people with chronic illnesses viewed or treated in your culture?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are you averse to blood transfusions?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Is organ donation acceptable to you?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis>Are you listed as a potential organ donor?</emphasis></para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Would you consider having an organ transplant if needed?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Are health-care services readily available to you?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you have transportation problems accessing needed health-care services?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you feel welcome when you see a health-care professional?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What traditional health-care practices do you use? For example, mineral baths, sweating, acupuncture, acupressure, <emphasis>cai gao</emphasis>, coining, <emphasis>moxibustion</emphasis>, aromatherapy, etc.?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What home difficulties do you have that might prevent you from receiving health care?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry namest="c1" nameend="c2"><para role="SimplePara"><emphasis role="bold">Health-care practitioners</emphasis></para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What health-care providers do you see when you are ill? Physicians, nurses?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Do you prefer a same-sex health-care provider for routine health problems? For intimate care?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">What healers do you use beside physicians and nurses?</para></entry><entry/></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">For what conditions do you use healers?</para></entry><entry/></row></tbody></tgroup></table></sect1><sect1 id="ch0002s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise</title><para role="Para">Communication is probably the most import aspect of obtaining a good assessment. The onus of effective communication primarily lies with the health-care provider. Thus, providers must understand their own communication styles. When your personal communication practices differ from what is in the scholarly literature, posit why. See the variant cultural characteristics as a guide. Speak to each one of the following points:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify your cultural ancestry. If you have more than one cultural ancestry, chose the one with which you most closely associate.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explore the willingness of individuals in your culture to share thoughts, feelings, and ideas. Identify any area of discussion that would be considered taboo?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explore the practice and meaning of touch in your culture. Include information regarding touch between family members, friends, members of the opposite sex, and health-care providers.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify personal spatial and distancing strategies used when communicating with others in your culture. Discuss differences between friends and families versus strangers.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss your culture’s use of eye contact. Include information regarding practices between family members, friends, strangers, and persons of different age groups.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explore the meaning of gestures and facial expressions in your culture. Do specific gestures or facial expressions have special meanings? How are emotions displayed?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Are there acceptable ways of standing and greeting people in your culture?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the prevailing temporal relation of your culture. Is the culture’s worldview past, present, or future oriented? Temporality also include punctuality.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the impact of your culture on your nursing and/or health care. Be specific, not something that is very general.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1></chapter>
