<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0014" label="14"><title>14. People of German Heritage</title><sect1 id="ch0014s0004"><title>14. People of German Heritage</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_14">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_14</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0014">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:efenkl@fiu.edu">efenkl@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Communication, Biocultural ecology, Nutrition, Health behavior</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0014s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title><para role="Para">The Federal Republic of Germany is one of the most densely populated countries in Europe, with a population of over 80 million people. 60 million Americans are of German heritage. The first wave of German immigrants came to the United States for religious freedom and settled along the eastern seaboard. The second wave arrived between 1840 and 1860 and was fleeing political persecution, poverty, and starvation. Many worked as indentured servants. The 1930s and 1940s saw a third wave because of the rise of fascism in Germany.</para><para role="Para">Germans have a deep respect for education. Credibility, social status, and level of employment are based on educational achievement. Germans receive a stronger education than Americans, with the German undergraduate degree being equal to the American master’s degree. Great diversity exists among German Americans. Based on individuality and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>, the aggregate data in this profile might not fit some German Americans. Because many German immigrants were discriminated against in the 1940s, and after World War II, many Germans changed their names.</para><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">German is the official language of Germany; however, many German dialects exist, making it difficult for some to understand each other. German is a low-contextual language, with a greater emphasis on verbal than nonverbal communication. A high degree of social approval is shown to people whose verbal skill in expressing ideas and feelings is precise, explicit, and straightforward.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Feelings are considered private and are often difficult to share. Sharing one’s feelings with others often creates a sense of vulnerability or is looked on as a weakness.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Expressing fear, concern, happiness, or sorrow allows others a view of the personal and private self, creating a sense of discomfort and uneasiness. Therefore, philosophical discussions, hopes, and dreams are only shared with family members and close friends.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Emotions are experienced intensely but are not always expressed. “Being in control” includes harnessing one’s emotions and not revealing them to others. Newer generations are more demonstrative in sharing their thoughts, ideas, and feelings.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that just because a person may not express or display emotions that the person does not care about his or her health or the situation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">In traditional families where the father plays a dominant role, little touching occurs between the father and children. This relationship may become more demonstrative as parents and children age. Affection between a mother and her children is more evident. In other families, there is an outward expression of love from parents, grandparents, and extended family members; hugs and kisses are a “reaffirmation of love.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Whereas close friends are often extended warmth through handshakes, brief embraces, and sometimes kisses, strangers are kept at arm’s length and greeted formally. Germans generally are careful not to touch people who are not family or close friends.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most individuals place a high value on privacy.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Doors are used to protect privacy. A closed door requires a knock and an invitation to enter, regardless of whether the door is encountered in the home, business, or in-patient facility. Even looking into a room from the outside is considered a visual intrusion.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not enter a patient’s room without knocking on the door, announcing yourself, and requesting permission to enter.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Eye contact is maintained during conversations. Staring at strangers is considered rude.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">To focus on the present is to ensure the future. The past, however, is equally important, and Germans often begin their discussions with background information.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most pride themselves on their punctuality. There are rarely good excuses for tardiness or delays that disturbs the “schedule” of events. <emphasis role="bold">If the health-care provider is late with an appointment or treatment, provide a thorough explanation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Traditionally, Germans keep social relations on a formal basis. Those in authority, older people, and subordinates are always addressed formally. Only family members and close friends address each other by their first names. Younger generations or the more acculturated may be less formal in their interactions. Health-care providers will find that many patients vary widely in their observance of these rules of etiquette.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Greet patients formally unless told to do otherwise. Ask patients how they would like to be addressed.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Traditional families view the father as head of the household. In the United States, the husband and wife are more likely to make decisions mutually and share household duties.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Older people are sought for their advice and counsel, although the advice may not always be followed. They are admired for maintaining their independence and their continued contributions to society. Many live alone or with aging spouses. Helping parents or grandparents to remain in their own home is important. For those who grow dependent, moving in with children or in a retirement nursing home is a viable choice.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Include the extended family in decision-making. Consider using family members to assist with personal care and treatments when the need arises.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Prescriptive behaviors for children include using good table manners, being polite, doing what they are told, respecting their elders, sharing, paying attention in school, and doing their chores.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Prescriptive behaviors for adolescents include staying away from bad influences, obeying the rules of the home, sitting like a lady, and wearing a robe over pajamas.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Restrictive and taboo behaviors for children include talking back to adults, talking to strangers, touching another person’s possessions, and getting into trouble. Restrictive and taboo behaviors for adolescents include smoking, using drugs, chewing gum in public, having guests when parents are not at home, and having run-ins with the law.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Family and lifelong friendships are highly valued. Concern for one’s reputation is a strong value. One’s family reputation is considered part of a person’s identity and serves to preserve one’s social position.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Pregnancy outside marriage results in overt or subtle disapproval. Because families are concerned about their reputations in the community, the presence of an unwed mother taints their reputation and may result in the family being ostracized by others. If marriage follows the pregnancy, less sanctioning occurs, but the fact that pregnancy existed before marriage creates a stigma for the woman, and sometimes for the child, that may last for the rest of their lives.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Although same-sex marriage is not legal in Germany, registered partnerships for same-sex couples have been legal since 2001, which provides most of the same rights as opposite-sex married couples receive. However, many older gays and lesbians may fear exposure because of the extreme discrimination homosexuals experienced in Nazi Germany. <emphasis role="bold">When encountering gays and lesbians who need support, a referral to one of the gay and lesbian religious or community groups may be helpful. Do not disclose same-sex relationships to others.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">For Germans being on time is important. Business communication should remain formal: shaking hands daily, using the person’s title with the last name, and keeping niceties to a minimum.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">For the German manager, credentials and education confirm their credibility and lead to power. Germans, who have no translation for “fair play,” are assertive by putting other people in their place. Nuances and jargon can frustrate the individual who does not understand idioms and colloquial expressions.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Help other employees understand the formality of German employees. Explain the culture of the American workforce and legalities of “fairness.”</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0004" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Germans range from tall, blond, and blue-eyed to short, stocky, dark-haired, and brown-eyed. Because many Germans have fair complexions, skin color changes and disease manifestations can easily be observed. For those with fair skin, prolonged exposure to the sun increases the risk for skin cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Counsel patients on exposure to sun and recommend protection.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0014s0001ta01">14.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for German Americans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><table id="ch0014s0001ta01"><title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 14.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to German</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/><colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/><tbody><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Causes</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Myotonic muscular dystrophy</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Hereditary hemochromatosis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Sarcoidosis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Dupuytren’s disease</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Peyronie’s disease</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cystic fibrosis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Hemophilia</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cholelithiasis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0005" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Smoking and excessive alcohol consumption remain high-risk behaviors for many Germans. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation and limiting alcohol consumption.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most individuals enjoy the outdoors, fresh air, and exercise. Sports are played for exercise and the pleasure of participating in group activities. Encourage water sports and other activities among older people, people with disabilities, mothers, and small children. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage health club memberships for exercise.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0006" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Food is a symbol of celebration for Germans and is often equated with love. Children are rewarded for good behavior with food. Their infatuation with food can lead to overeating, resulting in obesity.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Real cream and butter are used. Gravies, sauces, fried foods, rich pastries, and sausages are only a few of the culinary favorites that are high in fat content; meats are stewed, roasted, and marinated and are often served with gravies. Vegetables (fresh is preferred) are often served in a butter sauce. Foods are also fried in butter, bacon fat, lard, or margarine. Traditional food preparation methods use high-fat ingredients that add to nutritional risks. Garlic and onions may be eaten daily to prevent heart disease.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">One-pot meals such as string beans and potatoes, cabbage and potatoes, pork and sauerkraut, stews, and soups are served as family meals. Casseroles are also popular. Foods prepared with vinegar and sugar as flavorings are also favorites. Potato salad, cucumber salad, coleslaw, pickled eggs, pickled cucumbers, cauliflower, tongue, and herring are common examples of favored foods. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage reducing portion size, overcoming harmful food rituals, and reducing fat intake.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Those who are ill receive egg custards, ginger ale, or tomato soup (without cream) to settle their stomach. Prune juice is given to relieve constipation. Soup from fresh tomato juice is used to treat a migraine headache.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Ginger ale or 7-Up relieves indigestion and settles an upset stomach. After gastrointestinal illnesses, a recuperative diet is administered to the sick family member, beginning with sips of ginger ale over ice. If this is retained, hot tea and toast are offered. The last step is coddled eggs, a variation of scrambled eggs prepared with margarine and a little milk. If these foods are tolerated, the sick person returns to the normal diet.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0007" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">All usual methods of contraception ( <emphasis>Verhütungsmittel</emphasis>) are easily available in Germany. Heterologous artificial insemination, use of contraceptive pills, and unnatural contraception are forbidden among strict Catholic Germans. Therapeutic or direct abortion is forbidden as the unjust taking of innocent life. <emphasis role="bold">Assist patients in identifying acceptable fertility practices within their religious practices.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Prescriptive practices during pregnancy include getting plenty of exercise and increasing the quantity of food to provide for the fetus. Restrictive practices during pregnancy include not stretching and not raising the arms above the head to minimize the risk of the cord wrapping around the baby’s neck.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">A child born with the membrane (the amniotic sac, also knows as a “veil”) over its head is believed to be a special child, a belief shared by many cultures.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Prescriptive practices for the postpartum period include getting plenty of exercise and fresh air for the baby. If the mother is breast-feeding, she should eat foods that enhance the production of breast milk, such as malt beverages. <emphasis role="bold">Assist mothers in identifying nonharmful foods and beverages that improve milk production.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0008" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Death is a transition to life with God. Because illness is sometimes perceived as a punishment, the duration and intensity of the dying process may be seen as a result of the quality of the life led by the person. Death is considered part of the life cycle, a natural conclusion to life. Individuals who embrace a set of religious beliefs may look forward to a life after death, often a better life.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Careful selection of the clothes to be worn by the deceased and the flowers that represent the immediate family is important. Traditionally a 3-day period of mourning is reserved after the death of a family member.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The body of the deceased is prepared and “laid out” in the home, where support from family and friends is readily available. Neighbors come to do the chores and to sit with the family of the deceased until the burial. A short service is held in the home before the body is taken to the church, where family and friends can attend a funeral service. After the church services, the body is taken to the cemetery for burial. After a short graveside service, the minister invites everyone at the graveside service to go to the home of the deceased for food.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Wearing black or dark clothing when attending a viewing or a funeral may be expected of both family and friends. Crying in public is permissible among some families, but in others the display of grief is private. <emphasis role="bold">Accept varied expressions of grief.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0009" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Major religions include Roman Catholicism, Methodism, and Lutheranism. Other religions, such as Judaism, Islam, and Buddhism, have substantial membership. <emphasis role="bold">Recognize that individuals’ decisions may vary from the formal position of their religious groups.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Prayer is used to ask for healing, for effectiveness of treatments, for strength to deal with the symptoms of the illness, and for acceptance of the outcome of the course of the illness. Prayers are often recited at the bedside with all who are present joining hands, bowing their heads, and receiving the blessing from the clergy.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most families have a family bible, which is passed down through the generations. It serves as spiritual comfort and as a reservoir of family historical data such as the dates of births, marriages, and deaths. Individual sources of strength are their beliefs in God and in nature, although they may not attend church on a regular basis.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Family loyalty, duty, and honor to the family are strong values. <emphasis role="bold">Assist patients with obtaining clergy as needed.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0010" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">In traditional families, the mother usually ensures that children receive check-ups, get immunizations, and take vitamins. Women in the family often administer folk/home remedies and treatments. German Americans use a variety of over-the-counter drugs, believing that individuals are responsible for their own health.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Common, natural folk medicines include roots, herbs, soups, poultices, and medicinal agents such as camphor, peppermint, and spirits of ammonia. Folk medicine includes “powwowing,” use of special words, and wearing charms.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Ascertain if over-the-counter and folk remedies are being used so as to determine if there are contraindications with prescription medications.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Even when experiencing pain, many individuals continue to carry out their family and work roles. Many value being stoic when experiencing pain. <emphasis role="bold">Health-care providers may not be able to identify verbal or nonverbal clues about pain among Germans. Careful interviewing and astute observation must be used to accurately assess the level of pain they experience. Explain that pain medication will help the healing process.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Mental illness may be viewed as a flaw, resulting in this group being slow to seek help because of the lack of acceptance and the stigma attached to needing help. Physical disabilities caused by injury are more acceptable than those caused by genetic problems.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">People’s discomfort with expressing personal feelings to strangers may impede the counseling process and influence the counseling methods used. Most need to discuss the past without expressing their feelings. <emphasis role="bold">Recognize that patients may not readily discuss feelings, especially during the initial counseling session.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Rehabilitation is consistent with Germans’ health beliefs because it helps return them to productive lives.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Blood transfusions, organ donation, and organ transplants are acceptable medical interventions.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0014s0001s0011" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Health-care providers hold a relatively high status among Germans. This admiration stems from the love of education and respect for authority.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most individuals accept care from either gender. Some younger and older, more traditional women prefer intimate care from a same-sex health-care provider.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0014s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">14.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Distinguish German communication practices between family and outsiders.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What protocol does Germans expect with a “closed door”?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Describe taboo behaviors for German adolescents.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Name and describe at least three genetic diseases common among Germans.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are the primary foods a German might use while recuperating from and illness?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Describe some prescriptive and restrictive German postpartum practices.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What might you do to encourage a stoic German to accept pain medication?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How is mental illness perceived by Germans?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify at least three common folk remedies commonly used by Germans.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Describe a traditional German funeral.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0014s0003" role="bibliography"><title>Bibliography</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0014s0003bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0014s0003bib01">CIA (2024) The World factbook: Germany. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/germany/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/germany/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0014s0003bib02">FKulig JC, Fan H (2013) Understanding death and dying among the low-German-speaking Mennonites. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/271954003_Understanding_Death_and_Dying_Among_the_Low-German-Speaking_Mennonites"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/271954003_Understanding_Death_and_Dying_Among_the_Low-German-Speaking_Mennonites</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0014s0003bib03">Jain A, Al Khalili Y (2023) Congenital myotonic dystrophy. In: Stat Pearls [internet]. Stat Pearls Publishing, Treasure Island, FL</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0014s0003bib04">Lehmann-Willenbrock N, Allen JA, Meinecke AL (2013) Observing culture: differences in U. S.-American and German team meeting behaviors. Psychology faculty. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://digitalcommons.unomaha.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1102&amp;context=psychfacpub"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://digitalcommons.unomaha.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi? article=1102&amp;context=psychfacpub</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0014s0003bib05">Steckler J (2013) People of German heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach, 4th edn. F. A. Davis Company, Philadelphia</bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
