<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0024" label="24">
  <title>24. People of Japanese Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0024s0004">
    <title>24. People of Japanese Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_24">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_24</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Ivette M. Hidalgo</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0024">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Carmen Rizzetto Duque</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0024">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Ivette M. Hidalgo</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:ihidalgo@fiu.edu">ihidalgo@fiu.edu</ulink></para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Carmen Rizzetto Duque</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:caduque@fiu.edu">caduque@fiu.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Heritage, Communication, Nutrition, Spirituality, Health care practice</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0024s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Nihon</emphasis>, or <emphasis role="bold">Nippon</emphasis>, as Japan is called in the Japanese language, is a 1200-mile chain of islands in the northwestern Pacific Ocean. The land is mountainous with steep ravines and prone to various geological phenomena, mostly earthquakes and active volcanos. The main islands are Hokkaido, Honshu, Shikoku, Kyushu, and Okinawa. Japan borders Russia, Korea, and China, and its modern history has, until recently, been shaped by conflict with these countries. Japanese citizens residing in North America tend to settle in large commercial and educational centers.</para>
    <para role="Para">Education is highly valued; the literacy rate in Japan is nearly 100%. About 56% of all young people go on to higher education. The alumni network primarily provides job placements; the school one attends determines, to a great extent, where one is employed after graduation. <emphasis>Issei</emphasis> (first-generation Japanese immigrants) vary widely in their English-language ability. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Nisei</emphasis></emphasis> (second-generation immigrants) and <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">sansei</emphasis></emphasis> (third-generation immigrants) were educated under the American educational system to the extent that they were permitted; for example, educational access was limited or segregated during the World War II internment of American citizens of Japanese ancestry. Acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture determine the degree of traditionality of Japanese in the United States and elsewhere. Therefore, this profile will not fit all Japanese.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese is the language of Japan with the exception of the indigenous Ainu people.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese communicate in high-context style. Meaning communication is sophisticated, subtle, and layered. Messages are both spoken and read “between the lines.” Messages may be often implied but not openly expressed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Speaking Japanese without an accent is considered a criterion for being Japanese. If other non-Japanese languages are spoken, the person is considered half-Japanese or non-Japanese.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because high-school graduates in Japan complete 6 years of English, even newer Japanese immigrants and sojourners can speak, understand, read, and write English to some extent.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">While the language barrier may be an obstacle to verbal instructions or explanations in English-speaking health-care settings, Japanese patients are likely to use written materials effectively. Simple communication tools printed in Japanese and English can aid in communication.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Men tend to speak more coarsely and women with more gentility or refinement.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Light social banter and gentle joking are a mainstay of group cohesiveness.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Polite discussion unrelated to business, often over <emphasis>o-cha</emphasis> (green tea), precedes business negotiations. Relationship-building and respect for personal privacy are important aspects of working relationships in all sectors.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Open communication is discouraged, making it difficult to learn what people think. In particular, saying “no” is considered extremely impolite; rather, one should let the matter drop.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A high value is placed on “face” and “saving face.” Asking someone to do something he or she cannot do induces loss of face or shame. For people to be shown wrong is deeply humiliating. People feel shame for themselves and their group, but they are respected when they bear shame in stoic silence. Because of ethnic homogeneity, an ingrained sensitivity to the feelings of others, and close contact with one’s family, classmates, and work group, vague and intuitive communication is well understood by fellow group members.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Giving a yes answer does not necessarily mean yes as it does in the Western context.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional Japanese exhibit considerable control over body language. Anger or dismay may be quite difficult for Westerners to detect.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Avoiding confrontation and disruption is considered an appropriate behavior for maintaining a good relationship. Expression of feelings and opinions is not often done to maintain harmony.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Smiling and laughter are common shields for embarrassment or distress.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prolonged eye contact is not polite even within families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Social touching occurs among group members but not among people who are less closely acquainted. In general, body space is respected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Intimate behavior in the presence of others is taboo, although this is changing among the younger generations and in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When people greet one another, whether for the first time or for the first time on a given day, the traditional bow is performed. The depth of the bow, its duration, and the number of repetitions reflect the relative status of the parties involved and the formality of the occasion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Overall orientation is toward the future. Punctuality is highly valued.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family names are stated first, followed by given names. Seki Noriko would be the name of a woman, Noriko of the Seki family. The family names of both men and women, married or single, are designated by the suffix <emphasis>-san</emphasis>, but one does not use that designation when referring to oneself.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women generally assume their husband’s family name upon marriage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Elders are referred to respectfully. The designation <emphasis>sensei</emphasis> (master) is a term of respect used with the names of physicians, teachers, bosses, or others in positions of authority.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Greet Japanese patients with a handshake and address them formally by their last name until invited to do otherwise.</emphasis> An offer to shake hands by a Westerner is reciprocated graciously.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The predominant family structure is nuclear. The role of wife and mother is dominant.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, the father is believed to be the authority figure and therefore decides what is right for the family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are socialized to study hard, make their best effort, and be good group members. They are taught to take care of each other, and girls are taught to take care of boys. Self-expression is not valued. They are expected to have good manners, be respectful, obedient, and do well in school.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese parents do not commonly display public affection as Western parents do.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be aware of differences in spousal relationships when assessing the quality of family dynamics and communication, sexual health, and sensitivity to risk for sexually transmitted infections.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The primary relationship within a family is the mother–child relationship, particularly that of mothers and sons. It is customary for a mother to sleep with the youngest child until that child is 10 years old or older, and when a new baby is born, the older sibling may sleep with the father or a grandparent. <emphasis role="bold">Be aware of Japanese family sleeping practices and refrain from judgmental evaluation.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Babies are not allowed to cry; they are picked up instantly. Women constantly hold their babies in carriers on their chests and sleep with them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Corporal punishment is acceptable in Japan. <emphasis role="bold">Explain US child abuse laws to patients.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional teens and college students generally do not date. They typically join clubs, membership in which is taken seriously; most social activities, such as ski trips, are club activities. Japan has the lowest incidence of teen birth in the world. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that dating holds the amount of concern for Japanese young people that it does for American teens. Do not assume that Japanese youth are well informed about sexuality and sexual health risks.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people are respected and cared for by the family in the home, if at all possible, with the eldest son being the responsible family member. <emphasis role="bold">Be sensitive to Japanese patients’ sense of obligation and commitment to older people. Help families network within the Japanese American community for both social support and for resources or for good long-term care facilities.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In Japan, a small segment of women have long lived outside the usual constraints for their gender. Women of “the floating world,” or the entertainment industry, enjoy a fair amount of autonomy. The most traditional of these, the <emphasis>geisha</emphasis>, live in all-female communal arrangements. Geisha are not prostitutes, and they are now recognized as a cultural treasure. <emphasis role="bold">Geisha entertainment industries exist in North America.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Tolerance for marriage of a Japanese person to a foreigner is less than in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A gay and lesbian social network is evident, although they are not generally talked about. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to family members.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">American practices designed to avoid liability, such as informed consent, are not routinely implemented in Japanese health-care settings. <emphasis role="bold">Explain American practices such as informed consent, the legal and professional requirements of patient autonomy, and the legalities of defensive charting on orientation.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">To be loyal and attached to a group or organization is an embedded characteristic of Japanese society. The company’s prosperity may become more important than individual prosperity making the well-being of the group more important than their self-interests.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain to new employees about the direct communication practices of Amculture.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese workers are sensitive to colleagues and superiors. Saying “no” or delivering bad news is extremely difficult; they may avoid issues or indicate that everything is fine rather than state the negative. <emphasis role="bold">Ask less acculturated Japanese to demonstrate procedures instead of asking directly if they understand the procedure.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The orientation toward family ties and intimacy, combined with beliefs based on Buddhist and Confucian traditions, leads to long-term respect for people and the development of processes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A high value is placed on “face” and “saving face.” Asking someone to do something he or she cannot do induces loss of face or shame. For people to be shown wrong is deeply humiliating. <emphasis role="bold">Use tactful communication and approach sensitive and controversial topics carefully to allow the person to “save face.”</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prolonged eye contact is not polite even within families and among friends. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that lack of eye contact means the person is not listening, is not caring, or is being less than truthful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Racial features include epicanthal skin folds that create the distinctive appearance of Asian eyes (dark in color), a broad and flat nose, “yellow” skin that varies markedly in tone, and a physique that is not too heavy. Hair is straight and naturally black, with differences in shade. <emphasis role="bold">Rely on color changes in the mucous membranes and sclerae to assess oxygenation and liver function.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Negative blood types account for less than 1% of the population.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0024s0001ta01">24.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Japanese in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. The leading causes of death are cancer, heart disease, and cerebrovascular disease.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Asthma, related to dust mites in the <emphasis>tatami</emphasis> (straw mats that cover floors in Japanese homes), is one of the few endemic diseases. The most common seasonal allergen in Japan is cedar pollen and it causes allergic rhinitis in the spring. Cedar pollinosis is termed as “a folk disease” in Japan. Asthma death rates are lower in Japan, but the prevalence of severe asthma disease is the same as that in Western countries. <emphasis role="bold">The same condition can affect patients in the United States.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Drug dosages may need to be adjusted for the physical stature of Japanese adults. Many Asians are poor metabolizers of mephenytoin and related medications, potentially leading to increased intensity and duration of the drugs’ effects. Dosages for patients with heart failure and reduced ejection fraction are on the lower end. It has been hypothesized that this is due to their small body size and increased drug sensitivity. The patient’s geographic region of residence influences the prescribed dosage as well.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be aware that most Asians tend to be more sensitive to the effects of some beta blockers, many psychotropic drugs, and alcohol.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most individuals require lower doses of some benzodiazepines and neuroleptics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Opiates may be less effective analgesics, but gastrointestinal side effects may be greater than among white people. <emphasis role="bold">Take patients’ body mass into consideration in dosing; even with that precaution, patients’ responses to drugs need to be monitored carefully.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0024s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 24.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Japanese Americans</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Heart disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Renal disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Asthma</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Vogt–Koyanagi–Harada syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Takayasu disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Acatalasemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cleft lip/palate</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Oguchi disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Smoking rates are high among Japanese and Japanese Americans. <emphasis role="bold">Children exposed to secondhand smoke may demonstrate emotional and behavioral problems. Begin teaching smoking cessation in elementary school.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Alcohol (rice wine) is part of many social rituals, such as picnics, to celebrate cherry blossoms, autumn leaves, or moon viewing. Adults commonly drink beer and sake in the home, and children may be seen purchasing alcohol.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nomikai “after-work drinks” is an accepted event meant to help spark conversation and build relationships among colleagues. Once alcohol is consumed, people can relax and speak freely; they are forgiven for what they say because of the alcohol. <emphasis role="bold">Be aware of the prevalence of smoking and heavy alcohol consumption, particularly among men. Give specific medical reasons why they must abstain, thus providing a socially acceptable excuse.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mothers’ time-honored strategy of rewarding academic diligence with candy and other treats contributes to the issue of the fitness of youth. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage mothers to offer other rewards instead of candy and non-nutritious treats for academic excellence.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Public safety consciousness is high; Japanese readily use seat belts and other safety measures such as child safety seats and helmets.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Dietary staples include rice, beef, poultry, pork, seafood, root vegetables, cabbage, persimmons, apples, and tangerines.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rice is the mainstay of the traditional diet and is included in all three meals as well as snacks. Rice consumption has greatly decreased. At breakfast, more bread is eaten compared to rice. A traditional breakfast includes fish; pickles, <emphasis>nori</emphasis> (various seaweeds used to flavor or garnish meals); a raw egg stirred into the hot rice; <emphasis>miso</emphasis> (soybean-based) soup; and tea. Some people prefer a Western breakfast of toast or cold cereal and coffee.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rice has a symbolic meaning related to the <emphasis role="bold">Shinto</emphasis> religion, analogous to the concept of the “bread of life” among Christians. A staple of schoolchildren’s <emphasis>o-bento</emphasis> (lunch box) is a white bed of rice garnished with a red plum pickle, reminiscent of the Japanese flag. Meals combine elements of land and sea.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because of women’s societal role change and children’s attendance in afterschool programs, more children are eating alone, which has led to an increased consumption of instant foods.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">It is believed that people who eat with others consume a well-balanced meal versus those who eat alone. Even though most people believe that eating with their families is important, those that are in their 20s and 50s do not eat as frequently with their families.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Eateries for children (kodomo shokudo) provide meals for free or at low cost to children and other people, such as the elderly living alone, disabled people, and people who want to talk with others about their child-rearing problems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because more people are active at night, they are eating later in the evening which has led to more individuals skipping breakfast.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Malnutrition used to be the primary problem and now obesity is prevalent. Despite the latter, Japan is one of the countries with the highest longevity. The average lifespan for males is 81.09 years and for females is 87.26 years.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Schoolchildren eat lunch or their <emphasis>o-bento</emphasis>, packed with rice, pickles, and meat or fish. A popular lunch among working people is a steaming bowl of ramen (noodles) in broth or cold noodles on a hot summer day. Instant broth, although high in sodium, is another popular quick lunch.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A traditional dinner is a pot of boiled potatoes, carrots, and pork seasoned with sweet sake, garlic, and soy sauce or a stir-fried meat and vegetable dish.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The daily intake of sweets can be high and often includes European-style desserts, pastries, and cookies, sweet bean cakes, soft drinks, and heavily sweetened coffee, which may contribute to the high incidence of tooth decay.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Increasingly, westernized food tastes, resulting in higher fat and carbohydrate intake, have contributed to the rise in obesity and associated increases in diabetes, heart disease, and premature death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Obesity and depression are increasing in Japan, and they are positively associated with high processed food intake.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There is growing public awareness that the sodium content of traditional soups and sauces contributes to the high rate of cerebrovascular accidents. <emphasis role="bold">Undertake dietary assessment on admission. Incorporate traditional food practices and preparation practices in dietary counseling sessions.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Green tea, although high in caffeine, is a good source of vitamin C. Garlic and various herbs are used widely for their medicinal properties.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals have difficulty digesting milk products because of lactose intolerance. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage use of reduced-lactose milk, tofu, and unboned fish to meet calcium needs.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Iron deficiency anemia is a concern among young women and can be alleviated with dietary counseling or dietary supplements. Nori is a traditional food source of iron.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Oral contraceptives became legal in Japan in 1999. Condoms remain the most common contraceptive method. Most women have several abortions during their married lives. It is difficult for women to obtain emergency contraceptive pills in Japan. They require a medical prescription, are expensive, and are not covered by national health insurance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japan has low infant and perinatal mortality rates. It is one of the safest countries in the world in which to give birth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pregnancy is highly valued within traditional culture as a woman’s fulfillment of her destiny. Women may enjoy the attention and pampering that they get at no other time. They may prepare themselves for the possibility of pregnancy when they become engaged and eliminate alcohol, caffeine, soft drinks, and tobacco.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Complementary and alternative medicine (CAM) are favored and implemented during pregnancy by Japanese women.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women often return to their mother’s home for the last 2 months of their pregnancy and through the first 2 months postpartum. <emphasis role="bold">Explore a woman’s expectations during pregnancy and the possibility that she might return to Japan. Finding another Japanese woman who has experienced childbearing in the United States and who can share her experiences would support the pregnant patient.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Loud noises, such as a train or a sewing machine, are thought to be bad for the baby.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Shinto shrines sell amulets for conception and easy delivery. Husbands do not commonly attend the births of their children. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make the husband feel guilty if he does not want to be in the delivery room.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese women have poor access to obstetric care and analgesia medication during labor. There is a shortage of anesthesiologists. Vaginal deliveries are usually performed without medication. To give in to pain dishonors the husband’s family. Many of the older generations of Japanese women believe that the bond between the mother and child is strengthened through the labor process and the pain that is experienced. Japan enjoys one of the world’s lowest infant mortality rates, at 1.9 per 1000 live births and neonatal mortality rate at 0.9 per 1000 live births.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, postpartum women do not bathe, shower, or wash their hair for at least the first week.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Breast-feeding is taken seriously. According to a national survey, more than 90% of Japanese women expressed a desire to breastfeed. Maternal rest and relaxation are deemed essential for success. If the mother is asleep, the grandmother feeds the baby formula. Women who give birth in the United States may resent the American expectation that they will resume self-care and child-care activities quickly. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the expectations for postpartum care; exercise sensitivity and help plan for assistance upon early discharge.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The taboo against open discussion of serious illness and death is evident. The frequency of end-of-life discussions by nurses, physicians, and care staff is minimal. Hospice care in Japan is scarce but needed due to the increased aging population and decline of three-generational households. Hospice patients may not want to be told their prognosis in order to allow a peaceful death and to spare both the patient and the family the difficulty of having to discuss the situation. They generally worry about becoming a burden and not being able to carry out their responsibilities within their social or family circle.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Hospice and palliative care professionals may have to rely on implicit behaviors to admit patients for care.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When a person is dying, the family should be notified of impending death so they can be at the dying person’s bedside. Traditionally, the eldest son has particular responsibility during this time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Japanese wake and funeral are now typically held in the funeral parlor or ceremonial hall instead of in the home. The average number of attendants has markedly declined from 180 to 46.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prior tradition is that when death occurs an altar is constructed in the home. Currently, most families do not have altars in their home and monthly memorial services are also not being done. The Japanese seldom cry at funerals, and the majority have a limited belief in the afterlife. The Buddhist belief is that if you shed your tears for the dead, the dead river will be flooded and the deceased will not be able to reach the other world. This can cause the spirit to wander and cause harm to the living. Photographs of the deceased are displayed, and floral arrangements are placed within and outside the home. A bag of money is hung around the neck of the deceased to pay the toll to cross the river to the hereafter. Visitors bring gifts of money and food for the bereaved family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Infants in Japan may have their own cemeteries and family members may or may not be expected to visit the grave thereafter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The mourning period is 49 days, the end of which is marked by a family prayer service and the serving of special rice dishes. Beliefs are common that the dead need to be remembered and that failure to do so can lead the dead to rob the living of rest; therefore, special prayer services can be conducted for the 1st, 3rd, 7th, and 13th anniversaries of the death.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many people in Japan adhere to more than one religion (Shintoism 70.5%, Buddhism 67.2%, Christianity 1.5%, and others 6.2%).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Shinto, the indigenous religion, is the locus of joyful events such as marriage and birth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many festivals are marked by offerings, parades, and a carnival on the grounds of the shrine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Buddhism has permeated artistic and intellectual life. Very few people regularly attend services, but most are registered temple members, if only to ensure a family burial plot.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One-half (1.5) percent of Japanese people are Catholic or Protestant. Most do not identify themselves solely with one religion or another and even a baptized Christian might have a Shinto wedding and a Buddhist funeral.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many accept the Buddhist belief in reincarnation; the eternal life of the soul is also recognized in the Shinto faith.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Kampo</emphasis> (healers) often set up shop in the vicinity of the temple or shrine, and a person might be seen scooping incense smoke onto an ailing body part. Prayer boards might bear requests for special healing. Newborns are taken to a shrine for a blessing. Additional blessings take place on November 15 when a child is 3, 5, or 7 years old. Visits to shrines and temples are social, recreational, and spiritual outings. Souvenirs and refreshments are usually available, and the hike into the prayer area provides exercise.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There is great tolerance for self-indulgence even during minor illnesses. Because Japanese people are less likely to express feelings verbally, this indulgence may be a way for people to affirm caring for one another nonverbally. Termination of pregnancy when the health of the fetus is in doubt is common, and most parents want medically compromised neonates not to be treated aggressively when prognoses are not favorable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Help patients with legal obligations who face value conflicts with termination of pregnancy and not treating medically compromised newborns.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The concept of <emphasis>ki</emphasis>, the life force or energy and how it flows through the body is integral to traditional Chinese healing modalities, including acupuncture. Good health requires the unobstructed flow of <emphasis>ki</emphasis> throughout the body.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The concepts of <emphasis>yin</emphasis> and <emphasis>yang</emphasis> are reflected in modern attitudes, as is the need to balance five energy sources: water, wood, fire, earth, and metal. Strategies that help to restore balance include the use of herbal medicines, bed rest, bathing, and having a massage. One traditional form of massage, <emphasis>shiatsu</emphasis> (acupressure), involves redirection of energy along the Chinese meridians by application of light pressure to what we might recognize as acupuncture points.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Leisure activities that promote health include hobbies and amusements, travel, sports, self-education, and volunteer activities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While Chinese tradition calls for a restoration of balance when one is ill, Shinto calls for purging and purification. Preoccupation with germs and dirt is not likely to interfere with daily life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditionally, in Japan, people use temples and shrines for their power to heal illness, promote health, and fulfill special wishes. <emphasis role="bold">Health-care providers who visit Japanese homes should note or even ask whether the family removes their shoes upon entering.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many pharmacies stock traditional herbal <emphasis>kampo</emphasis> preparations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most individuals make liberal use of both modern medical and traditional providers of health care. Residents in the United States have Internet and mail-order access to traditional medications, if they are not available locally. <emphasis role="bold">A complete health assessment includes inquiring about home therapies.</emphasis> Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0024s0001ta02">24.2</link></emphasis> lists common Japanese therapies.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Be sensitive to family issues that may underlie illnesses among patients. If psychotherapy is indicated, the therapist must be someone familiar with the Japanese culture. Resources may be obtained through Japanese churches or other religious organizations where Japanese people gather.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japanese high regard for the status of physicians decreases the likelihood of their asking questions or making suggestions about their care. The idea that patients should be given care options may be alien. Japanese are cautious about adopting surgery. <emphasis role="bold">Provide ample opportunity for dialogue and explain the choices that are offered. Use Japanese and Japanese American health-care providers to bridge gaps in understanding.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some individuals may need assistance in seeking care. Their verbal English skills may be an impediment to making their needs known and understanding the care they are offered, even though their ability to understand written information may be very good.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Itami</emphasis></emphasis> (pain) may not be expressed, and bearing pain is considered a virtue and a matter of family honor. Addiction is a strong taboo in Japanese society, making patients reluctant to accept pain medication.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Use a schedule of analgesic administration rather than an as-requested or patient-controlled approach to ensure adequate pain management. Explain that physiological status and healing are actually enhanced by pain control.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mental illness carries a significant stigma. Because emotional problems cannot be discussed freely, somatic manifestations are common and acceptable. Be aware that this may limit access to mental health care. The government is trying to increase knowledge about mental illness and decrease social stigma.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Handicapped people may bring shame or heartache to the family, although they are treated kindly.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Assumption of the sick role is highly tolerated by families and colleagues, and a long recuperation period is encouraged.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Donating blood is encouraged in Japanese society and blood transfusions are accepted.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Critical care and organ transplantation and donation issues need to be approached sensitively. People rely more heavily on the physician’s opinion, and the family may have difficulty negotiating the cessation of treatment. <emphasis role="bold">The family is considered a unit and health care providers must communicate with both patients and families.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Japanese are uncomfortable talking about end-of-life. <emphasis role="bold">The concept of advance directives is unknown to many. Carefully explain advance directives to patients.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0024s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 24.2</emphasis> Common Japanese therapies</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Morita</emphasis></emphasis> therapy is an indigenous strategy for addressing <emphasis>shinkei shitsu</emphasis>, excess sensitivity to the social and natural environment. Introspection is seen as harmful. <emphasis>Morita</emphasis> therapy focuses on constructive physical activity to help patients accept reality as it is</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Naikan</emphasis></emphasis> therapy is one of reflection on how much goodness and love are received from others</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0024s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Physicians, referred to as <emphasis>sensei</emphasis>, are highly esteemed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Japan has one of the largest elderly populations in the world. Individuals aged 65 years and older accounted for 28.1% of the total population in 2018, and that percentage is estimated to reach 33.3% in 2036 and 38.4% in 2065. Japan is focused on increasing the number of home care medicine practicing physicians to help meet this population’s medical needs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, health care workers endured increased stress which has led them to suffer from conditions such as depression, insomnia, and anxiety.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Self-care as a philosophy is not evident among most. Being told what to do by the physician or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kampo</emphasis></emphasis> health-care provider is expected, and his (or, occasionally, her) authority is not questioned.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nurses and nursing are highly regarded, reflecting traditional taboos against illness and impurity as well as the status of women. Currently, in Japan, nurses are well respected, even though women in general are not. In the past, nurses were not highly respected because “good women” did not touch people with an illness unless they were immediate family members. If she did touch “sick bodies,” the woman would become tainted and less pure.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Home care and the orchestration of many community-based providers may be resisted by residents who expect long recuperations in the hospital. <emphasis role="bold">Explain how the health-care delivery system works in the United States and the functions of the different health-care providers.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0024s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">24.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Japanese use the term <emphasis>sensei</emphasis> when referring to older people. What does this term mean?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Distinguish between male and female communication styles.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What does “saving face” mean? How is “saving face” used when communicating with health-care providers?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>List and explain at least three genetic health conditions common among the Japanese.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is the word for Japanese traditional healers? When might one purchase Japanese herbs?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What terms are used to distinguish three generations of Japanese?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is the traditional religion of the Japanese? What are some of its principal tenets?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the concepts of <emphasis>yin</emphasis> and <emphasis>yang</emphasis> when referred to in health care.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain <emphasis>morita</emphasis> and <emphasis>naikan</emphasis> therapies<emphasis>.</emphasis> For what conditions are they used?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is <emphasis>itami</emphasis> and how it is expressed?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0024s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0024s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib01">Adachi N (2019) Dietary transition and food and nutrition policies in Japan. Nagoya J Nutr Sci 5:1–14</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib02">Becker CB, Taniyama Y, Kondo-Arita M, Yamada S, Yamamoto K (2020) How grief, funerals, and poverty affect bereaved health, productivity, and medical dependence in Japan. OMEGA J Death Dying 85(3):669–689. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222820947573">https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222820947573</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222820947573">https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222820947573</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib03">Benedict TO (2023) Spiritual ends: religion and the heart of dying in Japan. DOAB Home. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://directory.doabooks.org/handle/20.500.12854/95731"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://directory.doabooks.org/handle/20.500.12854/95731</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib04">CIA (2023) World Factbook: Japan. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/japan/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/japan/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib05">Duranto PA, Nakayama S (2005) Japanese communication avoidance, anxiety, and uncertainty during initial encounters. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Japanese-Communication-Avoidance%252C-anxiety%252C-and-Duronto-Tsukuba/76b89f2206f1f91e8359d75b58a2ed5de7340b27"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Japanese-Communication-Avoidance%2C-anxiety%2C-and-Duronto-Tsukuba/76b89f2206f 1f91e8359d75b58a 2ed 5de7340b27</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib06">Galanti GA (2001) Japanese Americans and self-care: a lesson in cross-cultural care. West J Med 174(3):208–209<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1136/ewjm.174.3.208">https://doi.org/10.1136/ewjm.174.3.208</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=11238363">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1071320">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib07">Hamano J, Hanari K, Tamiya N (2019) Attitudes and other factors influencing end-of-life discussion by physicians, nurses, and care staff: a nationwide survey in Japan. Am J Hosp Palliat Med 37(4):258–265. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1049909119876568">https://doi.org/10.1177/1049909119876568</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1049909119876568">https://doi.org/10.1177/1049909119876568</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib08">Hidalgo I, Brooten D, Youngblut JM, Roche R, Li J, Hinds AM (2020) Practices following the death of a loved one reported by adults from 14 countries or cultural/ethnic group. Nurs Open 8(1):453–462. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.646">https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.646</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.646">https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.646</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33318853">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7729787">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib09">Hikoyeda N, Tanabe MKG (2010) Health and health care of Japanese American elders. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://geriatrics.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/downloads/ethnomed/japanese/downloads/japanese_american.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://geriatrics.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/downloads/ethnomed/japanese/downloads/japanese_american.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib10">Hirata K, Matsumoto K, Hatakeyama Y, Onishi R, Seto K, Hasegawa T (2023) Social burden of three major diseases in Japan: a time trend and future projections using the comprehensive cost of illness method. PLoS One 18(1): e0280311. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0280311">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0280311</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0280311">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0280311</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=36630469">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9833557">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib11">Imamura A (2003) The Japanese family. Asia Society. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.asianstudies.org/wp-content/uploads/the-japanese-family-faces-twenty-first-century-challenges.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.asianstudies.org/wp-content/uploads/the-japanese-family-faces-twenty-first-century-challenges.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib12">Ito M, Hattori K (2013) People of Japanese heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach, 4th edn. F. A. Davis Company, Philadelphia</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib13">Iwata H, Matsushima M, Watanabe T, Sugiyama Y, Yokobayashi K, Son D, Satoi Y, Yoshida E, Satake S, Hinata Y, Fujinuma Y (2020) The need for home care physicians in Japan—2020 to 2060. BMC Health Serv Res 20(1):752. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-020-05635-2">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-020-05635-2</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-020-05635-2">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-020-05635-2</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32799898">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7429680">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib14">Kavanaugh CM, Jong J (2020) Is Japan religious? J Stud Religion Nat Cult 14(1):152–180<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1558/jsrnc.39187">https://doi.org/10.1558/jsrnc.39187</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib15">Lai J, Ma S, Wang Y, Cai Z, Hu J, Wei N, Wu J, Du H, Chen T, Li R, Tan H, Kang L, Yao L, Huang M, Wang H, Wang G, Liu Z, Hu S (2020) Factors associated with mental health outcomes among health care workers exposed to coronavirus disease 2019. JAMA Netw Open 3(3): e203976. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.3976</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32202646">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7090843">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib16">Lem WG, Kawata KH, Kobayashi T, Oyama H (2023) Public stigma related to people with mental health conditions among Japanese company employees. J Clin Med Res 15(3):139–147. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.14740/jocmr4868">https://doi.org/10.14740/jocmr4868</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.14740/jocmr4868">https://doi.org/10.14740/jocmr4868</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37035848">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10079372">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib17">Maeda Y, Takahashi K, Yamamoto K, Tanimoto T, Kami M, Crump A (2019) Factors affecting the provision of analgesia during childbirth, Japan. Bull World Health Organ 97(9):631–636. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2471/blt.19.230128">https://doi.org/10.2471/blt.19.230128</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2471/blt.19.230128">https://doi.org/10.2471/blt.19.230128</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31474776">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6705500">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib18">Murakami K, Livingstone MBE, Sasaki S (2018) Thirteen-year trends in dietary patterns among Japanese adults in the National Health and Nutrition Survey 2003—2015: continuous westernization of the Japanese diet. Nutrients 10(994):1–15</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib19">Nagaishi M (2020) Diagnostic and dialogic organization development assumptions: their fit with Japanese culture. Organ Dev J 38(3):33–44</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib20">Nagase H (2019) Severe asthma in Japan. Allergol Int 68(2):167–171. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alit.2019.02.004">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alit.2019.02.004</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alit.2019.02.004">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.alit.2019.02.004</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30878568">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib21">OECD (2021) Tackling the mental health impact of the COVID-19 crisis: an integrated, whole-of-society response. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://oecd.org/coronavirus/policy-responses/tackling-the-mental-health-impact-of-the-covid-19-crisis-an-integrated-whole-of-society-response-0ccafa0b/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://oecd.org/coronavirus/policy-responses/tackling-the-mental-health-impact-of-the-covid-19-crisis-an-integrated-whole-of-society-response-0ccafa 0b/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib22">Pagliai G, Dinu M, Madarena MP, Bonaccio M, Iacoviello L, Sofi F (2021) Consumption of ultra-processed foods and health status: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Nutr 125(3):308–318<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114520002688">https://doi.org/10.1017/S0007114520002688</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32792031">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib23">Pappa S, Ntella V, Giannakas T, Giannakoulis VG, Papoutsi E, Katsaounou P (2020) Prevalence of depression, anxiety, and insomnia among healthcare workers during the COVID-19 pandemic: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Brain Behav Immun 88:901–907. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.026">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.026</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.026">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbi.2020.05.026</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32437915">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7206431">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib24">Parkes CM, Laungani P, Young B (1997) Death and bereavement across cultures. Routledge, London</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib25">Peng-Ng L, Chye-Goh PS (2014) Incidence of discontinuation of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors due to cough, in a primary healthcare centre in Singapore. Pub Med 55(3):146–149. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.11622/smedj.2014034">https://doi.org/10.11622/smedj.2014034</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.11622/smedj.2014034">https://doi.org/10.11622/smedj.2014034</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib26">Sato Y (2021) ‘Others’ among ‘us’: exploring racial misidentification of Japanese youth. Jpn Stud 41(3):303–321. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/10371397.2021.1982645">https://doi.org/10.1080/10371397.2021.1982645</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/10371397.2021.1982645">https://doi.org/10.1080/10371397.2021.1982645</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib27">Shinozaki N, Murakami K, Asakura K, Masayasu S, Sasaki S (2023) Consumption of highly processed foods in relation to overall diet quality among Japanese adults: a nationwide study. Public Health Nutr 26(9):1784–1797. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/s1368980023000721">https://doi.org/10.1017/s1368980023000721</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/s1368980023000721">https://doi.org/10.1017/s1368980023000721</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37092752">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10478055">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib28">Shiraishi M, Matsuzaki M, Kurihara S, Iwamoto M, Shimada M (2020) Post-breastfeeding stress response and breastfeeding self-efficacy as modifiable predictors of exclusive breastfeeding at 3 months postpartum: a prospective cohort study. BMC Pregnancy Childbirth 20(1):730. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-020-03431-8">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-020-03431-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-020-03431-8">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12884-020-03431-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33238937">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7687691">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib29">Smith O (2017) Mapped: the world’s most (and least) religious countries. The Telegraph. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/maps-and-graphics/most-religious-countries-in-the-world/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.telegraph.co.uk/travel/maps-and-graphics/most-religious-countries-in-the-world/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib30">Sonoda K, Takedai T, Salter C (2022) Communication sheet eases barriers for Japanese patients and health professionals. BMC Health Serv Res 22(1):1–6. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-022-08371-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-022-08371-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-022-08371-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-022-08371-x</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib31">Sorano S, Emmi S, Smith C (2021) Why is it so difficult to access emergency contraceptive pills in Japan? Lancet Reg Health West Pac 7:100095. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100095">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100095</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100095">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100095</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=34327420">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8315389">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib32">Statistics Bureau Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications. (2022) Statistical handbook of Japan 2021—統計局ホームページ. Statistics Bureau of Japan. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.stat.go.jp/english/data/handbook/pdf/2021all.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.stat.go.jp/english/data/handbook/pdf/2021all.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib33">Tahara M, Mashizume Y, Takahashi K (2020) Coping mechanisms: exploring strategies utilized by Japanese healthcare workers to reduce stress and improve mental health during the COVID-19 pandemic. Int J Environ Res Public Health 18(1):131. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18010131">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18010131</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18010131">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph18010131</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33375444">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7795636">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib34">Taneri P, Wehrli F, Roa-Diaz ZI, Oche AI, Dante S, Hamidreza R, Bally L, Minder B, Kiefter-de Jong J, Laine JE, Bano A, Glisic M, Muka T (2022) Association between ultra-processed food intake and all-cause mortality: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Epidemiol 191(7):1323–1335. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwac039">https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwac039</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwac039">https://doi.org/10.1093/aje/kwac039</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35231930">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib35">Teng TK, Tromp J, Tay WT, Anand I, Ouwerkerk W, Chopra V, Wander GS, Yap JJ, Mac Donald MR, Xu CF, Chia YM, Shimizu W, Richards AM, Voors A, Lam CS (2018) Prescribing patterns of evidence-based heart failure pharmacotherapy and outcomes in the Asian-HF registry: a cohort study. Lancet Glob Health 6:1008–1018<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30306-1">https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30306-1</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib36">Teng TK, Cooper L, Tay WT, Luo N, Sharma A, Whellan D, Anand I, Pina IL, Tromp J, Richards AM, Kraus WE, Connor CM, Mentz RJ, Lam CSP (2019) Association between body surface area and prescribed doses of guideline-directed medications among international patients with heart failure and reduced ejection fraction. Eur J Heart Fail 22(4):754–758. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/ejhf.1648">https://doi.org/10.1002/ejhf.1648</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/ejhf.1648">https://doi.org/10.1002/ejhf.1648</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31849161">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib37">Wada K, Ueyama J, Konishi K, Goto Y, Koda S, Mizuta F, Tamura T, Watanabe K, Ando K, Kondo T, Nagata C (2020) Associations between exposure to tobacco smoke and behavioral problems in preschool Japanese children. J Environ Public Health 2020:7591263. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/7591263">https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/7591263</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/7591263">https://doi.org/10.1155/2020/7591263</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32508936">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7244947">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib38">Watanabe A, Inoue S, Okatsu A, Eto H, Oguro M, Kataoka Y (2023) Complementary and alternative medicine use by pregnant women in Japan: a pilot survey. BMC Complement Med Ther 23(1):298. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-023-04126-1">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-023-04126-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-023-04126-1">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12906-023-04126-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37620968">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10464089">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0024s0003bib39">World Bank Open Data (2023) Health. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://data.worldbank.org/topic/health"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://data.worldbank.org/topic/health</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
