<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0021" label="21"><title>21. People of Irish Heritage</title><sect1 id="ch0021s0004"><title>21. People of Irish Heritage</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_21">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_21</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Francisco Brenes</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0021">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosa Roche</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0021">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Francisco Brenes</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:fbrenes@fiu.edu">fbrenes@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosa Roche</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:rroche@fiu.edu">rroche@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Heritage, Biocultural ecology, Health behavior, Health-care providers</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0021s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title><para role="Para">The Republic of Ireland, also known as Eire and the Emerald Isle, covers most of the island bearing its name. The remainder of the island, Northern Ireland, is part of Great Britain. During the potato famine between 1846 and 1848, thousands of Irish died from malnutrition, typhus, dysentery, and scurvy, and millions immigrated to America. Over 38 million people of Irish descent live in the United States. The Irish in America are a diverse group and vary in their beliefs according to acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para><para role="Para">Most Irish immigrants initially settled in industrial areas in northeastern United States along the Atlantic Coast. The Irish attained success in America because they spoke the same language, had the same physical appearance as other European Americans, and mastered the political system. They have made significant contributions in politics, the labor movement, the Catholic Church, the arts, and service to their country.</para><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The major languages spoken in Ireland are English and Irish (Gaelic); the latter is the official language and is spoken primarily in West Ireland. The Irish enjoy puns, riddles, limericks, and storytelling.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish accent has a nasal quality and is spoken with a strong inflection on the first syllable of a word, resulting in a loss of weak syllables. When one becomes accustomed to hearing the Irish-accented English used by newer immigrants, there is little difficulty in understanding the speaker. The Irish language is low-context, using many words to express a thought.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Some common Gaelic words and their meanings are <emphasis>shamrock</emphasis> for “emblem,” <emphasis>limer</emphasis> for “folklore character,” <emphasis>colleen</emphasis> or <emphasis>lassie</emphasis> for “girl,” <emphasis>sonsie</emphasis> or <emphasis>sonsy</emphasis> for “handsome,” <emphasis>cess</emphasis> for “luck,” <emphasis>brogue</emphasis> for “shoe,” <emphasis>dudeen</emphasis> for “pipe tobacco,” and <emphasis>paddy</emphasis> for “Irishman.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Even though most Irish delight in telling long stories, when discussing personal matters, they are much less expressive unless they are talking with close friends and family. Even then, many are still reluctant to express their innermost thoughts and feelings. <emphasis role="bold">The collaboration of care with a mental health specialist of the same ethnocultural group or of European descendant may promote the expression of feelings in the Irish with psychiatric morbidity. Timely accessible mental health care increases positive patient outcomes; however, in parts of Ireland there are delays in mental health services due to lack of referrals between general practitioners and other health-care providers.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Humility and emotional reserve are considered virtues. Displays of emotion and affection in public are avoided and are often difficult in private. To many, caring actions are more important than verbal expressions.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish use direct eye contact when speaking with each other. Not maintaining eye contact may be interpreted as a sign of disrespect, guilt, or evidence that the other person cannot be trusted.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Personal space is important to the Irish, who may require greater distance in spatial relationships than other ethnocultural groups.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Although the Irish may be less physically expressive with hand and body gesturing, facial expressions are readily displayed with frequent smiling even during times of adversity. <emphasis role="bold">Many Irish underreport symptoms of pain and use more nonpharmacological interventions before seeking medical care. Primary care providers should assess cues of physical pain in this cultural group such as grimacing, facial flushing, guarding, or blood pressure elevation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish in America, with their strong sense of tradition, are typically past-oriented. They have an allegiance to the past, their ancestors, and their history. While respecting the past, they balance “being” with “doing,” and they plan for the future by investing in education and saving money. Many Irish see time as being elastic and flexible. <emphasis role="bold">Altering cultural perceptions of punctuality requires patience and understanding. The goal is not to force punctuality but to initiate a respectful dialog and facilitate an open exchange of ideas that may lead to positive shifts in attitudes toward punctuality.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis>Mac</emphasis> before a family name means “son of,” whereas the letter <emphasis>O</emphasis> in front of a name means “descended from.”</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The traditional Irish family is nuclear, with parents and children living in the same household.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Irish families emphasize independence and self-reliance in children. Boys are allowed and expected to be more aggressive than girls, who are raised to be respectable, responsible, and resilient. Children are expected to have self-restraint and self-discipline and to be respectful and obedient to their parents, elders, and church and community figures.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Adolescent years are a time for experiencing emotional autonomy, independence, and attachment outside the family while remaining loyal to the family and maintaining the traditional Irish belief in the importance of family. Peer-group pressures at school may have a significant influence and are often incongruent with the belief systems of Irish Americans. <emphasis role="bold">Cultural differences between Irish immigrant parents and their acculturated children may cause distress in families and place the latter group at risk for conduct or behavioral disorders. Because it may be difficult for some Irish Americans to express their feelings, encourage openness between parents and teenagers.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Provisions are made in Irish homes for care of older family members, a task that becomes increasingly difficult when both parents work outside the home. Irish respect the experience of older people and seek their counsel for decision making.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Actively including the older population into decision making regarding health-care activities will help bridge the gap between age groups and foster an understanding of each other’s perspectives.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish value physical strength, endurance, work, the ability to perform work, children, and the ability to provide their children with the needed education to attain respectable socioeconomic status and professional accomplishments. Same-sex relationships continue to carry a stigma for some; however, they are becoming more acceptable in the United States and in Ireland. <emphasis role="bold">Overall, the disclosure of same-sex relationships in the Irish culture has become more accepted and supported in recent years. However, there is ongoing work needed to create an inclusive society where all individuals, regardless of their sexual orientation, feel comfortable and safe in expressing their identities and relationships.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Because cultural differences between Ireland and the United States are minimal, Irish assimilate into the workforce easily.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">When change is necessary to improve the status quo, the Irish readily relinquish traditional beliefs and adjust to the workforce. Even though the Irish are typical of past-oriented groups in other ways, they tend to question the status quo of the U. S. workforce. The Irish in America have taken many leadership positions and helped with unionization and other activities to express their collective autonomy.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The low contextual use of language, in which most of the message is in an explicit mode rather than an implicit mode, enhances pragmatic communications in the workforce.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Personal space is important and may require greater distance in spatial relationships than other ethnocultural groups. <emphasis role="bold">In the Irish culture personal space is generally respected but the concept and norms of personal space can vary depending on the context and individual preferences. Do not take offense if the Irish stand farther from you than expected.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0004" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Most Irish have dark or red hair, ruddy cheeks, and fair skin; however, other variations exist in hair and skin color. The fair complexion of the Irish places them at risk for skin cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the harmful effects of the sun and encourage the use of sun block and other types of protection from the sun.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Because mining is an important economic activity in Ireland, miners are at increased risk for respiratory diseases. In addition, the cool maritime climate of Ireland increases susceptibility to respiratory diseases. <emphasis role="bold">Assess newer immigrants who worked in mining industries for respiratory illnesses.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0021s0001ta01">21.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Irish Americans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Provide education and counseling regarding lifestyle and dietary changes to reduce risks associated with cardiovascular diseases.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Screen for osteoporosis in women in their late 60s or even younger if assessment data indicate it.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The major cause of infant mortality in Ireland is congenital abnormalities. Other conditions with a high incidence among Irish newborns are phenylketonuria (PKU), neural tube defects, and fetal alcohol syndrome.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Encourage women who give birth at home to seek PKU screening for their infants.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Explain the hazards of alcohol intake during pregnancy.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Counseling or cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) could be offered as a first-line treatment option for Irish pregnant women who misuse alcohol. Provide effective coping strategies such as deep breathing, imagery, journaling, prayer, and exercise. Explain the importance of avoiding places that promote alcohol use.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist><table id="ch0021s0001ta01"><title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 21.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Irish Americans</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/><colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/><tbody><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Health condition</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cause</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Coronary heart disease</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Phenylketonuria</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Osteoporosis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Alcoholism</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Skin cancer</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0005" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Smoking has been identified as a major risk factor causing premature mortality from cancer in Ireland and among the Irish in America. <emphasis role="bold">Primary efforts include partnering with teachers beginning in elementary school to teach the negative effects of smoking and vaping on health. Encourage patients to stop smoking, and assist them in finding smoking cessation programs with group and one-to-one counseling. Cognitive behavioral therapy combined with pharmacological interventions can assist chronic smokers with smoking cessation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The use of alcohol and IV drugs are major health problems among Irish Americans. Alcohol problems in Ireland are among the highest internationally. Alcoholism researchers generally agree that Irish ancestry puts individuals at risk for developing drinking problems. Irish pubs are popular establishments that have become synonymous with alcohol intake, lively music, and a vivacious time. <emphasis role="bold">Collaboration between government agencies, schools, communities, families, and health-care providers is essential in creating a comprehensive approach to primary prevention of alcohol and drug use in Ireland.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">This image of the Irish pub perpetuates the stereotype of Irish as heavy drinkers; do not ascribe this label to all Irish Americans. Because drinking may be a way of coping with problems, assist Irish patients in exploring more effective coping strategies, and caution them against the dangers of mixing alcohol with medications.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0006" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Irish food is unpretentious and wholesome if eaten in recommended proportions. Food is an important part of health maintenance and celebrations. Vitamins are commonly used as a dietary supplement.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Meat, potatoes, and vegetables are dietary staples. Lamb, mutton, pork, and poultry are common meats. Seafood includes salmon, mussels, mackerel, oysters, and scallops. Popular Irish dishes include Irish stew made with lamb, potatoes, and onions.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Potatoes are used in a variety of ways. <emphasis>Colcannon</emphasis> is made with hot potatoes, mashed with cabbage, butter, and milk, and seasoned with nutmeg. This dish may be served at Halloween. <emphasis>Champ</emphasis> is a popular dish made with mashed potatoes and scallions. The scallions are cut in small pieces, including the green tops, boiled in milk until tender, and then added to the mashed potatoes and served with butter. Potato cakes, made with mashed potatoes, flour, salt, and butter are shaped into patties and fried in bacon grease. Potato cakes are served hot or cold with butter and sometimes molasses or maple syrup. Another popular dish is Dublin coddle, made with bacon, pork sausage, potatoes, and onions. Oatmeal is popular in Ireland. Soda bread, another popular food, is made with flour, baking soda, salt, sugar, cream of tartar, and sour milk.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Mealtimes are important occasions for Irish families to socialize and discuss family concerns. Meals are eaten three times a day, with a large breakfast in rural areas, lunch around noon, and a late dinner. Some Irish Americans continue the afternoon tradition of “tea,” a light sandwich or biscuit with hot tea.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Because the Irish diet has the potential for being high in fats, cholesterol, and carbohydrates, assist patients with balanced food selections and preparation practices that reduce their risk of cardiovascular disease.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0007" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish believe that pregnant women who do not eat a well-balanced diet or do not eat the right kinds of food may cause the baby to be deformed.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish share the belief, common to many other ethnic groups that the mother should not reach over her head during pregnancy because the baby’s cord may wrap around its neck. A taboo behavior in the past, which some women still respect, is that if the pregnant woman sees or experiences a tragedy, a congenital anomaly may occur. <emphasis role="bold">Providing factual information and dispelling myths regarding pregnancy will help ensure the health and well-being of expectant mothers and their babies.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Eating a well-balanced diet after delivery continues to be a prescriptive practice for the Irish to ensure a healthy baby and maintain the mother’s health. Plenty of rest, fresh air, and sunshine are also important for maintaining the mother’s health. Going to bed with wet hair or wet feet causes illness in the mother.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0008" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Many Irish are fatalists and acknowledge the inevitability of death. The American emphasis on technology and dying in the hospital may be incongruent with the Irish belief that family members should stay with the dying person. <emphasis role="bold">Making arrangements for families to stay with patients in the hospital and in long-term care facilities may provide comfort and disclosure to patients and their families.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Whereas men are expected to be more stoic in their bereavement, women are usually more expressive. <emphasis role="bold">Expect and accept a wide variety of grief expression among the Irish.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">A wake continues as an important phenomenon in contemporary Irish families and is a time of melancholy, rejoicing, pain, and hopefulness. The occasion is a celebration of the person’s life.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Cremation is an individual choice, and there are no proscriptions against autopsy if required.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0009" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The predominant religion of most Irish is Catholicism: the church is a source of strength and solace. Other religions common among Irish in America include various Protestant denominations, such as the Church of Ireland, Presbyterian, Quaker, and Episcopalian.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">In times of illness, Irish Catholics receive the Sacrament of the Sick, which includes anointing, communion, and a blessing by the priest. The Eucharist, a small wafer made from flour and water, is given to the sick as the food of healing and health. Family members can participate if they wish.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">When dealing with sick individuals, it is important to prioritize and respect their preferences as it contributes to patient centered care and overall well-being.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Attending mass daily is a common practice among many traditional and devout Irish Catholic families. Prayer is an individual and private matter. In times of illness, the clergy may offer prayers with the sick as well as with the family. <emphasis role="bold">Give patients privacy for prayer whether or not a clergy member is present.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">For those who practice their religion regularly, holy day worship begins at 4 p.m. the evening preceding the holy day. All Sundays are considered holy days. The obligation to fast and abstain from meat on specified days is relinquished during times of illness.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Some wear religious medals to maintain health. <emphasis role="bold">Religious emblems provide solace and should not be removed.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0010" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Many Irish use denial as a way of coping with physical and psychological problems. The Irish view of life is illustrated in the belief that life is black with long suffering and the less said about it, the better.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many Irish ignore symptoms and delay seeking medical attention until symptoms interfere with the ability to carry out activities of daily living. Irish limit and understate problems and handle problems by using denial. Because Irish may not be very descriptive about their symptoms, treatment may be more difficult.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Encourage early intervention and seeking health professionals for illnesses. Factually explain the importance of early intervention and primary care.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Illness or injury may be linked to guilt and is considered to be the result of having done something morally wrong. Restraint is a <emphasis>modus operandi</emphasis> in the Irish culture; temptation is ever-present and must be guarded against.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most Irish believe one is obligated to use ordinary means to preserve life. Extraordinary means may be withheld to allow the person to die a natural death. The sick person and family define extraordinary means. Finances, quality of life, and effects on the family usually influence the decision. <emphasis role="bold">Arrange for a family conference to address issues and concerns in hospice and palliative care.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">In most Irish families, nuclear family members are consulted first about health problems. Mothers and older women are usually sought for their knowledge of folk practices to alleviate common problems such as colds. The Irish believe that having a strong religious faith, keeping one’s feet warm and dry, dressing warmly, eating a balanced diet, getting enough sleep, and exercising are important for staying healthy. <emphasis role="bold">Optimize compliance for reducing health risks by emphasizing these important cultural values.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Irish practices include wearing religious medals to prevent illness, using cough syrup made from honey and whiskey, taking honey and lemon for a sore throat, drinking hot tea with whiskey for a cold, drinking hot tea for nausea, drinking tea and eating toast for a cold, and putting a damp cloth on the forehead for a headache. Some folk practices may be harmful, such as the use of senna to cleanse the bowels every 8 days, eating a lot of oily foods, and avoiding seeing a physician. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients to reveal all traditional and home remedies being used to treat symptoms. Provide factual information about potentially harmful folk and traditional practices.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The behavioral response of the Irish to pain is stoicism, usually ignoring or minimizing it. <emphasis role="bold">Providing effective coping techniques including deep breathing, prayer, guided imagery and encouraging pain medication when necessary help with the healing process.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">One explanation for high rates of mental illness <emphasis role="bold">and suicide</emphasis> may be associated with the Irish having difficulty describing emotions and expressing feelings. <emphasis role="bold">Encouraging the expression of emotions and feelings can lead to healthier emotional processing and stronger social connections, thus leading to the promotion of mental health awareness and the reduction of suicide.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Blood transfusions are acceptable to most Irish Americans. Many participate in organ donation and indicate their willingness to do so on their driver’s licenses.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Obtain organ-donor status on an individual basis, be sensitive to patients and family concerns, explain procedures involved with organ donation and procurement, answer questions factually, and explain the risks involved.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0021s0001s0011" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The Irish respect all health-care professionals.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Although the Irish are not noted for being overly modest, some may prefer to receive intimate care from someone of the same gender. In general, men and women may care for each other in health-care settings as long as privacy and sensitivity are maintained.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0021s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify four common health problems among Irish Americans. Provide a recommendation to address each problem.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are some childrearing practices common among the Irish?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How are emotions displayed among the traditional Irish?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify two high-risk behaviors common among the Irish. What health education would you provide to decrease these behaviors?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>The family of a deceased patient invites you to a wake. What might you expect from a traditional wake?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What is the dominant religion among the Irish? How might you partner with the church to improve the health of the Irish?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Most Irish speak low-contexted English. What does this mean and how might it be displayed on an intake assessment?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify at least three common traditional health-care practices.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>List at least three common traditional beliefs practiced by pregnant women.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify at least common health conditions among newborns. What health teaching would you do to decrease these conditions?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>11. <emphasis role="bold">What are some cultural differences and challenges experienced by acculturated children and their Irish immigrant parents?</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>12. <emphasis role="bold">What treatment modalities are available for pregnant women at risk for alcoholism?</emphasis></para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0021s0003" role="bibliography"><title>Bibliography</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0021s0003bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib01">CIA (2023) World factbook: Ireland. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/ireland/#introduction"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/ireland/#introduction</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib02">Dejone K, Olyaei A, Lo J (2020) Alcohol use in pregnancy. Clin Obstet Gynecol 62(1):142–155<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/GRF.0000000000000414">https://doi.org/10.1097/GRF.0000000000000414</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib03">Durand H, Monahan K, Mc Guire B (2021) Prevelance and impact of dysmenorrhea among university students in Ireland. Pain Med 22(12):2835–2845<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/pm/pnab122">https://doi.org/10.1093/pm/pnab122</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33822197">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8666000">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib04">Fitzpatrick M, Newton J (2005) Profiling mental health needs: what about your Irish patients? Br J Gen Pract 55(519):739–740<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=16212846">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1562353">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib05">Ireland guide: a look at Irish language, culture, customs, and etiquette (2016) Commisceo Global. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/ireland-guide"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/ireland-guide</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib06">Irish potato famine: gone to America (2010) The history place. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.historyplace.com/worldhistory/famine/america.htm"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.historyplace.com/worldhistory/famine/america.htm</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib07">Linton J, Green A, Chilton L, Duffee J, Dilley K, Gutierrez R, Keane V, Krugman S, Mc Kelvey C, Nelson J (2019) Providing care for children in immigrant families. Pediatrics 144(3): e20192077<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2019-2077">https://doi.org/10.1542/peds.2019-2077</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31427460">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib08">Mauger A (2021) A great race of drinkers? Irish interpretations of alcoholism and drinking stereotypes, 1945–1975. Med Hist 65(1):70–89<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/mdh.2020.51">https://doi.org/10.1017/mdh.2020.51</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7739064">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib09">Myers Shim S (2013) People of Irish heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach, 4th edn. F. A. Davis, Philadelphia</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib10">Noonan M, Galvin R, Jomeen J, Doody O (2019) Public health nurses’ perinatal mental health training needs: a cross sectional survey. J Adv Nurs 75(11):2535–2547<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.14013">https://doi.org/10.1111/jan.14013</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30937923">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib11">Parents’ perspective on parenting styles and disciplining children (2010) National children’s strategy research series. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.tcd.ie/childrensresearchcentre/assets/pdf/Publications/Parents%25E2%2580%2599_Perspectives_on_parenting_styles.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.tcd.ie/childrensresearchcentre/assets/pdf/Publications/Parents’_Perspectives_on_parenting_styles.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib12">Purnell L, Foster J (2003a) Cultural aspect of alcohol use: part I. Drug Alcohol Prof 3(3):1723</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib13">Purnell L, Foster J (2003b) Cultural aspect of alcohol use: part II. Drug Alcohol Prof 2(3):3–8<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1108/17459265200300012">https://doi.org/10.1108/17459265200300012</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib14">Rapple BA (2003) Irish Americans. Countries and their culture. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.everyculture.com/multi/Ha-La/Irish-Americans.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.everyculture.com/multi/Ha-La/Irish-Americans.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0021s0003bib15">Reynolds C, Egan B, O’Malley E, Mc Mahon L, Sheehan S, Turner M (2019) Fetal growth and maternal alcohol consumption during early pregnancy. Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol 236:148–153<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejogrb.2019.02.005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejogrb.2019.02.005</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30927706">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
