<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0030" label="30"><title>30. People of Russian Heritage</title><sect1 id="ch0030s0004"><title>30. People of Russian Heritage</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_30">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_30</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tatayana Maltseva</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0030">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Irina Rozenfeld</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0030">2</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para role="AffiliationText">Dr. Kiran C. Patel College of Osteopathic Medicine, Nova University, Fort Lauderdale, FL, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tatayana Maltseva</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:bogopolt@fiu.edu">bogopolt@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Irina Rozenfeld</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:rozenfel@nova.edu">rozenfel@nova.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Russian and ethnic languages, Gender roles, Family roles, Childbearing practices, Alternative lifestyles, Diseases and health conditions, Variations in drug metabolism, High-risk health behaviors, Death rituals, Spirituality</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0030s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title><para role="Para">The Russian Federation (Russia), the largest country in the world with a population of 141.5 million, is composed of 21 republics, several regions, and multiple provinces. Russian geography consists of two continents: Asia and Europe. The multicultural diaspora of Russians shows the diversity of acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>) as well as the physical size of the country. There are approximately around 2.9 million Russian Americans living in the United States. This chapter focuses on Russians who are immigrants to the United States. Many Russians are very well educated. Given the complexity of Russian immigration, most of the information in this chapter pertains to people of Russian heritage who emigrated in the latter part of the twentieth century and at the beginning of the twenty-first century.</para><para role="Para">Everyone could obtain higher education in the former Soviet Union. However, upon arrival to the United States, many highly qualified and educated Russian immigrants have difficulty in practicing their profession and securing employment in their specialties. This contributes to diminishing their self-esteem.</para><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The official language of Russia is Russian. However, most educated Russians in the United States speak English to some extent because scientific literature in Russia is published in English.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many Russians do not understand medical language and have difficulty communicating abstract concepts or understanding American dialects. <emphasis role="bold">It is recommended to use a professional interpreter and speak slowly and clearly with a medium tone of voice and refrain from a loud conversation when communicating with Russian immigrants.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Older Jewish immigrants speak <emphasis role="bold">Yiddish</emphasis>. Younger Jewish immigrants usually do not speak Yiddish because of lack of resources in learning Yiddish in Russia.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Punctuality is a cultural standard, and many Russians arrive early for their scheduled appointments. It is customary for Russian immigrants to take medications until symptoms disappear and save the remaining for future use. Russians prepare food and essential supplies for current and future usage. It is common for them to have an abundant stock of items for many days and weeks ahead. It is also customary for Russian immigrants to borrow medications from their Russian friends and neighbors. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of taking all medications on a regular basis as prescribed, emphasize that some prescriptions can be refilled, and use only medications prescribed to them.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Direct eye-to-eye contact is maintained among family and friends. Speech is usually clear and concise in most situations. Most Russians prefer a clear action plan instead of an uncertain dialog without a plan or goals.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Eye contact is not usually maintained when speaking with government officials or authority figures. Direct eye contact during meetings and communicating with authority figures may be perceived as an invasion of privacy and may feel uncomfortable during the conversation.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians accept touch in healthcare settings but prefer not to be hugged or kissed by strangers. A handshake is acceptable.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians do not appreciate nonverbal gestures such as standing with hands inserted into pockets or arms crossed over the chest; neither do they appreciate slouching postures when being interviewed. Many Russians prefer to seek care from Russian-speaking healthcare providers. They are prone to seek multiple consultations from different providers until they develop trust with a provider.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Address Russians by their last name and title such as Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., or Dr. You can greet patients with a handshake.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Family, children, and older adults are highly respected and valued. It is customary for Russians to have extended family living together for communication and support.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Decision-making among current immigrants is usually democratic. They prefer to consult with their parents and oldest children in the decision-making process. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients who they want to be a healthcare surrogate and include them in medical decisions.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">It is common in Russian culture for grandparents to take care of their grandchildren while their parents are at work. <emphasis role="bold">Include grandparents and older family members in health education for their grandchildren.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Older parents live with their children when self-care is a concern. It is customary for Russians not to place their elderly parents in long-term care facilities. Russians ask for help from friends and other family members to take care of their aging parents.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Help families to prevent caregiver burden. Provide resources about long-term care facilities if needed and encourage the family to visit the facility before a decision is made to place a family member there.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Children of all ages are expected to succeed in school, obtain a higher education, help care for older family members, and do household chores in a timely matter.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Adolescents are not expected to engage in sexual activity. Sexual and contraceptive education is still lacking in Russia. Acculturation to the American culture and lack of traditional family roles may predispose young Russian immigrants to high-risk behaviors, unprotected sexual activities, substance usage, and unexpected pregnancy.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Divorce is accepted without stigma. Same-sex marriages are not supported by Russians even though the Russian penal code was revised in 1997 and homosexuality is no longer considered a crime. However, even now, many hide their homosexuality from the family in fear of rejection.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose sexual orientation, particularly same-sex orientation, to family members.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Russians practice positive politeness, respect, and accountability in the workplace. They value time and support the rule of work and society. Not showing up for an appointment or to work without prior notification is considered disrespectful in Russian culture.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">When negotiating work contracts or project implementation, Russians express their passion for completing the project and invest considerable time and effort in supporting decisions.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">With colleagues and friends, Russians communicate directly, which is considered a sign of respect and sincerity.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians may practice non-direct eye contact when speaking with government officials, a practice common in Russia where making eye contact with government officials could lead to questioning, invasion of personal space, or disrespect. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that the lack of eye contact means the person is not paying attention, does not care, or not providing correct information.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The tone of voice may be loud, as Russians prefer to prove their point of view by articulating loudly. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret a loud voice volume as a sign of anger.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0004" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Russians who have immigrated to the United States and elsewhere are predominately white Caucasians and have a physical structure like other white Americans, making them prone to skin cancer.</para><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Encourage the use of sunblock and instruct all family members about the dangers of skin cancer.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0030s0001ta01">30.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Russians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><table id="ch0030s0001ta01"><title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 30.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Russians</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/><colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/><tbody><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Causes</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Alcoholism</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Depression</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Gastrointestinal disorders</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Respiratory diseases</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Cancer due to radiation</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Dental disease</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Hyperlipidemia and obesity</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0005" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Both men and women have high smoking rates. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation and assist with finding smoking cessation programs.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Molecular genetic risk factors for alcohol dependence are associated in the Russian population with increased alcohol consumption, particularly in Russian males.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Intimate partner violence is common in Russia and is related mostly to high rates of alcohol consumption. Russian Americans tend not to report domestic violence to authority figures and are reluctant to seek services for domestic violence.</para><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Explain support services available for intimate partner violence and help patients gain access to the services.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Screen all newer immigrants for conditions common in their home country. Provide scientific information and assist in finding services and resources.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many who come from Ukraine, Byelorussia, and the Western part of Russia were exposed to the radiation effects of the Chernobyl disaster, resulting in a high incidence of thyroid cancer, respiratory problems, cardiovascular diseases, depression, and post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD).</para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0006" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Common foods in the Russian culture include a variety of dairy products, marinated or pickled vegetables, salads from fresh vegetables with sour cream and mayonnaise, soup made from beets (borscht), cabbage, buckwheat, potatoes, yogurt, soups, stews, and hot tea and milk with honey. Cold and iced drinks are not preferred.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Meat choices include beef, pickled herring, smoked fish, anchovies, sardines, cold tongue, chicken, ham, sausage, and salami. Bread is a must with every meal. The diet overall is high in fat, salt, and cholesterol.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Determine preferred foods and preparation practices before providing dietary counseling. Incorporate traditional foods into dietary modifications. Encourage fruits and vegetables.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0007" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Marriage and childbearing are part of the Russian culture. Contraception for Russian women is allowed without sanctions or taboos. Currently, the most popular contraceptive methods among Russian families are condoms, followed by intrauterine devices and birth control pills. Russian males do not consider vasectomies as a method of contraception. Many new immigrants may not be aware of different methods of fertility control. The abortion rate has decreased in Russia since the introduction of family planning programs by the Russian Ministry of Health.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Inform patients of the variety of common birth control methods.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Pregnant women have regular prenatal checkups, which are mandatory in Russia. During pregnancy, women are encouraged to rest. They do not perform heavy lifting, hard work, and strenuous physical activities. They are also protected from bad news or unpleasant information that can be harmful to the fetus. Pregnant women are encouraged to eat foods that are high in iron, calcium, and vitamins. Strawberries, citrus fruits, peanuts, and chocolate are avoided to prevent allergies in the newborn.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">As labor approaches, women take laxatives and enemas to facilitate delivery. Traditionally in Russia, husbands and relatives do not participate in the delivery or visit the hospital postpartum. There are no cultural restrictions for fathers or female relatives not to participate in delivery in the United States and elsewhere. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients who they wish to be involved in the delivery.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Breastfeeding is encouraged as Russians believe that breastmilk will increase the immune system of the newborn. Some women breastfeed until the infant reaches the toddler stage.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Peri care with warm water is important. A binder is worn to help the mother’s figure return to normal.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">In Russia, women receive 8 weeks of maternity leave before delivery and up to 3 years of leave after newborn delivery. <emphasis role="bold">Explain family medical leave practices for expectant parents.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0008" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Russians’ families protect a terminally ill family member. They want to be notified about imminent death first before the patient is told.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most families prefer to care for the dying family member at home.</para><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Facilitate transferring the dying person to the home if the family wishes and has the means to provide terminal care. Assist with obtaining hospice home care.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russian families believe that everything should be done to save their loved ones and often will not agree to disconnect the life support. They will not discuss advance directives, living will, durable power of attorney, or do not resuscitate procedures. They might not sign these documents. A Russian Orthodox pastor may perform a special prayer, hymn, or vigil over the deceased.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Ask permission from the family before contacting clergy.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many Russian families do not believe in cremation; most prefer interment.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Both men and women may wear black as a sign of mourning. All mirrors are covered in the deceased’s home. Expression of grief varies greatly. Russian Orthodox families mourn the death of a family member for at least 40 days. <emphasis role="bold">Recognize a wide variety of grieving and bereavement practices among Russians.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0009" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Russians are closely associated with the Orthodox Christian Church. The Russian Federation recognizes Orthodox Christianity, Buddhism, Islam, and Judaism as established religions.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians in the United States and elsewhere may or may not practice a religion or call themselves atheists. <emphasis role="bold">Discuss individual religious practices and spirituality with patients and family during the interview.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0010" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Most Russians define health as the absence of disease.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russian immigrants might not be familiar with the healthcare insurance system in the United States because Russia has a public healthcare system. Some clinics and hospitals in Russia are private, where patients pay out of pocket for their treatment. <emphasis role="bold">Explain health reimbursement procedures and elicit assistance from case managers to obtain health insurance coverage as needed.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Hospitalization lasts in Russia between 3 and 4 weeks. Some patients may expect the same on immigration. <emphasis role="bold">Explain hospitalization routines. Upon discharge refer patients to home healthcare agencies if needed and teach the family how to care for recuperating family member at home.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Single females do not do Pap tests in Russia; only married women perform them in women’s center clinics. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the significance of Pap tests and mammography, regardless of the woman’s marital status.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many individuals prefer staying warm to prevent colds and other illnesses. Most like to keep the temperature warm in their rooms. Russians may also be unwilling to apply ice or drink cold drinks with ice. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the application of ice compress in exact terms. Ask if the patient wants ice in their drinks.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most Russians consider pain as a sign of weakness and may not ask for pain medicine.</para><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Offer and encourage pain medicine and explain that it will help with the healing process.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Many Russians fear having X-ray or CT scan because of exposure to radiation. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of X-rays and CT scan procedures and that healthcare facilities use minimal radiation exposure.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Patients are not comfortable being told about terminal diagnoses or cancer because it is believed to make the condition worse. <emphasis role="bold">Inform patients about poor prognosis gradually, on their terms, and preferably in several meetings. Consult with family members first and pay attention to their verbal and nonverbal cues for readiness to hear news about a terminal illness.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Cupping is a common procedure in Russia for the treatment of respiratory infections in health care settings and at home. <emphasis role="bold">Do not mistake circular ecchymotic areas on children’s or adults’ back as abuse. Ask if they have been practicing cupping.</emphasis> Alcohol-saturated cotton or other materials may be introduced into the cup. Cotton or another material is lighted inside the cup and removed; then, the hot cup is turned upside down on the patient’s back. The skin is drawn into the cup by vacuum. The cup is pulled off the skin within 10–15 min, leaving round ecchymotic areas 1–1½ in. wide.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Common cultural practices include using herbal remedies and tinctures available from pharmacies, soaking one’s feet in warm water for a cold, gargling with salt water for a sore throat, aromatherapy for a variety of respiratory illnesses, mud and mineral baths to promote healing, and herbs and teas for fever and colds. Russians are accustomed to using sauna called <emphasis>banya</emphasis> and massage therapy to prevent respiratory illnesses and to facilitate relaxation. <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate nonharmful folk practices into allopathic prescriptions.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">A national Russian tradition is to collect mushrooms and berries from the forest. Russians practice the preservation of wild mushrooms and berries. This may contribute to botulism from mushroom preservation and diabetes from high sugar concentration in berries preserve. <emphasis role="bold">Assess traditional Russian practices of wild mushrooms and berries. Educate Russians about the prevention of botulism and diabetes.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Most Russians are accustomed to seeing multiple healthcare providers. Each provider may give prescriptions. Patients rarely inform the provider about seeing other providers. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically ask patients if they are seeing other healthcare providers and taking any prescription medications, over-the-counter medications, or traditional herbal remedies and teas.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians will not disclose mental health issues unless they are experiencing a crisis. They might present with vague somatic complaints because mental illness carries a significant stigma and punishment in Russia. Many Russians consider mental illness as a weakness. <emphasis role="bold">Screen for anxiety, depression, and post-traumatic stress disorder in immigrants.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Russians may have a great fear of contracting HIV from blood transfusions. Most Russians do not believe in organ donation. <emphasis role="bold">Explain safety procedures with blood transfusions and organ donation.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2><sect2 id="ch0030s0001s0011" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.1.11 </emphasis> Health Care Providers</title><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">Healthcare providers are very well respected by Russian immigrants. Because nurses function in higher roles in the United States and some other countries, Russian immigrants may view nurses as physicians. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the roles and education of nurses.</emphasis></para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">Men and women are accustomed to living together in very small apartments or communal living; thus, most do not have a problem with privacy. Healthcare professionals’ gender is not generally a concern in providing care.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild"><emphasis role="bold">Always ask about gender concerns before performing breast pelvic or rectal exams on patients.</emphasis></para></listitem></itemizedlist></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0030s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are traditional verbal and nonverbal communication practices in Russian culture?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How do Russians value their time and punctuality?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are the decision-making practices of current Russian immigrants?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>List one health care condition in Russians in each of the three categories: environment, lifestyle, and genetics. What can you do to decrease the incidence and prevalence of these diseases?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are common high-risk health behaviors among Russian immigrants? Include some strategies for reducing them.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What are fertility practices among Russians? What education would you provide to the family about childbirth and contraception practices?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Many Russians are afraid of having X-rays and CT scans. What is the reason for this? What can you do to decrease their fear?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify a traditional treatment that Russians use for respiratory symptoms. How would you know that this treatment is being used?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify some practices women use during pregnancy.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Identify some cultural and traditional Russian practices. Which of them might have harmful effects?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0030s0003" role="bibliography"><title>Bibliography</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0030s0003bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib01">Ameredia Integrated Cultural Market (2023) Russian American demographics. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ameredia.com/resources/demographics/russian.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ameredia.com/resources/demographics/russian.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib02">Eckemoff EH, Sudha S, Wan D (2018) End of life care for older Russian immigrants—perspectives of Russian immigrants and hospice staff. J Cross Cult Gerontol 33:229–245. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9353-9">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9353-9</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9353-9">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9353-9</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30109463">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib03">Handtke O, Schilgen B, Mösko. (2019) Culturally competent healthcare—a scoping review of strategies implemented in healthcare organizations and a model of culturally competent healthcare provision. PLoS One 14: e0219971. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0219971">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0219971</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0219971">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0219971</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31361783">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6667133">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib04">Maltseva T (2021) People of Russian heritage. In: Purnell LD, Fenkl EA (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib05">Nersessova KS, Jurcik T, Hulsey TL (2019) Differences in beliefs and attitudes toward depression and schizophrenia in Russia and the United States. Int J Soc Psychiatry 65(5):388–398. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0020764019850220">https://doi.org/10.1177/0020764019850220</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0020764019850220">https://doi.org/10.1177/0020764019850220</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31159634">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib06">Orekhovskaya NA, Chistyakov AA, Kryukova NI, Krokhina JA, Ospennikov YV, Makarova EV (2019) Orthodoxy and modernity their contact facets in Russian society. Eur J Sci Theol 15(2):67–77</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib07">Stoeckl K (2020) The rise of the Russian Christian right: the case of the world congress of families. Relig State Soc 48(4):223–238. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/09637494.2020.1796172">https://doi.org/10.1080/09637494.2020.1796172</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/09637494.2020.1796172">https://doi.org/10.1080/09637494.2020.1796172</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0030s0003bib08">U. S. Census Bureau (2023) Russia—demographic data as of July 1, 2023. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.census.gov/popclock/world/rs"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.census.gov/popclock/world/rs</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
