<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0013" label="13">
  <title>13. People of Filipino Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0013s0004">
    <title>13. People of Filipino Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_13">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_13</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Nelson Tuazon</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0013">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">University Health, San Antonio, TX, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Nelson Tuazon</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:Nelson.tuazon@uhtx.com">Nelson.tuazon@uhtx.com</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Communication, Family roles, Health behavior, Nutrition, Spirituality</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0013s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Filipinos, predominantly of Malayan ancestry, have been influenced by the neighboring Chinese, Japanese, East Indian, Indonesian, Malaysian, and Islamic cultures and by influences from Spanish and American colonization. The Philippine archipelago consists of 7107 around 7,640 islands. The tropical climate is suitable for year-round agriculture and fishing, but it is affected by the seasonal northeast and southwest monsoons.</para>
    <para role="Para">Filipino Americans are a diverse group whose regional variations influence the spoken dialect, food preferences, and traditions as well as the other variant characteristics of culture discussed in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>. Aggregate data in this profile may not be accurate for some more acculturated Filipinos. Most Filipinos who live in the United States reside in California, Hawaii, Illinois, New Jersey, New York, Washington, and Texas. Since the passage of the 1965 Immigration Act, the Philippines have become the largest source of immigrants from Asia. Economic and educational opportunities and reunification with family members in the United States are the primary motivating factors for emigration. Filipinos view educational achievement as a pathway to economic success, status, and prestige for the individual and the family.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although more than 100 dialects are spoken in the Philippines, most Filipinos speak the national language, Filipino or <emphasis role="bold">Tagalog</emphasis>. English is used for business and legal transactions, and in school beyond the third grade. Business and social interactions commonly use a hybrid of Tagalog and English (Tag-Lish) in the same sentence.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Filipinos have different levels of proficiency and may practice <emphasis>translanguaging</emphasis> where they speak more than one local dialect and use English simultaneously.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nouns are used in place of the generic and gender-neutral pronouns <emphasis>siya</emphasis> (singular “he/she”) and <emphasis>sila</emphasis> (plural “they/them”). Hence, it is customary for Filipinos to use “he” and “she” interchangeably in reference to the same individual. <emphasis>Sila</emphasis> is also used as a sign of respect, usually when addressing the elderly or esteemed individuals.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Communication is highly contextual. The individual is acculturated to attend to the context of the interaction and to adopt appropriate behaviors.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Filipinos are observant, displaying an intuitive feeling about the other person and the contextual environment during interactions. Meanings are embedded in nonverbal communication.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The emphasis on maintaining smooth interpersonal relationships brings a consequent ambiguity in communication to prevent the risk of offending others.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Filipinos may sacrifice clear communication to avoid stressful interpersonal conflicts and confrontations. Saying “no” to a superior may be considered disrespectful, which predisposes an ambiguous positive response.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Focusing on action-oriented strategies may be seen as coercive.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Saving face, a characteristic pattern of behavior employed to protect the integrity of both conversants, is a consequence of the cultural value placed on maintaining smooth interpersonal relations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During a teaching session, a Filipino patient’s nod may have several meanings, such as comprehension or agreement (“Yes, I hear you”; “Yes, we are interacting”; “Yes, I can see the instructions”) or some other message that may be difficult for the patient to disclose. “Yes” does not always mean understanding or agreement.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Asking for a return demonstration of a procedure can help ensure understanding. Speak clearly and slowly. Allow time for a response to questions.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One may not disagree, talk loudly, or look directly at a person who is older or who occupies a higher position in the social hierarchy. Direct eye contact depends on the extent of acculturation, amount of time in the United States, age, and education. Some individuals may avoid prolonged eye contact with authority figures and older people as a form of respect. Older men may refrain from maintaining eye contact with young women because it may be interpreted as flirtation or a sexual advance. <emphasis role="bold">Just because Filipino patients do not maintain direct eye contact does not mean they are not listening, are not being truthful, or do not care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most individuals are comfortable with silence and allow the other person to initiate verbal interaction as a sign of respect. Greater distance is observed when interacting with outsiders and people in positions of authority.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Same-sex closeness and touching are normal behaviors. Young adults of the same sex may hold hands, put one arm over another’s shoulder, or walk arm-in-arm.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Filipinos have a relaxed temporal outlook. They have a healthy respect for the past, the ability to enjoy the present, and hope for the future. Past orientation is evident in their respect for elders, strong sense of gratitude, obligation to older generations, and honoring the memories of dead ancestors. Future orientation is manifested in the strong sense of family commitment to provide for the education of the young, parental participation in the care of their children and grandchildren, and a strong work ethic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Promptness for social events is determined situationally. “Filipino time” means arriving much later than the scheduled appointment, which can be from one to several hours.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children carry the surnames of their father and their mother. For example, Jose Romagos Lopez and Leticia Romagos Lopez are the children of Maria Romagos and Eduardo Lopez. The middle name or initial is the mother’s maiden name. After marriage, Jose keeps the same name, whereas his sister’s name becomes Leticia Lopez Lukban (her husband being Ernesto Lukban). The middle name is generally abbreviated as an initial. Nicknames symbolize affectionate regard for the person and are commonly used instead of the first name; hence, Nini, Baby, Bongbong.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Address Filipino adults by their title or professional affiliation such as Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., Dr., or attorney. Ask what name is used for legal purposes.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In contemporary families, although the father is the acknowledged head of the household, authority is considered egalitarian. The mother plays an equal and often major role in decisions regarding health, children, and finances.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional female roles include caring for the sick and children, maintaining positive relationships with kin, and managing the home.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Parents and older siblings are involved in the care and discipline of younger children.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In extended family households, older relatives and grandparents share much authority and responsibility for the care and discipline of younger members. Institutionalization of aged parents is tantamount to abandonment of filial obligation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Parents traditionally expect their children to pursue a college education, have economically productive careers, and raise a family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Dating at an early age is discouraged for young daughters. Sex education and sex are not usually discussed openly within the family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">As a country, although the Philippines is considered the most gender-equal in Asia, there remains discrimination against the LGBTQ+ community. Studies show that the negative attitudes toward the LGBTQ+ community may lead to high self-stigma among the members of the LGBTQ+ community. A survey conducted in 2023 shows growing support for gays and lesbians (Westerman, 2023). In the Philippines, a survey shows growing support for gays and lesbians, NPR.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Current research suggests the complexity of the intersection of the Filipino identity and masculity; the experience of Filipino boys is likely to vary from their peers coming from different racial identities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional families desire that their daughters remain chaste before marriage. Pregnancy out of wedlock brings shame to the whole family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Conditions such as mental illness, divorce, terminal illness, criminal offenses, unwanted pregnancy, and HIV/AIDS are not readily shared with outsiders until trust is established. In times of illness, the extended family provides support and assistance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A family visit to the hospital may take on the semblance of a family reunion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include nuclear and extended family for support in time of serious illnesses.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Make arrangements for visitations by large numbers of family. Elicit help for visitor control from a respected family member.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Homosexuality may be recognized but is often considered an aberrant behavior. Thus, to save face and decrease stigmatization for the family, it may not be openly practiced or acknowledged.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Racism is a continuing theme voiced by Filipino nurses working with Americans. Filipino nurses have been recruited in large numbers where acute shortages of American-trained nurses exist. This has reinforced the cultural tendency toward collective solidarity by defining the context of interactions within the insider-outsider continuum. <emphasis role="bold">Develop culturally specific staff development programs that include Filipinos and Americans.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The cultural concept of shared identity with other Filipinos creates a propensity among Filipino nurses to speak in their own dialect with each other to the exclusion of non-Filipino coworkers and patients. <emphasis role="bold">Explain organizational rules about when and where a foreign language can be spoken in the American workforce.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Assertive communication is difficult for Filipinos who have been acculturated to avoid conflict. They may consider it impolite and disrespectful to confront or challenge the authority of a superior. When a problem with a manager occurs, a Filipino may communicate through a mediator, usually another Filipino, who is in the same level within the hierarchy as the manager.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the cultural value of assertiveness in the American workforce.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Filipinos feel comfortable performing what they perceive as caring tasks for patients that American nurses expect patients to do for themselves. Initially they may not be inclined to teach and demonstrate procedures to patients because of their traditional belief in doing the caring tasks for patients. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the American value of self-care with patients and families.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Filipino values of shared perception and being one with others create a cooperative, rather than competitive, outlook. An individual produces for the group and puts the group above his or her own personal gain. The businesslike and competitive perspectives of Americans, in which behavior is internally motivated by individual gain, may be interpreted as selfish and uncaring. Self-proclamations of accomplishments may be seen as offensive. It is more meaningful recognition for a group to acknowledge and celebrate a member’s achievement, which is assessed in terms of how the action benefited the group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Bicultural development of Filipino and non-Filipino staff should be the goal of orientation and training. Biculturalism requires awareness of self and others and the ability to adapt behaviors that build positive relationships with others who may be different from oneself. Role model to help Filipinos assert themselves and feel confident in problem-solving and conflict resolution.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Filipinos place importance on maintaining self-esteem and dignity by saving face and avoiding shame. A Filipino may say “yes” to avoid hurting other people’s feelings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Their sensitivity and attention to other people’s feelings are often exhibited as indecisiveness, which many Americans interpret as lack of assertiveness. Filipinos are taught not to show open disagreement. Less acculturated Filipinos may not understand the directness of Americans and, thus, may find it insulting. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the expectation of assertiveness by all professionals in the American workforce.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The concept of individual accountability and responsibility in a highly litigious society, such as the US, may initially be difficult for Filipino nurses to understand. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the litigious nature of the American culture and the need for defensive charting.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The typical Filipino may come from a multiracial genetic background. The youthful features of Filipinos may make it difficult to assess their age. Common Filipino physical features may include jet black to brunette or light-brown hair, dark- to light-brown pupils with eyes set in almond-shaped eyelids, deep brown to very light tan skin tones, mildly flared nostrils, and slightly low to flat nose bridges.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The high melanin content of the skin and mucosa may pose problems when assessing signs of jaundice, cyanosis, and pallor. <emphasis role="bold">Assess anemia, pallor, and jaundice in the conjunctiva and palms and soles of the feet.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Filipinos range in height from under 5 ft. to the height of average Americans.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Approximately 40% have blood type B and a low incidence of the Rh-negative factor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0013s0001ta01">13.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Filipinos in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0002#ch0002"><emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Newborns may have Mongolian spots: bluish-green discolorations on their buttocks that are physiological and that eventually disappear.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Liver cancer tends to be diagnosed in the late stages of the disease and appears to be associated with the presence of the hepatitis B virus. Silent carriers of the virus are common among Asians, and its presence is detected only when other problems are being evaluated. <emphasis role="bold">Routinely screen for hepatitis B virus among recent immigrants.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Asians require lower doses of central nervous system depressants such as haloperidol, have a lower tolerance for alcohol, and are more sensitive to the adverse effects of alcohol.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because of availability of over-the-counter antibiotics and lack of adequate medical monitoring of these drugs in the Philippines, Filipino immigrants may be insensitive to the effects of some anti-infectives.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A positive reaction to tuberculin or to the Mantoux test is observed because of the practice of giving bacille Guérin-Calmette vaccinations in childhood. <emphasis role="bold">Chest X-rays and sputum cultures are recommended for screening and diagnosis of tuberculosis.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0013s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 13.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to filipinos</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemias</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactose intolerance</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Coronary artery disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hypercholesterolemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Renal stones</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hyperuricemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Gout</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Arthritis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic?, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thyroid cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Breast cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Prostate cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Filipinos who are more acculturated have higher rates of alcohol misuse and increased smoking rates. E <emphasis role="bold">xplain the physical and psychological problems of tobacco and alcohol misuse.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Less educated Filipinos in the United States have increased rates of HIV/AIDS compared with other Asians/Pacific Islanders. <emphasis role="bold">Take every opportunity to include HIV/AIDS education in elementary school and in health teaching.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The more recent immigrants in the United States frequently do not access health services until their illness is advanced because they are not aware of available services and may not have linguistic competence in the English language. <emphasis role="bold">Educate the Filipino community about the availability of services. Provide interpreters as necessary.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food and meal patterns emphasize generosity, hospitality, and thoughtfulness, which support group cohesiveness. Spanish, Chinese, and American influences are integrated into contemporary cuisine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Foods may be sautéed, fried, or served with a sauce. Rice is a staple food and is usually eaten at every meal, either steamed, fried, or as a dessert.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Balut</emphasis> (egg that has been fertilized) is an iconic Filipino food but has received checkered reputation in the United States and the Western world.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Sawsawan</emphasis> (condiment) is typical of Filipino cuisine and represents culinary significance in terms of esthetics, social relevance, and symbolic context.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Kakanin (local rice or root crop delicacies)</emphasis> is part of the daily food consumption among Filipinos, typically as snacks (in between meals) or dessert (after meals).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Except for babies and young children, milk is almost absent in the Filipino diet, partly due to lactose intolerance. Milk in desserts such as egg custard and ice cream seems to be tolerated.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cold drinks or foods such as orange juice or fresh tomatoes are not served for breakfast in order to prevent stomach upset.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Dietary calcium is derived from green leafy vegetables and seafood.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Households may keep potted medicinal plants that are used for common colds, stomach upsets, urinary tract infections, and other minor ailments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Daily consumption of garlic to combat hypertension is common. Ginger root is boiled and served as a beverage to relieve sore throats and promote digestion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Bitter melon is prepared and eaten as a vegetable and believed to prevent diabetes. Greens such as <emphasis>malunggay</emphasis> (moringa) and <emphasis>ampalaya</emphasis> leaves are used in stews to regain stamina for someone believed to be anemic or run-down. <emphasis role="bold">Knowledge of indigenous food sources and meal patterns, nutritional content of Filipino foods and American food substitutes, and accessibility of traditional ingredients are important aspects of nutritional assessment and counseling.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The only acceptable methods of contraception are natural family planning methods. Abortion is considered a sin. Recent Filipino immigrants who come from urban areas and who are more educated may be open to alternative methods of birth control.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Filipino women are embarrassed to have males perform vaginal examinations. <emphasis role="bold">Obtain a female health-care provider whenever possible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">The pregnant Filipino woman’s network of family and community health advisers, whose opinions she respects, are important support for building trust and rapport in the patient-provider relationship.</emphasis> Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0013s0001ta02">13.2</link></emphasis> describes common beliefs about pregnancy.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some prefer to have their mothers rather than their husbands in the delivery room.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some women may prefer the squatting position for birthing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common reasons for not breast-feeding are insufficient milk, mother working, nipple and breast problems, and mother’s poor health.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Supplementing breast-feeding with other liquids and foods occurs as early as 2 months. <emphasis role="bold">Educate mothers and family members on the importance of breast-feeding</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Beliefs about the postpartum period are included in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0013s0001ta03">13.3</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0013s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 13.2</emphasis> Prenatal beliefs about pregnancy</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Some women refuse to take vitamins because they are afraid that vitamins could deform the fetus</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Some individuals believe that when pregnant women crave certain foods, the craving should be satisfied to avoid harm to the baby. They believe that if the mother craves dark-skinned fruit or dark-colored food, the infant’s skin will be dark</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Sudden fright or stress may harm the developing fetus</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eating blackberries will make the baby have black spots</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eating black plums will give the baby dark skin</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eating twin bananas will result in twins being born</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eating apples will give the baby red lips</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• When a woman’s stomach is not round or the mother’s face is blemished, the baby will be a boy</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Going outside during a lunar eclipse is harmful to the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Going out in the morning dew is bad for the baby because evil spirits are present</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Funerals are avoided because the spirit of the dead person may affect the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wearing necklaces may cause the umbilical cord to wrap around the baby’s neck</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Sitting by a doorway will make the delivery difficult</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Sitting by a window when it is dark may let evil spirits come to the pregnant woman</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Sweeping at night may sweep away the good spirits</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Knitting might tangle the baby’s intestines at birth</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Naming the baby before it is born or after a dead person is bad luck</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table id="ch0013s0001ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 13.3</emphasis> Postpartum practices and beliefs</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Mothers should eat plenty of hot soups (chicken with papaya) to promote milk production</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Postpartum mothers should avoid exposure to cold and should use warm water to drink and bathe for a month</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Showers are prohibited because they may cause arthritis. However, the woman’s mother may give her a sponge bath with aromatic oils and herbs, or a <emphasis>hilot</emphasis>, traditional healer, may give an aromatic herbal steam bath followed by full body massage, including the abdominal muscles, to stimulate a physiological reaction that has both physical and psychological benefits</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eating sour or ice-cold foods may cause abdominal cramps for both the baby and mother</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• The mother and baby should not go out for a month except to visit a doctor</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• One should give money to charity or to the needy when a baby comes to one’s house for the first time</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• The baby’s abdomen is wrapped with a cloth until the umbilical cord falls off to prevent an umbilical hernia</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Garlic, salt, or a rosary is placed near the baby’s crib to ward off evil spirits</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Hanging the baby’s placenta in a tree will make the baby a good climber</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family members generally wish to provide intimate caregiving for the patient regardless of the setting. <emphasis role="bold">Make arrangements for the family to participate in caregiving.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Illness and death may be attributed to supernatural and magic or religious causes such as punishment from God, angry spirits, or sorcery.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Religiosity and fatalism contribute to stoicism in the face of pain or distress as a way of accepting one’s fate.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Before the decision is made to inform the patient about his or her terminal condition, a discussion among family members should occur. They may request the doctor to not divulge the truth to protect the patient.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The ethical principles of beneficence and malfeasance take precedence over patient autonomy.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Planning for one’s death is taboo and may be considered tempting fate. Hence, many traditional Filipinos are averse to discussing advance directives or living wills.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A priority for the family is to gather around the dying person and during the immediate period after death to pray for the soul of the departed. <emphasis role="bold">When death is imminent, contact a priest if the family is Catholic. Do not remove religious medallions, rosary beads, a scapular, or religious figures from the patient or from the bedside.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After death, a wake may last from 3 days to 1 week (to wait for the arrival of kin from other states or countries).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women generally show emotions openly by crying, fainting, or wailing. Men are expected to be more stoic and grieve silently.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cremation is acceptable to avoid the spread of disease.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">On the first-year anniversary of death, family and friends are reunited in prayer to commemorate this event.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many women wear black clothing for months or up to a year after the death. The 1-year anniversary ends the ritual mourning.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The dominant religious affiliations are Catholicism (the majority), Protestantism, Islam, and Buddhism. Most seek medical care; they believe that part of the efficacy of a cure is in God’s hands or by some mystical power.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Penitensiya</emphasis> (repentance) is a Lenten Filipino spiritual ritual that may be viewed as controversial because of the violent nature of this ritualistic act.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Novenas and prayers are often said on behalf of the sick person. Performance of religious obligations and sacraments and daily prayers are some of the ways health and peaceful death are achieved. <emphasis role="bold">Provide for spiritual needs of patients by making accommodations to their practicing beliefs.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Strength comes from an intimate relationship with God, family, friends, neighbors, and nature. The concept of self is formed from the relationship with a divine being.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Filipinos are fatalistic, tending to accept fate easily, especially when they feel they cannot change a situation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Decisions about when, where, and from whom to seek help are largely influenced by the intimate circle of family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include nuclear and extended family in health-care decision making when the patient requests.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many accept and adhere to medical recommendations while using alternative sources of care suggested by trusted friends and family members, which include indigenous medical practices. Often, major decisions are delegated to the physician rather than to the patient or family taking an active collaborative role in decision making.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Stress that medications need to be taken as prescribed, medications are ordered specifically for each ailment, unused drugs should be discarded.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A high value is placed on personal cleanliness. Keeping oneself clean and free of unpleasant body odors is viewed as good for one’s health and face-saving. To be slovenly and disorderly is to be shamelessly irresponsible. Aromatic baths are taken both for pleasure and to restore balance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Illness in infancy and childhood may be attributed to the “evil eye.” Healing rituals may involve religion (prayers and exorcism), sacrifices to appease the spirits, use of herbs, and massage.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Balance and moderation are embedded in the hot and cold theory of healing. Change should be introduced gradually. Sudden changes from hot to cold, from activity to inactivity, from fasting to overeating, and so forth, introduce undue bodily stresses that can cause illness.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe that after strenuous physical activity, a rest should precede a shower; otherwise the person could develop arthritis. Exposure to sudden cold drafts may induce colds, fever, rheumatism, pneumonia, or other respiratory ailments. Some avoid handwashing with cold water after ironing or heavy labor. Exposure to cold such as showers is avoided during menstruation and during the postpartum period.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many accept minor ailments stoically and consider them natural imbalances that will run their normal course and disappear.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Patients often do not complain of pain despite physiological indicators. Many view pain as part of living an honorable life and view this as an opportunity to reach a fuller spiritual life or to atone for past transgressions. <emphasis role="bold">Offer and, in fact, encourage pain relief interventions.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mental illness may be attributed to an external cause such as witchcraft, soul loss, or spirit intrusion.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Minimal expressions of psychological and emotional discomfort may be observed. The discomfort in discussing negative emotions with outsiders may be manifested by somatic complaints or ritualistic behaviors, such as praying.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explore the underlying meaning of somatization (loss of appetite, inability to sleep) and observe patient interactions with others for valuable information.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many believe that mental illness is hereditary and that it carries a certain stigma.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Beliefs and practices regarding depression vary from the different indigenous populations. These beliefs are influenced by magico-spiritual factors, relational problems, economic pressure, and emotional factors.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family members tend to take care of emotional problems to minimize exposing the problems to outsiders. <emphasis role="bold">Involving a trusted family member or friends, initiating contact with a Filipino mental health worker, especially a Filipino physician, may increase the likelihood of getting the person into a treatment program.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The birth of a child with a developmental disability may be viewed as God’s gift, an opportunity to become a better person or family, a curse from some unknown “angry spirit,” negligence while pregnant, or a family matter that should be kept private; institutionalization may not be readily accepted.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Organ donation is not an option, except perhaps in cases in which a close family member is involved. Many Filipinos who follow Catholic traditions believe that keeping the body intact as much as possible until death is preparation for the afterlife. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information on organ donation and transplantation.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0013s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Western medicine is familiar and acceptable to most. Some accept the efficacy of folk medicine and may consult both allopathic and indigenous healers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Folk healers are less common in the United States, with the exceptions of the West Coast and Hawaii. When available, they contribute by facilitating cultural rapport between health-care providers and patients.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">hilot</emphasis></emphasis> (traditional healer) is often willing to be included in the counseling session and provide support for the patient’s compliance with medical treatment. The <emphasis>hilot</emphasis> may provide a special prayer to be incorporated into the medically prescribed treatment plan to increase the patient’s sense that all available resources are being used.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Linguistically and ethnically congruent health-care providers are preferred.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A health-care provider of the same gender and the same culture may encourage more Filipinos to take advantage of disease prevention services.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include a Filipino primary care provider whenever possible. A bilingual person is helpful to improve communication with older Filipinos.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0013s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">13.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is the most common languages spoken by Filipinos? What is <emphasis>Taglish</emphasis>?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is meant by “Filipino time?”</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe the name format for Filipinos.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe Filipino communication practices.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the most common health conditions of Filipinos?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are acceptable birth control practices for <emphasis>traditional</emphasis> Filipinos?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe at least three prenatal beliefs about pregnancy.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is a <emphasis>hilot</emphasis>?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What healing rituals are used for a child with the “evil eye”?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>To what might Filipinos attribute mental illness?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0013s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0013s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib01">Alibudbud R (2023) Gender in mental health: toward an LGBTQ+ inclusive and affirming psychiatry and mental healthcare in The Philippines. Front Psych 1–4:1189231. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1189231">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1189231</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1189231">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1189231</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib02">Aster KGV, Castillo JRB, Cheng SR, Trillana JPL, Varlez YMB, Mercado JMT (2023) Sawsawan: explicating the culinary heritage significance of Philippine condiments using bibliometrics (1972–2018). J Ethnic Foods 10(1):1–15. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s42779-023-00186-3">https://doi.org/10.1186/s42779-023-00186-3</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s42779-023-00186-3">https://doi.org/10.1186/s42779-023-00186-3</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib03">Benard S, Manago B, Acosta Russian A, Cha Y (2023) Mapping the content of Asian stereotypes in the United States: intersections with ethnicity, gender, income, and birthplace. Soc Psychol Q 86(4):432–456. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/01902725221126188">https://doi.org/10.1177/01902725221126188</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/01902725221126188">https://doi.org/10.1177/01902725221126188</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib04">Cann V (2020) Negotiating identities: Being “boy,” being “Filipino,” being “other”. Boyhood Stud 13(1):23–42. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3167/bhs.2020.130103">https://doi.org/10.3167/bhs.2020.130103</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3167/bhs.2020.130103">https://doi.org/10.3167/bhs.2020.130103</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib05">CIA (2024) The World Factbook: the Philippines. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/philippines/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/philippines/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib06">De Castro AB, Gee GC, Takeuchi DT (2009) Job-related stress and chronic health conditions among Filipino immigrants. J Immigr Minor Health 10(6):551–558<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-008-9138-2">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10903-008-9138-2</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib07">De Villa BDM, Domingo TMM, Ramirez RJC, Mercado JMT (2022) Explicating the culinary heritage significance of Filipino kakanin using bibliometrics (1934–2018). Int J Gastron Food Sci 28:100522. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2022.100522">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2022.100522</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2022.100522">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijgfs.2022.100522</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib08">Galanti GA (2000) Filipino attitudes toward pain medication: a lesson in cross-cultural care. J Immigr Minor Health 10(6):551–558</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib09">Johnson-Kozlow M, Matt GE, Rock CL, de la Rosa R, Conway TL, Romera RA (2011) Assessment of dietary intakes of Filipino-Americans: implications for food frequency questionnaire design. J Nutr Edu Behav 43(6):505–510<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jneb.2010.09.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jneb.2010.09.001</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib10">Magat M (2020) Localizing the ‘ethnic:’ Balut-eating contests and identity performance among Filipino Americans. West Folk 79(1):105–126</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib11">Manielleas: 30 Superstitions Filipinos practice during funerals (2024). <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.manillenials.com/filipino-superstitions-funerals-pamahiin-sa-patay/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.manillenials.com/filipino-superstitions-funerals-pamahiin-sa-patay/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib12">Moreno-Lacalle RC, Bangsal MR, Bay-Ya MRT, Erese KAR, Gabol LAP, Geronimo MM, Legiralde SBB, Lomandas MMA, Menzi MMR, Real CDL, Solis JMBF, Ufina KU, Lacanaria MGC (2023) Beliefs and practices on depression among selected Filipino indigenous peoples: a focused ethnography. J Trans Nurs 34(5):321–329. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/10436596231183183">https://doi.org/10.1177/10436596231183183</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/10436596231183183">https://doi.org/10.1177/10436596231183183</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib13">Munoz CC (2013) People of Filipino heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach, 4th edn. F. A. Davis Company, Philadelphia</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib14">Parba J (2021) Teaching critical vocabulary to Filipino heritage language learners. Educ Sci 11:260<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/educsci11060260">https://doi.org/10.3390/educsci11060260</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib15">Philippines guide: A look at Filipino language, culture, and etiquette (2016). <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/phillippines-guide"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.commisceo-global.com/country-guides/phillippines-guide</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib16">Siojo R (n.d.) Filipino beliefs on pregnancy. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://philippines-events-culture.knoji.com/philippine-beliefs-on-pregnancy/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://philippines-events-culture.knoji.com/philippine-beliefs-on-pregnancy/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0013s0003bib17">Wight AC, Victoria M (2022) ’ Hayan na ang mga Hampas-dugo! (the penitents are coming!)’: Penitensya as religious-dark tourism. Tour Stud 22(1):89–113. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/14687976211067261">https://doi.org/10.1177/14687976211067261</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/14687976211067261">https://doi.org/10.1177/14687976211067261</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
