<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0001" label="1"><title>1. Transcultural Diversity and Health Care</title><sect1 id="ch0001s0005"><title>1. Transcultural Diversity and Health Care</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_1</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0001">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0001">2</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">College of Health and Nursing Sciences, Excelsior University, Albany, NY, USA</para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:lpurnell@udel.edu">lpurnell@udel.edu</ulink></para><para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis><?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:efenkl@fiu.edu">efenkl@fiu.edu</ulink></para><para role="keywords">Population, Diversity, Characteristics, Cultural competence</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0001" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">1.1 </emphasis> The Need for Culturally Competent Health Care</title><para role="Para">The need for cultural competence is increasingly recognized by health-care providers and health-related organizations in the United States and globally. The social ideology of a melting pot has been replaced by recognizing that people deserve respect within their cultural framework and as individuals. The literature on health and health-care disparities across ethnic, social, and economic groups continues to demonstrate compelling evidence for health-care providers and health-care organizations to be attentive to cultural diversity and inclusion as well as cultural competency. Major goals of Healthy People 2030 that impact on health disparities, with culture being one force to help eliminate them, are to (a) attain high-quality, longer lives free of preventable disease, disability, injury, and premature death; (b) achieve health equity, eliminate disparities, and improve the health of all groups; (c) create social and physical environments that promote good health for all; and (d) promote quality of life, healthy development, and healthy behaviors across all life stages.</para><para role="Para">Culture is defined as the totality of socially transmitted behavioral patterns, beliefs, values, customs, lifeways, arts, and all other products of human work and thought characteristics of a population of people that guide their worldview and decision-making. These patterns may be explicit or implicit, are primarily learned and transmitted within the family, are shared by most members of the culture, and are emergent phenomena that change in response to global phenomena and technological advancements. Culture is learned first in the family, then in school, and then in the community and other social organizations. Culture is largely unconscious and has powerful influences on health and illness beliefs and treatment. Health-care providers must recognize, respect, and integrate patients’ cultural beliefs and practices into health prescriptions to help eliminate or mitigate health disparities and provide patient satisfaction.</para><para role="Para">This handbook describes aggregate data on the dominant cultural characteristics of selected ethnocultural groups and provides a guide for assessing cultural values, beliefs, and practices. Based on individuality and the <emphasis role="bold">variant cultural characteristics of culture</emphasis> listed below, aggregate data will <emphasis role="bold">not fit every individual in a cultural group.</emphasis> Health-care providers who understand their own cultures and their patients’ cultural values, beliefs, and practices are in a better position to interact with their patients and provide culturally acceptable care that increases opportunities for health promotion and wellness; illness, disease, and injury prevention; and health maintenance and restoration. To this end, health-care providers need both cultural general and specific cultural knowledge. The more one knows about a cultural group, the more targeted will be the assessment and interventions. Without specific knowledge of cultural groups for whom they provide care, health-care providers might not know what questions to ask to provide culturally competent care. However, any generalization made from aggregate data about the behaviors of a cultural group or individual is almost certain to be an oversimplification; within all cultures are subcultures, ethnic groups, and individuals who do not adhere to all the values of their dominant culture and vary according to variant cultural characteristics as identified later in this chapter. Subcultures, ethnic groups, and ethnocultural populations are groups of people who have experiences different from those of the dominant culture with which they identify. For this Guide, subcultures are defined as a group of people from several cultures who join together for an array of reasons. For example, a support group for substance abusers, bikers, or veterans may have members from European American, Korean, and Panamanian cultures; they create their own subculture within their dominant culture.</para><para role="Para">Culture has a powerful unconscious impact on health professionals. Each health-care provider adds a unique dimension to the complexity of providing culturally competent care. The way health-care providers perceive themselves as competent providers is often reflected in the way they communicate with patients. Thus, it is essential for health providers to think about themselves, their behaviors, and their communication styles in relation to their perceptions of different cultures. Before addressing the multicultural backgrounds and unique individual perspectives of each patient, health-care professionals must first address their own personal and professional knowledge, values, beliefs, ethics, and life experiences in a manner that optimizes assessment of and interactions with patients who come from a culture different from that of the health-care provider. Self-awareness in cultural competence is a deliberate and conscious cognitive and emotional process of getting to know oneself: one’s own personality, values, beliefs, professional knowledge, standards, ethics, and the impact of these factors on the various roles one plays when interacting with individuals who are different from oneself. The ability to understand oneself sets the stage for integrating new knowledge related to cultural differences into the professional’s knowledge base and perceptions of health interventions.</para><para role="Para">Culture and race are not synonymous. However, the controversial term <emphasis>race</emphasis> must be addressed when learning about culture. Race is genetic and includes physical characteristics that are similar among members of the same group, such as skin color, blood type, and hair and eye color. Although there is less than a 1% genetic difference among the races, this difference is significant when conducting health assessments, determining genetic conditions, and prescribing medications and treatments, as outlined in culturally specific chapters that follow. People from a given racial group may, but do not necessarily, share a common culture. Perhaps the most significant aspect of race is social in origin; race can either decrease or increase opportunities, depending on the environmental context.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0002" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">1.2 </emphasis> Variant Characteristics of Culture</title><para role="Para">Major attributes that shape peoples’ worldview and the extent to which people identify with their cultural group of origin are called variant characteristics of culture. Some characteristics may change while others remain stable over life. Variant characteristics include:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">nationality,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">race,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">skin color,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">gender,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">age,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">religious affiliation,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">educational status,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">socioeconomic status,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">occupation,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">military experience,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">political beliefs,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">urban versus rural residence,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">enclave identity,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">marital status,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">parental status,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">physical characteristics,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">sexual orientation,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">gender issues,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">health literacy,</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">length of time away from the country of origin, and</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">reason for migration (sojourner, immigrant, or undocumented status).</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para role="Para">Immigration status influences a person’s worldview. For example, people who voluntarily immigrate generally acculturate and assimilate more easily. Sojourners who immigrate with the intention of remaining in their new homeland for only a short time or refugees who think they may return to their home country may not have the need or desire to acculturate or assimilate. Additionally, undocumented individuals (illegal immigrants) may have a different worldview from those who have arrived legally. Some variant characteristics of culture may be fluid and should not be seen as categorically imperative.</para><para role="Para">The literature reports many definitions for the terms <emphasis>cultural awareness, cultural sensitivity</emphasis>, and <emphasis>cultural competence</emphasis>. Sometimes, these definitions are used interchangeably. However, cultural awareness has more to do with an appreciation of the external or material signs of diversity, such as the arts, music, dress, or physical characteristics. Cultural sensitivity has more to do with personal attitudes and not saying things that might be offensive to someone from a cultural or ethnic background different from that of the health-care provider. Increasing one’s consciousness of cultural diversity improves the possibilities for health-care providers to provide culturally competent care. Cultural competence, as used in this book, means:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Developing an awareness of one’s own existence, sensations, thoughts, and environment without letting them have an undue influence on those from other backgrounds.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Demonstrating knowledge and understanding of the patient’s culture, health-related needs, and culturally specific meanings of health and illness.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Continuing to learn about cultures of patients to whom one provides care.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Recognizing that the variant cultural characteristics determine the degree to which patients adhere to the beliefs, values, and practices of their dominant culture.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Accepting and respecting cultural differences in a manner that facilitates the patient’s and family’s abilities to make decisions to meet their needs and beliefs.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Not assuming that the health-care provider’s beliefs and values are the same as the patient’s.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Resisting judgmental attitudes such as “different is not as good.”</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Being open to cultural encounters.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Being comfortable with cultural encounters.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Adapting care to be congruent with the patient’s culture.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Engaging in cultural competence is a conscious process and not necessarily a linear one.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Accepting responsibility for one’s own education in cultural competence by attending conferences, reading professional literature, and observing cultural practices.</para></listitem></orderedlist><para role="Para">As of April 2020, the census recorded a resident population of 331,449,281 in the 50 states and the national capital of Washington, D. C., reflecting an increase of 7.4%, or 22,703,743, over that of 2010 (U. S. Department of Commerce: U. S. Census Bureau <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0004bib01">2022</link></emphasis>). Also, as of 2022, nearly 46.2 million immigrants lived in the United States, the most in U. S. history.</para><para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0002ta01">1.1</link></emphasis> presents the diversity of the U. S. population.</para><table id="ch0001s0002ta01"><title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 1.1</emphasis> Diversity of the U. S. population as of 2021</title><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/><colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/><tbody><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">White</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">59.3%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Hispanic or Latino origin</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">18.9%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Black and African American</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">12.6%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Asian</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">5.9%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Persons with two or more races</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">2.3%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">American Indian/Alaskan Native</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">0.7%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Some other race</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">0.5%</para></entry></row><row><entry><para role="SimplePara">Native Hawaiian and other Pacific Islanders</para></entry><entry><para role="SimplePara">0.2%</para></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><para role="SimplePara">Data from “US population by year, race, age, ethnicity, &amp; more”. USAFacts. May 18, 2023. Retrieved June 4, 2024 from <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/</emphasis></ulink></emphasis></para><para role="Para">The census collects data on two categories: race and ethnicity; therefore, these numbers total more than 100%. Race and Hispanic origin are two separate and distinct categories. Race categories as used in Census 2020 include the following:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>1. <emphasis>White</emphasis> refers to people having origins in any of the original peoples of Europe, the Near East, the Middle East, and North Africa. This category includes Irish, German, Italian, Lebanese, Turkish, Arab, and Polish.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>2. <emphasis>Black</emphasis> and <emphasis>African American</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the black racial groups of Africa and include Nigerians and Haitians and any person who self-designated this category regardless of origin.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>3. <emphasis>American Indian</emphasis> and <emphasis>Alaskan Native</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the original peoples of North, South, and Central America and who maintain tribal affiliation or community attachment.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>4. <emphasis>Asian</emphasis> refers to people having origins in any of the original peoples of the Far East, Southeast Asia, and the Indian subcontinent. This category includes the terms <emphasis>Asian Indian, Chinese, Filipino, Korean, Japanese, Vietnamese, Burmese, Hmong, Pakistani</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Thai</emphasis>.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>5. <emphasis>Native Hawaiian</emphasis> and other <emphasis>Pacific Islander</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the original peoples of Hawaii, Guam, Samoa, Tahiti, the Mariana Islands, and Chuuk.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>6. <emphasis>Some other race</emphasis> was included for people who are unable to identify with the other categories. Additionally, the respondent could identify, as a write-in, with two races (U. S. Department of Commerce: U. S. Census Bureau <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0004bib01">2022</link></emphasis>).</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0003" role="Heading"><title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">1.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What changes in ethnic and cultural diversity have you seen in your community over the last 5 years? Over the last 10 years? Have you had the opportunity to interact with newer groups?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What health disparities have you observed in your community? To what do you attribute these disparities? What can you do as a professional to help decrease these disparities?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Who in your family had the most influence in teaching you cultural values and practices? Mother, father, grandparent?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What activities have you done to increase your cultural competence?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Given that everyone is ethnocentric to some degree, what do you do to become less ethnocentric?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How do you distinguish a stereotype from a generalization?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How have your variant characteristics of culture changed over time?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Distinguish between a stereotype and a generalization.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What ethnic and racial groups do you encounter on a regular basis? Do you see any racism or discrimination among these groups?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What does your organization do to increase diversity and cultural competence?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0004" role="bibliography"><title>Bibliography</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0001s0004bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0004bib01">U. S. Department of Commerce: U. S. Census Bureau (2022) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.commerce.gov/bureaus-and-offices/census"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.commerce.gov/bureaus-and-offices/census</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0004bib02">U. S. Department of Health and Human Services (2024) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://health.gov/healthypeople"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://health.gov/healthypeople</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0004bib03">US population by year, race, age, ethnicity, &amp; more. USAFacts. 18 May 2023. Accessed 4 Jun 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
