<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0033" label="33">
  <title>33. People of Turkish Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0033s0004">
    <title>33. People of Turkish Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_33">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_33</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Marshelle Thobaben</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0033">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Sema Kuguoglu</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0033">2</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Nursing, Cal Poly Humboldt, Arcata, CA, USA</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Nursing, Medipol University, Istanbul, Turkey</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Marshelle Thobaben</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:Marshelle.Thobaben@humboldt.edu">Marshelle.Thobaben@humboldt.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Uralic-Altaic language with 20 dialects, Cultural communication patterns, Format for names, Biological variations, Diseases and health conditions, High-risk behaviors, Maternity practices, Death rituals, Spirituality, Alternative life styles, Traditional practices</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0033s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">The Turkish diaspora in the United States is primarily concentrated in states such as New York, California, New Jersey, and Florida. The community comprises individuals from diverse backgrounds, with many coming from elite and upper-middle-class segments. Education holds considerable value in Turkish culture, and a substantial number of Turkish Americans hold advanced degrees, reflecting their commitment to academic pursuits. The Turkish community in the United States exhibits a wide array of beliefs and practices influenced by factors such as acculturation, individuality, and varying cultural characteristics (discussed in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>).</para>
    <para role="Para">Prior to its independence, Türkiye had already initiated a process of Westernization. However, it was under the leadership of its former president, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk, that Westernization and secularism became synonymous with the country’s transformation. From 1923 to 1938, Atatürk implemented numerous progressive reforms, which included the ban on the traditional fez, the prohibition of polygamy, the establishment of civil marriage contracts, the abolition of communal law for ethnic minorities, the transition from Islamic law to a civil law legal system, the promotion of nationalism and pride, educational and cultural reforms, the compulsory adoption of surnames, the shift of the weekly day of rest from Friday to Sunday, and the election of 17 female deputies to the National Assembly.</para>
    <para role="Para">Even after his passing on November 10, 1938, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk remains highly revered as the founding father of Türkiye, given his transformative impact on the nation’s social, political, and cultural landscape.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turkish, spoken by approximately 90% of the population, employs a linguistic structure that does not differentiate between gender-specific pronouns, such as “he” and “she,” or possessive forms like “her” and “his.” However, it is noteworthy that Turkish does maintain a distinction between formal and informal forms of the second-person singular pronoun “you.” This linguistic characteristic reflects the societal emphasis on hierarchical status within Turkish culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The pronunciation of Turkish names can pose challenges for Americans, and others, due to historical and script-based differences. Up until 1928, the Turkish language was transcribed using the Arabic script. However, guided by Atatürk’s initiatives, a distinct Turkish alphabet based on the Latin script was introduced. This modern Turkish alphabet bears similarities to the English counterpart but lacks the letters “w” and “x.” Furthermore, the Turkish alphabet accommodates certain distinctive phonetic nuances. For instance, certain sounds are represented by an undotted “i,” as well as accented “ö” and “ü,” while a “ç” with a cedilla signifies sounds akin to “sh” and “ch.” These nuanced aspects of the Turkish alphabet mirror the phonetic intricacies of the language and contribute to the distinctive pronunciation of Turkish names.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Elevated vocal tones are common in Turkish communication, indicating enthusiasm rather than anger. Simultaneous speech or interruptions during discussions are not inherently rude, except when a person of lower status interrupts a higher-status individual. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret speaking in a loud voice as anger.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In Turkish society, there is a prevailing emphasis on group affiliation over individualism. Identity is often shaped by factors such as familial ties, group memberships, educational institutions, and professional associations. The notion of privacy holds less significance, as Turks commonly lean toward collaborative dynamics within their social circles encompassing family and friends. However, it’s worth noting that inter-group competition can be notably intense despite the cooperative tendencies observed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the context of Turkish society, women typically find avenues for expressing anger within the confines of same-sex friendships and familial bonds. These channels are considered acceptable, as is the case when addressing individuals of lower social strata. However, it is important to acknowledge that women often encounter constraints in openly venting their frustrations toward their spouses or individuals occupying higher positions of influence.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Engaging in physical contact such as touching, hand-holding, and gentle patting is considered socially acceptable among individuals of the same sex in friendships, as well as between individuals of opposite sexes who are in romantic relationships. Similarly, there exists a closer personal space between same-sex friends compared to opposite-sex partners, with physical proximity being esteemed as an indicator of emotional intimacy. <emphasis role="bold">Touch, when necessary, is allowed and expected from healthcare providers. However, strict Muslims may not shake hands or touch members of the opposite sex, especially if they are not related.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Eye contact serves as a means of conveying respect in Turkish culture. In the presence of individuals holding higher social status, it is customary to maintain intermittent eye contact to signal attentiveness. Nonetheless, it is important to exercise discretion, as extended or sustained eye contact can be construed as impolite or even suggestive of flirtatious behavior. <emphasis role="bold">Maintain eye contact with patients, demonstrating respect and truthfulness.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In Turkish culture, a prevailing inclination toward formal attire is evident. On social occasions, men often opt for suits instead of more casual sports jackets and slacks. Women, however, tend to embrace modest clothing choices, favoring skirts and dresses over trousers. It is noteworthy that more conservative Muslim women might adhere to particularly modest clothing and may use black or colorful printed scarves to cover their heads. However, it’s important to acknowledge the evolving nature of fashion trends. Among the younger demographic, denim jeans and casual attire are progressively gaining traction, particularly for less formal gatherings. This shift underscores the dynamic interplay between tradition and contemporary preferences within Turkish dress codes. <emphasis role="bold">Expect a wide variety of dress among Turks, depending on religiosity, acculturation, and age.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turkish individuals commonly exhibit a proclivity for openly expressing a range of emotions, including happiness, disgust, approval, disapproval, and sadness, through readily discernible facial expressions and gestures. The negation “no” is frequently conveyed through the raising of eyebrows or a subtle lifting of the chin, often accompanied by a sharp snapping or “tsk” sound. An emblem of appreciation involves bringing together the fingertips and thumb, followed by a kissing gesture, which is frequently employed to convey gratitude for food. These distinctive nonverbal cues and gestures form an integral aspect of Turkish communication norms.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Maintaining a meticulously clean home is a source of pride within Turkish culture, underscored by the customary practice of removing shoes upon entering. It is commonplace for Turkish hosts in both Türkiye and, to a significant extent, the United States and some other countries, to provide guests with slippers. Irrespective of footwear, revealing the sole of one’s foot is deemed disrespectful. Additionally, women are expected to observe modest sitting postures, typically maintaining knees together and refraining from crossing them. These cultural norms reflect the value placed on cleanliness, hospitality, and decorum in Turkish society. <emphasis role="bold">Home healthcare providers should look for cues and ask if they should remove their shoes when entering the home of a Turkish family.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the realm of business relationships and healthcare appointments, the significance of punctuality is steadily growing within the Turkish American community. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of being punctual for healthcare appointments.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Titles serve as essential markers of respect and social status within Turkish culture. When addressing individuals, even those unknown, it is customary to employ their relevant titles, such as Bey (Mr.), Hanim (Mrs., Miss, or Ms.), <emphasis>Doktor</emphasis>, or <emphasis>Profesör</emphasis>. The same principle extends to familial interactions, where specific titles reflecting relationships are employed. For instance, terms like agbi (older brother or older close male friend), amca (uncle or elderly male relative or stranger), abla (older sister or older close female friend), teyze (maternal aunt or older female relative or older female stranger), and yenge (wife of a brother or paternal uncle) are utilized. This practice underscores the importance of demonstrating respect and acknowledging social dynamics through appropriate address. <emphasis role="bold">Greet patients formally with their title or Mr., Mrs., or Ms.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In a highly traditional Turkish household, the father assumes a role of unequivocal authority. However, within families embracing less traditional values, a notable shift toward spousal equality becomes evident, particularly in nuclear family structures where the wife possesses a strong educational background and is engaged in professional pursuits outside the home. Notably, contemporary women in Türkiye tend to exhibit a greater degree of Westernization in comparison to certain counterparts within Middle Eastern or Muslim societies. This variance underscores the evolving dynamics shaping gender roles and cultural influences in modern Türkiye. <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain the family spokesperson before eliciting health-care decisions. Accept family decision-making patterns without judgment.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Upon entering the school system, children are met with expectations to dedicate themselves to their studies, demonstrate respect, and adhere to the guidance of their elders, including older siblings. Conventional norms dictate that children refrain from engaging in disruptive behavior or expressing defiance toward their superiors. It’s worth noting that traditional views permit a degree of light corporal punishment as a means of discipline, although practices in this regard are undergoing change due to evolving societal perspectives. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the legalities of child abuse in the United States and elsewhere.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Circumcision stands as a significant rite of passage for male children within Turkish culture. This occasion is marked by familial celebration involving the extended family and includes the bestowing of gifts upon the newly circumcised boys. While the traditional practice allows for circumcision up to approximately 12 years of age, contemporary customs are shifting toward hospital-based procedures shortly after birth. This evolution reflects the intersection of tradition and modern medical practices in the Turkish context.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sexual interaction is notably discouraged among unmarried youth in Turkish society, with a particular emphasis on preserving chastity, especially in the case of women for whom virginity holds substantial cultural significance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While financial self-sufficiency holds significance within Turkish culture, the pursuit of independence from the family unit is not strongly promoted. Adult offspring, particularly sons, continue to play a vital role in their parent’s lives, and it is anticipated that they will assume caregiving responsibilities for their elders in later years. This emphasis underscores the enduring familial bonds and intergenerational obligations within Turkish society.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Parents or other family members are often consulted before major decisions are made.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Facilitating compliance with health prescriptions and health education can be effectively achieved through the strategic organization of a family conference led by a designated family spokesperson. This approach proves advantageous in fostering understanding and garnering support for recommended health practices within the family unit.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Among young individuals, residing within their parental home is customary until marriage unless educational pursuits or professional obligations necessitate alternative living arrangements. While arranged marriages persist within certain segments of Turkish society, this practice is comparatively less prevalent among Turkish individuals residing in Western countries.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Individuals are ingrained with a sense of responsibility to care for their parents when the need for assistance arises. The active involvement of grandparents in the upbringing of their grandchildren is pronounced, particularly when they share a household. This intergenerational dynamic underscores the pivotal role of family support in Turkish culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within numerous Turkish families, the extended family encompasses aunts, uncles, cousins, and in-laws. This expansive network fosters a cooperative dynamic that extends to diverse aspects of life, encompassing the sharing of responsibilities such as child care, labor, and sustenance as circumstances require. This collaborative ethos underscores the significance of familial bonds in Turkish cultural traditions. <emphasis role="bold">Use the extended family arrangement for health teaching and home care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The prevalence of divorce is on the rise, although it continues to carry a certain social stigma, particularly for women. The act of divorcing remains culturally unfavorable. In cases of widowhood, there exists a customary practice of extended family support, where the deceased husband’s family assumes responsibility for the care of the widow. Depending on factors such as age and socioeconomic status, widows may have the opportunity to remarry, reflecting the flexibility within this traditional framework.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The acceptance of homosexuality in Turkish society is gradually emerging, albeit with a certain degree of reservation. Many Turks exhibit a reluctance to align themselves with the gay community openly. There exists a noticeable hesitancy among individuals to establish affiliations with this demographic, reflecting the evolving but still somewhat distant reception of homosexuality within the cultural context. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to family members or others.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Türkiye is characterized by a culture that prioritizes group dynamics, and this orientation often extends to the workplace, which tends to emphasize a team-oriented approach.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Turkish cultural inclination toward relationship-oriented interactions can result in a reliance on personal connections and networks to achieve tasks. The process of cultivating relationships and networks, while intrinsic to Turkish norms, might be perceived as nepotism or excessive socializing from an American standpoint. <emphasis role="bold">Orient nurses to the Turkish perspective on relationships and the Turkish perspective of relationship to American nurses.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within the Turkish work environment, there exists an anticipation for a hierarchical relationship between supervisors and subordinates. The practice of delivering criticism indirectly is not only customary but also valued, as it serves to “save face.” It’s important to note that openly critiquing a Turkish individual, especially in a public setting, can be deeply offensive and detrimental to interpersonal dynamics. <emphasis role="bold">Do not criticize Turks in front of other employees.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">They may be reticent about asking questions for fear of exposing a lack of knowledge. <emphasis role="bold">Ask employees to demonstrate a procedure to ensure understanding.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turks handle differences of opinion in a brisk and clear-cut manner.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because most Turkish immigrants speak English, language barriers in the workplace may be only subtle.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turkish cultural norms dictate that confrontational interactions conducted in an assertive manner have the potential to erode relationships. Consequently, conflict resolution predominantly revolves around collaborative approaches, supported by elements of compromise and assertiveness. Compromise and avoidance tend to manifest among peers, whereas accommodation behaviors are more commonly employed when interacting with superiors. This nuanced conflict resolution framework reflects the cultural emphasis on maintaining harmonious interpersonal connections.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Türkiye is recognized for its significant power distance, reflecting the substantial psychological and emotional gap that often exists between superiors and subordinates. The culture places a strong emphasis on respecting authority, resulting in a centralized administrative structure and an authoritarian leadership approach that characterizes various facets of Turkish society.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Turkish population is a mosaic in terms of appearance, complexion, and coloration. Appearances range from light-skinned with blue or green eyes to olive or darker skin tones with brown eyes. Mongolian spots, usually found at or near the sacrum, are common among Turkish babies and should not be confused with bruising.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0033s0001ta01">33.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Turks in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. See Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0002#ch0002"><emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Endemic goiter associated with iodine deficiency is a major health problem in Türkiye despite iodine prophylaxis. <emphasis role="bold">Screen newer immigrants for helminthiasis and goiter.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assess for lactose intolerance as part of the intake interviews, and help patients identify alternative sources of calcium. Assess Turkish patients for β-thalassemia before prescribing medications.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turks in Türkiye have high rates of occupational injuries. <emphasis role="bold">Provide education regarding safety issues in occupational health.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turks are at high-risk for multiple cancers because of the Chernobyl accident in the Soviet Union in 1986; this includes children born after this period as well.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0033s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 33.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Turks</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Helminthiasis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Goiter</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Behçet’s disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitic diseases</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Rickets</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Sickle cell disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cigarette smoking is widespread in Türkiye and tends to start at an early age. Türkiye is a major producer of tobacco in the world. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients to cease smoking and help them access smoking cessation programs. Start teaching the hazards of smoking in elementary school.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turks tend to consume less alcohol than Americans or Europeans, perhaps as a result of the Muslim culture that discourages more than moderate alcohol use.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food preferences in Türkiye encompass a diverse range of options, often contributing to a well-rounded and health-conscious diet. Turkish cuisine, while not excessively spicy, is distinguished by meticulous and skillful preparation. The culinary tradition places great value on both the aesthetic presentation and the nutritional quality of dishes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although a typical family dinner in Türkiye might exhibit simplicity, guests are commonly treated to an abundant selection of dishes. The prevailing sentiment is that more food signifies generosity leading to instances where dinner guests are presented with a profusion of culinary offerings. This approach sometimes results in guests finding it challenging to consume everything on their plates, as Turkish hostesses are inclined to offer replacements for consumed items repeatedly. In accordance with etiquette, polite guests typically decline the initial offer, signifying a cultural practice rooted in hospitality and respect.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Breakfast is typically a simple meal of <emphasis>beyaz peynir</emphasis> (white feta cheese), olives, tomatoes, eggs, cucumbers, toast, jam, honey, and Turkish tea. Turks typically eat dinner at about 8 p.m. <emphasis role="bold">Take mealtimes into consideration when teaching Turkish patients about medication therapies.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The spectrum of soups in Turkish cuisine spans from delicately flavored options to more substantial choices. Hors d’oeuvres encompass a wide array of petite dishes, ranging from hot to cold, including items such as olive oil-stuffed grape leaves, olives, Circassian chicken with walnut sauce, dried mackerel, roasted chickpeas, and crispy fried savory cheese pastries. These appetizers are frequently complemented by <emphasis>rakí</emphasis>, a traditional anisette liquor derived from grapes, typically served over ice with water and sipped at a leisurely pace. This culinary tradition reflects the rich diversity and meticulous attention to detail inherent in Turkish gastronomy.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Salads in Turkish cuisine consist of a medley of fresh ingredients such as lettuce, tomatoes, cucumbers, and onions, often combined with raw vegetables. These salads are typically dressed with olive oil and either lemon juice or vinegar. Turkish culinary practices often involve the preparation of meat in modest portions, often accompanied by various vegetables, potatoes, or rice. Notable dishes within Turkish gastronomy encompass <emphasis>köfte</emphasis>, which are small, well-seasoned meatballs, as well as <emphasis>kebabs</emphasis> consisting of skewered beef or lamb complemented by an assortment of vegetables. This culinary selection is emblematic of the meticulous blending of flavors and textures that characterizes Turkish cuisine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Yogurt, a culinary creation attributed to the Turkish people, holds a fundamental position within the Turkish diet. Its consumption is often integrated into meals served at elevated temperatures rather than being relegated to a cold breakfast option. This cultural approach to yogurt underscores its versatile role as a complement to various dishes, emblematic of the inventive and diverse culinary traditions of Türkiye.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rice and <emphasis>börek</emphasis> are important parts of Turkish culinary tradition. <emphasis>Börek</emphasis> is made by wrapping <emphasis>yufka</emphasis> (thin sheets of flour-based dough) around meat, cheese, or spinach and then frying or baking until the dough is flaky.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turkish desserts can be classified into four distinct categories: opulent and sugary pastries, exemplified by <emphasis>baklava</emphasis>; creamy and indulgent puddings; cooked fruits offering a sweet profile; and the inclusion of fresh fruits. A customary practice involves concluding meals with a selection of fresh fruits, often accompanied by coffee or tea. This dessert tradition exemplifies the multifaceted nature of Turkish cuisine, where a diversity of flavors and textures are harmoniously integrated into culinary offerings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Renowned for its robust and sweet profile, Turkish <emphasis>kahve</emphasis>, a dark and dense coffee, holds a distinguished place in the culinary landscape. <emphasis>Ayran</emphasis>, a blend of yogurt and milk, is the prevailing cold beverage in Türkiye, enjoyed by individuals of all ages. It’s notable that the Islamic faith mandates abstaining from pork consumption and alcohol consumption, but adherence varies based on individual levels of religious observance. The diversity in practice reflects the nuanced relationship between faith and cultural practices within the Muslim community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Given the diversity among food options in the United States and elsewhere, provide dietary counseling according to the individual’s unique food choices and practices.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Ramazan</emphasis>, the Islamic tradition known as <emphasis role="bold">Ramadan</emphasis> in Arabic countries, entails a month-long fasting practice observed by devout Muslims across the globe. Throughout the course of Ramazan, individuals refrain from eating or drinking from sunrise until sunset. The extent of adherence to this practice varies considerably, ranging from those who do not observe it to those who meticulously adhere to its tenets. This variance reflects the diverse spectrum of observance within the global Muslim community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within the Sunni Muslim tradition, the commencement of Ramazan observance occurs at the onset of puberty. Some adherents hold the belief that women have an obligation to fast even during pregnancy and the postnatal phase. In contrast, Alevi Muslims do not impose fasting obligations on either gender. Typically, pregnant and postpartum women, individuals traveling, and those dealing with illness are exempt from fasting, although there may be an expectation to compensate for missed days at a later point, thereby illustrating the nuanced approach to fasting regulations across different situations within the Islamic framework. <emphasis role="bold">Health teaching strategies for Turks in America and elsewhere should include the recognition and prevention of dehydration, bloating, constipation, and fatigue during periods of Ramazan fasting (see Chap.</emphasis><emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0008#ch0008"><emphasis role="RefSource"><emphasis role="bold">8</emphasis></emphasis></ulink></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">).</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fasting can potentially lead to an array of digestive issues and pose health risks, particularly in the case of pregnant or postnatal women and their infants. The physiological changes associated with fasting may jeopardize the well-being of both the mother and the child, underscoring the importance of considering individual health conditions and circumstances when observing fasting practices within specific religious contexts. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information regarding fasting and the potential effect on some health conditions.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Molasses, <emphasis>baklava</emphasis>, <emphasis>lokum</emphasis> (Turkish delight), tahini, honey and nuts, and raisins are believed to increase strength and sexual vigor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fruits, especially bananas, oranges, tangerines, and apples, are brought to convalescing people, helping them to regain their strength and aiding in the healing process.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Chicken soup is a common remedy for cold and flu symptoms. An <emphasis>ebe</emphasis> (a traditional Türkiye midwife) relies on various herbs and home remedies to heal patients. <emphasis>Ebegömeci</emphasis> (a spinach-like leaf or herb) may be prepared for topical or oral use to treat inflammation, infection, and sometimes infertility.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Tea, cinnamon, hot water with sugar, ginger, mint, and various roots are used separately or in various combinations to treat rheumatism, low blood pressure, intestinal gas, colds, and flu. Nettles may be used topically for rheumatism, arthritis, and varicose veins.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A traditional folk remedy for diabetes involves the process of boiling olive leaves and subsequently refrigerating the resulting infusion before consuming the extracted juice.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Lapa</emphasis>, a watery rice mixture with a gruel-like texture, or a boiled potato may be used to treat diarrhea and is followed by yogurt to replace the natural flora of the intestines.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask Turkish patients if they are using traditional dietary practices and incorporate them into prescription therapies. Because malnutrition may be a significant problem among economically disadvantaged Turks immigrating to the United States and elsewhere, consider extensive nutritional assessments for more recent immigrants.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Until the 1960s, the sale of contraceptives and the dissemination of birth control education were prohibited in Türkiye. The legality of abortion and sterilization, with exceptions for medical necessities, remained restricted until 1983. Presently, prevalent contraception methods among Turkish women encompass withdrawal, utilization of intrauterine devices, and the use of birth control pills. This historical progression reflects the evolving landscape of reproductive health practices within Turkish society. <emphasis role="bold">Given the history of family planning in Türkiye, be open to culturally congruent ways to discussions of family planning with Turkish people in the United States and elsewhere.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Motherhood holds a position of considerable reverence within Turkish culture, and pregnant women are afforded extensive care and comfort, often accommodating their cravings. Pregnant individuals are commonly encouraged to maintain their routine activities or work as long as they feel at ease. This approach underscores the cultural esteem for motherhood and the collective effort to ensure the well-being of expectant mothers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many pregnant women take prenatal vitamins, drink a lot of milk, and apply salves such as Vaseline to avoid stretch marks. Light exercise, such as walking, is encouraged, but weather conditions often hamper such efforts because Turks generally avoid wet or cold weather, fearing its ill effects on one’s health.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Turks prefer hospitals for physician-assisted child delivery. The husband and the birth mother’s father may be present during the birthing process. Expressions of discomfort and pain are quite acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The postpartum period can last up to 40 days. Light exercise is encouraged during this period, and bathing, an important part of the Muslim tradition, is strongly encouraged.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A distinct dietary item known as “ <emphasis>lousalik</emphasis>” is customarily offered to postpartum women. <emphasis>Lousalik</emphasis> is a sweet, sherbet-like substance created by dissolving <emphasis>lousalik</emphasis> beads in hot water. This carbohydrate-rich preparation is designed to enhance the woman’s vitality during the postpartum phase. Hot soups and fluid consumption, including milk, feature prominently in the diets of postpartum women, particularly those breastfeeding. The practice of breastfeeding is highly esteemed among the majority of Turkish individuals, and while it is commonly embraced, it is typically approached with modesty. This cultural perspective reflects the significance attributed to maternal health and child-rearing practices. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage the incorporation of nonharmful postpartum practices with Western interventions.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A customary practice involves the placement of a small blue bead, known as a “nazar boncuk,” on the left shoulder of a child. This bead is believed to offer protection against the perceived malevolent influence of the “evil eye,” specifically guarding against the influence of the evil angel purportedly whispering into the child’s left ear. Additionally, other traditional safeguards include positioning iron beneath the baby’s mattress as a precaution against anemia. Likewise, tying a yellow ribbon to the crib is thought to avert jaundice, while affixing a red bow serves as a symbolic countermeasure to deflect any potential envious or negative energies. These practices reflect the cultural significance attributed to safeguarding infants from potential harm and ill intentions. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove protective beads or ribbons from the infant’s bedside.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Swaddling, a common practice, has been linked to congenital hip dislocation, pneumonia, and upper respiratory infections among young infants. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the harmful effect of swaddling.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cremation is not commonly practiced among Turkish Muslims due to their religious conviction that the body should remain intact. Following the passing of an individual, a ritualistic washing of the body takes place, after which it is enshrouded in a white sheet. This practice adheres to the cultural and religious importance placed on preserving the sanctity of the deceased individual’s physical form.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Muslim Turks are placed in the grave, with the right side of the body facing Mecca.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The traditional mourning period is 40 days, during which traditionally, those attending the ceremony wear black clothes or a black scarf.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While Muslim Turks hold a belief in the afterlife, the passing of an individual is consistently marked by profound sorrow and mourning. A common expression of condolences to those bereaved is “ <emphasis>Basınız sağ olsun</emphasis>,” which translates to “May your head be healthy.” This sentiment carries the hope that the mourning individual will not be overcome by grief. This cultural practice reflects the cultural and emotional sensitivity that surrounds the topic of death within Turkish society.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The predominant religious affiliation among Turks is Sunni Islam, while a minority belongs to the Alevi Muslim group. Notably, a substantial proportion of Turkish immigrants to Western countries tend to adhere to a more moderate interpretation of Islam. This religious diversity among Turkish expatriates underscores the varying degrees of religious observance and beliefs within this demographic, reflecting the broader spectrum of religious practices observed by Turks residing outside their homeland.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional prayer is practiced five times each day and can take place anywhere, as long as one is facing the holy city of Mecca. A special small rug called <emphasis>seccade</emphasis> is used for praying in places other than the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">cami</emphasis></emphasis>, mosque. When entering the <emphasis>cami</emphasis>, shoes are always removed, and women must cover their heads. Men and women go to separate parts of the <emphasis>cami</emphasis> for prayer. One prepares for prayer by ritual cleansing, which, at minimum, includes washing the face, ears, nostrils, neck, hands to the elbow, and feet and legs to the knee, three times each.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Caregivers may need to make special arrangements so that Muslims can practice their religious obligations when they are in a healthcare facility.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spiritual leaders or healers are sought for assistance with relationships or emotional problems. A <emphasis>muska</emphasis>, a paper inscribed by a <emphasis>hoca</emphasis> (an alderman) with a prayer in Arabic, is wrapped in fabric and hidden in the home or worn by the person seeking help. <emphasis>Turbe</emphasis> and <emphasis>yatir</emphasis> are the practice of going to the graves of scholars to pray about wishes, mental or emotional problems, or fertility problems. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Tesbih</emphasis></emphasis> (small beads traditionally used for praying) now take a more secular meaning and are often referred to as “worry beads.” <emphasis role="bold">Religious or folk items should not be removed because they provide comfort for the patient and removal may increase anxiety.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While the majority of Turks predominantly seek health and curative care from Western medicine provided by well-trained professionals, vestiges of traditional beliefs persist in parallel. A prevalent viewpoint attributing the origins of illness to imbalances of hot and cold elements endures within the cultural framework. For instance, ailments like diarrhea are ascribed to an excess of cold or heat, whereas conditions such as pneumonia are associated with extreme cold. This coexistence of modern medical practices and enduring traditional beliefs underscores the complex healthcare landscape in Turkish society.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Turks have a traditional fatalistic worldview, which is more common among those living in extended households who believe “You cannot change what God has written.” <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate factual information for the entire family regarding disease causation and treatment in patient education.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In the context of terminal illness, it is customary in Turkish medical practices to withhold the full severity of the condition from patients. This approach stems from the belief that imparting such information could potentially diminish hope, motivation, and the vital energy required for healing. Additionally, the disclosure of a terminal diagnosis might intensify patient anxieties pertaining to mortality and the impact on their loved ones. This approach is aligned with the perspective that the ultimate outcome is beyond human control and rests with divine will. This blend of cultural and spiritual considerations underscores the nuanced manner in which medical information is conveyed within the Turkish healthcare framework. <emphasis role="bold">Take cues from the patient and discuss the patient’s condition with the family before disclosing the severity to the patient.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within Turkish households, women typically assume the role of primary caregivers for the ailing. Moreover, pivotal healthcare decisions often rest in the hands of the individual held in the highest esteem for their level of education. This arrangement underscores the gender-specific care-taking dynamics and hierarchical decision-making process within the context of health and well-being in Turkish society. <emphasis role="bold">Determine the family spokesperson for decision-making on health issues and incorporate group interventions whenever possible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Türkiye demonstrates elevated rates of over-the-counter antibiotic and painkiller utilization, with aspirin often being embraced as a universal remedy for diverse afflictions, including gastric discomfort. A notable trend involves individuals, particularly those encountering financial constraints with regard to accessing medical services, frequently seeking guidance from pharmacists prior to consulting a physician. This practice reflects the significant role of pharmacists in the healthcare field and underscores the broader healthcare dynamics, including self-care and affordability considerations, prevalent within Turkish society. <emphasis role="bold">Assess Turkish patients for their use of over-the-counter medications to prevent conflicting or potentiating effects with prescription medications.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The belief in the “evil eye” holds significant cultural prominence within Turkish society. An inherent caution exists against excessively extolling one’s state of health, as it is thought that doing so may inadvertently attract misfortune through others’ envious gazes. This sentiment is so deeply ingrained that even taxi drivers and medical practitioners revere the protective power of the “ <emphasis>nazar boncuk</emphasis>,” a blue bead utilized as a shield against the malevolent effects of the evil eye. When discussing ailments, individuals consciously avoid employing themselves or others as examples, lest such descriptions inadvertently invite affliction upon the person being discussed. This intricate interplay between cultural beliefs and health-related conversations demonstrates the enduring influence of traditional superstitions within Turkish cultural norms.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The practice of using “kolonya” (cologne) is a cherished tradition that transcends religious and secular boundaries within Turkish culture. Stemming from a foundation of reverence for cleanliness, this practice involves applying cologne to the hands of guests both before and after meals, offering a dual benefit of sanitization and infusing a pleasant lemon fragrance. Additionally, inhaling the aroma from a cloth or handkerchief imbued with a cologne is employed as a remedy for alleviating motion sickness. Notably, within medical settings, patients may extend the gesture of offering cologne to physicians or nurses prior to undergoing an examination. This multifaceted utilization of cologne underscores its integral role in Turkish customs, blending hygiene, comfort, and cultural expressions of hospitality. <emphasis role="bold">Respect this custom as appropriate.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Other home remedies include using rubbing alcohol or a wet cloth to bring down a fever and warming the back to treat coughing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Turkish culture allows freedom to express pain through either emotional outbursts or verbal complaints. <emphasis role="bold">Accept a wide range of pain expression among Turkish patients.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although stigma is attached to mental illness, many families seek treatment or care for the patient at home. The most common reasons given for mental illness include discord among family members, marital and love problems, gossip, and other familial problems. Social causes include financial inadequacies, societal disorders, and a “struggle with life.” Men more frequently blame social causes for mental illness, and women often give psychological causes. <emphasis role="bold">Address somatization among Turkish patients with mental health concerns, and encourage the expression of their feelings. Incorporate group interventions whenever possible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within the context of hospitalization, the term “ <emphasis>refakatçı</emphasis>” pertains to the individual who remains overnight with the patient, offering indispensable emotional and physical support and solace. Demonstrating care and compassion serves to alleviate apprehensions and diminish feelings of isolation experienced by the patient. Additionally, family members may take on responsibilities such as aiding with bathing and tending to other physical requirements. Emphasizing a well-rounded, nutritious diet is deemed crucial for the process of recuperation, with a common practice being the provision of home-cooked meals brought from outside the hospital setting. This comprehensive approach underscores the multifaceted nature of Turkish healthcare customs, intertwining emotional well-being, familial involvement, and dietary considerations in the realm of patient care. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage family-assisted care, and allow families to provide homemade foods.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While blood transfusions are gaining acceptance, Turkish people usually prefer to receive blood from family members. Muslims traditionally prefer that the body remain intact after death, a belief that may conflict with organ donation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0033s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although Turkish people are inclined toward Western health-seeking behaviors, medical care tends to be holistic. Great value is placed on emotional well-being, especially as it affects physical well-being. Physicians may be “adopted” as members of their patient’s families, and it is common to give gifts (usually food) to the physician as an expression of gratitude.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Generally, treating someone of the opposite sex is not an issue among Turks. <emphasis role="bold">Ask each patient for preference on gender issues in health care.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Physicians, and to a lesser extent, nurses and midwives, have historically been held in very high esteem. Patients rarely question the authority of physicians, but the notion of obtaining a second opinion is gaining popularity.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0033s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the Turkish language and how it might be difficult for Americans to pronounce Turkish names. What might you do to ensure you pronounce a name correctly?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Give some examples of the collectivistic Turkish family versus the individualistic culture of European American and other nationalities. What implications does this have for patient education?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify communication practices related to touch among Turkish people. How does this vary among women, men, their religion, and tradition?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify genetic conditions common among Turks. Which of them has a lifestyle component?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe the practices conducted during the holy month of <emphasis>Ramazan</emphasis>? How would you change your practice to accommodate a person who is conducting these practices during <emphasis>Ramazan</emphasis>?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What function does somatization have in Turkish culture? How would you address a patient who is somaticizing?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is a <emphasis>nazar boncuk</emphasis>, and what is its function?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify two folk remedies and the conditions they are used for.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain why newer Turkish immigrants may easily assimilate into the dominant European American culture?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>As a nurse, you are visiting a Turkish patient in their home. What do you need to consider before entering their home?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0033s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0033s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib01">Bosrock MM (2006) European business customs &amp; manners: a country-by-country guide to European customs and manners. Meadowbrook, Minnetonka</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib02">CIA (2024) World Factbook: Turkey Turkiiye. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/turkey-turkiye/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/turkey-turkiye/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib03">Encyclopedia Britannica (2023) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.britannica.com/place/Turkey"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.britannica.com/place/Turkey</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib04">Fassaert T, Hesselink AE, Verhoeff AP (2009) Acculturation and use of health care services by Turkish and Moroccan migrants: a cross-sectional population-based study. BMC Public Health 9:332. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://bmcpublichealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2458-9-332"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://bmcpublichealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/1471-2458-9-332</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2458-9-332">https://doi.org/10.1186/1471-2458-9-332</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=19744326">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2749828">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib05">Hendrich B (2012) Introduction—beyond state Islam: religiosity and spirituality in contemporary Turkey. Eur J Turkish Stud 13 | 2011. Online since 17 Dec 2012, connection on 10 Jul 2023. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://journals.openedition.org/ejts/4527"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://journals.openedition.org/ejts/4527</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4000/ejts.4527">https://doi.org/10.4000/ejts.4527</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib06">Kara B (2017) Self-related health and associated factors in older Turkish adults with type 2 diabetes: a pilot study. J Transcult Nurs 28(1):40–48<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659615601484">https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659615601484</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=26303253">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib07">Karakas F, Sarigollu E, Kavas MJ (2015) Discourses of collective spirituality and Turkish Islamic ethics: an inquiry into transcendence, connectedness, and virtuousness in Anatolian tigers. J Bus Ethics 129(4):811–822<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10551-014-2135-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10551-014-2135-6</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib08">Ozbassaran F, Ergul S, Temel AB, Aslan GG, Coban A (2011) Turkish nurses’ perceptions of spirituality and spiritual care. J Clin Nurs 20:21–22<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2702.2011.03778.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2702.2011.03778.x</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib09">Senay B (2010) State of origin: Turkish migration and multiculturalism in Australia. In: Erdogan MM (ed) Yurtdışındaki Türkler 50: Yılında Göç ve Uyum = Turks abroad: migration and integration in its 50th year. Orion, pp 287–296</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib10">Serdar U (2011) Traditional fold medicine in the Turkish folk culture. Turk Stud 6(4):317–327</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib11">Thobaben M, Kuguoglu S (2013) People of Turkish heritage. In: Purnell L (ed) Transcultural health care: a culturally competent approach (chapter on Davis Plus web site), 4th edn. F. A. Davis Company, Philadelphia</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib12">Thobaben M, Kuguoglu S (2021) People of Turkish heritage. In: Purnell L, Fenkl E (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach. Springer, Cham. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-51399-3_28">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-51399-3_28</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-51399-3_28">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-51399-3_28</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0033s0003bib13">Yaman A, Mesman J, van Ijzendoom MH, Bakermans-Kranenbutg MJ, Linting M (2010) Parenting in an individualistic culture with a collectivistic cultural background: the case of Turkish immigrant families with toddlers in the Netherlands. J Child Fam Stud 19(5):617–628<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-009-9346-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10826-009-9346-y</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=20835387">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2928918">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
