<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0005" label="5">
  <title>5. People of American Indian/Alaskan Native Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0005">
    <title>5. People of American Indian/Alaskan Native Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_5</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Kathy Prue-Owens</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0005">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Helen and Arthur E. Johnson Beth-El College of Nursing and Health Sciences, University of Colorado Colorado Springs, Colorado Springs, CO, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Kathy Prue-Owens</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:kprueowe@uccs.edu">kprueowe@uccs.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Communication, Family roles, Workforce issues, Biocultural ecology, Spirituality</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">This chapter provides a general overview of American Indians and Alaskan Natives (AI/AN) followed by a more detailed description of the Navajo Nation as one exemplar. Space does not permit an extensive discourse on each tribe. The 2020 census reports 9.7 million people identified as American Indian and Alaska Native alone or in combination with another race. This is a significant increase from the 5.2 million in 2010. Around 20% live in American Indian areas/reservations or Alaska Native villages. The census report is tabulated based on an AI/AN write-in response to the 2020 census race question indicating that there is a changing demographics among AI/AN. National findings indicate that the Alaska Native alone population grew 10.9% to 133,311 while the AN alone or in any combination population increased 45.6% to 241,797. A similar increase is seen in the American Indian alone population which grew 11.6% to 2,159,802 while the alone or in any combination population nearly doubled to 6,363,796.</para>
    <para role="Para">There are more than 574 federally recognized sovereign AI/AN tribes, of which 231 are Alaskan Natives and are divided into five groups: Aleuts, Northern Eskimos (Inupiat), Southern Eskimos (Yuit), Interior Indians (Athabascans), and Southeast Coastal Indians (Tlingit and Haida). In addition, there are approximately 400 non-federally recognized tribes, each with its unique customs and beliefs. Some Alaskan Natives do not mind being called Eskimos or Indians; however, some do not like to be called Native Americans or Eskimos and prefer Alaskan Native, Alaska Indian, or Inuits. The amount of Indian blood or blood quantum necessary to include enrolment requirements is dependent on each tribe. For example, the Cherokee Nation laws are based on legal documentation that demonstrates direct ties to the tribe with no blood quantum. However, the Navajo Nation requires at least one biological parent to be enrolled with the Navajo Nation, the applicant must meet the minimum ¼ Navajo blood quantum requirement. Many of the Sioux Nations from the great plains area require ¼ blood quantum and three generations of lineal descent.</para>
    <para role="Para">Indian Health Service (HIS): The Indian Health Service (IHS) was designed to fulfill the U. S. government’s role in providing health care to American Indians and Alaskan Natives (AI/AN); however, inadequate funding has left those who depend on the IHS with only limited health care.</para>
    <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">Overall, AI/ANs are extremely diverse groups of people. Some are very traditional, some are highly acculturated, and some selectively combine tradition with the European American culture. Many share similar, but not exact, traditions, beliefs, and values.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">AI/ANs are a particularly vulnerable population in terms of accessing health care.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">High poverty rates, increasing suicides, individual high-risk health behaviors, social factors, low educational levels, chronic conditions and greater health disparities make it particularly important for accessing and receiving ongoing supportive and preventive care.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">One-third of AI/ANs are in families with incomes below the federal poverty line. The median household income for American Indian and Alaska Natives is $49,906.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">One in five adults has not graduated from high school; 65 % earn a high school diploma compared with 75.2% of the U. S. population. The college graduation rate is also much lower, with 9.3% compared to the national average of 20.3%.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">Almost half of uninsured adults do not have a usual source of care, making it difficult to receive preventive services and timely care for acute health problems.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para role="Para">The IHS is divided into 12 regions, each with either hospital, clinics, or outreach areas. The regions are listed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0001ta01">5.1</link></emphasis>. Federally recognized tribes are considered sovereign nations, giving them independent authority over their territories with the power to rule and make laws.</para>
    <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">Although the IHS includes access to some specialty care and has established urban Indian health clinics, shortages in funding and a lack of facilities and health-care professionals have left many eligible AI/ANs struggling to obtain timely, high-quality health care.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para role="Para">The AI/AN population is a young population with a median age of 31 years compared with 37 years for the US overall.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <table id="ch0005s0001ta01">
      <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.1</emphasis> Regions of the Indian Health Service</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Region</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Area(s) served</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Great plains area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">North Dakota, South Dakota, Iowa, and Nebraska</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Alaska area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">State of Alaska</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Albuquerque area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">New Mexico, Colorado, and Texas</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Bemidji area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Indiana, Minnesota, Michigan, and Wisconsin</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Billings area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Montana and Wyoming</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">California area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">California and Hawaii</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Nashville area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Eastern US</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Navajo area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Arizona, New Mexico, and Utah</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Oklahoma city area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Oklahoma, Kansas, and portions of Texas</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Phoenix area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Arizona, California, Nevada, and Utah</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Portland area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Oregon</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Tucson area</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para role="SimplePara">Southern Arizona</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">AI/ANs are collective cultures and avoid conflict and confrontation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Each tribe has its own language, but some languages are similar to each other.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Younger people speak English. Some older people may know only their traditional tribal language or perhaps Spanish in the southwestern part of the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">If needed, use professional interpreters whenever possible. Confidentiality is taken seriously. Often the younger family members will serve as interpreters.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Trust and privacy are major elements that facilitate a clearer communication.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Greeting with Mr., Mrs., or Miss shows respect and is always safe. Even the use of sir or ma’am is appropriate. While use of the given name is preferred by some; wait for permission to use it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Asking for help with pronunciation of a surname is appreciated.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Greet everyone in the room and establish relationships. A light handshake is appropriate with a simple nodding of the head gestures an acknowledgment of the person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Depending on the situation, punctuality may not be valued. Lateness is not meant as disrespect but is the result of a different sense of time. Explain the importance of timeliness if required and be flexible with appointment times whenever possible. Use of a watch is not common. Be aware that many do not have reliable transportation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Silence is a means of respect and thinking before speaking. Interrupting someone while he/she is talking is considered rude.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Strong emotions are not usually displayed verbally or nonverbally.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Direct questioning expecting an immediate answer is frowned upon. Ask questions in an indirect way, using a phrase such as “Tell me about…” or “Can you give more information…”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One does not have the right to speak for someone else.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Directly telling someone that he/she is wrong is considered rude.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Maintaining continued eye contact with someone during a conversation is considered disrespectful. Do not maintain direct and sustained eye contact during an assessment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Singling out a specific individual for an answer is disrespectful because if the person is wrong, he/she will meet peer disapproval.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A long pause in a conversation does not necessarily mean the person is finished talking. Wait for a nonverbal gesture that says the person has finished.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Do not use idioms, colloquialisms, or abstract ideas; those unacculturated to the dominant culture might not understand them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Greet AI/ANs with a <emphasis>light</emphasis> handshake, not a firm, pumping handshake.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A nod of the head may denote “I hear you,” not necessarily agreement with what has been said.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Loudness may be interpreted as aggressiveness.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most appreciate a space greater than 2 ft during a conversation, especially with strangers, and for some maybe up to 6 ft. Take cues from the patient.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The extended family is the primary social unit in most AI/AN culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most define family as members made up of fictive (blood-related) and nonfictive (non-blood-related) kin, extended family, and tribal community. One is rarely alone or without family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some tribes are patriarchal and patrilocal (a social system where a married couple lives with the husband’s family); others are matriarchal and matrilocal (a social system where a married couple lives with the wife’s family) in structure. Given the individuality in any family system, determine the family spokesperson ahead of time before a decision must be made.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional women are responsible for child rearing, domestic tasks, and the overall concerns of the family. In a more modernized version women’s roles are more varied. Determine in a “simple” how and where the women’s role is. Many tribes value the matriarchal role of the women especially if she is the primary caregiver.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The goal of family and parental support, within the context of the family of origin, is to foster interdependence.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family and parental support encompasses cultural and spiritual maintenance and satisfaction of physical and emotional needs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Lifelong interdependence among members is fostered.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In traditional families, children frequently attend adult events, but they are expected to remain silent unless invited to speak.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Child rearing is a family affair that includes aunts, uncles, and cousins. While the mother bears the primary child-rearing responsibility in a traditional family, fathers, and siblings are active participants.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rather than learning from direct verbal instruction, children are expected to learn through observation and from examples.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">It is acceptable for children to be disciplined in public.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children demonstrate their skills and knowledge by what they can do rather than what they say.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Gay and lesbian lifestyles have long been accepted in many tribes, although there are individual variations. Alternative lifestyles are accepted readily in most tribes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people are held in high respect and are a good source for family care.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Punctuality may not be valued. Explain the importance of timeliness in reporting to work if required.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Understanding of family dynamics as it relates to transportation, child/parent care, and work is important to understand.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Do not use idioms, colloquialisms, or abstract ideas; those unacculturated with the dominant American culture might not understand them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Greet AI/ANs with a <emphasis>light</emphasis> handshake, not a firm, pumping handshake. Introduction of others in the room is not always done so acknowledging others is important.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Do not single out a specific individual for an answer; if the person is wrong, he/she will meet peer disapproval.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Actions speak louder than words; if something is promised, make sure the promise is carried out or give an explanation as to why it could not be done.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While some American Indians are well over 6 ft tall, others are well under 6 ft, especially Eskimos.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most have little body hair, brown skin, and epicanthal folds; however, with intermarriage, many AI/ANs have no distinct characteristic features.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Eskimos are susceptible to narrow-angle glaucoma because they have a shallow chamber and thicker lenses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">AI/ANs have the highest rate of poverty of any racial group in the nation. They also have the highest rates of crime, suicide, alcoholism, gang membership, and sexual abuse. Suicide rates among AI/AN persons increased nearly 20% from 2015 (20.0 per 100,000) to 2020 (23.9), compared with a &lt;1% increase among the overall U. S. population (13.3 and 13.5, respectively)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nearly half of all Native American women (46%) have experienced rape, physical violence, or stalking by an intimate partner. One in three Indian women will, at some point in her life, experience the violence and trauma of rape.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">On some reservations, Native American women are murdered at a rate more than ten times the national average. The National Crime Information Center (2016) reported that 5712 reports of missing American Indian and Alaska Native women and girls (MMIWG) through the U. S.</para>
          <para role="Para">This vulnerability state indicates that NA women make up a significant portion of missing and murdered cases. The murder rates are ten times higher than the national average for women living on reservations, but murder is the 3rd leading cause of death for NA women.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The rate of child abuse is twice as high as the national average. For every 1000 of these cases being reported, an average of 15.2 of these cases were for American Indian/Alaska Native children.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The prevalence of diabetes mellitus is at least twice that of any other racial and ethnic group. AI/ANs have high rates of obesity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The leading causes of death are cancer, chronic liver disease, unintentional injuries, diabetes, and heart problems. AI/ANs die at higher rates than other Americans from tuberculosis, alcoholism, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, unintentional injuries, homicide, and suicide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Domestic violence rates are also alarming, with more than 4 in 5 American Indian and Alaska Native adults (83%) experiencing some form of violence in their lifetime. This translates to almost three million people who have experienced psychological aggression or physical violence by intimate partners, stalking, or sexual violence. Explain abuse laws at every opportunity. Educate teachers and tribal leaders on the signs and symptoms of suicide ideology.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While bullying does not cause suicide, a stressful environment and persistent, emotional victimization can increase a person’s risk of suicide. Incorporate anti-bullying recommendations of <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="http://stopbullying.gov"><emphasis role="RefSource"><emphasis role="bold">stopbullying.gov</emphasis></emphasis></ulink></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">More than one-quarter smoke. Partner with schools beginning in elementary school for anti-smoking campaigns.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One in five is a binge drinker. Work with tribal leaders to develop support groups for alcohol and drug misuse. Begin teaching about alcohol and drug misuse beginning in elementary schools.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Incorporate in elementary schools in conjunction with tribal leaders “I Strengthen My Nation,” an IHS campaign that empowers Native youth to resist drugs and alcohol and motivates parents to talk openly to their children about drug and alcohol use. In addition, <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="http://wernative.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">we Rnative.org</emphasis></ulink></emphasis> offers young people information on puberty, sexual violence, suicide, cultural preservation, and other important health topics.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although great variation exists, most AI/AN diets are high in fat and sugar.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include a dietary assessment as part of the intake interview.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Availability of fresh fruits and vegetables may be severely limited, especially during winter in cold climates and on reservations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask if any particular food is taboo, what foods are consumed for health promotion, and what foods are consumed during illness.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Birth control practices are usually an individual choice.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some do not discuss birth control with providers until significant trust is established.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Each tribe has specific foods believed to be beneficial for pregnancy. <emphasis role="bold">Ask about specific foods at each stage of the pregnancy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women in many tribes remain active throughout their pregnancies.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe that wearing a necklace may cause the baby to be born with the umbilical cord wrapped around its neck.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe that if a pregnant woman walks through a door backward, she will have a breech delivery.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe that blowing up balloons may cause premature rupture of the membranes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe that leaving projects unfinished may prolong labor.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Stoicism during labor and delivery is valued by some. <emphasis role="bold">Ask frequently if pain medicine is needed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Younger, more urban generations may not adhere to any traditional birthing practices.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For some tribes, the father is not usually present during the birth. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make the father feel guilty if he does not want to participate until after the delivery.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Delivering in a kneeling or squatting position is preferred by some.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In some tribes, the placenta is saved and buried, returning it to mother earth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Postpartum, the mother may be isolated according to the sex of her child; 1 month for a boy and 2 months for a girl. However, this is not a widespread belief.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many women resume their normal activities within a week and are expected to care for their babies as well as other family members.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women often turn to their mothers for advice after birth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some tribes do not name the baby for a week or longer after the delivery and may include an English name along with a tribal name. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that not naming the baby means the parents do not care about or do not want the baby.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some tribes often name a newborn after a recently deceased respected relative.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Both sexes are seen as gifts from nature.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In general, AI/AN religions do not have precise beliefs about life after death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some believe in reincarnations with rebirth as a human, as a ghost, as an animal, or as a combination of these.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Burial ceremonies vary by tribe. For example, the burial ceremony of the Zuni requires individuals to take 3 days off from work.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Autopsy is generally acceptable. <emphasis role="bold">Explain legal requirements if necessary.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Expect and respect a wide variation on bereavement.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some tribes have preserved their spiritual beliefs in writing or as an oral tradition.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some adhere to the Native North American Church. Others may be more traditional, practice mostly Christian religions, or combine the two.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Native North American Church practices have four requirements for good health: food, sleep, cleanliness, and good thoughts. The four divisions of nature are also a holistic part of spirituality: spirit, mind, body, and life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Routes of spiritual connectedness include singing, drumming, dancing, and using sweat lodges. <emphasis role="bold">Warn about dehydration when using sweat lodges.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0001ta02">5.2</link></emphasis> lists the major values between AI/AN tribes and the European American culture.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0005s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.2</emphasis> Tribal values versus European American values</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tribal traditional cultural values</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">European American values</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Group, clan, or tribal emphasis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Individual emphasis</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Present oriented</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Future oriented</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Time, always with us</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Time, use every minute</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Age</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Youth</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cooperation</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Competition</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Harmony with nature</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Conquest of nature</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Giving, sharing</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Saving</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pragmatic</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Theoretical</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Mythological</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Scientific</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Patience</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Impatience</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Mystical</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Skeptical</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Shame</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Guilt</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Permissiveness</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Social coercion</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Extended family and clan</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Immediate family</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Nonaggressive</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Aggressive</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Modest</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Over confident</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Silence</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Noise</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Respect others’ religion</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Convert others to religion</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Religion, way of life</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Religion, a segment of life</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Land, water, forest</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Land, etc.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Belong to all</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Private domains</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Beneficial, reasonable</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Avarice, greedy</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Use of resource</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Use of resource</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Religion, medicine, and healing are inseparable among AI/AN populations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Diseases can be attributed to natural or unnatural forces, the scientific theories of illness and disease, or a combination of both.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Natural remedies are preferred, although the specific herbal remedies vary significantly by tribe and region of the country and depend on environmental influences for what is available.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients about specific herbal and tribal remedies so they do not conflict with or potentiate allopathic medicines and treatment.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate IHS programs that give general directions for health-care providers: Breastfeeding Promotion and Support, Diabetes Treatment and Prevention, Epidemiology, Elder Care Initiative, Health Weight for Life, Influenza, and HIV/AIDS (</emphasis>
            <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
              <ulink url="http://www.ihs.gov">
                <emphasis role="RefSource"><emphasis role="bold">www. IHS.gov</emphasis></emphasis></ulink>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Family conferences are appreciated with serious illness.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mental illness may be seen as violation of tribal taboos or loss of harmony with the environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Organ donation is not usually practiced, but it is usually an individual choice.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">“Shaman” is often used refer to traditional AI/AN healer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spirits may be encouraged to occupy the shaman’s body during public lodge ceremonies. Drum beating and chanting aid this process.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Tribal spiritual healers may be used in combination with allopathic providers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Ask for disclosure of all treatments and explain possible complications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Partner with traditional healers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Similar to identifying over the counter, explore possible alternative treatments.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2 </emphasis> People of Navajo Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">The Navajo Nation claim the distinction of being the largest tribe: at least one-fourth Navajo blood is required to be considered a member of the tribe. The Navajo Indians are nomadic and wander great distances, searching for adequate grazing grounds for their sheep. Because of severe economic conditions and high unemployment rates, significant migration occurs into and out of the reservations. Commercial activities on reservations are limited to businesses owned by Navajo Indians or partnerships in which a Navajo must own the controlling interest. Many Native Americans who leave their reservations experience culture differences, and many return to their reservation on a regular basis to refresh and renew themselves through Blessingway ceremonies/dances.</para>
    <para role="Para">Rug-weaving and jewelry making are the most common forms of art among the Navajo. They are also noted for sand paintings, which were traditionally used in healing ceremonies by medicine people and not originally intended for sale.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Navajo language was not reduced to writing until the 1970s; consequently, many older people speak only their native language, and few are literate in the English language. The younger populations are usually bilingual, with their native tongue spoken primarily in the home. Be extremely careful when attempting to use the Navajo language, because minor variations in pronunciation may change the entire meaning of a word or phrase. Differences in pronunciation, particularly while speaking with an older Navajo, may cause a misunderstanding. Such misunderstandings make subsequent caring for the individual difficult. It is often safer to use an interpreter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Talking loudly among Navajo Indians is considered rude. Voice tones are quiet but not monotone. Their language is full of inflections with different meanings, making the language melodious with a quiet volume.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most generally do not share inner thoughts and feelings with anyone outside their clan. It may take nontribal health-care providers a long time to build trust.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Navajo are comfortable with long periods of silence. Interest in what an individual says is shown through attentive listening skills. One may be considered immature if answers are given quickly or one interrupts another who is forming a response. Failing to allow adequate time for processing information may result in an inaccurate response or no response. Allow time to respond to questions. Follow-up with a clarification to ensure comments are understood.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Touch among the Navajo is unacceptable unless one knows the person very well. Observation body language for determining cues related to the permissibility of touch. Ask permission and explain the reason for touch. Never assume that touch is ok even after establishing a relationship.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The acceptable personal space for American Indians is greater than that of American cultures. Do not take offense if the patient stands at a greater distance from what you are accustomed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Shaking hands is the traditional greeting. The handshake is light, more of a passing of the hands. Shaking hands with the Navajo is an acceptable greeting even gesturing a slight head nod is acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pointing with the finger is considered rude. Rather than pointing a finger to indicate a direction, individuals shift their lips toward the desired direction. Do not point with your finger. Rather shift your lips to or verbally confirm the direction.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sustained direct eye contact is rude and possibly confrontational. Even close friends do not maintain eye contact. Not maintaining eye contact does not mean the patient or family is being less than truthful.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The time sequence is present, past, and future, in that order. Very little planning is done for the future because the Navajo view is that many things are outside of one’s control and may affect or change the future. In fact, the Navajo language does not have a future-tense verb. To plan for the future is sometimes viewed as foolish. Events do not always start on time, but rather time starts when the group gathers. To help prevent frustration in scheduling events, time factors need to be taken into consideration and the speaker made aware of these unique time perceptions. Appointments may not always be kept, especially if someone else in the clan needs help.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people are addressed as grandmother or grandfather or as mother or father by their clan. Otherwise, they are called by a nickname. A health-care provider can call an older Navajo “grandmother” or “grandfather” as a sign of respect.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Whereas men are considered important, grandmothers and mothers are at the center of Navajo society. When providing family care, note that no decision is made until the appropriate older woman is present. Find the appropriate gatekeeper; otherwise, time is lost and the problem must be addressed again later.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The relationship between brother and sister is often more important than the relationship between husband and wife.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Even though children may be named at birth, their names are not revealed until their first laugh, when they are considered to officially have a soul and self-identity. This protects the children and keeps them in tune with the Holy People.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Infants are kept in the cradleboard until they begin walking. However, hip dysplasia may be exacerbated by cradleboards. The use of diapers has decreased the incidence of hip dysplasia because diapers bind the hips in a slightly abducted position. Encourage the use of diapers, and explain the hazard of using a cradleboard.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The use of formula has become popular, resulting in an increased incidence of bottle caries because many babies go to bed with a bottle of juice, soda or pop. This practice causes children to lose their teeth by the age of 4 years. Educate parents about dental caries and the hazards of sweet drinks and the importance of breastfeeding.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A primary social premise is that no person has the right to speak for another. Thus, children are allowed to make their own decisions; for example, children may be allowed to decide if they want to take their medicine. Explain the importance of taking medicines as prescribed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">An important ceremonial ritual for teenage girls is the onset of menarche, which is celebrated with special foods that symbolize passage into adulthood, with only aunts and grandmothers participating.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family unit consists of the nuclear family and relatives such as sisters, aunts, and their female descendants.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family goals do not center on wealth or the attainment of possessions. In fact, if one person has more wealth than other relatives, the member who has more has a responsibility to assist relatives who have less.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A sister’s children are considered the same as her own children. If a mother dies or for some other reason cannot care for her children, the grandmother or sister will raise the children as her own.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people are looked on with clear deference. Younger adults are faced with the responsibility of caring for relatives.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">There are few nursing homes, and hospitals are forced to keep patients until nursing home placement is found. When nursing home placement is found, it may be at a great distance from the family, making it difficult for family visits. If a nursing home becomes the healthcare option, it is important to carry on traditional practices as this can make the transition easier.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Alternative lifestyles are not discussed but are quietly accepted. Special individuals exist who are not looked on with disfavor but rather are accepted as being different.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Navajo are compelled to attend ceremonies and often must take time from work to do so. Balance the needs of the individual against organizational requirements for taking time off work. Allow annual leave or allow employees to earn religious compensatory time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many American Indians avoid people with whom they are in conflict. Persistence in dealing immediately with the conflict causes additional ill feelings. If one tribal member has a disagreement with another, then that member does not address the second party face to face. Rather the member tells a third person, who then relays the information to the second party. Resolve conflicts through third-party compromise.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One individual should not be singled out to answer a question because one’s mistakes are generally not forgotten by the group. Improved success is achieved if the American Indian is allowed to observe a task several times before being asked to demonstrate it. Their first effort at completing the task in front of a group should occur without error. This is especially true when delivering care to their people. Mistakes that have been made are discussed in the community. Allow adequate time for observation for a greater chance of success the first time a procedure is performed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Educational levels may be low. Work assignments should be made in clear, concrete terms. Input from the individual is at the discretion of that person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Younger supervisors may not be respected because they are not perceived as possessing the life experiences necessary to lead. Major decisions are made by the group with the assistance of the group leader, who is generally the senior woman. Thus, a young male manager on the reservation may face resistance when attempting to direct a work group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Indian Health Service is required to hire a Native American when possible. This law is referred to as the Indian Preference Law.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">English may not be their primary language. Allow extra time for a verbal response to think about a response and translate it into English. Then confirm the context of the statement.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most American Indian students are not good test takers. Although the individual may have the knowledge necessary to complete an examination, the translation of the knowledge into written form is especially difficult. When tested verbally on the same material, students tend to score higher on the examination. To the extent possible, examinations that consist of return demonstration and that do not use abstract terminology are preferred. Provide special classes that teach multiple-choice test taking.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Skin color varies from light brown to very dark brown. To assess for oxygenation in darker-skinned people, examine the mucous membranes and nail beds for capillary refill. Anemia is detected by examining the mucous membranes for pallor and the skin for a grayish hue. To assess for jaundice, examine the sclera rather than relying on skin hue. Newborns commonly have Mongolian spots on the sacral area. Do not mistake these spots for bruises and suspect child abuse.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Navajo appear Asian, with epithelial folds over the eyes. They are generally taller and thinner than other American Indian tribes. The Navajo have traditionally been good runners and excel in relay races and long-distance running. Remember that these characteristics are not seen with everyone; variations in this population do exist. Good history gathering is important and must be done in a sensitive, calm, nonthreatening manner.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0002ta03">5.3</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions in the Navajo in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The water on areas of the Navajo reservation is often impure and unchlorinated, making those who drink it susceptible to water-borne diseases such as shigellosis. Salmonella is common because of the lack of refrigeration and hypothermia because of frequent snowstorms and conditions that limit Navajo ability to gather wood. Teach patients how to protect themselves from rodent-borne diseases. At every opportunity teach about the combination of environmental and lifestyle factors to decrease the incidence of parasitic and infectious diseases and illnesses and injury prevention. Good handwashing techniques based on resources is important.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Lidocaine reactions occur in 29% of the Navajo population as compared with 11–15% of European Americans. Carefully observe for lidocaine reactions particularly when providing emergent care such as for numbing areas like for providing sutures to an individual.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0005s0002ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.3</emphasis> Health conditions common to Navajos</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Shigellosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Salmonella</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Respiratory illnesses</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Otitis media</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Plague</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tick fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Muerto Canyon Hanta virus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Combined immunodeficiency syndrome (SCIDS)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Navajo neuropathy</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Albinism</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Alcohol misuse</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Suicide</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Homicide</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Unintentional injuries</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Gastrointestinal disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Infant mortality</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Heart disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cirrhosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Fetal alcohol syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Alcohol use is more prevalent than any other form of substance abuse. Health problems related to alcoholism include motor vehicle accidents, homicide, suicide, and cirrhosis.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spousal abuse is common and is frequently related to alcohol use. The wife is the usual recipient of the abuse, but occasionally the husband is abused.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Suicide is a problem among the adolescent population. Whereas space does not permit an extensive review of the American Indian/Alaskan Native National Suicide Prevention Strategic Plan at <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="https://www.cdc.gov/suicide/pdf/suicideprevention_strategicplan-508.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cdc.gov/suicide/pdf/suicideprevention_strategicplan-508.pdf</emphasis></ulink></emphasis> health-care. Providers are encouraged to access this plan. Educate elementary school teachers on suicide ideology and make referrals to health-care providers as necessary.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Noncompliance with seat-belt use is high. Teach patients the importance of using child safety seats, helmets, and seat belts.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Life events and religious ceremonies are celebrated with food. Food is not generally associated with promoting health or illness. Herbs are used in the treatment of many illnesses to cleanse the body of ill spirits or poisons. Encourage and teach about healthy food choices and preparation practices. Access the link between what families traditionally use and provide nutritional support to what is used in the home.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sheep are a major source of meat, and sheep brains are a delicacy. Fry bread and mutton are cooked in lard. Access to fresh fruits or vegetables is minimal except during the fall. Squash is common at harvest time. Corn is an important staple. Corn pollen is used in the Blessingway and many other ceremonies.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Diets may be deficient in vitamin D because many individuals suffer from lactose intolerance or do not drink milk. Recommend nondairy foods that are high in calcium or making stews and purees using animal bones.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional Navajos do not practice birth control and, thus, do not limit the size of their families. Large families are considered favorably because, in times past, many children died at an early age. Encourage prenatal care, carefully explaining the detrimental effects on the mother and infant if prenatal care is not sought.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Twins are not considered favorably and are frequently believed to be the work of a witch, in which case one of the babies must die. Sometimes the mother may have difficulty caring for two infants. Twins may be readmitted to the hospital for neglect and failure to thrive. Culturally sensitive counseling related to adoption. Encourage tribal members to adopt the children.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">It is especially important to adhere to the many prescriptive and restrictive taboo practices related to pregnancy, which involve both husband and wife. See Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0002ta04">5.4</link></emphasis>, Navajo Taboos Regarding Expectant Women, and Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0002ta05">5.5</link></emphasis>, Taking Care of Yourself During Pregnancy: Navajo Rules for Expectant Couples.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During labor, the mother wears birthing necklaces made of juniper seeds and beads to assist with a safe birth. Woven belts or sashes are used to help push the baby out. This practice is also used by Navajo midwives in caring for their patients.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Navajo are reluctant to deliver their babies in hospital settings. They know that people have died in hospitals and thus perceive that pregnant women should not be around the dead or in a place where people have died.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A taboo practice among the Navajo is purchasing clothes for an infant before birth. Do not interpret not buying clothes for the infant as not wanting the baby. Simply provide emotional support to the expecting mother.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Immediately after birth, the placenta is buried as a symbol of the child being tied to the land. Sometimes it is burned in a fire. This is considered a safe place because fire is sacred and protects the baby against evil spirits.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After birth, the baby is given a mixture with juniper bark to cleanse its insides and rid it of mucus. In addition, a ceremonial food of corn pollen and boiled water is given. Corn symbolizes healthy nutrients and an enduring nature.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0005s0002ta04">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.4</emphasis> Navajo Taboos regarding expectant women</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">1. Do not wear two hats at once; you will have twins (or two wives)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2. Do not hit babies in the mouth; they will be stubborn and slow to talk</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">3. Do not have a weaving comb (rug) with more than five points; your baby will have extra fingers</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4. Do not have a baby cross its fingers; its mother will have another one right away</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">5. Do not swallow gum while you are pregnant; the baby will have a birthmark</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6. Do not kill animals while your wife is pregnant; the baby will look like a bird</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">7. Do not stand in the doorway when a pregnant woman is present</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">8. Do not make a slingshot while you are pregnant; the baby will be crippled</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9. Do not go to ceremonies while pregnant; it will have a bad effect on the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10. Do not eat a lot of sweet stuff while you are pregnant; the baby won’t be strong</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">11. Do not sleep too much when you are about to have a baby; the baby will mark your face with dark spots</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12. Do not look at a dead person or animal while you are pregnant; the baby will be sickly because of bad luck</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">13. Do not jump around if you are pregnant or ride a horse; it will induce labor</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">14. Do not cut gloves off at the knuckles, the baby will have short, round fingers</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">15. Do not cut a baby’s hair when it is small; it won’t think right when it gets older</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">16. Do not put on a Yei mask while your wife is pregnant; the baby will have a big head and look strange</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">17. Do not let a baby’s head stay to one side in the cradleboard; it will have a wide head</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">18. Do not watch or look at an accident while your wife is present; it will affect the baby</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">19. Do not sew on a saddle while your wife is pregnant; it will ruin the baby’s mouth</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="SimplePara">
        <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
          <ulink url="https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/MaternalChildHealth.V7.HiRez_.Sept_.30.20.pdf">
            <emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/Maternal Child Health. V7. HiRez_. Sept_.30.20.pdf</emphasis></ulink>
        </emphasis>
      </para>
      <table id="ch0005s0002ta05">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.5</emphasis> Taking care of yourself during pregnancy: Navajo rules for expectant couples</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis role="bold">During prenatal period</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis>Mind/soul</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Do’s</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Keep the peace</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Keep thoughts good</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Talk with “corn pollen sprinkled” words</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Say morning (dawn) prayers</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have shielding prayers if you have nightmares</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Don’ts</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Argue with partner or others</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Scold children</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Allow bad thoughts to occupy mind for long period of time</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Talk negatively or with criticism</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis>Body</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Do’s</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Eat foods good for baby</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Get up early and walk around</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have a Blessingway ceremony for a safe delivery</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Don’ts</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink milk or eat salt or foods taken away by Navajo ceremonies</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Lie around too much</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Tie knots</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Attend funerals or look at body of deceased person</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Be with sick people for long or go to crowded place</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Attend healing ceremonies for sick people like “Yei Bei Chai Dance”</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Look at dead animals or taxidermic trophies</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Look at eclipse of moon or sun</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Make plans for baby or prepare layette sets until after birth</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Lift heavy things</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Kill living things or cut a sheep’s throat</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Weave rugs or make pottery</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis role="bold">During labor</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis>Mind/soul</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Do’s</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Think about a good delivery</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have medicine people do “Singing Out Baby” chants</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have medicine person perform “Unraveling” songs if necessary</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Don’ts</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Let too many people observe labor; only people who are helping you in some way</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis>Body</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Do’s</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Loosen your hair</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink cornmeal mush</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wear juniper seed beads</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Burn cedar</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Hold onto sash belt when ready to push</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have someone apply gentle fundal pressure during pushing effort</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Get in squatting position for pushing</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink herbal tea to relax if necessary</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink herbal tea to strengthen contractions if necessary</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Don’ts</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Braid or tie hair in a knot</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Tie knots</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">
                <para role="SimplePara">
                  <emphasis role="bold">After birth of baby (postpartum period)</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Do’s</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Bury the placenta</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink juniper/ash tea to cleanse your insides</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink blue cornmeal mush</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Smear baby’s first stool on your face</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Breast-feed your baby</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wrap sash belt around waist for days after delivery</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Don’ts</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Drink cold liquids or be in cold draft</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Smell afterbirth blood for too long</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Show signs of displeasure if baby soils on you or during diaper change</para>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Have sexual intercourse for 3 months after delivery</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="SimplePara">
        <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
          <ulink url="https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/MaternalChildHealth.V7.HiRez_.Sept_.30.20.pdf">
            <emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/Maternal Child Health. V7. HiRez_. Sept_.30.20.pdf</emphasis></ulink>
        </emphasis>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">One death taboo involves talking with patients concerning a fatal disease or illness. Effective discussions require that the issue be presented in the third person, as if the illness or disorder occurred with someone else. Never suggest that the patient is dying. To do so would imply that the provider wishes the patient dead. If the patient does die, it would imply that the provider might have evil powers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The body must go into the afterlife as whole as possible. The body is not buried for approximately 4 days after death.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A cleansing ceremony must be performed after an individual dies or the spirit of the dead person may try to assume control of someone else’s spirit. Family members are reluctant to deal with the body because those who work with the dead must have a ceremony to protect themselves from the deceased’s spirit.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">If the person dies at home, the home/dwelling must be abandoned, or a ceremony must be held to cleanse it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Before burial, a ring is placed on the index finger of each hand, and the shoes are put on the wrong feet. This allows living relatives to recognize individuals if they come back and present themselves at ceremonial dances. Do not wear rings on your index fingers, as older people may not want to be around them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Excessive displays of emotion are not considered favorably among some tribes. Support survivors and permit family bereavement and grieving in a culturally congruent and sensitive manner that respects the beliefs of the tribe.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The American Indian religion predominates in many tribes. Sometimes hospital admissions are accompanied by traditional ceremonies and consultation with a pastor. Even if people are strong in their adopted beliefs, they honor their parents and families by having a traditional healing ceremony.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Navajo start the day with prayer, meditation, corn pollen, and running in the direction of the sun.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spirituality for most is based on harmony with nature. The meaning of life is derived from being in harmony with nature. The individual’s source of strength comes from the inner self and also depends on being in harmony with one’s surrounding.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prayers ask for harmony with nature and for health and invite blessings to help the person exist in harmony with the earth and sky. Prayer helps the Navajo to attain fulfillment and inner peace with themselves and their environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Spirituality cannot be separated from the healing process in holistic ceremonies. Illness results from not being in harmony with nature, from the spirits of evil people such as witches, or from violation of taboos. Healing ceremonies restore an individual’s balance mentally, physically, and spiritually. Assist with arrangements for healing ceremonies and practicing traditional religious beliefs and prayer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The core concepts of traditional Indian medicine are shown in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0002ta06">5.6</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0005s0002ta06">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.6</emphasis> Basic concepts of traditional Indian medicine</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Indians believe in a Supreme Creator</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Each person is a threefold being composed of mind, body, and spirit</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• All physical things, living and non-living, are part of the spiritual world</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• The spirit existed before it came into the body, and it will exist after it leaves the body</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Illness affects the mind and the spirit as well as the body</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wellness is harmony</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Natural unwellness is caused by violation of a taboo</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Unnatural wellness is caused by witchcraft</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Each individual is responsible for his or her own health</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many older people do not understand the theory of germs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Asking patients questions in order to make a diagnosis fosters mistrust. This approach is in conflict with the practice of traditional medicine men who tell people what is wrong without their having to say anything.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The medicine man is expected to diagnose the illness and prescribe necessary treatments for regaining health. In Western health care, the health-care provider asks the patient what he or she thinks is wrong and then prescribes a treatment. This practice is sometimes interpreted by American Indians as ignorance on the part of the white healer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Often great distances must be traveled to reach hospitals or health-care facilities. Many families do not have adequate transportation and must wait for others to transport them into town. Immunizations may be missed because parents do not have transportation. Pay close attention to the immunization status of patients on their arrival at the emergency department or clinic. If patients are not current with immunizations, scheduling an appointment may be a waste of time because they may not be able to return until a ride is found. Take time to administer the immunization on the spot or make a referral to the public health nursing office. It is important to address as many needs as possible during one visit as to limit the need for another visit.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pain control may be ineffective because the actual intensity of the individual’s pain is not obvious to the health-care provider and because patients do not request pain medication.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pain is viewed as something that is to be endured. Herbal medicines may be used without the knowledge of the health-care provider. Establishing trust will encourage patients to fully disclose herbal treatments used for pain control. Offer pain medicine and explain that it will promote healing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mental illness results from witches or witching (placing a curse) on a person. In these instances, a healer who deals with dreams or a crystal-gazer is consulted. Individuals may wear turquoise to ward off evil; however, a person who wears too much turquoise is sometimes thought to be an evil person and, thus, someone to avoid.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Rehabilitation as a concept is relatively new. Explain concepts of rehabilitation particular how it can link with the culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Those with physical or mental handicaps are not considered different; rather, the limitation is accepted, and a role is found for them within the society.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cultural perceptions of the sick role for the American Indian are based on the ideal of maintaining harmony with nature and with others. Older people frequently work even when they are seriously ill and often must be encouraged to rest.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Autopsy and organ donation are unacceptable practices to traditional American Indians. Explain that autopsy is a legal requirement in some instances.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0005s0002s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.2.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Provider</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Native healers are divided primarily into three categories: those working with the power of good, the power of evil, or both. Generally, these healers are divinely chosen and promote activities that encourage self-discipline, self-control, and acute body awareness. Some healers are endowed with supernatural powers, whereas others only have knowledge of herbs and specific manipulations. Acceptance of Western medicine is variable, with a blending of traditional health-care beliefs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many are suspicious of American Indian physicians. Many health concerns of American Indians can be treated by both traditional and Western healers in a culturally competent manner when these health-care providers are willing to work together and respect each other’s differences.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Western health-care providers, traditional medicine men, and herbal healers receive respect on the reservation. However, not all individuals accord equal respect to these groups, and many prefer one group over the other or use all three.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Navajo tribal health-care providers divide their knowledge into preventive measures, treatment regimens, and health maintenance. An example of a preventive measure is carrying an object or a pouch filled with objects prescribed by a medicine man that wards off the evil of a witch. Do not remove medicine pouches from patients.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The various types of traditional health-care providers are given in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0002ta07">5.7</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Male health-care providers are generally limited in the care they provide to women, especially during menses. Women are generally modest and wear several layers of slips. This practice is very common among elderly women. Provide a same-gender health-care provider for intimate care ensuring a family member is available. Not necessarily right at the examination table but within the room.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0005s0002ta07">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.7</emphasis> Traditional American Indian health-care providers</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">1. People who can use their power only for good can transform themselves into other forms of life and can maintain cultural integration in times of stress</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2. People who can use their powers for both evil and good are expected to do evil against someone’s enemies. People in this group know witchcraft, poisons, and ceremonies designed to afflict the enemy</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">3. The diviner diagnostician, such as a crystal-gazer, can see what caused the problem but cannot implement a treatment. Another example of this type is a hand trembler. These people, instead of using crystals, practice hand trembling over the sick person to determine the cause of an illness</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4. Specialist medicine people treat the disease after it has been diagnosed and specialize in the use of herbs, massage, or midwifery</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">5. Those who care for the soul send guardian spirits to restore a lost soul</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6. Singers, who are considered to be the most special, cure through the power of their song. These healers use laying on of hands and usually remove objects or draw disease-causing objects from the body while singing</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0003" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How does suicide, violence, and rape in AI/AN communities compare with the national average? What can health-care providers do to help decrease these conditions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the major health conditions of AI/ANs? On which of these can the health-care provider have a major impact.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the major high-risk health behaviors among AI/ANs? What are some major tactics to help decrease these behaviors?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>List the major values between AI/AN tribes and the European American culture.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Some AI/ANs lack trust in Indian physicians. Why might this happen? What can you do to help gain their trust in Indian physicians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the names of traditional healers? What conditions do they treat.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What tactics can be used to incorporate traditional healers with allopathic providers?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>List several birthing practices of the Navajo.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the tenets of the Native American Church?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How might you approach explaining to a patient and family of an impending death of a Navajo?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0004" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0005s0004bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib01">Navajo Nation Maternal and Child Health Needs Assessment (2020)<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/MaternalChildHealth.V7.HiRez_.Sept_.30.20.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.aastec.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/Maternal Child Health. V7. HiRez_. Sept_.30.20.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib02">Adakai M, Sandoval-Rosario M, Xu F, Aseret-Manygoats T, Allison M, Greenlund KJ et al (2018) Health disparities among American Indians/Alaska Natives—Arizona, 2017. Morb Mort Wkly Rep 67(47):1314–1318<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6747a4">https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6747a4</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib03">American Indian Religious Freedom Act of 1978 (AIRFA) (1978) 42 U. S. C. § 1996</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib04">Anderson RW (2016) Native American reservation constitutions. Const Polit Econ 27:377–398. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10602-016-9225-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10602-016-9225-7</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10602-016-9225-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10602-016-9225-7</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib05">Blood Quantum (2019) American Indian Enterprise &amp; Business Council-CDC, NGO, 501C3. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.aiebc.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.aiebc.org</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib06">Blood Quantum and Sovereignty: A Guide (2022) Native Governance Center. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nativegov.org/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://nativegov.org/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib07">Breathett K, Sims M, Gross M, Jackson EA, Jones EJ, Navas-Acien A et al (2020) Cardiovascular health in American Indians and Alaska Natives a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Circulation 141: e948–e959<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1161/CIR.0000000000000773">https://doi.org/10.1161/CIR.0000000000000773</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32460555">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7351358">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib08">Bureau of Indian Affairs (BIA) (2023). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bia.gov/bia"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bia.gov/bia</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib09">Carlson LA, Roberts MA (2006) Indian lands, “Squatterism,” and slavery: economic interests and the passage of the Indian removal act of 1830. Explor Econ Hist 43:486–504. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eeh.2005.06.003">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eeh.2005.06.003</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eeh.2005.06.003">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eeh.2005.06.003</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib10">Cherokee Tribal Policy (2023).<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.cherokee.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.cherokee.org</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib11">Childbearing Practices of Native Alaskans (2020) </bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib12">Clark Callister L (2016) Integrating cultural beliefs and practices when caring for childbearing women and families. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://nursekey.com/integrating-cultural-beliefs-and-practices-when-caring-for-childbearing-women-and-families/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://nursekey.com/integrating-cultural-beliefs-and-practices-when-caring-for-childbearing-women-and-families/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib13">Cooper LA, Ortega AN, Ammerman AS, Buchwald D, Paskett ED, Powell LH et al (2015) Beyond health equity: achieving wellness within American Indian and Alaska Native communities. Am. J. Public Health 105(S3): S376–S379<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2014.302447">https://doi.org/10.2105/AJPH.2014.302447</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib14">Dennis MK, Brewer JP (2017) Rearing generations: Lakota grandparents commitment to family and community. J Across Cult Gerontol 32:95–113. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-016-9299-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-016-9299-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-016-9299-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-016-9299-8</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib15">Department of Interior Bureau of Indian Affairs Federal Register (2019) Indian entitles recognized by and eligible to receive services from the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs. 84(22). 1 Feb 2019/Notices</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib16">Diabetes and American Indians/Alaska Natives. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/diabetes-and-american-indiansalaska-natives"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://minorityhealth.hhs.gov/diabetes-and-american-indiansalaska-natives</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib17">Drug Abuse &amp; Native American Indian Youth (2014). Accessed 6 Oct 2014<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://dodgingbullets.org/drug-abuse-native-american-indian-youth/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://dodgingbullets.org/drug-abuse-native-american-indian-youth/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib18">Ficklin E, Tehee M, Killgore RM, Isaacs D, Mack S, Ellington T (2022) Fighting for our sisters: community advocacy and action for missing and murdered Indigenous women and girls. J Soc Issues 78:53–78<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/josi.12478">https://doi.org/10.1111/josi.12478</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib19">Gaffney A, Mc Cormick D (2017) America: equity and equality in health 2. The Affordable Care Act: implications for health-care equity. Lancet 389:1442–1452<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30786-9">https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(17)30786-9</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=28402826">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib20">Gampa V, Smith C, Muskett O, King C, Sehn H, Malone J et al (2017) Cultural elements underlying the community health representative-client relationship on Navajo Nation. BMC Health Serv Res 17:19. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-016-1956-7">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-016-1956-7</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-016-1956-7">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-016-1956-7</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=28069014">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5223387">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib21">Garrow CE (2015) Tribal criminal law and procedure, 2nd edn. Rowman &amp; Littlefield, London</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib22">Gone JP, Blumstein KP, Dominic D, Fox N, Jacobs J, Lynn RS et al (2017) Teaching tradition: diverse perspectives on the pilot urban American Indian Traditional Spirituality Program. J Community Psychol 59(3-4):382–389. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajcp.12144">https://doi.org/10.1002/ajcp.12144</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/ajcp.12144">https://doi.org/10.1002/ajcp.12144</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib23">Greenleaf AT, Roessger KM, Williams JM, Motsenbocker J (2019) Effects of a rite of passage ceremony on veterans’ well-being. J Couns Dev 97:171–181. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/jcad.12248">https://doi.org/10.1002/jcad.12248</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/jcad.12248">https://doi.org/10.1002/jcad.12248</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib24">Greensky C, Stapleton MA, Walsh K, Gibbs L, Abrahason J, Finnie DM et al (2014) A qualitative study of traditional healing practices among American Indians with chronic pain. Pain Med 15:1795–1802<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/pme.12488">https://doi.org/10.1111/pme.12488</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=25041140">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib25">Halabi S (2019) The role of provinces, states, and territories in shaping federal policy for indigenous peoples health. Am Rev Can Stud 49(2):231–246. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/02722011.2019.1613797">https://doi.org/10.1080/02722011.2019.1613797</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/02722011.2019.1613797">https://doi.org/10.1080/02722011.2019.1613797</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib26">Hanson JD (2012) Understanding prenatal health care for American Indian women in a northern plains tribe. J Transcult Nurs 23(1):29–37. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659611423826">https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659611423826</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659611423826">https://doi.org/10.1177/1043659611423826</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=22052090">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib27">Haozous EA, Strickland CJ, Palacios JF, Arambula Solomon TG (2014) Blood politics, ethnic identity, and racial misclassification among American Indians and Alaska Natives. IJERPH 2014:1–9. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/321604">https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/321604</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/321604">https://doi.org/10.1155/2014/321604</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib28">Health Care for Urban American Indian and Alaska Native Women (2015) Number 515 (Reaffirmed 2021). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.acog.org/clinical/clinical-guidance/committee-opinion/articles/2012/01/health-care-for-urban-american-indian-and-alaska-native-women"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.acog.org/clinical/clinical-guidance/committee-opinion/articles/2012/01/health-care-for-urban-american-indian-and-alaska-native-women</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib29">Indian Affairs Manual (2019) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bia.gov/policy-forms/manual"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bia.gov/policy-forms/manual</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib30">Indian Health Service (2023) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ihs.gov"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ihs.gov</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib31">Indian Health Service “Fact Sheets” (2023) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ihs.gov/newsroom/factsheets/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ihs.gov/newsroom/factsheets/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib32">Indian Health Service Indian Health Disparities (2019) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ihs.gov/aboutihs"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ihs.gov/aboutihs</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib33">Indian Preference Law (2000) Indian Health Service. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.opm.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.opm.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib34">Indian Removal Act: 1830 (2023) Library of Congress. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/Indian.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/Indian.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib35">Johansson P, Schober DJ, Leon MA, Brueggemann G, Tutsch SF, Lyden E et al (2019) Adapting an evidence-based cardiovascular disease risk reduction intervention to urban American Indians. J Health Care Poor Underserved 30(2):618–636. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2019.0046">https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2019.0046</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2019.0046">https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2019.0046</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31130541">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib36">Johnson-Jennings M, Billiot S, Walters K (2020) Returning to our roots: tribal health and wellness through land-based healing. Genealogy 4(91):1–21</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib37">Joseph G (2021) The role of sovereignty in Indigenous community-based health interventions: a qualitative metasynthesis. Am J Community Psychol 2023:1–18</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib38">Ka’apu K, Burnette CE (2019) A culturally informed systematic review of mental health disparities among adult indigenous men and women of the USA: what is known? Br J Soc Work 49:880–898<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/bjsw/bcz009">https://doi.org/10.1093/bjsw/bcz009</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31308574">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6615176">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib39">Leavitt RA, Ertl A, Sheats K, Petrosky E, Ivey-Stephenson A, Fowler KA (2018) Suicides among American Indian/Alaska Natives—national violent death reporting system, 18 states, 2003-2014. Centers for Dis Control Prev Morb Mort Wkly Rep 67(8):237–242. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6708a1">https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6708a1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6708a1">https://doi.org/10.15585/mmwr.mm6708a1</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib40">Lewis JP, Boyd K, Allen J (2018) “We raise our grandchildren as our own:” Alaska Native grandparents raising grandchildren in Southwest Alaska. J Cross Cult Gerontol 33:265–286. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9350-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9350-z</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9350-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10823-018-9350-z</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29797108">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib41">Lopez JH, Bobroff KL (2019) Rooted indigenous core values: culturally appropriate curriculum and methods for civic education reflective of Native American culture and learning styles. Multicult Perspect 21(2):119–126. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/15210960.2019.1606640">https://doi.org/10.1080/15210960.2019.1606640</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/15210960.2019.1606640">https://doi.org/10.1080/15210960.2019.1606640</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib42">Masotti P, Dennem J, Banuelos K, Seneca C, Valerio-Leonce G, Inong CT et al (2023) The Culture is Prevention Project: measuring cultural connectedness and providing evidence that culture is a social determinant of health for Native Americans. BMC Pub Health 23(1):741–751. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-15587-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-15587-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-15587-x">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-023-15587-x</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib43">Mihesuah DA (2015) Sustenance and health among the five tribes in Indian territory, postremoval to statehood. Ethnohistory 62:263–284. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1215/00141801-2854317">https://doi.org/10.1215/00141801-2854317</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1215/00141801-2854317">https://doi.org/10.1215/00141801-2854317</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib44">Mitchell FM (2019) Water (in)security and American Indian Health: social and environmental justice implications for policy, practice, and research. R Soc Public Health 176:98–105. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2018.10.010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2018.10.010</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2018.10.010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2018.10.010</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib45">National Archives and Records Administration (2019) U. S. Department of the Interior. A guide to tracing American Indian &amp; Alaska Native ancestry. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.archives.gov/research/native-americans/dawes/intro.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.archives.gov/research/native-americans/dawes/intro.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib46">Native American Heritage Month (2023). Accessed 30 Nov 2023<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nativeamericanheritagemonth.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nativeamericanheritagemonth.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib47">Native Knowledge 360° Framework for Essential Understandings about American Indians. Smithsonian National Museum of the American Indian. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://americanindian.si.edu/nk360/pdf/NMAI-Essential-Understandings.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://americanindian.si.edu/nk360/pdf/NMAI-Essential-Understandings.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib48">Nava LT, Zambrano JM, Arviso KP, Brochetti D, Becker KI (2015) Nutrition-based interventions to address metabolic syndrome in the Navajo: a systematic review. JCN 24:3024–3045. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.libproxy.uccs.edu/10.1111/jocn.12921"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.libproxy.uccs.edu/10.1111/jocn.12921</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=26239838">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib49">Navajo Nation Government Reform Project Prepared By Dine Policy Institute (2013) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://ongd.navajo-nsn.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://ongd.navajo-nsn.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib50">Navajo Nation Human Rights Commission 2014 Shadow report, regarding the United States of America report submitted by states parties under Article 9 of the International Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination. Navajo Nation, AZ</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib51">Navajo Tribal Policy (2023).<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.cherokee.org/Services/146/Page/Default.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.cherokee.org/Services/146/Page/Default.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib52">Ng AE, Adjaye-Gbewonyo D, Vahratian A (2023) Health conditions and health care use among American Indian and Alaska Native adults by tribal land residential status: United States, 2019–2021. U. S. Department of Health and Human Services CDC National Center for Health Statistics No. 185. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/index.htm"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/index.htm</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib53">O’Keefe VM, Reger GM (2017) Suicide among American Indian/Alaska Native military service members and veterans. Psychol Serv 14(3):289–294. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000117">https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000117</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000117">https://doi.org/10.1037/ser0000117</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=28805413">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib54">Office of Indian Education (2023). Accessed 1 Dec 2023<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ade.state.az.us/asd/indianed"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.ade.state.az.us/asd/indianed</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib55">Office of Program Planning and Development Navajo Area Indian Health Service: Area Profile (1988) Navajo Area Indian Health Service</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib56">Official Native American Church of North America (2024) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nativeamerican.church/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://nativeamerican.church/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib57">Ornelas IJ, Osterbauer K, Woo L, Bishop SK, Deschenie D, Beresford SAA (2018) Gardening for health: patterns of gardening and fruit and vegetable consumption among the Navajo. J Community Health 43:1053–1060. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10900-018-0521-1">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10900-018-0521-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10900-018-0521-1">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10900-018-0521-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29779075">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8664238">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib58">Pacheco JA, Pacheco CM, Lewis C, Williams C, Barnes C, Rosenwasser L et al (2015) Ensuring healthy American Indian generations for tomorrow through safe and healthy indoor environments. Int J Environ Res Public Health 12:2810–2822. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph120302810">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph120302810</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph120302810">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph120302810</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=25749318">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4377934">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib59">Payne HE, Steele M, Bingham JL, Sloan CD (2018) Identifying and reducing disparities in mental health outcomes among American Indians and Alaskan Natives using public health, mental healthcare and legal perspectives. Adm Policy Ment Health Ment Health Serv Res 45:5–14. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-016-0777-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-016-0777-7</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-016-0777-7">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10488-016-0777-7</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib60">Pollock NJ, Naicker K, Loro A, Mulay S, Colman I (2018) Global incidence of suicide among Indigenous peoples: a systematic review. BMC Med 16(1):145–152. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-018-1115-6">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-018-1115-6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-018-1115-6">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-018-1115-6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30122155">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6100719">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib61">Public Law 67-85 (1921) The Snyder Act of 1921. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bia.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bia.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib62">Public Law 93-638 (1975) Indian Self-Determination and Education Assistance Act of 1975. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bia.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bia.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib63">Purnall LD, Fenkl EA (2021) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach cultural competence concepts in nursing care, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib64">Ross RE, Garfield LD, Brown DS, Raghavan R (2015) The Affordable Care Act and implications for health care services for American Indian and Alaska Native individuals. J Health Care Poor Underserved 26(4):1081–1088. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2015.0129">https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2015.0129</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2015.0129">https://doi.org/10.1353/hpu.2015.0129</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=26548665">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4824684">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib65">Sanchez-Rivera AI, Jacobs P, Spence C (2023) Detailed data for hundreds of American Indian and Alaska Native tribes. A look at the largest American Indian and Alaska Native tribes and villages in the nation, tribal areas and states. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/10/2020-census-dhc-a-aian-population.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/10/2020-census-dhc-a-aian-population.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib66">Schmidt RW (2011) American Indian identity and Blood Quantum in the 21st century: a critical review. Journal of Anthropology 2011:1–9<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/549521">https://doi.org/10.1155/2011/549521</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib67">Sequist TD (2021) Improving the health of the American Indian and Alaska Native Population. JAMA 325(1):1035–1036<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2021.0521">https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.2021.0521</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33724330">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib68">Shaeffer Riley N (2016) The new trail of tears. Encounter Books, New York</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib69">Sharma G, Keliher A, Deen J, Parker T, Hagerty T, Choi EE et al (2023) AHA scientific statement status of maternal cardiovascular health in American Indian and Alaska Native individuals: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association. Cir Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes 2023:443–455. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ahajournals.org/journal/circoutcomes"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.ahajournals.org/journal/circoutcomes</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib70">Spirituality (2002) Alaskan Native Knowledge Network. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ankn.uaf.edu/NPE/spirituality.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.ankn.uaf.edu/NPE/spirituality.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib71">Stopbullying.gov (2023) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.stopbullying.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.stopbullying.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib72">Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (2019) About us. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.samhsa.gov/about-us"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.samhsa.gov/about-us</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib73">Traditional Native American Values and Behavior (2023) <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://nwindian.evergreen.edu/curriculum/ValuesBehaviors.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://nwindian.evergreen.edu/curriculum/Values Behaviors.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib74">Tribal Enrollment Process (2023) U. S. Department of the Interior. Accessed 1 Dec 2023<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.doi.gov/tribes/enrollment"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.doi.gov/tribes/enrollment</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib75">Trude ACB, Kharmats A, Jock B, Liu D, Lee K, Martins PA et al (2015) Patterns of food consumption are associated with obesity, self-reported diabetes and cardiovascular disease in five American Indian communities. Ecol Food Nutr 54:437–454. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/03670244.2014.922070">https://doi.org/10.1080/03670244.2014.922070</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/03670244.2014.922070">https://doi.org/10.1080/03670244.2014.922070</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=26036617">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib76">U. S. Census Bureau (2020) Census Report for 2020. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.census.gov"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.census.gov</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib77">U. S. Department of the Interior: Bureau of Indian Affairs (2016) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bia.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bia.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib78">U. S. Department of the Interior: Bureau of Indian Education (2016) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bie.edu/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bie.edu/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib79">U. S. Government Accountability Office GAO (2012) Report to the honorable Dan Boren, house of representatives Indian issues federal funding for non-federally recognized tribes GAO-12-348</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib80">United Nations Human Rights Office of the high commissioner indigenous peoples and the United Nations human rights system, Fact Sheet No. 9 Rev. 2</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib81">Villarroel MA, Clarke TC, Norris T (2020) Health of American Indian and Alaska Native adults, by urbanization level: United States, 2014–2018. U. S. Department of Health and Human Services CDC National Center for Health Statistics No. 372. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/index.htm"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/index.htm</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib82">Walters KL, Johnson-Jennings M, Stroud S, Rasmus S, Charles B, John S et al (2018) Growing from our roots: strategies for developing culturally grounded health promotion interventions in American Indians, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian communities. Prev Sci 21:1–11. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-018-0952-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-018-0952-z</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-018-0952-z">https://doi.org/10.1007/s11121-018-0952-z</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib83">Wang H (2021) Why the Navajo Nation was hit so hard by coronavirus: understanding the disproportionate impact of the COVID-19 pandemic. Appl Geogr 134:1–10. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2021.102526">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2021.102526</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2021.102526">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2021.102526</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib84">WERNATIVE. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.wernative.org/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.wernative.org/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib85">Yeager Washington E, van Hover S (2011) Teaching about Navajo citizenship and sovereignty. Soc Stud 102(2):80–87. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00377996.2010.497177">https://doi.org/10.1080/00377996.2010.497177</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/00377996.2010.497177">https://doi.org/10.1080/00377996.2010.497177</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0004bib86">Zamora-Kapoor A, Sinclair K, Nelson L, Lee H, Buchwald D (2019) Obesity risk factors in American Indians and Alaska Natives: a systematic review. Pub Health 174:85–96. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2019.05.021">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2019.05.021</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2019.05.021">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.puhe.2019.05.021</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
