<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0022" label="22">
  <title>22. People of Italian Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0022s0004">
    <title>22. People of Italian Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_22">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_22</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Alessandro Stievano</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0022">1</link></superscript>, </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosario Caruso</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0022">2</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Gennaro Rocco</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0022">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Centre of Excellence for Nursing Scholarship, Opi Rome, Rome, Italy</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Department of Biomedical Sciences for Health, University of Milan, Milan, Italy</para>
    <para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Alessandro Stievano</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:alessandro.stievano@unicamillus.org">alessandro.stievano@unicamillus.org</ulink></para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosario Caruso</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:Rosario.caruso@grupposandonato.it">Rosario.caruso@grupposandonato.it</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Heritage, Nutrition, Pregnancy, Health behavior, Spirituality</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0022s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Italy is a parliamentarian Republic located in Southern Western Europe. Positioned in the middle of the Mediterranean Sea, it consists of a peninsula delimited by the Alps and surrounded by islands like Sicilia and Sardinia. Its population consists of nearly 60 million inhabitants; 5.3% of them come from different countries with a million of Romanian people. However, this chapter mainly focuses on the beliefs and practices of the Italians from mainland Italy. The large populations of Italians in the United States are not a homogeneous group and vary according to acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>. Italian Americans are concentrated in New York, New Jersey, Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, and California. Italian enclaves, or “Little Italy” areas, can be found in major cities throughout the United States.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <para role="Para">The official language of Italy is Italian; however, there are more than 20 dialects. Many second-generation Italian Americans do not speak Italian well or at all or speak in a jargon that sometimes is not understood by native Italians.</para>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">When a dialect-specific interpreter is not available, the interpreter should select words that have pure meanings from Tuscan Italian, which is the official language in the country (the language prompted in the Middle-Age by Dante Alighieri who is considered the Father of the Italian language).</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Italian discussions can become quite passionate, with voice volume raised and many people speaking at once. <emphasis role="bold">High voice volume does not mean anger, but rather passionate communication and this is true especially for inhabitants of the Southern parts of the country who immigrated in the United States.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Their willingness to share thoughts and feelings among family members is a major distinguishing characteristic. Positive and negative emotions and sentiments are permissible and encouraged with family members. Expressions of affection might erupt, and frequent kissing reaffirms the emotional bond among Italians.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The typical kiss is a kiss on each cheek. Gestures demonstrate a range of feelings, from eloquence to intense anger, and are conveyed in an economical, subtle, flowing, and almost imperceptible manner. For example, a slowly raised chin means “I don’t know.”</para>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Observe patients for nonverbal cues to obtain the full meaning of verbal communication</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Touching and embracing family and friends are common. Touching between men and women, between men, and between women can be observed during verbal communication.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Past orientation is evidenced by the pride Italians take in their home country’s rich Roman heritage. A future-oriented temporality is evidenced by the importance given to planning and saving for the future. First-generation and newer immigrants view time as an approximation rather than categorically imperative; second- and third-generation Italians adhere to clock time at least in the work situation and for appointments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The order of first and last names is frequently reversed in Italy. Pietropaolo Vincenzo is often used when Vincenzo is the person’s first name and Pietropaolo is the last name. Nicknames are common and used among family and friends.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A person is called by the first or given name in social situations and by a title such as Miss, Ms., Mr., Mrs., or Dr. and his or her last or family surname in the health-care environment. Ask recent immigrants the order of the name to ensure an accurate health-care record.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <para role="Para">Traditional families recognize the father’s authority. The father’s decision may be accepted as a strong principle, even among his married children. To criticize one’s father is considered disrespect toward the entire family.</para>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women usually dominate decision-making on child-rearing issues and family social events. Even though traditional roles remain strong in second- and third-generation families, a trend toward more egalitarian relationships is evolving.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children are taught to have good manners and respect for older people. Boys and girls are encouraged to be independent and expected to contribute to the family’s support as soon as they are old enough to work. <emphasis role="bold">Adolescent girls are expected to remain virgins until they marry even; this habit is rapidly evolving.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The home is the focus of family gatherings. Sons and daughters visit frequently during the week and after church on Sundays to share a large meal at the parents’ house.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">To many older people, the ideal living situation is to maintain one’s own home near one’s children. Older people receive respect, gratitude, and love in return for their many sacrifices.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Italian Americans have an actively functioning kinship and extended family system that is the primary focus of solidarity for the nuclear family. <emphasis role="bold">Because the extended family is close and frequent visits are important, Italians make special arrangements for visitation when patients are in acute or long-term care facilities.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Social status for most families comes from family lineage. Titles are more important than names. It is important to i <emphasis role="bold">dentify Italians with a title such as Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., or Dr. to increase compliance with health treatments and regimens.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most do not reject another family member because of an infraction or alternative lifestyle such as divorce, living together before marriage, or being involved in a same-sex relationship. The individual is accepted without consequences.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When the need arises, Italians foster social support referrals for gays or lesbians and assist patients in contacting dedicated services or religious groups such as Dignity USA.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Italians living in the United States are punctual, and rarely miss work commitments due to a cold, headache, or minor illnesses. If completing their work requires staying later, they do so.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although the family is of utmost importance to Italians, work takes priority over family unless serious family situations arise. This cultural predisposition parallels the European American work ethic.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because of language barriers, first-generation Italians and newer immigrants are more likely to accept assigned tasks without expecting any decision-making authority.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Italian discussions can become quite passionate, with voice volume raised and many people speaking at once. <emphasis role="bold">High voice volume does not necessarily mean anger but rather passionate communication.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Italians as a group have varied physical characteristics. Those from a predominantly northern background have lighter skin, lighter hair, and blue eyes, whereas those from the south of Rome, particularly from Sicily, have dark, often curly hair; dark eyes; and olive-colored skin.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In dark-skinned patients, the skin turns ashen instead of blue in the presence of cyanosis and decreased hemoglobin levels. Examine the sclera, conjunctiva, buccal mucosa, tongue, lips, nailbeds, and palms of the hands and soles of the feet. To assess for jaundice, look at the conjunctiva and in the buccal mucosa for patches of bilirubin pigment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0022s0001ta01">22.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Italians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mediterranean-type G-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G-6-PD) deficiency and β-thalassemia has a profound effect on drug metabolism. Because of conditions such as hypoxemia and acidosis, the ingestion of fava beans and the administration of sulfonamides, antimalarial agents, salicylates, and naphtha quinolones can exacerbate these conditions; take extra precaution when prescribing these drug therapies especially from Italians who originated from Sardinia.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0022s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 22.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Italian Americans</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health condition</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cause</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Familial Mediterranean fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">G-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Coronary artery disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Vogt-Koyanagi-Harada syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Nasopharyngeal cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many immigrants continue to smoke. Alcoholism also presents a risk in this group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assess for illnesses related to smoking and alcohol misuse, especially among newer immigrants. Encourage patients to cease or decrease smoking. Incorporate anti-smoking campaigns in elementary school. Promote responsible drinking.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food is symbolic of a connection between a child and the parents; food represents the product of the father’s labor, prepared with care by the mother. A mother may demonstrate her affection by feeding her family and anyone else she likes. To the average “mom,” love is a four-letter word: food.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The diet, rich in vegetables, pasta, fruit, fish, and cheese, varies according to the region of Italy from which the individual originated. Northern Italian foods are rich in cream and cheese, resulting in a potentially high intake of fat. Southern Italian foods are prepared in red sauces, spices, and added salt and constitute the famous Mediterranean diet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Because of regional variations in food selections and preparation practices, specifically inquire about the diet, preferably during intake assessments.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Dietary staples are spaghetti, lasagna, ravioli, fettuccine, special spaghetti called linguine or trenette with pesto, tortellini, bucatini, and rigatoni. Vegetables, fresh fruit, and beans are common. Other popular Italian foods include lentils; sausage; eggplant parmigiana; salami; olive oil; espresso and cappuccino coffee; wine; ice cream (gelato); pastries such as cannoli and biscotti; and cheeses such as provolone, gorgonzola, ricotta, pecorino cheese, and parmesan cheese. Other common dishes include escarole, Caesar salad, calzone, and pizza. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0022s0001ta02">22.2</link></emphasis> lists the Italian names of popular foods with their descriptions and ingredients. Wine is taken at almost every meal, and red wine, mixed with water, is given to children with meals to maintain healthy blood.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A common practice in Italian alternative medicine for health promotion is eating a clove of garlic every night before going to bed to prevent upper respiratory infections. Garlic may also be worn around the neck when there is an epidemic of influenza or other upper respiratory ailments to prevent the wearer from getting the infection. Eating a fresh raw egg every morning keeps the person strong. Fresh dandelions are used to make a salad or are boiled to make soup to give the person strength.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0022s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 22.2</emphasis> Italian foods</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Common name</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Description</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Ingredients</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Calamari</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Squid, fried or on pasta</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Floured squid fried in olive oil or in red sauce</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Frittata</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Italian omelet</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Eggs, peppers, and onions cooked in olive oil</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Minestrone</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Soup with greens</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Escarole and beans with garlic and other herbs</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parmigiana di melanzana</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Eggplant parmesan</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Eggplant, tomato sauce, bread crumbs, Parmesan cheese, and mozzarella cheese</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pasta con pesto</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pesto sauce served over linguine or trenette</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Sauce of basil, nuts, olive oil, and garlic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pasta e fagioli</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Macaroni and beans</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Shell-shaped pasta, kidney beans, and tomato sauce</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pasta marinara</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pasta in tomato sauce</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tomato sauce</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pizza fritta</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Fried dough with sugar and cinnamon</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Bread dough fried in oil and sprinkled with sugar and cinnamon</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Prosciutto</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Thinly sliced ham</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Delicate, thin ham served with melon</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Spaghetti aglio e olio</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Spaghetti with olive oil and garlic</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Spaghetti, olive oil, garlic, and red pepper</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tortellini</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Little rounds of pasta in white or red sauce</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pasta dough stuffed with meat and/or cheese</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Veal scaloppine</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Medallions of veal</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Veal sautéed with wine, butter, and lemon</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many third-generation Italian Americans use birth control from the beginning of marriage; sex is commonly discussed in the family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sprinkling salt under and around the bed of a newly married couple makes them fertile.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common beliefs and customs about pregnancy are shown in Box <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0022s0001ad01">22.1</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some women still prefer having their children delivered at home by a family physician or a midwife. If labor does not progress rapidly enough, a neighbor has to spit out the window. This ritualistic spitting has the power to break any magic spell that might have brought the ill fortune of slow labor. Nowadays, f <emphasis role="bold">ew Italian Americans believe in many of these traditional practices.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A traditional postpartum woman is not allowed to wash her hair, take a shower, or resume her domestic chores for 2 or 3 weeks after birth so she can rest. The woman’s mother and other female family members tend to the chores and assist with the care of the new baby.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mothers are expected to breastfeed to restore the health of the reproductive organs and keep the mother and baby free of infections. The size of the baby is perceived as an index of the successful maintenance of maternal and wifely responsibilities. <emphasis role="bold">However, People of Italian origins tend to comprehend that to be born oversized does not always mean to be in a good health.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <sidebar id="ch0022s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3 ParaTypeOverview">
        <title>Box 22.1 Beliefs About Pregnancy</title>
        <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Traditional beliefs related to pregnancy include the following:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
          <listitem>
            <para role="Para">Coffee spills may result in the baby being born with a birthmark where the coffee was spilled.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para role="Para">Women must abstain from sexual relationships while pregnant.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para role="Para">If the expectant mother craves for a particular food that is not satisfied, a congenital anomaly may occur or the baby will be marked.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para role="Para">If a pregnant woman is not given the food she smells, the fetus moves and a miscarriage results.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para role="Para">A pregnant woman should not reach over her head because harm may come to the baby.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Death is a great social loss and brings an immediate response from the community. It means sending food and flowers (chrysanthemums), giving money, and congregating at the home of the deceased. Friends and distant relatives bring food. The funeral procession to the cemetery is a symbol of family status, which is determined by the number of cars in the procession.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within the context of fatalism in Catholicism, many Italians view death as God’s will; thus, a fatal diagnosis may not be discussed with the ill family member.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Emotional outpourings can be profuse. Women, especially form the South, may mourn dramatically, even histrionically, for the whole family. They do not merely weep; they may rage against death for the harm it has done to the family. Family members may moan and scream for the deceased throughout the church service. Screaming is an effort to ensure that Jesus, Mary, and the saints hear what the bereaved are thinking and feeling.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The real time of sorrow comes at the end of the ceremony when the priest and nonfamily congregation say good-bye. At this time, the family is left on its own for a time with the loved one. Older women may throw themselves onto the casket to prevent it from leaving the church.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While men mourn, they do so in the fashion of <emphasis>pazienza</emphasis> (patience). Their constant, silent, and expressionless presence may be their only act of public mourning. When the loss is a child or spouse, expressions of grief continue for years.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">In a more globalized and interconnected society, these death rituals tend not to be so striking anymore; however, for very traditional families they still have a strong significance.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">More traditional families hold anniversary masses for the deceased and wear black for months or years.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The predominant religion is traditional Roman Catholicism, the center of which is the celebration of Mass, the Eucharist, which is the commemoration of Christ’s sacrificial death and of his resurrection. Other sacraments are baptism, confirmation, confession, matrimony, ordination, and anointing of the sick. When a loved one becomes ill, prayers are said at home and in church for the person’s health.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">To help patients to obtain the basic rites of the Sacraments of the Sick, which includes anointing, communion, and, if possible a blessing by the priest is crucial for many Italians.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most pray to the Virgin Mary, the Madonna, and a number of saints.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Even though Catholics are obligated to fast or abstain from meat and meat products on certain days of the year, the sick are not bound by this practice.</para>
          <para role="Para">Despite the church’s exception for the sick, many first-generation immigrants choose to fast. Respect fasting if it is not harmful to the patient’s health condition is seen as a sign of respect.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Prayer and having faith in God and the saints help Italian Americans through illnesses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Niceties of Catholic orthodoxy and enlightened learning are employed together with pagan practices such as beliefs in witches, ghosts, and supernatural entities. The lessons of common sense and science are freely mingled with those of magico-religious beliefs. Many Italian American families display shrines to the Blessed Virgin in their backyards.</para>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Respect and acknowledge religious beliefs to gain the trust of patients</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In traditional terms, illnesses are attributable to (a) wind currents that carry disease, (b) contamination, (c) heredity, (d) supernatural (God’s will) or human causes, and (e) psychosomatic interactions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within the context of fatalism, diseases largely run their own course; thus, it is better to leave the investigation into health problems until a condition becomes so obvious that it cannot be neglected. <emphasis role="bold">Health-care providers should</emphasis> p <emphasis role="bold">rovide factual information and dispel myths.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Nervousness, hysteria, and many other mental illnesses are attributed to an evil spirit entering the body and remaining in the body until it is cast out by making its abiding place so unpleasant that it is forced to leave.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The extended family may be the frontline resource for intensive advice on emotional problems. Mental health specialists are frequently perceived as inappropriate agents for meeting problems that are beyond the expertise of the family and local community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Il mal occhio</emphasis></emphasis> (the evil eye), which is also called <emphasis>occhio cattivo</emphasis> (bad eye), <emphasis>occhio morto</emphasis> (eye of death), and <emphasis>occhio triste</emphasis> (wicked eye), has its roots in ancient Greece. Individuals can protect themselves from the evil eye by using magical symbols and by learning the rituals of the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">maghi</emphasis></emphasis> (wizards). Amulets, miniature representations of natural or man-made weapons that fight off the evil eye include teeth, claws, and replicas of animal horns that are worn on necklaces or bracelets, held in a pocket, or sewn into clothing. <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Cornicelli</emphasis></emphasis> (little red horns) are very common and can be purchased in Italian neighborhoods as good-luck charms. Many believe in obtaining as much protection from the evil eye as possible. An array of pictures and statues of the Madonna and saints are liberally distributed throughout their homes and supplement these red horns, which are often hung over a door. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove amulets; they provide great solace to the patients.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common plant derivatives used in folk healing are olive oil, lemon juice, wine, vinegar, garlic, onion, lettuce, and tobacco. A crown of lemon leaves is believed to cure a headache, as are wild fennel, deadly nightshade, and sorrel. The leaves and flowers of the wild mallow herb, <emphasis>malva</emphasis>, are used to make tea, providing cool energy and positive effects on the lungs and stomach. When suffering from a fever, a person is given hot rather than cold drinks. For indigestion, a mixture of coffee grounds and sugar is taken. Grain sprouts, especially those grown in the dark, in consecrated ground, in the churchyard, or in a crypt, are believed to protect against Satan and the forces of chaos.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sulfur and lemon juice are mixed as an ointment for scabies, and potato or lemon slices are bound to the wrists to reduce fever.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals do not use available resources because they have little faith in health-care providers. In addition, the high cost of institutional care may be a deterrent for many. <emphasis role="bold">Provide a cultural agent for newer immigrants who have difficulty with the English language and who are unfamiliar with the health-care system.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women are more likely than men to report pain experiences and express symptoms fully; they expect immediate treatment. Most are expressive with chronic pain.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The sick role is not entered without personal feelings of guilt; thus, individuals may keep sickness a secret from their family and friends and are not inclined to describe the details because they blame themselves for the health problem. Suppressing emotions and stress from fear, guilt, and anxiety can cause illness. Most believe that people who have disabilities should be cared for by the family at home; very few individuals are placed in long-term care facilities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A person with a physical or mental disability is not stigmatized because the condition is believed to be God’s will.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Judicious use of medications and blood transfusions are permissible and morally acceptable as long as the benefits outweigh the risks to the individual; thus, there is little objection to accepting a blood transfusion. Organ donation is morally permissible when the benefits to the recipient are proportionate to the loss of the organ to the donor and when the organ does not deprive the donor of life or the functional integrity of the body. <emphasis role="bold">Organ transplant is an individual decision.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0022s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mystical powers are not limited to saints. For the traditional, certain humans are believed to have immediate and potent access to magical powers. These are the <emphasis>maghi</emphasis>, “wizards” and the <emphasis>streghe</emphasis>, “female witches,” who are granted various amounts of black magic power at birth. A powerful sorcerer is called <emphasis>lupo mannaro</emphasis> (werewolf). These extraordinary people are thought to possess or influence the evil eye. They have the power to cast spells, cause or cure ailments, and change events by using their own force—even their gaze is thought to be potent. These traditional beliefs may be practiced by first-generation Italian immigrants but hold little value for second- and third-generation Italian Americans.</para>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Accept and incorporate folk practices into treatment plans, along with providing written instructions for biomedical treatments.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Success in persuading children to take medicine depends on the trust the mother has in the health-care provider. If the health-care provider is Italian or makes an effort to understand the Italian culture, the mother is more compliant. <emphasis role="bold">Assigning providers of the same culture is advantageous for the patient.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0022s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">22.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe traditional Italian American gender roles. What are their implications for health-care decision-making?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How do you determine cyanosis and jaundice in dark-skinned Italians?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are common health conditions for Italian Americans?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the dangers associated with the ingestion of fava beans and the administration of sulfonamides, antimalarial agents, salicylates, and naphthaquinolones in Italian Americans?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify several foods used for health promotion. What illnesses will they help prevent?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Identify some common beliefs and customs about pregnancy? Are any of them harmful?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>In traditional terms, to what are illnesses attributed?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Many traditional Italians believe in <emphasis>Il mal occhio</emphasis>. What is this and what is done to protect oneself?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are <emphasis>maghi</emphasis> and <emphasis>streghe</emphasis>? What are their functions?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Explain the basic rites of the Sacrament of the Sick. What is the purpose?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0022s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0022s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib01">CIA (2024) World factbook: Italy. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/italy/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cia.gov/the-world-factbook/countries/italy/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib02">Dignity USA (2008). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.dignityusa.org/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.dignityusa.org/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib03">Giordano J, Mc Goldrick M, Kages JG (2008) Italian families. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.dgapractice.com/documents/ItalianFamilies.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.dgapractice.com/documents/Italian Families.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib04">Italy (2016) World Health Organization. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.who.int/countries/ita/en/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.who.int/countries/ita/en/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib05">Italy: Countries and their Culture (2016). <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.everyculture.com/Ge-It/Italy.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.everyculture.com/Ge-It/Italy.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib06">Italy versus the United States: Family and Social Structures (2019). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://lifeinitaly.com/italy-vs-united-states-family-and-social-structures/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://lifeinitaly.com/italy-vs-united-states-family-and-social-structures/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib07">Stievano A, Rocco G, Shaffer FA, Caruso R (2021) People of Italian heritage. In: Purnell L, Fenkl EA (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0022s0003bib08">Taruscio D, Kodra Y, Ferrari G, Vittozzi L (2014) The Italian National Rare Disease Registry. Blood Transfus 12(Suppl 3): s606–s613<bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=24922301">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4044798">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
