<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0008" label="8">
  <title>8. People of Arab Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0008s0005">
    <title>8. People of Arab Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_8">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_8</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Suha Ballout</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0008">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Manning College of Nursing and Health Sciences, University of Massachusetts, Boston, MA, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Suha Ballout</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:Suha.Ballout@umb.edu">Suha.Ballout@umb.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Arab heritage, Communities, Legacy, Identity, Cultural responses</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0008s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Exploring the richness of the Arab heritage showcases a journey through time, tracing back to the nomadic desert tribes that roamed the Arabian Peninsula. Rooted in a shared language, <emphasis role="bold">Arabic</emphasis>, and united by the teachings of <emphasis role="bold">Islam</emphasis>, a faith that blossomed in seventh-century Arabia. Arab heritage is a mix of vibrant cultural heritage, literature, cuisine, traditional crafts, and resilience in the face of political challenges and conflicts. Despite common bonds of language and history, the Arab residents of each country defy homogeneity, exhibiting diversity of religion, thoughts, attitudes, and behaviors. These cultural variations weave a vibrant narrative within and across countries and regions. From the tradition-bound farmers of rural Yemen and fertile agriculture in Palestine to the enterprising small business owners of Beirut and Syria, each facet of Arab identity reflects a unique blend of history, geography, and circumstance. Significant cultural differences exist not only within individual countries and regions but also across them. It is important to recognize that the individual differences among Arabs exceed the boundaries set by cultural, religious, and societal norms. Immigrant Arab communities, on the other hand, may display considerable cultural variations influenced by factors like religion, country of origin, refugee status, length of residence, ethnic background, education, economic situation, employment status, social networks, and proficiency in English.</para>
    <para role="Para">Interestingly, despite this diversity lies a unifying thread—a profound respect for individuality that transcends cultural, religious, and social norms. Arabs, whether native or immigrant, embody a spectrum of experiences shaped by a multitude of factors including religion, country of origin, refugee status, and more. Each layer adds complexity, enriching the collective heritage and highlighting the dynamic nature of Arab identity. In this chapter, we discuss the Arab heritage to explore its complexities, celebrate its diversity, and honor its enduring legacy.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0008s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2 </emphasis> Understanding Arab American Identity, Perceptions, and Successes</title>
    <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
      <emphasis role="bold">Tapestry of Landscapes, Cultures, and Societies</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="Para">The Arab countries span the Middle East and North Africa and encompass a diverse array of landscapes, cultures, and societies. The term “Arab countries” typically refers to the nations where Arabic is the primary or official language and where Arab culture and heritage are predominant. The majority of Arab countries include Algeria, Bahrain, Comoros, Djibouti, Egypt, Iraq, Jordan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Libya, Mauritania, Morocco, Oman, Palestine, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Somalia, Sudan, Syria, Tunisia, United Arab Emirates, and Yemen. It is worth noting that some countries, such as Sudan and Somalia, have many non-Arab populations and have multiple official languages. In addition, there are Arab populations and cultural influences in other countries outside of this list, however, they may not be considered predominantly Arab nations. Most Arab immigrants to the United States arrived during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. This period witnessed significant waves of immigration from various regions of the Arab world, particularly from present-day Lebanon, Syria, Palestine, and Jordan. Many Arab immigrants during this time sought economic opportunities, escaping political instability, religious persecution, and poverty in their homelands. They settled in urban areas such as New York, Detroit, and Chicago where they contributed to the cultural and economic fabric of American society. Subsequent waves of Arab immigration occurred in the mid-twentieth century and continue to the present day with immigrants arriving for various reasons: including family reunification, education, and employment opportunities.</para>
    <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title><emphasis role="bold">The Legacy of Arab Immigration</emphasis> Arab immigrants in the United States contribute to the nation’s rich culture with an estimated population of around three million persons. Arab immigrants trace their ancestry to various countries across the Arab world, including Lebanon, Syria, Egypt, Morocco, Iraq, Jordan, Palestine, Yemen, Tunisia, Algeria, and numerous Gulf countries. Their immigration history is marked by waves with the first wave of immigrants arriving between 1887 and 1913, driven by a quest for economic opportunities and the desire to secure financial stability potentially enabling them to invest in their ancestral villages or establish businesses upon their return. These first-wave Arab Americans engaged in unskilled labor with a majority being male and a large proportion being undereducated coming from mountainous or rural regions. Currently, Lebanon accounts for 32% of Arab American immigrants while 11% originate from Egypt (Arab American Institute Demographics <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib26">2024</link></emphasis>). The second wave of immigrants came to the United States after World War II with an increase after the Palestinian-Israeli conflict and the enactment of the Immigration Act of 1965. Unlike the economically driven Lebanese Syrian Christians of the first wave, the majority of second-wave immigrants were refugees fleeing war-torn and politically unstable nations primarily occupied Palestine, Jordan, Iraq, Yemen, Lebanon, and Syria. From 2008 to 2018, immigrants from the Arab world originated from countries including Iraq, Egypt, Somalia, Morocco, and Lebanon with a large portion including professionals and individuals pursuing higher education who have chosen to remain in the United States (Arab American Institute Demographics <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib26">2024</link></emphasis>). These migration patterns highlight the diverse socioeconomic factors influencing Arab immigration to the United States, ranging from economic aspirations to escaping conflict and seeking educational opportunities. Geographically, Arab immigrants reside in metropolitan areas with approximately 94% residing in urban centers. Large Arab American populations can be found in states such as Michigan, California, New York, Illinois, and Florida with cities like Dearborn (Michigan) and Los Angeles (California) hosting substantial Arab American communities (Arab American Institute Demographics <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib26">2024</link></emphasis>).</title>
      <para/>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>Perceptions of People of Arab Heritage and Arab Countries Sentiments toward Arabs and Arab countries around the world vary based on several influences such as historical events, political dynamics, media portrayals, cultural exchanges, and personal experiences. Appreciation for Arab culture, history, and contributions to various fields such as literature, science, and architecture is widespread. Arab civilization has left a lasting mark on history through its advancements in mathematics, astronomy, medicine, and philosophy, among other disciplines. From the poetry of Al-Mutanabbi to the architectural works of Alhambra, Arab creativity and innovation continue to inspire admiration. The hospitality and generosity associated with Arab societies evoke respect and admiration. Arab countries, with their rich cultural heritage, ancient landmarks, and natural beauty are recognized as premier tourist destinations attracting visitors eager to explore historical sites like the pyramids of Egypt, the ancient city of Petra in Jordan, or the bustling markets of Morocco. There is widespread support for Arab causes such as the Palestinian struggle for statehood among individuals and groups advocating for human rights and social justice reflecting a global commitment to fairness and equity.</title>
      <para role="Para">On the other hand, unfortunately, negative sentiments toward Arabs and Arab communities persist and are fueled by prejudice, discrimination, and stereotypes perpetuated in media portrayals that depict Arabs in a negative light (Alsaidi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib24">2023</link></emphasis>; Hashem and Awad <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib46">2021</link></emphasis>; Kader et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib52">2020</link></emphasis>). The association of Islam with Arab culture leads to Islamophobia, which can result in bias and discrimination against Arabs compounded by geopolitical tensions between Arab-majority countries and Western nations (Hashem and Awad <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib46">2021</link></emphasis>; Kader et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib52">2020</link></emphasis>). Countries like Iraq, Syria, and Iran are often met with hostility due to perceived conflicts and tensions further exacerbating negative perceptions. Also, fear and distrust toward Arab immigrants or refugees prevail, particularly in the context of debates surrounding immigration policies and national security concerns contributing to social divisions and barriers to integration. These negative sentiments not only perpetuate harmful stereotypes but also hinder efforts toward promoting understanding and cooperation between diverse communities. Healthcare professionals must recognize that many Arab Americans do not align with the ideological anti-Western movement. Arab individuals should not be stereotyped based on their cultural background. Research conducted by Kulwicki and colleagues examining the impact of 9/11 on Arab American nurses in Detroit showed instances of discrimination against Muslims and Arabs including name-calling, intimidation, verbal assaults regarding appearance and religion, as well as unwarranted suspicion and questioning often supported by the media. Similar perceptions of Arab Americans related to anti-Muslim sentiments among healthcare providers have been reported in other studies.</para>
      <para role="Para">Mixed sentiments toward Arab countries are also prevalent, reflecting the complexities of their political landscapes and socioeconomic transformations. In countries like Egypt or Saudi Arabia, admiration for their rich cultural heritage often coexists with criticism of human rights records and political repression leading to ambivalence and conflicting views. Similarly, skepticism or uncertainty is observed toward Arab countries undergoing rapid social and economic changes such as Saudi Arabia and the Gulf states where modernization efforts sometimes clash with traditional values creating a sense of unease among some observers. Overall, sentiments toward Arabs and Arab countries are multifaceted influenced by individual experiences, cultural backgrounds, and geopolitical realities. Efforts aimed at promoting cross-cultural understanding, challenging stereotypes, and fostering dialog can play an essential role in cultivating more nuanced and empathetic attitudes toward Arabs and Arab countries on a global scale.</para>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad03" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>The Arab Identity and the Healthcare ProfessionThe diverse nature of Arab culture poses a challenge in presenting a comprehensive account of Arab Americans compounded by limited research literature on Arabs in the Americas. Early Arab immigrants, primarily Christians from present-day Lebanon and Syria, arrived during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, emphasizing assimilation and easily integrating into mainstream American society. However, Arab Americans tend to be overlooked in national studies as they are often classified as White in census data rather than as a distinct ethnic group. To provide a more inclusive portrayal of Arab Americans incorporating literature describing Arabs in their home countries supplements research on Arab Americans residing in various states such as Michigan, Illinois, New York, Ohio, and the San Francisco Bay area of California. While it is assumed that first-generation immigrants may share some attitudes and behaviors with their counterparts in the Arab world, caution is advised against making assumptions about Arab or Arab American clients without thorough individual assessment.</title>
      <para role="Para">Healthcare professionals need to understand Arab culture, history, religion, and the diverse experiences of Arab communities around the world. This knowledge is key for providing culturally competent care and fostering positive patient–provider relationships. Healthcare professionals must recognize and challenge negative stereotypes and prejudices that may impact the care of Arab patients, particularly in the context of Islamophobia and discrimination. Understanding the complex socio-political landscapes of Arab countries can inform discussions around health disparities, access to care, and the impact of geopolitical tensions on individual and community health. By promoting cross-cultural understanding, challenging stereotypes, and fostering dialog, healthcare professionals can contribute to creating more inclusive and equitable healthcare environments for Arab patients and communities worldwide.</para>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad04" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>Educational and Occupational Success Among Arab Americans People of Arab heritage, in general, prioritize professional occupations, emphasizing the importance of education as a pathway to white-collar careers. Recent data indicates that both US-born and foreign-born Arab Americans exhibit higher educational attainment compared to the national average. Over 90% of Arab Americans have completed high school, a contrast to 32% of the total U. S. population. Around 20% of Arab Americans hold post-graduate degrees. In comparison to European Americans, Arab Americans are more likely to be self-employed and hold managerial and professional specialty occupations. Around 45% are employed in managerial or professional roles while 29% work in sales and 16% in service positions. Arab American households in the United States have a mean annual income of $60,398, surpassing the national average of $52,029 for all households (Arab American Institute Demographics <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib26">2024</link></emphasis>). These data show the strong emphasis on education and professional success within the Arab American community contributing to their overall economic prosperity and higher-than-average household income.</title>
      <para/>
    </sidebar>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.1 </emphasis> Communication</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad05" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Dominant Language and Dialects Arabic is the official language across the Arab world, including both modern and classical forms. Modern Standard Arabic is used in formal contexts such as written communication, radio broadcasts, and academic lectures while colloquial Arabic specific to each community is utilized for everyday spoken interactions (Suleiman <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib77">2019</link></emphasis>). Arab individuals often blend Modern Standard Arabic and colloquial Arabic depending on the context and level of formality. The diversity of dialects, characterized by variations in accent, intonation, and vocabulary, can pose challenges in communication between Arab immigrants from different regions such as Syria and Lebanon compared to those from Iraq and Yemen (Suleiman <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib77">2019</link></emphasis>). Generally, Arab communication is characterized by repetition and expressive gestures, especially in serious discussions which may be perceived as confrontational or aggressive by external observers. While English serves as a common second language in countries like Egypt, Jordan, Lebanon, Yemen, Iraq, and Kuwait, French is prevalent in Lebanon, Algeria, and Morocco. Literacy rates in the Arab world exhibit significant disparities ranging from 93% for men and 30% for women in Yemen to 95% for men and 85% for women in Jordan.</title>
        <para role="Para">Despite proficiency in languages other than Arabic, Arab American patients still encounter significant language and communication barriers within American healthcare settings. These challenges often arise from differences in cultural norms, communication styles, and healthcare terminology between Arab American patients and healthcare providers (Abuelezam et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib10">2018</link></emphasis>; Aseeri <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib27">2020</link></emphasis>; Fleischer and Sadek <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib39">2024</link></emphasis>). Studies have highlighted that many Arab American patients face difficulties expressing their healthcare needs and understanding medical instructions from providers resulting in misunderstandings and confusion (Abuelezam et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib10">2018</link></emphasis>; Fleischer and Sadek <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib39">2024</link></emphasis>). Consequently, this miscommunication can lead to delayed appointments, reluctance to disclose personal health information, and overall dissatisfaction with healthcare experiences. These communication barriers have tangible consequences as they delay Arab American patients’ access to timely and appropriate healthcare services and compromise the effectiveness of healthcare treatment. Addressing these challenges requires healthcare professionals to adopt culturally sensitive communication strategies, utilize interpreters or bilingual staff when necessary, and foster trust and rapport with Arab American patients to ensure their healthcare needs are adequately met.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad06" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Arab Communication Dynamics Arab communication is characterized by a nuanced approach where the context of the situation often carries more significance than the words spoken. Privacy is highly valued among Arabs leading them to resist disclosing personal information to strangers, particularly regarding familial health matters. Within the circle of friends and relatives, Arabs freely express their emotions and feelings. These communication patterns are better understood when viewed through the lens of Arab cultural norms. In close-knit family settings, personal needs are often anticipated without explicit verbalization due to the strong bonds within the family unit. Also, nonverbal cues and unspoken expectations play a significant role in communication within Arab families.</title>
        <para role="Para">Establishing personal relationships with healthcare professionals is important for Arabs before they feel comfortable sharing personal information. Both the manner and tone of communication are as essential as the actual words spoken, as Arabs are sensitive to the respect and courtesy shown to them (Abuelezam et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib10">2018</link></emphasis>; Suleiman <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib77">2019</link></emphasis>). Social niceties such as greetings, inquiries about well-being, and sharing a cup of tea or coffee precede discussions of business matters. Physical proximity, steady eye contact, and appropriate touch (e.g., limited to members of the same sex) are common in conversations, reflecting the closeness and warmth inherent in Arab interpersonal interactions. Adhering to proper sitting and standing etiquette is also critical as deviations may be interpreted as a sign of disrespect.</para>
        <para role="Para">In personal relationships, verbal agreements hold greater significance than written contracts as they are seen as a matter of honor. Yet, in business dealings, there is an increasing reliance on written contracts. Arab culture places great emphasis on maintaining harmonious relationships and upholding dignity and honor. When faced with adversity or wrongdoing, Arabs often respond with a sense of resignation expressed through the phrase “ <emphasis>maalesh</emphasis>,” meaning “never mind; it doesn’t matter.” In challenging situations, individuals may be shielded from unpleasant news for as long as possible and informed gently when necessary. Disagreements are often hinted at indirectly or mediated through intermediaries to preserve social harmony and save face for all parties involved. This mediation process assures the petitioner that their concerns have been addressed with maximum influence and tact (Khosh et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib53">2020</link></emphasis>).</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad07" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Suggestions for Communication with People of Arab Heritage or Descent</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Healthcare professionals should consider adopting an approach that balances expertise with warmth, aiming to minimize status differences. Arab Americans often feel uncomfortable in the presence of authority figures and are sensitive to their feelings, fearing discrimination or belittlement.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Nurses and other healthcare professionals should consider investing time in building rapport before discussing medical matters. Showing genuine interest in the patient’s background and adjustment to American life can facilitate open communication and help in understanding potential traumatic immigration experiences.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Role responsibilities, especially regarding history taking and physical examinations, should be openly communicated, especially to newer immigrants who may not be familiar with the healthcare system’s hierarchy. While some Arab American immigrants may recognize nurses’ elevated scope of practice in the United States, they may still perceive them as medical assistants or housekeepers.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Nurses should consider conducting comprehensive assessments and explaining the relevance of the information gathered to address physical complaints effectively.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Healthcare professionals should try to understand and respect family dynamics, recognizing that a family member may serve as a spokesperson for the patient. Family members may also edit information they deem inappropriate and act as advocates for the patient seeking assistance from influential intermediaries if necessary.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Healthcare professionals should try to convey hope and optimism in their communication, understanding that the concept of “false hope” may not resonate with Arab patients who believe in God’s infinite power to cure. The amount and type of information shared should be carefully considered to maintain a balance.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Respect for the patient’s modesty and dignity is paramount. Islamic teachings prohibit unnecessary physical contact between unrelated adults of opposite genders such as shaking hands. Healthcare professionals should be mindful of these cultural norms, especially when interacting with female patients to ensure their comfort and trust in the healthcare setting.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad08" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Predestination and Time Perception Among Arab Immigrants First-generation Arab immigrants often adhere to the belief in predestination that asserts that God has predetermined the events of one’s life. This belief encourages individuals to strive for the best outcomes while recognizing that ultimate control rests with a higher power. Plans and aspirations are often accompanied by the phrase “ <emphasis>inshallah</emphasis>,” meaning “if God wills,” signifying an acknowledgment of divine authority over one’s fate. Additionally, both blessings and misfortunes are commonly attributed to the will of God rather than solely to individual actions (Mpofu <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib65">2018</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">Across the Arab world, there exists a relaxed attitude toward punctuality except in the context of formal business or professional engagements. Life moves at a more leisurely pace compared to Western standards where social gatherings and appointments often lack strict start and end times. While some individuals may prioritize punctuality, it is common for appointments to begin later than scheduled. However, within Arab American communities, especially among those engaged in professional or business occupations, punctuality, and adherence to deadlines and appointments are regarded as essential virtues. This cultural disposition toward time reflects a broader worldview that values interpersonal relationships and flexibility over rigid adherence to schedules. Understanding these nuances in cultural attitudes toward time can facilitate smoother interactions and collaborations between Arab immigrants and individuals from different cultural backgrounds promoting mutual understanding and respect.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad09" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Navigating Social Etiquette in Arab Culture Traditional etiquette stresses the exchange of handshakes upon both arrival and departure in Arab culture. However, when an Arab man is introduced to an Arab woman, it is customary for him to wait for the woman to initiate the handshake. In traditional Muslim customs, persons may refrain from shaking hands with members of the opposite gender. In such cases, both women and men often place their right hand over their chest as a respectful gesture in place of shaking hands.</title>
        <para role="Para">Titles hold significance in Arab culture and are typically used in conjunction with the individual’s first name. For instance, it is common to address someone as “Mr. Khalil” or “Dr. Ali.” Alternatively, some individuals may prefer to be addressed with familial titles, such as “mother” ( <emphasis>Um</emphasis>) or “father” ( <emphasis>Abu</emphasis>), followed by the name of their eldest son (e.g., Abu Khalil, which translates to “father of Khalil”). It is also customary for married women to retain their maiden names reflecting the importance of lineage and familial connections in Arab society (Suleiman <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib77">2019</link></emphasis>).</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad10" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Gender Dynamics and Modesty in Arab Families Gender dynamics within Arab families often adhere to traditional patriarchal structures where men typically hold authoritative roles and decision-making responsibilities while women are often perceived as subordinate. Younger family members defer to their elders (Aldossari and Chaudhry <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib14">2024</link></emphasis>; Druker Shitrit et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib35">2024</link></emphasis>; Hurley <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib49">2024</link></emphasis>). Despite the persistence of these conventional roles in some regions, there is a noticeable trend toward more progressive attitudes regarding gender equality, particularly in urban contexts (Hurley <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib49">2024</link></emphasis>). Modesty is highly valued among both genders in Arab families, influencing their attire and behavior with conservative clothing choices prevalent. For Muslim women, the hijab is widely viewed as a symbol of modesty and cultural identity covering the body except for the face and hands. Many choose to wear it as an expression of their faith and cultural adherence (Aldossari and Chaudhry <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib14">2024</link></emphasis>; Almutawaa et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib19">2024</link></emphasis>; Druker Shitrit et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib35">2024</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">In traditional Arab families, women are seen as subordinate to men. While husbands may hold obvious influence in public, wives often exercise significant power behind the scenes, particularly concerning domestic affairs and childcare. This power dynamic emphasizes the importance of understanding cultural intricacies within Arab families. Within extended families, decision-making authority often falls to older male figures, although women may gain influence with age, particularly after their children reach adulthood. The bond between mothers and sons is typically strong with sons often prioritizing their mother’s wishes and preferences. However, as nuclear families replace extended ones, these traditional norms are evolving (Aldossari and Chaudhry <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib14">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
        <para role="Para">Gender roles in Arab families are typically delineated, with men fulfilling roles as breadwinners, protectors, and decision-makers while women are responsible for childcare, household management, and maintaining successful marriages. Despite increasing opportunities for women in professional careers in urbanized Arab countries, family and marriage remain primary commitments for many and caregiving often takes precedence. Unfortunately, these traditional gender roles are sometimes misinterpreted in Western contexts fueling stereotypes of dominant Arab males and passive, oppressed females. This misinterpretation can contribute to conservative Arab Americans perceiving criticisms of gender roles as attacks on their culture and family values (Aldossari and Chaudhry <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib14">2024</link></emphasis>; Khosh et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib53">2020</link></emphasis>).</para>
        <para role="Para">Modesty is a core value among Arabs, influencing attire choices and behavior with many considering the hijab a symbol of Muslim identity and moral integrity. However, while the hijab may be seen as protective within Muslim communities, it is often misinterpreted by some Americans as a symbol of oppression. It is essential to recognize that the hijab is a personal choice with some women within the same family choosing to wear it while others do not depending on individual preferences. Even those who do not wear it during the day often wear it during religious activities like prayer and Quran reading. Understanding these nuances of gender dynamics and modesty within Arab families is crucial for healthcare professionals to provide culturally sensitive care, build trust, and improve health outcomes for Arab patients (Almutawaa et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib19">2024</link></emphasis>; Druker Shitrit et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib35">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
        <para role="Para">Gender dynamics and modesty norms influence family dynamics and social interactions within Arab communities reflecting broader cultural values and traditions. While traditional gender roles may persist in some areas, there is a growing acceptance of more egalitarian perspectives on gender within Arab societies with an ongoing emphasis on modesty and cultural identity. Healthcare professionals must understand these gender dynamics within Arab families to foster cultural sensitivity, respect traditional gender roles, and build trust with Arab patients. This understanding facilitates effective communication by enabling healthcare providers to tailor their approach to cultural norms, thereby enhancing rapport and understanding. Also, awareness of gender dynamics enables healthcare professionals to navigate health decision-making processes within Arab families ensuring the inclusion of relevant family members and addressing disparities that may disproportionately affect women or men. Respect for privacy and modesty preferences such as the preference for same-gender healthcare providers contribute to a more dignified care experience. This cultural understanding enables healthcare professionals to deliver culturally competent care that honors patients’ values and preferences leading to improved healthcare outcomes and patient satisfaction.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad11" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Parental Roles and Child Rearing in Traditional Arab FamiliesIn traditional Arab families, the roles of fathers and mothers concerning their children are clearly defined and distinct. Typically, fathers take on the role of disciplinarians while mothers serve as allies and mediators providing unwavering love and kindness. Although some fathers may believe in maintaining a degree of fear, family relationships are generally characterized by affection and sentimentality. Children are deeply cherished, indulged, and actively involved in all family activities (Abdul-Haq <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib05">2018</link></emphasis>). Within Arab culture, the upbringing of children to reflect positively on the family is a significant responsibility. The character and achievements (or shortcomings) of a child are often attributed to the influence of upbringing and parental guidance. Given the emphasis on collective familism over individualism in Arab culture, adherence to adult rules is highly valued, and child-rearing practices are geared toward fostering accommodation and cooperation (Abdul-Haq <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib05">2018</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">Maintaining family honor is paramount and children are expected to conduct themselves honorably to avoid disgracing their families. Also, respect for parents and elders is instilled from a young age in traditional families with children encouraged not to question elders and to obey older siblings although these norms are gradually evolving to grant children more autonomy. Discipline methods may include physical punishment and shaming with a focus on external repercussions rather than internal reflection. Unlike Western adolescents, which emphasize the acquisition of personal identity and separation from the family, Arab adolescents are encouraged to remain closely connected to their family system. Family interests and opinions often heavily influence career and marriage decisions with academic success being particularly emphasized due to its association with social status.</para>
        <para role="Para">Behaviors that may tarnish family honor, such as academic underachievement, sexual activity, substance use, and delinquency are actively avoided, especially among girls who are expected to uphold chastity and decency (Abdul-Haq <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib05">2018</link></emphasis>). Adolescence in North America may offer Arab adolescents’ greater opportunities for academic achievement and more freedom in career choices compared to their counterparts in Arab countries. However, this career choice freedom can lead to cultural conflicts between American and Arab values causing significant tensions within Arab American families. Parents often express concerns about conflicting values regarding dating, extracurricular activities, alcohol consumption, and substance use among their children, highlighting the importance of understanding these cultural nuances for healthcare professionals.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad12" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Family Dynamics and Social StructuresIn Arab society, the family serves as the fundamental socioeconomic unit where members collaborate to ensure livelihood, raise children, and uphold their status and influence within the community. Family members typically reside close to one another often engaging in intermarriage such as between first cousins although this practice varies across different countries. Regardless of practicality or capability, there exists a strong expectation among family members to provide support to one another with loyalty to the family superseding personal needs. Preserving family honor is of utmost importance and guides the conduct of all family members (Abdul-Haq <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib05">2018</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">Within the hierarchical structure of the family, older members command significant respect and it is customary for children, especially sons, to assume the responsibility of caring for elderly parents. Consequently, elderly parents are commonly looked after within the family home until their passing, despite the sacrifices involved. In traditional Arab families, the burden of caring for family members primarily falls on older men, with brothers assuming responsibility for unmarried sisters in the absence of the father. In the unfortunate event of a husband’s demise, his family is expected to provide for his widow and children. Family leaders are also expected to leverage their influence to provide support to relatives, although these expectations are shifting as nuclear families increasingly replace extended family structures, leading to challenges in caring for elderly relatives (Abdul-Haq <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib05">2018</link></emphasis>).</para>
        <para role="Para">While educational achievements, prestigious occupations like engineering, medicine, law, and accumulated wealth contribute to social status in Arab culture. Family lineage remains the foremost determinant of social standing in traditional Arab societies. Certain character traits such as piety, generosity, hospitality, and good manners are honored and can further elevate an individual’s social status within the community.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad13" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Navigating Norms and Activism Most adults in Arab cultures enter a marital relationship with monogamous unions being the norm despite the option for polygamous marriages according to Islamic law. However, studies show that polygamous marriages are relatively rare among Arab Muslims with only a small percentage opting for multiple spouses. While homosexuality exists across all cultures, it continues to be highly stigmatized within Arab societies (Abboud et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib01">2020</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib02">2022</link></emphasis>). A significant proportion of HIV/AIDS cases among Arabs are attributed to men engaging in sexual activity with other men reflecting the challenges faced by LGBTQ individuals in Arab communities (Saliba et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib75">2024</link></emphasis>). In some Arab countries, homosexual behavior is even considered a criminal offense leading many individuals to conceal their sexual orientation due to fear of familial shame and social ostracism (Abboud et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib02">2022</link></emphasis>). Nevertheless, there has been a notable increase in activism among Arab American LGBTQ individuals with some openly advocating for the rights of the LGBTQ community in Arab countries and among Arab Americans (Abboud et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib03">2024a</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib04">b</link></emphasis>). In certain Arab countries like Lebanon, there are emerging LGBTQ organizations that aim to support and advocate for the rights of this marginalized population challenging legal and cultural barriers to alternative lifestyles (Abboud et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib01">2020</link></emphasis>; Hatoum <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib47">2018</link></emphasis>). Recent research in Lebanon has shown positive attitudes and behaviors among mental health providers toward LGBTQ patients suggesting a potential shift toward greater acceptance and support within certain sectors of Arab society (Dandashly <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib33">2021</link></emphasis>; Hatoum <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib47">2018</link></emphasis>; Lebanon’s LGBT People Reclaim Their Power <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib55">2020</link></emphasis>). Similarly, LGBTQ Arab organizations in the United States are actively engaged in raising awareness and combating cultural stereotypes and stigma associated with LGBTQ identities within Arab communities to promote equity and acceptance for all individuals regardless of sexual orientation (Dandashly <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib33">2021</link></emphasis>; Hatoum <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib47">2018</link></emphasis>; Lebanon’s LGBT People Reclaim Their Power <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib55">2020</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para/>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad14" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Cultural Influences on Work Dynamics and Mental Health Cultural variances that may influence work dynamics include beliefs and customs regarding family structure, gender roles, control over life circumstances, fostering harmonious interpersonal relationships, safeguarding dignity and honor, and the significance placed on upholding one’s reputation. Disparities in attitudes toward time management, educational methodologies, cognitive patterns, and the degree of emphasis on objectivity may exist between Arab and American cultures. However, due to the exposure of many second-generation professionals to education in the United States, these distinctions are often more pronounced among less-educated, first-generation Arab Americans.</title>
        <para role="Para">In recent times, exacerbated by ongoing political unrest in Arab nations and escalating unemployment and poverty rates, stress, depression, and mental health conditions have become increasingly prevalent among first-generation immigrants, refugees, and individuals residing in conflict-ridden Arab regions (Horne <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib48">2024</link></emphasis>). Factors contributing to this mental health burden include separation from family members, challenges adapting to American societal norms, marital discord, and intergenerational tensions, particularly concerning adolescents acculturated to American values through educational and social environments (Abuelezam and El-Sayed <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib09">2021</link></emphasis>; Pampati et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib68">2018</link></emphasis>). Also, concerns about the safety and economic welfare of relatives in their home countries have heightened the susceptibility of Arab immigrants to mental health conditions.</para>
        <para role="Para">Discrimination-related stressors also significantly impact the work experiences of Arab Americans (Alsaidi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib24">2023</link></emphasis>; Kader et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib52">2020</link></emphasis>). While major incidents of discrimination such as termination and physical assaults are relatively uncommonly reported, instances of intimidation, suspicion, derogatory remarks about religious practices, and patient refusal for treatment by Arab American nurses have been reported (Hashem and Awad <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib46">2021</link></emphasis>; Saadi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib73">2023</link></emphasis>). Arab Americans are acutely aware of prevalent misconceptions held by the broader American society regarding Arabs, including perceptions of inferiority, backwardness, sinister motives, and propensity for violence. Additionally, the misrepresentation of mainstream Islam and the stereotyping of Muslims as extremists and confrontational further exacerbate the challenges faced by Arab Americans in navigating their religious practices within a predominantly secular American society (Hashem and Awad <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib46">2021</link></emphasis>). Conflicts often arise concerning matters like marriage, divorce, banking, inheritance, and the observance of religious obligations such as Friday prayers and dietary restrictions, particularly among children balancing Islamic requirements with the norms of the American public school system (Fleischer and Sadek <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib39">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad15" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Understanding Work Dynamics in American and Arab EnvironmentsIn contrast to the American workplace culture, which emphasizes meeting deadlines, achieving profit targets, and maintaining a competitive edge, the Arab work environment is characterized by a more relaxed and sociable atmosphere. Business relationships often intertwine with personal friendships, often over cups of sweet tea, blurring the lines between socializing and work-related discussions. Managers in Arab workplaces typically rely on personal influence and persuasion to motivate employees, and performance evaluations often consider not only job skills but also personality and social behavior.</title>
        <para role="Para">Distinct workplace norms further differentiate American and Arab work cultures. In the United States and some other countries, professional positions are typically earned based on merit with laws applied uniformly and work often taking precedence over familial obligations. Values such as honesty, reliance on facts and logic and direct, constructive criticism are highly regarded. In contrast, in the Arab world, social status within the workplace is often influenced by family connections, although these practices are gradually evolving. Flexibility with rules and regulations is common with family responsibilities often prioritized over job demands. Subjective perceptions frequently guide actions, and criticism is often taken personally, seen as a challenge to one’s dignity and family honor.</para>
        <para role="Para">Supervisors and managers in Arab offices are expected to openly praise their employees to reassure them that their efforts are recognized and appreciated. While such direct praise may sometimes make Americans feel uncomfortable, Arabs typically expect and appreciate acknowledgment when they believe they have earned it. This cultural contrast highlights the importance of understanding and adapting to different workplace norms and communication styles when operating in multicultural environments.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad16" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Skin Color and Other Biological Variations While there is a common stereotype associating Arabs with dark or olive skin tones, it is worth recognizing the diversity within the Arab population (Galaz <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib40">2019</link></emphasis>). While many Arabs do indeed have darker complexions, it is common to find individuals with blonde or auburn hair, blue eyes, and fair skin. This diversity is particularly evident among Arabs from North African countries like Egypt, Morocco, and Tunisia where individuals may have black skin and African features (Galaz <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib40">2019</link></emphasis>; Kader et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib52">2020</link></emphasis>). When assessing health conditions in individuals with darker skin tones such as Arabs, it is important to note that detecting changes in color such as pallor (i.e., pale skin) or cyanosis (i.e., bluish discoloration) can be more challenging. In such cases, healthcare professionals may find it helpful to examine the oral mucosa (i.e., the inner lining of the mouth) and conjunctiva (i.e., the membrane covering the eye) for signs of these color changes. This comprehensive approach ensures accurate assessment and diagnosis, leading to appropriate healthcare interventions.</title>
        <para/>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad17" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Diseases and Health Conditions People of Arab descent encounter various health challenges influenced by genetic factors, cultural practices, socioeconomic status, and disparities in healthcare access. Predominant among these concerns are cardiovascular diseases like coronary artery disease, hypertension, and stroke often exacerbated by sedentary lifestyles, high-cholesterol diets, and tobacco use (Ahmadi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib11">2024</link></emphasis>; Al-Ajlouni et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib13">2024</link></emphasis>; Ferrari et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib38">2024</link></emphasis>; Rashidi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib70">2024</link></emphasis>). Also, Type 2 diabetes is increasingly prevalent in Arab communities, driven by factors such as obesity, unhealthy dietary habits, and potential genetic susceptibility (Al-Ajlouni et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib13">2024</link></emphasis>). Cancer, including lung and colorectal cancer, contributes significantly to mortality rates among Arab Americans influenced by tobacco consumption, environmental exposures, and genetic predisposition (Allehebi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib16">2024</link></emphasis>; Al Rabeeah et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib22">2024</link></emphasis>; Al-Shamsi and Musallam <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib25">2024</link></emphasis>; Mansour et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib59">2024</link></emphasis>). Mental health disorders like depression, anxiety, and post-traumatic stress disorder are prevalent, particularly among those affected by conflict and acculturation stress, compounded by stigma and limited access to culturally competent mental healthcare services (Abuelezam and El-Sayed <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib09">2021</link></emphasis>; Pampati et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib68">2018</link></emphasis>; Sweileh <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib78">2024</link></emphasis>). Infectious diseases such as tuberculosis, hepatitis, and parasitic infestations remain significant concerns in rural Arab regions due to inadequate sanitation and healthcare infrastructure (Al Salman et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib12">2020</link></emphasis>; Mostafavi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib64">2022</link></emphasis>). Genetic disorders like G-6-PD deficiency, sickle cell anemia, and thalassemias are more prevalent due to high rates of consanguineous marriages and genetic predisposition. Maternal and child health issues persist characterized by high rates of infant mortality and pregnancy complications necessitating improved access to prenatal care and maternal healthcare services (Alqifari <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib21">2024</link></emphasis>; Elbarazi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib36">2024</link></emphasis>; Rezki and Fateh <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib71">2024</link></emphasis>). Respiratory conditions like asthma and COPD are prevalent and exacerbated by environmental factors such as air pollution and tobacco smoke exposure (Almarshoodi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib17">2024</link></emphasis>; Fleischer and Sadek <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib39">2024</link></emphasis>; Hamid et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib42">2024</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib43">2024</link></emphasis>; Hanafi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib44">2024</link></emphasis>; Olimat et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib67">2024</link></emphasis>). Unhealthy lifestyle behaviors, including tobacco use and sedentary habits, contribute to chronic diseases like obesity and diabetes among Arab populations. Nurses and healthcare professionals play a crucial role in providing culturally sensitive care, advocating for health equity, and implementing tailored interventions to address the unique healthcare needs of individuals with Arab heritage (Wehbe-Alamah et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib82">2024</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">The health challenges faced by Arabs in war-torn countries are multifaceted and deeply entrenched within the complex context of ongoing conflict, displacement, and humanitarian crisis (Hamid et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib42">2024</link></emphasis>; Hanafi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib44">2024</link></emphasis>; Mohsin et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib63">2024</link></emphasis>; Veronese et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib81">2024</link></emphasis>). One primary concern is the prevalence of trauma and injuries resulting from the violence of war, including bombings, gunfire, and armed conflict. Civilians often sustain severe physical injuries such as burns, fractures, and wounds, necessitating immediate medical attention and long-term rehabilitation. Moreover, the psychological impact of war is profound, with many individuals grappling with post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), depression, anxiety, and other mental health conditions. Exposure to violence, displacement, and the loss of loved ones exacerbates the prevalence of mental health disorders among war-affected populations (Mahamid et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib57">2024</link></emphasis>; Manzanero et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib60">2024</link></emphasis>; Tarabay and Golm <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib79">2024</link></emphasis>; Veronese et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib81">2024</link></emphasis>). Additionally, the conditions of displacement, overcrowded living environments, and inadequate access to clean water and sanitation facilities heighten the risk of infectious disease outbreaks (Vahidniya et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib80">2024</link></emphasis>). Diseases like cholera, typhoid fever, malaria, and diarrheal illnesses spread rapidly in refugee camps and displaced communities, posing significant public health challenges. Furthermore, conflict disrupts food production, distribution, and access leading to widespread malnutrition and famine. Both acute and chronic malnutrition among children are prevalent with devastating consequences for growth, development and overall health. Access to healthcare is severely impacted by conflict with medical facilities destroyed, shortages of essential medicines and the displacement of healthcare workers. Many individuals struggle to access basic healthcare services, including maternal and child health services resulting in preventable deaths and complications. The plight of displaced individuals further exacerbates health vulnerabilities, exposing them to harsh living conditions, inadequate shelter, and limited access to healthcare. Children are particularly vulnerable facing malnutrition, lack of education, and exposure to violence and trauma. Reproductive health services are also disrupted posing risks for pregnant women and newborns due to limited access to skilled birth attendants and emergency obstetric care. Addressing the health needs of Arabs in war-torn countries requires collaborative efforts from humanitarian organizations, governments, and the international community. Urgent interventions are needed to provide emergency medical care, mental health support, nutrition assistance, and access to clean water and sanitation. Long-term efforts should focus on rebuilding healthcare infrastructure, strengthening health systems, promoting peace and stability, and addressing the root causes of conflict to improve the health and well-being of affected populations (Hamadeh et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib41">2024</link></emphasis>; Manzanero et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib60">2024</link></emphasis>; Tarabay and Golm <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib79">2024</link></emphasis>; Veronese et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib81">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad18" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Variations in Drug Metabolism Limited information is available regarding drug metabolism and sensitivity among individuals of Arab heritage. It has been reported that approximately 1–1.4% of Arabs may face challenges in metabolizing debrisoquine and similar substances including certain antiarrhythmics, antidepressants, beta-blockers, neuroleptics, and opioid agents. As a result, a small proportion of Arab Americans may experience elevated blood levels and adverse effects when prescribed standard dosages of antidepressants. Conversely, some individuals may not adequately metabolize codeine into morphine, leading to suboptimal analgesic effects even with typical codeine dosages. This variation in drug metabolism highlights the importance of considering individual genetic factors and ethnic differences when prescribing medications to individuals of Arab descent as it may impact treatment efficacy and safety outcomes. Healthcare providers should be aware of these potential differences to optimize medication management and minimize the risk of adverse drug reactions among Arab populations.</title>
        <para/>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <para role="Para">High-risk health behaviors among people of Arab descent or heritage encompass a range of practices that pose significant threats to individual and public health. Despite Islamic teachings discouraging tobacco use, smoking remains deeply ingrained in Arab culture, often seen as a gesture of hospitality. This cultural norm is reflected in the higher smoking rates and lower cessation rates among Arab Americans compared to European Americans. Although efforts have been made to reduce tobacco use in many Arab countries, smoking continues to rise in some regions. In addition to conventional cigarette smoking, the use of water pipes, commonly known as hookah, shisha, or narghile, is prevalent among both adults and youth (Atrooz et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib28">2024</link></emphasis>; HARB <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib45">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Data from the 2018 Arab and Chaldean Behavioral Risk Factor Survey indicate a slight decrease in the percentage of Arab Americans reporting ever smoking or using hookah from 38.1% in 2013 to 30.8% in 2018. However, there remains a perception among many smokers that hookah use is a safer alternative to cigarette smoking. The prevalence of cigarette smoking among Arab adults is reported to be 17.2%, with a higher prevalence among males than females. Acculturation levels have been linked to nicotine dependence with less-assimilated Arab Americans exhibiting higher smoking rates (Atrooz et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib28">2024</link></emphasis>; HARB <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib45">2024</link></emphasis>; Labibidi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib54">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Alcohol consumption among Arab Americans is influenced by Islamic prohibitions, leading to overall lower rates of alcohol consumption compared to the general population. However, a subset of Arab Americans engages in substance abuse, primarily involving alcohol. Substance abuse treatment centers in areas with large Arab American populations report admissions for alcohol, marijuana, heroin, and crack cocaine abuse, primarily among males. Despite these challenges, a significant portion of Arab Americans abstain from alcohol use, reflecting adherence to cultural norms (Rostam-Abadi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib72">2024</link></emphasis>; Safadi <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib74">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Sexual health practices also contribute to high-risk behaviors among people of Arab descent with limited data available on HIV/AIDS prevalence among Arab Americans (Alsabri et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib23">2024</link></emphasis>; Saliba et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib75">2024</link></emphasis>). Cultural norms of modesty, particularly among Arab women, may inhibit access to reproductive health services, including HIV testing and prevention measures. Despite improvements in breast and cervical cancer screening rates, challenges persist in addressing domestic violence and other reproductive health issues among Arab American women, especially new immigrants.</para>
      <para role="Para">Socioeconomic factors significantly influence health behaviors and outcomes among Arab Americans with education and income levels serving as strong indicators of health risk and service utilization. Disparities in healthcare coverage exist, with a higher prevalence of uninsured individuals among Arab Americans compared to other ethnic groups. Additionally, physical and mental disabilities among Arab Americans are comparable to those among white Americans, highlighting the need for accessible and culturally competent healthcare services (Abuelezam et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib10">2018</link></emphasis>; Alsabri et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib23">2024</link></emphasis>).</para>
      <para role="Para">Addressing high-risk health behaviors among people of Arab descent requires comprehensive strategies that consider cultural beliefs, socioeconomic factors, and access to healthcare. Culturally sensitive interventions aimed at tobacco cessation, substance abuse prevention, and sexual health education are essential. Moreover, efforts to improve healthcare access and reduce disparities should prioritize education and outreach initiatives tailored to the needs of Arab American communities. By addressing these challenges holistically, healthcare providers and policymakers can work toward improving health outcomes and promoting well-being among people of Arab heritage.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad19" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Meaning of Food Food serves as a cornerstone of Arab culture, deeply intertwined with social customs, familial bonds, and expressions of identity. Across the Arab world, sharing meals with family and friends is not merely a matter of sustenance but a cherished ritual that fosters connection and community. Whether it is a festive celebration, a casual gathering, or a formal dinner party, food acts as a unifying force bringing people together to forge lasting memories and strengthen relationships. One of the striking aspects of Arab cuisine is its remarkable diversity, reflecting the intricate blend of flavors, ingredients, and culinary techniques across different regions. From the aromatic spices of North African dishes to the hearty stews of the Levant and the seafood specialties of the Gulf, each culinary tradition tells a unique story of cultural heritage and regional pride. This diversity not only celebrates the richness of Arab culinary heritage but also serves as a testament to the historical trade routes and cultural exchanges that have shaped Arab cuisine over centuries. Food plays a central role in religious observances, particularly during Ramadan, the holy month of fasting observed by Muslims worldwide. Each day, fasting is broken with a communal meal known as <emphasis role="bold">iftar</emphasis>, where families and communities come together to share a feast and express gratitude for blessings. This shared experience of breaking fast symbolizes unity, compassion, and spiritual renewal, reinforcing bonds of kinship and solidarity.</title>
        <para role="Para">In addition to religious rituals, food also serves as a powerful expression of hospitality in Arab culture. The act of preparing and serving food to guests is considered a gesture of warmth, generosity, and respect. Whether welcoming visitors into the home or dining out at a local restaurant, the abundance and variety of dishes offered reflect the host’s desire to ensure the comfort and satisfaction of their guests. For Arab women, in particular, the preparation and presentation of food carry deep cultural significance. Traditionally, a woman’s culinary skills are seen as a reflection of her love and dedication to her family, with elaborate meals serving as a tangible expression of care and devotion. In social settings, the quality and quantity of food served are indicators of hospitality and esteem with hosts striving to uphold their honor and reputation through the generosity of their offerings. So, food embodies the essence of Arab identity, encapsulating values of community, tradition, and shared heritage. Through the sharing of meals, Arabs reaffirm their connections to family, culture, and faith, celebrating the richness of their culinary traditions while forging bonds of kinship and friendship that transcend borders and generations. Islamic teachings emphasize holistic well-being, encouraging adherents to consume wholesome foods, avoid prohibited substances like pork and alcohol, and maintain moderation in all aspects of life. As Arab communities navigate the complexities of modern life, the preservation and celebration of culinary heritage continue to serve as a source of resilience, unity, and cultural pride.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad20" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Common Foods and Food Rituals Common Foods and Food Rituals among people of Arab heritage or descent are not only about sustenance but also about cultural preservation, social bonding, and religious observance. Arab cuisine, characterized by its rich flavors and diverse ingredients, serves as a cornerstone of cultural identity and pride. Rice, bread (especially flatbreads like pita and khubz), lentils, chickpeas, and couscous form the foundation of many traditional Arab dishes. These staple ingredients are versatile and are prepared in various forms across different regions, reflecting both local tastes and historical influences. <emphasis>Mezze</emphasis>, a selection of small dishes served as appetizers or snacks is an integral part of Arab dining. <emphasis>Mezze</emphasis> platters often feature a colorful array of dips, salads, and finger foods, providing a communal and convivial dining experience. Arab cuisine is renowned for its succulent grilled meats, such as kebabs, shawarma, and kofta. These dishes are often seasoned with a blend of aromatic spices and herbs, adding depth and complexity to the flavors. Rice is a staple in Arab cooking and is often featured in savory dishes such as <emphasis>biryani</emphasis>, <emphasis>maqluba</emphasis>, and <emphasis>kabsa</emphasis>. These rice-based dishes are often cooked with fragrant spices and served as hearty main courses for family meals and festive occasions.</title>
        <para role="Para">Arab desserts are a celebration of sweetness and indulgence, with treats like <emphasis>baklava</emphasis>, <emphasis>knafeh</emphasis>, and <emphasis>halva</emphasis> tantalizing taste buds with their rich textures and flavors. These confections are often enjoyed during special occasions and religious festivals symbolizing joy and abundance. Coffee and tea hold a special place in Arab culture, serving as symbols of hospitality and social connection. Arabic coffee, infused with cardamom and other spices, is traditionally served in small cups as a gesture of welcome and respect. Mint tea, brewed with fresh mint leaves and sugar, is a refreshing beverage enjoyed throughout the Arab world.</para>
        <para role="Para">Food rituals among people of Arab heritage or descent are deeply ingrained in daily life and social interactions. Offering food to guests is considered a sacred duty in Arab culture, reflecting the value placed on generosity and hospitality. Hosts take pride in preparing elaborate meals for guests, ensuring they feel welcome and cherished. Family gatherings and celebrations often revolve around food, with meals serving as a focal point for strengthening familial bonds and fostering a sense of belonging. These gatherings are opportunities for sharing stories, laughter, and cherished family recipes. Food also plays a central role in religious rituals, particularly during Ramadan, the month of fasting observed by Muslims. The pre-dawn meal ( <emphasis>suhoor</emphasis>) and the evening meal ( <emphasis>iftar</emphasis>) during Ramadan are occasions for communal dining and spiritual reflection reinforcing values of empathy, gratitude, and self-discipline.</para>
        <para role="Para">Cooking and sharing traditional recipes are cherished traditions passed down through generations, with family members often gathering in the kitchen to bond over food preparation. These culinary traditions serve as a link to the past, preserving cultural heritage and nurturing a sense of continuity and belonging. Arab festivals and celebrations are marked by feasting and culinary indulgence with communities coming together to enjoy food, music, and festivities. Traditional dishes are prepared with care and served in abundance, symbolizing abundance, prosperity, and communal unity. So, food serves as more than just nourishment for people of Arab heritage or descent—it reflects cultural identity, social cohesion, and shared values. By honoring and preserving culinary traditions, individuals and communities celebrate their heritage and forge connections that transcend borders and generations. Also, understanding food-related customs and rituals is essential for healthcare providers to provide culturally competent care, particularly during religious observances like Ramadan where dietary practices may impact medical management and treatment adherence.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad21" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Dietary Practices for Health Promotion Dietary practices among people of Arab heritage or descent are deeply rooted in tradition, culture, and culinary heritage. Traditional Arab dietary beliefs often associate good health with eating properly, consuming nutritious foods, and fasting to cure disease. This perspective is influenced by teachings attributed to the prophet Mohammed who emphasized the importance of moderation in eating and the relationship between diet and health. In Arab dietary tradition, maintaining balance among different food types—such as hot, cold, dry, and moist—is considered essential for well-being. According to these beliefs, illness can result from excessive eating, consuming nutritionally deficient food, or mixing opposing types of foods. Conversely, abstinence and moderation are seen as remedies that allow the body to expel disease. The condition of the alimentary tract holds particular importance in Arab perceptions of health with gastrointestinal complaints often being a primary reason for seeking healthcare among Arab Americans. However, dietary-related health issues extend beyond digestive concerns. For example, obesity has become a significant problem among second-generation Arab American women and children, often due to the adoption of American dietary habits, including the consumption of high-fat and calorie-dense snacks.</title>
        <para role="Para">To promote health and well-being within Arab communities, it is essential to encourage dietary practices that align with cultural traditions while supporting optimal nutrition:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Encourage the consumption of whole, minimally processed foods such as fruits, vegetables, whole grains, legumes, nuts, and seeds. These foods provide essential nutrients and fiber while supporting overall health and well-being.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Promote mindful eating practices and moderation in portion sizes to prevent overeating and support weight management. Encourage individuals to listen to their hunger and fullness cues and to enjoy meals in a relaxed setting.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Advocate for a balanced diet that includes a variety of carbohydrates, proteins, and healthy fats. Incorporate lean sources of protein such as poultry, fish, legumes, and tofu, along with healthy fats from sources like olive oil, avocados, and nuts.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Encourage the reduction of highly processed foods, sugary snacks, and high-fat desserts in favor of whole, nutrient-dense options. Educate individuals about reading nutrition labels and making informed choices about packaged foods.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Respect cultural preferences and traditions while promoting healthful dietary practices. Explore ways to adapt traditional recipes and meals to align with nutrition recommendations without compromising cultural identity.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Emphasize the importance of staying hydrated by drinking water throughout the day. Encourage the consumption of herbal teas and limit sugary beverages to support hydration and overall health.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem role="ListItem">
            <para>Provide education and resources about nutrition, healthy eating habits, and disease prevention within the context of Arab culture. Offer cooking classes, nutrition workshops, and culturally relevant resources to empower individuals and families to make healthful choices.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para role="Para">By promoting these dietary practices within Arab communities, healthcare providers and educators can support individuals in maintaining cultural traditions while prioritizing their health and well-being. Collaboration between healthcare providers, community leaders, and individuals is essential to address dietary-related health issues and promote positive health outcomes within Arab populations.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad22" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Nutritional Deficiencies and Food Limitations Nutritional deficiencies and food limitations among individuals of Arab heritage are influenced by various factors, including cultural practices, dietary habits, socioeconomic status, and access to healthcare. While Arab cuisine is known for its rich flavors and ingredients, certain dietary patterns and cultural norms may contribute to specific nutritional concerns. Iron deficiency is a prevalent concern, particularly among women of childbearing age and children due to insufficient dietary intake (Jalambo et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib50">2018</link></emphasis>). The traditional Arab diet may lack adequate sources of iron, emphasizing the importance of incorporating iron-rich foods such as legumes, fortified cereals, and leafy greens into daily meals to prevent anemia. Limited consumption of dairy products in Arab cultures may contribute to calcium deficiency, impacting bone health. To address this, individuals should be encouraged to consume alternative sources of calcium such as fortified plant-based milk, leafy greens, almonds, and sesame seeds to support optimal bone health. Factors such as limited sun exposure and cultural practices like covering the skin may lead to vitamin D deficiency, especially in regions with minimal sunlight. Dietary sources of vitamin D and supplementation may be necessary to address deficiencies and support bone health and immune function (Masoud et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib61">2020</link></emphasis>). Individuals following a strict vegetarian or vegan diet in Arab cultures may be at risk of vitamin B12 deficiency due to limited intake of animal products. Incorporating fortified foods or considering supplementation can help prevent deficiencies, particularly among those with limited meat consumption.</title>
        <para role="Para">In regions with low iodized salt intake or limited access to iodine-rich foods like seafood, iodine deficiency disorders may occur. Educating individuals about the importance of iodized salt and promoting the consumption of iodine-rich foods can help prevent deficiencies and support thyroid health. Inadequate folate intake may contribute to neural tube defects in newborns and anemia in adults. Encouraging the consumption of folate-rich foods such as leafy greens, legumes, citrus fruits, and fortified grains is essential for preventing deficiencies and supporting overall health. Food allergies and intolerances, such as lactose intolerance or gluten sensitivity, may affect individuals of Arab heritage, necessitating dietary modifications and medical intervention to prevent adverse reactions and ensure optimal nutrition.</para>
        <para role="Para">Cultural and religious dietary practices, such as halal food requirements and fasting during Ramadan, may impact nutrient intake and dietary patterns. Healthcare providers should respect and support individuals’ cultural and religious beliefs while guiding them on maintaining a balanced diet during periods of fasting or dietary restrictions. Addressing nutritional deficiencies and food limitations among individuals of Arab heritage requires a holistic approach that considers cultural beliefs, dietary preferences and access to resources. Healthcare providers can play a vital role in promoting nutrition education, providing culturally sensitive dietary counseling, and facilitating access to nutritious foods and supplements to support optimal health and well-being within Arab communities. Additionally, understanding and accommodating cultural and religious dietary restrictions are essential for providing culturally competent care to individuals of Arab heritage.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad23" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Fertility Practices and Views Toward Pregnancy Fertility practices and views toward pregnancy among individuals with Arab heritage are influenced by a complex interplay of cultural, religious, social, and familial factors. Arab culture places a high value on fertility and childbearing, often considering it a blessing and a fulfillment of familial and societal expectations (Raghavan et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib69">2024</link></emphasis>; Sharkia and Taubman-Ben-Ari <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib76">2024</link></emphasis>). Islamic teachings emphasize the importance of procreation and raising righteous offspring further reinforcing positive attitudes toward pregnancy and childbirth (Nisar and Benedict <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib66">2024</link></emphasis>). Pregnancy is viewed as a communal event within Arab families and communities. Expectant mothers receive extensive support from family members, friends, and neighbors throughout their pregnancy journey, including emotional support, practical assistance, and advice on prenatal care and childbirth. Couples often engage in preconception care practices to optimize their health and fertility. This may involve adopting a nutritious diet, maintaining a healthy lifestyle, and seeking medical advice to address any underlying health conditions that could affect fertility or pregnancy outcomes.</title>
        <para role="Para">Some individuals incorporate traditional remedies and practices into their fertility journey, such as herbal supplements, dietary modifications, and rituals believed to enhance fertility and promote a healthy pregnancy. These practices hold cultural and historical significance within Arab communities. In cases of infertility, couples may seek medical interventions such as fertility treatments and assisted reproductive technologies. Despite some cultural reservations, seeking medical assistance for infertility is becoming more common among Arab individuals and couples. Expectant mothers receive prenatal care and education to ensure the health and well-being of both mother and baby. This includes regular check-ups with healthcare providers, prenatal screenings, childbirth education classes, and guidance on nutrition, exercise, and childbirth preparation.</para>
        <para role="Para">Gender roles influence fertility practices within Arab families, with women often expected to prioritize motherhood (Sharkia Taubman-Ben-Ari <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib76">2024</link></emphasis>). Men also play a supportive role in the fertility journey, providing emotional support and participating in family planning decisions. Childbirth is considered a significant life event, and expectant mothers adhere to cultural customs and traditions surrounding childbirth and postpartum care. This includes preferences for specific birthing practices and the involvement of female relatives or midwives during labor. Despite positive attitudes toward pregnancy and childbirth, individuals may encounter stigma associated with infertility or pregnancy loss within Arab communities. Open discussions about reproductive health and support for those experiencing fertility challenges are essential to address stigma and promote well-being.</para>
        <para role="Para">While high fertility rates were favored historically, there has been a decline in fertility rates influenced by urbanization, education, and access to healthcare. Contraceptive use has become more prevalent, although cultural, religious, and socioeconomic factors may influence contraceptive decision-making. Overall, fertility practices and views toward pregnancy among individuals with Arab heritage are shaped by cultural traditions, religious beliefs, family dynamics, and socioeconomic factors. By understanding and respecting these diverse perspectives, healthcare providers can offer culturally sensitive care and support to individuals and couples navigating the fertility journey and pregnancy experience within Arab communities.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad24" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Prescriptive, Restrictive, and Taboo Practices in the Childbearing Family Prescriptive, restrictive, and taboo practices surrounding childbirth and the postpartum period among individuals of Arab heritage are deeply rooted in cultural, religious, and societal norms.</title>
        <para role="Para">In Arab culture, childbirth is viewed as a family affair. It is common for extended family members, particularly female relatives, to be actively involved in the pregnancy, childbirth, and postpartum care. They provide emotional support, practical assistance, and traditional remedies to the expectant mother. Arab families often adhere to traditional birthing practices passed down through generations. These may include specific rituals, prayers, or customs believed to ensure safe delivery and protect the mother and baby from harm.</para>
        <para role="Para">Modesty is highly valued in Arab culture, particularly concerning matters related to childbirth and the postpartum period (Druker Shitrit et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib35">2024</link></emphasis>). Women may be expected to maintain modesty by covering their bodies and refraining from interactions with unrelated males during labor and after childbirth. In some Arab communities, women may be subject to dietary restrictions during pregnancy and postpartum. Certain foods or spices believed to be harmful to the mother or baby may be avoided, while others considered beneficial for recovery and lactation may be encouraged.</para>
        <para role="Para">There may be a taboo surrounding discussions about childbirth complications or maternal health issues within Arab families. Some individuals may avoid talking openly about potential risks or challenges during pregnancy and labor due to cultural beliefs or fears of stigma. Naming the baby before birth is often considered taboo in Arab culture, as it is believed to attract the evil eye or negative energy. Instead, families may wait until after the baby is born to announce and formally name the newborn. While breastfeeding is encouraged and widely practiced in Arab communities, there may be taboos surrounding public breastfeeding. Some women may feel uncomfortable nursing in public due to cultural norms and expectations regarding modesty.</para>
        <para role="Para">These practices reflect the cultural values, religious beliefs, and social norms within Arab families. While some practices may provide emotional support and cultural continuity, others may present challenges or limitations for individuals navigating the childbearing experience. It is important for healthcare providers to be aware of these practices and to provide culturally sensitive care that respects the preferences and beliefs of individuals of Arab heritage.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad25" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Death Rituals and Expectations Death rituals and expectations among people with Arab heritage are deeply rooted in cultural, religious, and societal traditions. Islamic traditions heavily influence these rituals, as most individuals of Arab heritage practice Islam. According to Islamic beliefs, death is viewed as a transition to the afterlife, and the deceased is treated with utmost respect and dignity. Following death, the body of the deceased is typically washed and covered in white cloth, a process known as “ <emphasis>ghusl</emphasis>” and “<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kafan</emphasis></emphasis>.” This ritual purification is performed by family members or designated individuals of the same gender. Muslims believe in performing a special funeral prayer for the deceased, known as “ <emphasis>Salat al-</emphasis><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Janazah</emphasis></emphasis>,” usually performed in congregation to seek forgiveness and mercy for the deceased. Prompt burial is encouraged in Islam, preferably within 24 h after death. Graves are typically oriented toward the <emphasis>Qiblah</emphasis> (the direction of the Kaaba in Mecca) and marked with simple headstones. Family and friends gather to participate in the burial process and offer condolences to the bereaved.</title>
        <para role="Para">Arab communities observe a mourning period following the death of a loved one, known as “<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">azza</emphasis></emphasis>,” lasting 3 days to 1 week. During this time, family members receive visitors who offer condolences and support. Death is considered a communal event in Arab culture and the bereaved receive extensive support from family, friends, and neighbors, providing practical assistance, emotional support, and condolences. Expressing condolences and offering support to the bereaved is a significant aspect of Arab death rituals. Visitors often bring food and gifts to the grieving family as a gesture of sympathy and solidarity. Memorial services may be held on the anniversary of the deceased’s death, known as “<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Yawm al-Dhikr</emphasis></emphasis>” (Day of Remembrance).</para>
        <para role="Para">Arab Muslims believe in an afterlife where individuals are held accountable for their actions in this world, viewing death as a transition to eternal life. While Islamic traditions provide a framework for death rituals among Arab communities, there may be variations based on regional, cultural, and individual preferences. So, these rituals play a crucial role in providing comfort and honoring the memory of the departed loved ones.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad26" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Responses to Death and GriefIn Arab heritage communities, responses to death and grief are deeply influenced by cultural, religious, and societal norms. Mourning periods and practices may vary among Muslims and Christians emigrating from different Arab countries. Extended mourning periods may be practiced if the deceased is a young man, a woman, or a child. However, in some cases, Muslims may perceive extended periods of mourning as defiance of the will of God. Family members are asked to endure with patience and good faith in Allah what befalls them, including death. Whereas friends and relatives are to restrict mourning to 3 days, a wife may mourn for 4 months, and in some special cases, mourning can extend to 1 year. Although weeping is allowed, beating the cheeks, or tearing garments is prohibited. For women, wearing black is considered appropriate for the entire period of mourning.</title>
        <para role="Para">Death is considered a communal event, and the bereaved receive extensive support from family, friends, and neighbors. Community members often rally around the grieving family, providing practical assistance, emotional support, and condolences. This sense of community helps alleviate the burden of grief and provides comfort to those mourning the loss. Expressing condolences and offering support to the bereaved is a significant aspect of Arab culture. Visitors often visit the grieving family, bringing food, and gifts, and offering heartfelt condolences. These gestures of sympathy and solidarity are deeply appreciated and help the grieving family feel supported during their time of loss. Religious rituals and practices play a central role in coping with death and grief among individuals of Arab heritage, especially among Muslims. Islamic traditions provide a framework for mourning rituals, including washing, and covering the deceased, performing funeral prayers, and observing a mourning period. These practices offer solace and spiritual comfort to the bereaved, reinforcing beliefs about the afterlife and divine mercy.</para>
        <para role="Para">Arab communities typically observe a mourning period following the death of a loved one, known as “ <emphasis>azza</emphasis>.” During this time, family members receive visitors who offer condolences and support. Mourning rituals may include recitation of the Quran, prayers for the deceased, and gatherings to honor the memory of the departed loved one. Cultural customs and traditions also influence responses to death and grief among individuals of Arab heritage. These may vary based on regional, familial, and individual preferences. For example, some families may observe specific rituals or practices passed down through generations while others may incorporate local customs or traditions into their mourning process. While grief is a natural response to loss, individuals of Arab heritage often view death as a natural part of life and accept it as God’s will. This perspective provides a sense of peace and resignation helping the bereaved cope with their loss and find meaning amid sorrow. Responses to death and grief among people of Arab heritage are characterized by a strong sense of community support, adherence to religious practices, and cultural customs that provide comfort and solace to the bereaved during their time of mourning.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad27" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Religious Practices and Use of PrayerNot all Arab Americans adhere to Islam; various Christian denominations such as the Copts from Egypt, the Chaldeans from Iraq, and the Maronites from Lebanon are prominent within Arab communities. Despite the diversity of religious practices and liturgies among Christians and Muslims, there are shared theological beliefs owing to Islam’s roots in Judaism and Christianity. Both Muslims and Christians believe in a singular God, share reverence for many prophets, anticipate the Day of Judgment, acknowledge the existence of Satan, and hold beliefs regarding heaven, hell, and an afterlife. Notably, Islam diverges from Catholicism and Christian Orthodoxy in its absence of a formal priesthood. Instead, Islamic scholars or religious <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">sheikhs</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis>,</emphasis> esteemed figures within Islamic communities, fulfill the role of <emphasis>imam</emphasis>, or “prayer leader.” The imam’s responsibilities encompass leading congregational prayers, officiating marriages and funerals, and providing spiritual guidance and interpretation of Islamic teachings. Seeking counsel from a local imam can be beneficial for Arab American Muslims grappling with healthcare decisions (Mpofu <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib65">2018</link></emphasis>).</title>
        <para role="Para">The degree of religious observance varies among individuals, ranging from nominal adherence to devout practice. However, owing to the intertwined nature of religion and governance in many Arab countries, a certain level of religious engagement is culturally expected. For instance, Islamic principles profoundly influence various facets of life in Jordan, among other Arab countries. Under Islamic law, abortion is considered a criminal act, while foster parenting is encouraged, although adoption is prohibited (Büchler and Schneider Kayasseh <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib31">2018</link></emphasis>). Infertility treatments sanctioned by Islamic jurists are the only options available. Family matters, including marriage, divorce, guardianship, and inheritance, are adjudicated in Islamic law courts, applying <emphasis>shariah</emphasis>.</para>
        <para role="Para">Public schools incorporate Islamic education and provide prayer spaces and schedules are adjusted to accommodate Islamic holidays and the weekly congregational prayer on Fridays. During Ramadan, businesses close during daylight hours, and workdays are abbreviated to facilitate fasting. Friday marks the beginning of the weekend to enable attendance at communal prayers. Also, adhering to Islamic tradition, which mandates respect and protection for followers of other monotheistic faiths, Christians have separate religious institutions and educational facilities. In Saudi Arabia, however, the practice of religions other than Islam is officially prohibited. For Arab American Christians, church involvement holds significant cultural and spiritual importance. Many partake in fasting and participate in ceremonial church services to observe Catholic and Orthodox Christian holidays. Christian symbols, such as crosses and depictions of the Virgin Mary, may be displayed or worn. Also, educational institutions often provide classes on Christianity to reinforce religious teachings and traditions.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad28" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Meaning of Life and Individual Sources of StrengthFor Muslims, Islam embodies the concept of “submission to Allah,” representing a profound commitment to the divine will and guidance. Life’s purpose revolves around devout worship and spiritual devotion, aimed at preparing for the afterlife by fulfilling religious obligations outlined in the Qur’an, Islam’s holy scripture, and the <emphasis>hadith</emphasis>, the recorded sayings, and actions of the Prophet Muhammad. Central to Islamic practice are the five pillars, or fundamental duties, which include the declaration of faith, performing the five daily prayers, giving alms to the needy, observing fasting during the holy month of Ramadan, and undertaking the pilgrimage to Mecca, known as <emphasis>Hajj</emphasis>.</title>
        <para role="Para">Despite the strong emphasis on familial ties and interconnectedness in Arab societies, religious faith often holds the utmost significance. Whether adherents of Islam or Christianity, Arabs typically exhibit a profound identification with their religious communities, with religious affiliation constituting a fundamental aspect of personal identity alongside family lineage. In everyday life, the presence and influence of God and His divine power are acknowledged and revered, shaping individuals’ beliefs, actions, and interactions within their communities and broader society.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad29" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Spiritual Beliefs and Health Care Practices Many Muslims integrate spiritual practices into their approach to healthcare, often combining spiritual remedies such as prayer and <emphasis>Quranic</emphasis> recitation with conventional medical treatment. Devout patients may request specific accommodations, such as facing Mecca during prayers and ensuring cleanliness through ritual ablution before worship. In Islamic tradition, cleanliness is predominant, as prayers are only deemed acceptable when performed in a clean environment, with a clean body and attire. Hygiene is also emphasized, reflecting a belief in the importance of cleanliness for both physical and spiritual health. Also, Muslims are encouraged to support their communities by visiting the sick and assisting those in need, reflecting a sense of social responsibility and compassion. Illness is sometimes perceived as a form of divine punishment for sins, though many Muslims view it as a test or trial that serves to expiate sins and strengthen character. Responses to illness often include patience, endurance, and unwavering hope in Allah’s mercy with devout individuals believing that even seemingly irreversible conditions may be cured if they align with Allah’s will. Suffering is seen as a means of earning greater rewards in the afterlife, reinforcing the belief in the sanctity of life and prohibiting practices like euthanasia and assisted suicide. Arab American Christians share similar spiritual beliefs regarding healthcare with Orthodox or Catholic Christians. They prioritize caring for the body and observe similar burial practices. A visit from a priest is customary, especially for Catholic patients who may receive the sacrament of the sick as part of their spiritual care. This intertwining of faith and healthcare underscores the importance of spirituality in providing comfort and support to individuals facing illness or adversity within Arab American communities.</title>
        <para/>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad30" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Health-Seeking Beliefs and Behaviors Health-seeking beliefs and behaviors among individuals of Arab heritage are deeply intertwined with cultural, religious, and social factors, shaping their approach to wellness and healthcare utilization (Aseeri <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib27">2020</link></emphasis>; Zimmerman and Shaw Jr <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib83">2020</link></emphasis>). Arab culture emphasizes the significance of familial and community ties, influencing health-seeking behaviors. Seeking advice and support from family members, friends, and community leaders is common practice. Decision-making regarding healthcare often involves consulting with elders or respected community members reflecting the collective nature of decision-making within Arab families. Religious beliefs, particularly within Islam, profoundly impact health-seeking behaviors. Islamic teachings emphasize the importance of maintaining both physical and spiritual well-being. Prayer, Quranic recitation, and adherence to religious rituals are integrated into healthcare practices. Many Muslims believe in the healing power of faith and may combine spiritual practices with conventional medical treatment, viewing illness as a test of faith and an opportunity for spiritual growth.</title>
        <para role="Para">Traditional healing practices, such as herbal remedies and cupping therapy, are prevalent among individuals of Arab heritage. These practices, rooted in cultural traditions and passed down through generations, are often utilized alongside modern healthcare. While some traditional remedies complement conventional treatment, others may be preferred due to cultural preferences or beliefs, highlighting the importance of holistic approaches to health. Access to healthcare services significantly influences health-seeking behaviors. In regions with limited healthcare infrastructure, individuals may rely more on home remedies or traditional healers. Conversely, in areas with advanced healthcare systems, access to hospitals, clinics, and trained medical professionals shapes health-seeking behaviors, underscoring the role of healthcare accessibility in influencing health outcomes.</para>
        <para role="Para">The stigma surrounding certain health conditions, particularly mental health disorders, may deter individuals from seeking timely medical attention within Arab communities (Abo-Rass et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib07">2024</link></emphasis>; Sweileh <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib78">2024</link></emphasis>). Cultural taboos or misconceptions about illness can contribute to delays in seeking care or reluctance to discuss health concerns openly highlighting the need for culturally sensitive healthcare practices. Gender roles and expectations impact health-seeking behaviors, with women often assuming the role of primary caregivers. Cultural norms regarding modesty and gender segregation may influence access to certain healthcare services, particularly for women’s health issues. Modesty concerns may lead to reluctance in seeking care, particularly if it involves disrobing or examination by male physicians.</para>
        <para role="Para">Among Arab immigrants or diaspora communities, health-seeking behaviors may evolve due to exposure to different healthcare systems (Abo-Rass et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib07">2024</link></emphasis>; Aseeri <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib27">2020</link></emphasis>). Acculturation may lead to a blend of traditional practices with mainstream healthcare approaches as individuals navigate cultural identity and integration into new societies, highlighting the dynamic nature of health beliefs and practices. Socioeconomic factors, including education level and income influence health-seeking behaviors. Higher education and socioeconomic status correlate with better access to healthcare services and increased health literacy leading to proactive health-seeking behaviors and preventive care practices. However, disparities in access to care may persist among marginalized populations, underscoring the importance of addressing socioeconomic barriers to healthcare access.</para>
        <para role="Para">While Arab Americans may readily seek care for acute symptoms, preventive care utilization such as well-child visits and health screenings may be limited, particularly among low-income populations. Cultural factors, including present orientation and reluctance to plan, contribute to the underutilization of preventive services. Arab Americans prioritize coping with existing stressors and illnesses over preventive measures, highlighting the need for culturally tailored approaches to preventive care delivery. Understanding these multifaceted influences is crucial for healthcare providers to deliver culturally competent care that respects the beliefs and preferences of individuals from Arab heritage. By addressing cultural, religious, and social factors, healthcare providers can foster trust, enhance communication, and promote equitable access to healthcare services within Arab communities.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad31" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Responsibility for Healthcare Responsibility for healthcare among individuals of Arab heritage is deeply rooted in cultural, familial, and religious beliefs. In Arab communities, the family plays a central role with members assuming caregiving roles for ill relatives and seeking guidance from elders in healthcare decision-making. Religious teachings, particularly within Islam, emphasize the importance of physical and spiritual well-being, integrating prayer and religious rituals into healthcare practices. While familial and religious factors shape healthcare decisions, individuals also bear accountability for their health. Arab communities prioritize preventive measures and encourage individuals to seek medical care when needed. Community support further enhances healthcare access with organizations and religious institutions offering assistance and advocacy.</title>
        <para role="Para">Healthcare providers are respected authority figures in Arab culture, with patients trusting their expertise and guidance. However, differences in healthcare approaches between Arab and American cultures can lead to misunderstandings. American healthcare emphasizes individualism and informed decision-making, while Arab culture values familism and submission to God’s will in healthcare matters. Regarding medical disclosure, Arab physicians may prioritize withholding grave diagnoses to preserve patients’ hope contrasting with American practices. Healthcare financing also differs with communal resources and government facilities often serving as primary means of healthcare access in Arab countries. Understanding and respecting these cultural nuances are crucial for healthcare providers to deliver effective and culturally sensitive care to individuals of Arab heritage. By acknowledging the multifaceted nature of responsibility for healthcare and bridging cultural gaps, providers can ensure better healthcare outcomes for Arab patients.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad32" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Folk Practices Folk practices among people of Arab heritage offer a window into the cultural tapestry that shapes daily life and community interactions (El-Shamy <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib37">2018</link></emphasis>). These practices, deeply rooted in tradition, religion, and social customs reflect a blend of superstitions, healing traditions, and rituals that have been passed down through generations. Despite Islamic teachings discouraging superstition, beliefs in the evil eye, envy, and supernatural entities like jinn persist in Arab folklore (El-Shamy <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib37">2018</link></emphasis>). Protective measures such as wearing amulets, reciting Quranic verses and invoking the name of Allah are common practices to ward off the evil eye. Concerns about jealousy and envy are particularly associated with the misfortune caused by the evil gaze.</title>
        <para role="Para">Traditional healing practices based on the Prophet’s teachings and the theory of humor are prevalent in Arab culture. Remedies often involve treating illnesses with their opposites, such as using hot treatments for cold ailments. Cupping therapy, cautery, and herbal remedies are favored methods alongside spiritual interventions like prayers and dietary adjustments. Rituals seeking divine protection and blessings play a significant role in Arab folk practices. These rituals may involve reciting prayers from the Quran, performing blessings for newborns or homes, or seeking intercession from saints or revered figures for specific needs or challenges. Arab communities mark significant life events with celebratory traditions, including weddings, births, and religious holidays. These occasions are characterized by communal gatherings, music, dance, and feasting, fostering social cohesion and cultural expression.</para>
        <para role="Para">Cultural taboos and customs shape behavior within Arab communities, guiding interactions and social norms. Practices such as avoiding disrespectful gestures and upholding hospitality and respect for elders are deeply ingrained cultural values. While not universally practiced, some Arab communities engage in astrological or divinatory practices for guidance or insight into the future. Astrology, palmistry, and dream interpretation hold cultural significance for those who adhere to these beliefs. Music and dance are integral components of Arab folk culture, serving as avenues for artistic expression, storytelling, and community bonding. Traditional instruments like the <emphasis>oud</emphasis> and <emphasis>tabla</emphasis> accompany regional dance styles, fostering a sense of cultural identity and heritage. Solemn ceremonies and collective expressions of grief characterize Arab mourning rituals. Customs such as washing and shrouding the deceased, reciting prayers, and observing mourning periods reflect the cultural significance placed on honoring the departed. These folk practices underscore the richness and complexity of Arab culture, evolving while preserving cultural identity and heritage. Despite variations across regions and communities, these traditions continue to shape the lives and experiences of individuals of Arab heritage bridging the past with the present in a tapestry of shared beliefs and customs.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad33" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Barriers to Healthcare Newly arrived and unskilled refugees from poorer parts of the Arab world face significant challenges in accessing healthcare services in their host countries. Factors such as refugee status, recent arrival, cultural differences, language barriers, financial constraints, and lack of awareness about available services compound the stresses of immigration and impact both health status and responses to health problems (Childress et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib32">2024</link></emphasis>; Mohsin et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib63">2024</link></emphasis>). These individuals are at particular risk for increased exposure to ill health and inadequate access to care due to a combination of cultural, linguistic, socioeconomic, and systemic barriers.</title>
        <para role="Para">Language and communication barriers pose significant challenges for recent Arab immigrants, as limited proficiency in the host country’s language impedes effective communication with healthcare providers. Without clear communication channels, misunderstandings may arise, leading to suboptimal care and reluctance to seek medical attention. Also, cultural competence among healthcare providers is essential to address the diverse needs and beliefs of Arab patients. Cultural misunderstandings, stereotypes, and biases may further hinder access to quality care and erode trust in healthcare professionals.</para>
        <para role="Para">The stigma surrounding mental health issues and seeking psychological support is prevalent in many Arab communities contributing to underutilization of mental healthcare services and untreated mental health conditions. Socioeconomic disparities, including poverty and lack of health insurance coverage, further exacerbate barriers to healthcare access limiting preventive care and specialized treatments for vulnerable individuals. Immigration status and documentation concerns also deter undocumented immigrants or those with uncertain status from seeking medical care, fearing legal repercussions or deportation.</para>
        <para role="Para">Cultural mistrust and discrimination, compounded by historical biases and negative portrayals of Arabs in media and society create additional barriers to healthcare access (Alsaidi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib24">2023</link></emphasis>). Arab individuals may fear discrimination or bias from healthcare providers based on ethnicity, religion, or national origin, leading to avoidance of healthcare services or selective disclosure of information. Limited availability of culturally competent care providers proficient in the Arabic language and familiar with Arab customs further delays access to quality care, particularly in regions or healthcare settings where such providers are scarce.</para>
        <para role="Para">Community and family dynamics, including patriarchal structures and gender roles, also influence healthcare decision-making and access among individuals of Arab heritage. Cultural norms regarding modesty, privacy, and familial obligations may impact individuals’ autonomy in seeking healthcare, with women and younger family members often deferring to elder relatives or male guardians. Addressing these complex barriers to healthcare requires a comprehensive approach that prioritizes cultural competence, linguistic accessibility, and equitable access to resources and services. Healthcare systems and providers must actively work to foster inclusive environments, promote diversity in the workforce, and implement policies and practices that recognize and address the unique needs of individuals with Arab heritage. By addressing these barriers, healthcare systems can enhance access to care, improve health outcomes, and promote health equity for individuals of Arab heritage.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad34" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Cultural Responses to Health and Illness Arabs regard pain as unpleasant and something to be controlled, often expecting immediate relief postoperatively due to their confidence in medical science. However, this expectation, combined with conserving energy for recovery, may lead to reluctance in adhering to postoperative routines like frequent ambulation. While expressive responses to pain are typically reserved for immediate family, during childbirth or for illnesses accompanied by spasms, Arabs may express pain more openly (Abudoush et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib08">2023</link></emphasis>; Maani et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib56">2021</link></emphasis>; Maki et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib58">2022</link></emphasis>). This differing response between family and healthcare providers can sometimes lead to conflicting perceptions of pain relief adequacy.</title>
        <para role="Para">The stigma surrounding mental illness is pervasive within Arab communities, often leading to denial, attributions to “bad nerves” or blame on evil spirits. Lebanese families for example, may deny mental illness altogether fearing community reactions, resulting in underreporting and avoidance of professional help (Pampati et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib68">2018</link></emphasis>). Consequently, mental distress may manifest as vague complaints like abdominal pain or lassitude, and patients may prefer somatic treatments over counseling with prayer and herbal remedies being more acceptable than psychiatric intervention. Hospitalization may also be resisted due to fears of abandonment further complicating access to mental healthcare. Similarly, attitudes toward disabilities are generally negative with low expectations for education and rehabilitation. Misconceptions about mental retardation persist due to limited exposure and social stigma resulting in the disabled being kept from public view. Family members typically assume caregiving responsibilities, often indulging and protecting the disabled person reflecting acceptance of dependency within Arab culture. These cultural responses underscore the importance of understanding and respecting cultural nuances in healthcare delivery. By acknowledging and addressing these beliefs and attitudes, healthcare providers can foster trust, improve patient-provider communication, and ultimately enhance healthcare outcomes within Arab communities.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad35" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Blood Transfusions and Organ Donation Blood transfusions and organ donation are significant medical procedures within Arab communities, each carrying cultural and religious implications. Blood transfusions are generally accepted among Arabs and Arab Americans, especially in emergencies or for treating severe conditions like anemia or bleeding (Almutairi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib18">2018</link></emphasis>; Braester et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib30">2022</link></emphasis>). While saving lives often overrides religious concerns in emergencies, conservative Muslim communities may have religious beliefs that limit the acceptance of blood transfusions (Almutairi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib18">2018</link></emphasis>; Braester et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib29">2020</link></emphasis>). Healthcare providers must ensure individuals understand the necessity and implications of blood transfusions, respecting their autonomy and providing adequate information for informed consent.</title>
        <para role="Para">Organ donation remains contentious among Arabs and Arab Americans due to religious beliefs, cultural values, and ethical considerations. Views on organ donation vary, influenced by beliefs about death, the afterlife, and body sanctity (Abdulrazeq et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib06">2020</link></emphasis>; Ali et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib15">2020</link></emphasis>; Al-Qerem et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib20">2022</link></emphasis>; Doerry et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib34">2022</link></emphasis>; Janahi et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib51">2018</link></emphasis>; Mekkodathil et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib62">2020</link></emphasis>). Some religious scholars permit it under specific conditions while others oppose it due to concerns about desecration or divine will. Cultural norms, familial expectations, and societal taboos also influence attitudes toward organ donation. Low donation rates are attributed to a lack of public education, misconceptions, and limited support from religious authorities. Providers must approach organ donation discussions sensitively, considering diverse perspectives and engaging in respectful dialog.</para>
        <para role="Para">In summary, while blood transfusions are generally accepted, organ donation remains complex due to arying religious, cultural, and ethical considerations. Sensitivity and understanding of individual beliefs are crucial for healthcare providers to support informed decision-making and promote acceptance of organ donation within Arab communities.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0002s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.2.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad36" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Traditional Versus Biomedical Providers Arab Americans exhibit a unique blend of traditional and biomedical healthcare practices, often seeking treatment in the United States, especially for complex health conditions. They possess a deep respect for Western medicine, valuing treatments that involve surgery, removal of causative agents, or intravenous therapies aimed at eradicating ailments. However, while they hold high regard for physical medical interventions, there is often a lack of trust or respect for mental health treatments among many Arab Americans. A prevailing sentiment among Arab Americans is that mental health services are not effective and are only necessary for individuals with severe mental disorders. Consequently, mental health services are underutilized within Arab American communities despite a greater need for such services among distressed immigrant populations. This skepticism toward mental health treatment may stem from cultural beliefs and stigmas surrounding mental illness.</title>
        <para role="Para">Gender and age considerations also play significant roles in healthcare interactions among Arab Americans. In Arab societies, interactions between unrelated males and females are uncommon with healthcare settings often segregated by sex. Shyness in women is valued and traditional Arab customs may lead Muslim men to ignore women out of politeness. Consequently, some Arab Americans may feel embarrassed or stressed when interacting with healthcare providers of the opposite sex. This discomfort may manifest as a reluctance to discuss personal information or undergo physical assessments and hygiene procedures. Arab American women may prefer to be seen by male healthcare providers, potentially excluding or denying men the opportunity to interact with or diagnose health conditions accurately, particularly for high-risk female patients within the Arab American community.</para>
      </sidebar>
      <sidebar id="ch0008s0002ad37" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
        <title>Status of Healthcare Providers Arab Americans hold science and medicine in high regard, often recognizing and celebrating the historical contributions of Arabs to the field of medicine. They view doctors as authoritative figures with significant knowledge and power. When seeking medical care, Arab American patients who lack English proficiency typically prefer to see Arabic-speaking doctors due to a sense of cultural and linguistic affinity. Many believe that Arab American doctors understand their cultural background and communication style better, making them feel more comfortable and at ease during medical consultations. However, among patients who are fluent in English, there is typically no preference for Arab doctors over American doctors. Some English-speaking patients even prefer American doctors, perceiving them as more professional and respectful than their Arab American counterparts.</title>
        <para role="Para">In Arab society, medicine is highly esteemed, while nursing is often seen as a less desirable profession due to societal norms that dictate certain behaviors for women. However, efforts are being made in many Arab countries to improve the image of nursing and enhance the working environment for nurses (Wehbe-Alamah et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0008s0004bib82">2024</link></emphasis>). American nurses are generally viewed more favorably due to their education, expertise, and ability to perform tasks traditionally reserved for physicians such as physical examinations. Younger Arab American immigrants, particularly those from Lebanon, Iraq, and Jordan tend to have more positive perceptions of nursing as a profession compared to the older generation. The hierarchical structure of Arab society is reflected in the roles and status of physicians and nurses. Physicians, typically older males, are seen as authority figures who expect nurses to defer to them in decision-making and information disclosure. Nurses, often younger females, conform to these expectations and may be relegated to roles as medical assistants and housekeepers rather than being recognized as critical thinkers and health educators. However, nursing is gradually gaining recognition as a profession in many Arab countries, with the establishment of professional organizations resembling the American Nurses Association.</para>
      </sidebar>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0008s0003" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3 </emphasis> Case Studies</title>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.1 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2</title>
      <para role="Para">Suha Abul Mona, an unmarried 23-year-old Arab woman, visits the clinic accompanied by her Middle Eastern parents and older brother. Suha complains of left lower quadrant abdominal pain and spotting, causing concern for her family. Despite feeling visibly uncomfortable and anxious, Suha’s family expresses worry about her condition.</para>
      <para role="Para">Describing a persistent, dull pain in her left lower abdomen, Suha rates it as a 6 out of 10 on the pain scale, noting it began a day ago and has since worsened. She mentions experiencing light vaginal spotting for the past 2 days, which is unusual for her menstrual cycle. Suha denies any history of irregular periods or recent changes in menstrual pattern, attributing her intermittent nausea to the abdominal discomfort. Having no significant medical history, surgeries, or chronic conditions, Suha denies recent illnesses, travel, or exposure to infectious diseases. She is not currently taking any medications, including contraceptives.</para>
      <para role="Para">The family actively participates in Suha’s healthcare decisions, expressing deep concern for her well-being. The nurse observes how traditional gender roles and familial expectations influence communication dynamics with Suha’s mother taking the lead in expressing health concerns while her father and older brother provide support. The nurse acknowledges the influence of Suha’s unmarried status on discussions about reproductive health and sexual activity within the family, respecting cultural norms and societal expectations.</para>
      <para role="Para">Performing a thorough physical examination, the nurse evaluates Suha’s abdominal pain and vaginal bleeding ordering laboratory tests like a complete blood count and urinalysis to assess for underlying causes. Maintaining confidentiality regarding sensitive health information, particularly related to sexual health and reproductive issues, is essential for Suha’s privacy and comfort.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What steps should the nurse take in this situation?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>How can the nurse employ culturally sensitive approaches to effectively address the needs of the Abul Muna family?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>How can the nurse ensure the best care for Suha?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Is it appropriate for the nurse to discuss the possibility of pregnancy with Suha when her parents are not present?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2.1</title>
      <para role="Para">Latif, a 75-year-old man diagnosed with end-stage liver cancer, is undergoing chemotherapy treatment. Experiencing constant nausea and decreased appetite as side effects of his cytotoxic medications, Latif often refuses to eat the food provided to him.</para>
      <para role="Para">Recognizing Latif’s eating difficulties, the nurse arranges for the dietician to assess his dietary preferences and provide personalized recommendations. During the visit, Latif expresses concern about the halal status of the meat in his meals, indicating his discomfort with consuming non-halal food. Despite the nurse’s explanation that the food was selected based on his dietary agreement, Latif remains uneasy about the meat’s halal status. Also, he voices dissatisfaction with the lack of vegetables and salads in his meals, believing them to be essential for nutrition.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Drawing from insights into Arab cultural norms, what steps could the nurse take in response to Latif’s concerns?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>How can the nurse and the dietician collaborate to improve Latif’s dietary intake in a culturally sensitive manner?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What strategies can the nurse employ to prevent similar situations from occurring in the future?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2.3</title>
      <para role="Para">Ms. Al-Mansoori is a 32-year-old pregnant woman who arrives at the delivery suite experiencing contractions. As the nurses assist Ms. Al-Mansoori to her bed, her husband contacts the nurse and expresses his preference for no men to enter his wife’s room. He insists that all nurses, doctors, and other staff attending to his wife be female. Also, he requests that no male personnel enter the room during the night as his wife will have her veil removed while she sleeps. The nurse faces a dilemma as the doctor on duty in the delivery suite is male and Ms. Al-Mansoori is fully dilated and prepared to deliver imminently. In response, the nurse places a note outside the Al-Mansoori family’s room, indicating that males are not permitted inside based on the patient’s preference.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Assess the nurse’s reaction based on your nursing education.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Interpret the cultural significance behind Mr. Al-Mansoori’s actions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What actions can the nurse take in this scenario?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0008s0004" role="bibliography">
    <title>References</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0008s0004bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib01">Abboud S, Naal H, Chahine A, Taha S, Harfouch O, Mahmoud H (2020) “It’s mainly the fear of getting hurt”: experiences of LGBT individuals with the healthcare system in Lebanon. Ann LGBTQ Public Popul Health 1(3):165–185<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1891/LGBTQ-2020-0001">https://doi.org/10.1891/LGBTQ-2020-0001</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib02">Abboud S, Veldhuis C, Ballout S, Nadeem F, Nyhan K, Hughes T (2022) Sexual and gender minority health in the Middle East and North Africa region: a scoping review. Int J Nurs Stud Adv 4:100085. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2022.100085">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2022.100085</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2022.100085">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnsa.2022.100085</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38745607">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11080540">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib03">Abboud S, Chaudhry AB, Pachankis JE (2024a) A qualitative exploration of minority stress, mental health, and sexual health among Arab immigrant sexual minority men in the United States. Cult Divers Ethn Minor Psychol. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2024-50365-001"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2024-50365-001</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib04">Abboud S, Chaudhry AB, Taweh O, Pachankis JE (2024b) “There’s a lot of conflict between your queer identity and also your Muslim or Arab identity;” a qualitative exploration of the intersectional minority stressors of US-born Arab sexual minority cisgender men. SSM-Qual Res Health 5:100393. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2667321524000027"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2667321524000027</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssmqr.2024.100393">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ssmqr.2024.100393</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=39105055">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11299854">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib05">Abdul-Haq AK (2018) The Arab family: formation, function and dysfunction. In: Caring for Arab patients. CRC Press, pp 77–88. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.07.030">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.07.030</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.07.030">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2012.07.030</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib06">Abdulrazeq F, Matsumoto MM, Zourob M, Al-Dobai A, Zeyad K, Marwan N, Qeshta A, Aleyani O (2020) Barriers in knowledge and attitudes regarding organ donation among urban Jordanian population. Saudi J Kidney Dis Transpl 31(3):624–638. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/sjkd/fulltext/2020/31030/Barriers_in_Knowledge_and_Attitudes_Regarding.7.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/sjkd/fulltext/2020/31030/Barriers_in_Knowledge_and_Attitudes_Regarding.7.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4103/1319-2442.289449">https://doi.org/10.4103/1319-2442.289449</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32655049">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib07">Abo-Rass F, Nakash O, Gelaye B, Khatib A, Abo Jabel H (2024) Determinants of intentions to seek formal mental health help among Palestinian adolescents in Israel. Int J Soc Psychiatry 70(4):720–729. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640231224658">https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640231224658</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640231224658">https://doi.org/10.1177/00207640231224658</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38312061">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib08">Abudoush AN, Ali K, Kiran T, Panagioti M, Poliakoff E, Mo Hom N, Husain N (2023) Exploring chronic pain related attentional experiences, distress and coping strategies among Arabic-speaking individuals in Jordan and the United Kingdom. Front Psychol 14:1268179. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1268179">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1268179</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1268179">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2023.1268179</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37849474">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10577280">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib09">Abuelezam NN, El-Sayed AM (2021) Objective and subjective poor mental health indicators among Arab Americans in Michigan: a population-based study. Ethn Health 26(2):225–234. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/13557858.2018.1494822">https://doi.org/10.1080/13557858.2018.1494822</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/13557858.2018.1494822">https://doi.org/10.1080/13557858.2018.1494822</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29972030">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib10">Abuelezam NN, El-Sayed AM, Galea S (2018) The health of Arab Americans in the United States: an updated comprehensive literature review. Front Public Health 6:262. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2018.00262/full"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2018.00262/full</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2018.00262">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpubh.2018.00262</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30255009">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6141804">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib11">Ahmadi M, Ahadi S, Khadembashiri MA, Khadembashiri MM, Mahalleh M, AziziKia H, Zare HR, Khah ASR, Hekmat H, Daroudi R (2024) Burden of ischemic heart disease in the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) and attributable risk factors: an epidemiological analysis from 1990 to 2019. IJC Heart Vasc 50:101316<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijcha.2023.101316">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijcha.2023.101316</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib12">Al Salman J, Al Dabal L, Bassetti M, Alfouzan WA, Al Maslamani M, Alraddadi B, Elhoufi A, Enani M, Khamis FA, Mokkadas E (2020) Management of infections caused by WHO critical priority Gram-negative pathogens in Arab countries of the Middle East: a consensus paper. Int J Antimicrob Agents 56(4):106104. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0924857920302879"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0924857920302879</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106104">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2020.106104</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32721603">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib13">Al-Ajlouni YA, Al Ta’ani O, Shamaileh G, Nagi Y, Tanashat M, Al-Bitar F, Duncan DT, Makarem N (2024) The burden of cardiovascular diseases in Jordan: a longitudinal analysis from the global burden of disease study, 1990–2019. BMC Public Health 24(1):879. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-18316-0">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-18316-0</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-18316-0">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-18316-0</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38515115">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10958901">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib14">Aldossari M, Chaudhry S (2024) Gendered precarity in Saudi Arabia: examining the state policies and patriarchal culture in the labor market. Gender Work Organ. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/gwao.13119">https://doi.org/10.1111/gwao.13119</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib15">Ali A, Ahmed T, Ayub A, Dano S, Khalid M, El-Dassouki N, Orchanian-Cheff A, Alibhai S, Mucsi I (2020) Organ donation and transplant: the Islamic perspective. Clin Transpl 34(4): e13832. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/ctr.13832">https://doi.org/10.1111/ctr.13832</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/ctr.13832">https://doi.org/10.1111/ctr.13832</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib16">Allehebi A, Al-Omair A, Mahboub B, Koegelenberg CF, Mokhtar M, Madkour AM, Al-Asad K, Selek U, Al-Shamsi HO (2024) Recommended approaches for screening and early detection of lung cancer in the Middle East and Africa (MEA) region: a consensus statement. J Thorac Dis 16(3):2142. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11009596/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11009596/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.21037/jtd-23-1568">https://doi.org/10.21037/jtd-23-1568</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38617789">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11009596">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib17">Almarshoodi K, Echevarria C, Kassem A, Mahboub B, Salameh L, Ward C (2024) An international validation of the “DECAF score” to predict disease severity and hospital mortality in acute exacerbation of COPD in the UAE. Hosp Pharm 59(2):234–240. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00185787231209218">https://doi.org/10.1177/00185787231209218</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00185787231209218">https://doi.org/10.1177/00185787231209218</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38450352">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib18">Almutairi AF, Salam M, Abou Abbas O, Nasim M, Adlan A (2018) The public’s risk perception of blood transfusion in Saudi Arabia. J Blood Med 9:75–82. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2147/JBM.S165923">https://doi.org/10.2147/JBM.S165923</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2147/JBM.S165923">https://doi.org/10.2147/JBM.S165923</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29892205">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5993037">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib19">Almutawaa DS, Nuttall P, Mamali E, Al-Mutawa FS, Al Juma DHM (2024) Paradoxes of (un) veiling and the extended self: the experiences of Arab-Muslim women in Kuwait. J Islamic Market 15(1):172–191. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JIMA-07-2022-0196/full/html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JIMA-07-2022-0196/full/html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2022-0196">https://doi.org/10.1108/JIMA-07-2022-0196</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib20">Al-Qerem W, Carter N, Ling J (2022) Attitudes to organ donation and transplantation: an insight from Jordan. Exp Clin Transplant 20(6):602–608. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jonathan-Ling-3/publication/361822043_Attitudes_to_Organ_Donation_and_Transplantation_An_Insight_From_Jordan/links/63b342aec3c99660ebc28d97/Attitudes-to-Organ-Donation-and-Transplantation-An-Insight-From-Jordan.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jonathan-Ling-3/publication/361822043_Attitudes_to_Organ_Donation_and_Transplantation_An_Insight_From_Jordan/links/63b342aec 3c99660ebc28d97/Attitudes-to-Organ-Donation-and-Transplantation-An-Insight-From-Jordan.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.6002/ect.2021.0419">https://doi.org/10.6002/ect.2021.0419</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35791834">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib21">Alqifari S (2024) Antenatal care practices: a population-based multicenter study from Saudi Arabia. Int J Women’s Health 16:331–343. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2147/IJWH.S452934">https://doi.org/10.2147/IJWH.S452934</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2147/IJWH.S452934">https://doi.org/10.2147/IJWH.S452934</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib22">Al Rabeeah SM, Alzahrani EM, Aldhahir AM, Siraj RA, Alqarni AA, Al Draiwiesh IA, Alqahtani AS, Almqati BS, Alharbi TG, Almuntashiri AA (2024) A population-based study of 15,000 people on knowledge and awareness of lung cancer symptoms and risk factors in Saudi Arabia. Front Oncol 14:1295847. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2024.1295847/full"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fonc.2024.1295847/full</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2024.1295847">https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2024.1295847</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38450193">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10916300">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib23">Alsabri MAH, Elsayed SM, Elshanbary AA, Sayed M, Zaazouee BF, Zehra SA, Alkubati SA, Alrubaiee GG (2024) Knowledge, attitude and perceptions of healthcare workers in Arab countries regarding basic life support; a systematic review and meta-analysis. Arch Acad Emerg Med 12(1): e32–e32. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Mohammed-Alsabri/publication/378567140_Arab_Countries_Regarding_Basic_Life_Support_a_Systematic_Review_and_Meta-Analysis/links/65e04855adf2362b635cd815/Arab-Countries-Regarding-Basic-Life-Support-a-Systematic-Review-and-Meta-Analysis.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Mohammed-Alsabri/publication/378567140_Arab_Countries_Regarding_Basic_Life_Support_a_Systematic_Review_and_Meta-Analysis/links/65e04855adf2362b635cd815/Arab-Countries-Regarding-Basic-Life-Support-a-Systematic-Review-and-Meta-Analysis.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38721445">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11077391">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib24">Alsaidi S, Velez BL, Smith L, Jacob A, Salem N (2023) “Arab, brown, and other”: voices of Muslim Arab American women on identity, discrimination, and well-being. Cult Divers Ethn Minor Psychol 29(2):163. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2021-26567-001"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2021-26567-001</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/cdp0000440">https://doi.org/10.1037/cdp0000440</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib25">Al-Shamsi HO, Musallam KM (2024) Not only a Western world issue: Cancer incidence in younger individuals in the United Arab Emirates. CA Cancer J Clin 74:227. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21839">https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21839</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21839">https://doi.org/10.3322/caac.21839</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38625753">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib26">Arab American Institute Demographics (2024). Arab American Institute. Accessed 18 Apr 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.aaiusa.org/demographics"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.aaiusa.org/demographics</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib27">Aseeri A (2020) Health literacy, social support, and diabetes self care among individuals of Arab descent. Wayne State University. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://search.proquest.com/openview/1ddfcd69fbf34a64d3914affe9a1f8c5/1?pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=51922&amp;diss=y&amp;casa_token=paUBStI0_1YAAAAA:DBb1EWZ-ZTMT8u1NvERa9sW-V_K-_cz8ZnzIeFdFDla7ytvRuzPpGI2byUrlJSRHetrocOL4pEY"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://search.proquest.com/openview/1ddfcd69fbf34a64d3914affe 9a 1f 8c 5/1? pq-origsite=gscholar&amp;cbl=51922&amp;diss=y&amp;casa_token=paUBStI0_1 YAAAAA: DBb1 EWZ-ZTMT8u 1 NvERa9sW-V_K-_cz 8 ZnzIeFdFDla 7ytvRuzPpGI2byUrlJSRHetrocOL4pEY</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib28">Atrooz F, Asfar T, Oluwole OJ, Garey L, Salim S, Zvolensky MJ (2024) Insights into cigarette and waterpipe use among Houston-based Arab immigrants and refugees. Open J Soc Sci 12(3):182–195. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.scirp.org/journal/paperinformation?paperid=131801"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.scirp.org/journal/paperinformation? paperid=131801</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib29">Braester A, Akria L, Yakir O, Shelev L, Barhoum M (2020) Blood myths and ethnic–cultural background as impediments in patient blood management education. J Relig Health 59(6):2918–2927. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10943-020-01015-6&amp;casa_token=Qm8lA8O8zpQAAAAA:zTmSnU8HI_BSyZmR56_LA6iOiSSg0WYxK3_hV1J3I5FUxWAOCRQwaydLCSmisTDXQrPhD72_3TXd1lgOEQ"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10943-020-01015-6&amp;casa_token=Qm8lA8O8zpQAAAAA: zTmSnU8 HI_BSyZmR56_LA6iOiSSg0 WYxK3_hV1J3I5 FUxWAOCRQwaydLCSmisTDXQrPhD72_3 TXd1lgOEQ</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01015-6">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01015-6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32285248">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib30">Braester A, Shaoul E, Mizrachi O, Akria L, Shelev L, Barhoum M (2022) Patient involvement in the transfusion decision-making can change patient blood management practice for better or worse. Acta Haematol 145(1):5–8. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://karger.com/aha/article/145/1/5/827341"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://karger.com/aha/article/145/1/5/827341</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1159/000518947">https://doi.org/10.1159/000518947</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=34525473">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib31">Büchler A, Schneider Kayasseh E (2018) Fostering and adoption in Islamic law-under consideration of the laws of Morocco, Egypt, and the United Arab Emirates. Electron J Islamic Middle Eastern Law (EJIMEL) 6:31–56. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/157736/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.zora.uzh.ch/id/eprint/157736/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib32">Childress S, Shrestha N, Covington E, Stark L, Seff I, Black B, McKay M (2024) Risk and protective factors for well-being and barriers to help-seeking among Arab-speaking MENA immigrants and refugees in North America: a scoping review. Glob Soc Welf:1–20. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40609-023-00330-6&amp;casa_token=fTqExXa5Vs8AAAAA:Vw9jEMgjrggYrbfIyecaI-0fAYjiGogd75_v7GbStiRpVuh_Ogji7OmcpN-x-Xr_6UaxMnyUzBn7nGzq"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40609-023-00330-6&amp;casa_token=fTqExXa5 Vs8 AAAAA: Vw9jEMgjrgg Yrbf IyecaI-0fAYji Gogd75_v 7 GbStiRpVuh_Ogji 7 OmcpN-x-Xr_6 UaxMnyUzBn7nGzq</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib33">Dandashly A (2021) The EU and LGBTI activism in the MENA—the case of Lebanon. Mediterr Polit 27(4):1–21. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/13629395.2021.1883287">https://doi.org/10.1080/13629395.2021.1883287</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/13629395.2021.1883287">https://doi.org/10.1080/13629395.2021.1883287</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib34">Doerry K, Oh J, Vincent D, Fischer L, Schulz-Jürgensen S (2022) Religious and cultural aspects of organ donation: narrowing the gap through understanding different religious beliefs. Pediatr Transplant 26(7): e14339. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/petr.14339">https://doi.org/10.1111/petr.14339</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/petr.14339">https://doi.org/10.1111/petr.14339</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35735257">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib35">Druker Shitrit S, Ben-Asher S, Ben-Atar E (2024) “The modesty guard” reflected in online comments in mainstream news sites. J Inf Commun Ethics Soc. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JICES-08-2023-0108/full/html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/JICES-08-2023-0108/full/html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib36">Elbarazi I, Alam Z, Ali N, Loney T, Al-Rifai RH, Al-Maskari F, Ahmed LA (2024) Health literacy among pregnant women in The United Arab Emirates: the Mutaba’ah study. Womens Health 20:17455057231224179. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/17455057231224179">https://doi.org/10.1177/17455057231224179</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/17455057231224179">https://doi.org/10.1177/17455057231224179</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib37">El-Shamy H (2018) Folklore of the Arab world. Humanities 7(3):67. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0787/7/3/67"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.mdpi.com/2076-0787/7/3/67</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/h7030067">https://doi.org/10.3390/h7030067</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib38">Ferrari AJ, Santomauro DF, Aali A, Abate YH, Abbafati C, Abbastabar H, Abd El Hafeez S, Abdelmasseh M, Abd-Elsalam S, Abdollahi A (2024) Global incidence, prevalence, years lived with disability (YLDs), disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs), and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 371 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories and 811 subnational locations, 1990–2021: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2021. Lancet. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(24)00757-8/fulltext"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(24)00757-8/fulltext</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib39">Fleischer NJ, Sadek K (2024) Arab, Middle Eastern, and North African health disparities research: a scoping review. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities:1–19. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40615-024-01972-8&amp;casa_token=wgtoSf-JmvsAAAAA:r0-b77UGrkKjpI9mVb2gB2y7MYSscqkc04ay_WS5TLZl6BuAIAjjvYO9aKj3KpQtIQXBvSAuzqheOirJ5A"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40615-024-01972-8&amp;casa_token=wgtoSf-JmvsAAAAA: r 0-b77 UGrkKjpI9mVb2gB2y 7 MYSscqkc04ay_WS5 TLZl6 BuAIAjjvYO9aKj3 KpQtIQXBvSAuzqheOirJ5A</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib40">Galaz S (2019). The most invisible of the invisibles: skin color and Arab American political ideology. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://polisci.ucsd.edu/undergrad/departmental-honors-and-pi-sigma-alpha/Sydney-Galaz_Senior-Honors_2019.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://polisci.ucsd.edu/undergrad/departmental-honors-and-pi-sigma-alpha/Sydney-Galaz_Senior-Honors_2019.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib41">Hamadeh A, El-Shamy F, Billings J, Alyafei A (2024) The experiences of people from Arab countries in coping with trauma resulting from war and conflict in the Middle East: a systematic review and meta-synthesis of qualitative studies. Trauma Violence Abuse 25(2):1278–1295. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/15248380231176061">https://doi.org/10.1177/15248380231176061</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/15248380231176061">https://doi.org/10.1177/15248380231176061</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37248949">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib42">Hamid GA, Muthanna A, Baom N (2024) Lung cancer epidemiology and histopathological classification: a study from Yemen. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gamal-Abdul-Hamid/publication/378667299_LUNG_CANCER_EPIDEMIOLOGY_AND_HISTOPATHOLOGICAL_CLASSIFICATION_A_STUDY_FROM_YEMEN/links/65e31f46c3b52a117006acbc/LUNG-CANCER-EPIDEMIOLOGY-AND-HISTOPATHOLOGICAL-CLASSIFICATION-A-STUDY-FROM-YEMEN.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gamal-Abdul-Hamid/publication/378667299_LUNG_CANCER_EPIDEMIOLOGY_AND_HISTOPATHOLOGICAL_CLASSIFICATION_A_STUDY_FROM_YEMEN/links/65e31f46c 3b52a117006acbc/LUNG-CANCER-EPIDEMIOLOGY-AND-HISTOPATHOLOGICAL-CLASSIFICATION-A-STUDY-FROM-YEMEN.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib43">Hamid GA, Muthanna A, Baom N (2024) Lung cancer epidemiology, diagnosis and treatment. Accessed 20 Apr 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gamal-Abdul-Hamid/publication/378310759_Lung_Cancer_Epidemiology_Diagnosis_and_Treatment/links/65d3d7b801325d4652155da2/Lung-Cancer-Epidemiology-Diagnosis-and-Treatment.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Gamal-Abdul-Hamid/publication/378310759_Lung_Cancer_Epidemiology_Diagnosis_and_Treatment/links/65d 3d 7b801325d4652155da 2/Lung-Cancer-Epidemiology-Diagnosis-and-Treatment.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib44">Hanafi I, Samra DA, Alsaqqa R, Naeem A, Shebli B, Ajlyakin G (2024) Lung cancer diagnoses and outcomes during the Syrian War, 2011-2018. JAMA Netw Open 7(3): e242091–e242091. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/article-abstract/2816029"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamanetworkopen/article-abstract/2816029</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.2091">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2024.2091</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38477917">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10938179">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib45">HARB A 2024. Hookah smoking and aggressive behavior among university Arab students in Israel. Accessed 20 Apr 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://ejournal.vfu.bg/pdfs/Adel%20Harb,%20HOOKAH%20SMOKING%20AND%20AGGRESSIVE%20BEHAVIOR%20AMONG%20UNIVERSITY%20ARAB%20STUDENTS%20IN%20ISRAEL%20(VFU).pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://ejournal.vfu.bg/pdfs/Adel%20 Harb,%20 HOOKAH%20 SMOKING%20 AND%20 AGGRESSIVE%20 BEHAVIOR%20 AMONG%20 UNIVERSITY%20 ARAB%20 STUDENTS%20 IN%20 ISRAEL%20(VFU).pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib46">Hashem HM, Awad GH (2021) Religious identity, discrimination, and psychological distress among Muslim and Christian Arab Americans. J Relig Health 60(2):961–973. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10943-020-01145-x&amp;casa_token=UEZlZ2-fKhAAAAAA:lLVDF6zf_DtZDIy5cf4yfPO-iTmkDshhBRqJeBJ0tVSPiHvLXS93FOb9SngjlECm4dgWyimL_MHIzZ_Euw"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10943-020-01145-x&amp;casa_token=UEZlZ2-fKhAAAAAA: lLVDF6zf_DtZDIy5cf 4yfPO-iTmk DshhBRqJeBJ0tVSPiHvLXS93 FOb9 SngjlECm4dg WyimL_MHIzZ_Euw</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01145-x">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-020-01145-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33403602">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib47">Hatoum BA (2018) Refusing to be unnatural—a study of the LGBT rights movement in Lebanon. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.duo.uio.no/handle/10852/64441"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.duo.uio.no/handle/10852/64441</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib48">Horne R (2024) Employment and social trends by region. World Employment and Social Outlook 2024(1):37–60. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/wow3.204">https://doi.org/10.1002/wow3.204</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/wow3.204">https://doi.org/10.1002/wow3.204</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib49">Hurley Z (2024) Developing feminist-decolonial-capabilities for emancipatory pedagogy: a case of Gulf-Arab women’s learner-positionalities. In: Lacković N, Cvejic I, Krstić P, Nikolić O (eds) Rethinking education and emancipation. Springer, Cham, pp 117–136. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-47044-8_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-47044-8_6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-47044-8_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-47044-8_6</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib50">Jalambo MO, Karim NA, Naser IA, Sharif R (2018) Prevalence and risk factor analysis of iron deficiency and iron-deficiency anaemia among female adolescents in the Gaza Strip, Palestine. Public Health Nutr 21(15):2793–2802. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/prevalence-and-risk-factor-analysis-of-iron-deficiency-and-irondeficiency-anaemia-among-female-adolescents-in-the-gaza-strip-palestine/654623F6ACCAD908CCD61ACEA523BFF1"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/prevalence-and-risk-factor-analysis-of-iron-deficiency-and-irondeficiency-anaemia-among-female-adolescents-in-the-gaza-strip-palestine/654623F6 ACCAD908 CCD61 ACEA523 BFF1</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980018001568">https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980018001568</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29911513">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10261006">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib51">Janahi FK, Al Rais A, Al Rukhaimi M, Khamis AH, Hickey D (2018) Public awareness of knowledge, belief, and attitude regarding organ donation and organ transplantation: a national survey from the United Arab Emirates. Transplant Proc 50(10):2932–2938. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0041134518310479"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0041134518310479</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.transproceed.2018.08.006">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.transproceed.2018.08.006</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30577150">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib52">Kader F, Bazzi L, Khoja L, Hassan F, de Leon CM (2020) Perceived discrimination and mental well-being in Arab Americans from southeast Michigan: a cross-sectional study. J Racial Ethn Health Disparities 7:436–445. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40615-019-00672-y&amp;casa_token=Iipn1SNuDcYAAAAA:XO3rkUAdnz031z6W7XBPOLxhMyKPeK0EoMl1jgt1JxbGKbgqWBCO9MUNgjqRTjkomv2hIPQ2OJrMwlLEhQ"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40615-019-00672-y&amp;casa_token=Iipn 1 SNuDcYAAAAA: XO3rkUAdnz031z 6W7 XBPOLxhMyKPeK0 EoMl1jgt 1 JxbGKbgqWBCO9 MUNgjqRTjkomv 2hIPQ2 OJrMwlLEhQ</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40615-019-00672-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s40615-019-00672-y</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31833009">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib53">Khosh NK, Khalil AA, Alhaded HHS (2020) Cultural values and norms of communication: a view from the Middle East. Proceedings of ADVED, 2020 (6th ed). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.academia.edu/download/106965242/96.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.academia.edu/download/106965242/96.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib54">Labibidi H, Lababidi G, Al Rifai M, Nasir K, Al-Kindi S (2024) Cardiovascular disease in Arab Americans: a literature review of prevalence, risk factors, and directions for future research. Am J Prev Cardiol 18:100665. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666667724000333"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2666667724000333</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpc.2024.100665">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajpc.2024.100665</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib55">Lebanon’s LGBT People Reclaim Their Power (2020) Human rights watch. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/07/lebanons-lgbt-people-reclaim-their-power"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.hrw.org/news/2020/05/07/lebanons-lgbt-people-reclaim-their-power</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib56">Maani W, Alrabayah M, Atiyat B, Abed A (2021) The role of Arab and Muslim scholars in defining and treating pain: a review article. Jordan Med J 55(2):55–60. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://archives.ju.edu.jo/index.php/jmj/article/view/105717"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://archives.ju.edu.jo/index.php/jmj/article/view/105717</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib57">Mahamid F, Veronese G, Bdier D (2024) Trauma predicts the desire to migrate and psychological well-being via belongingness and quality of life among Palestinians. Psychol Trauma. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2024-44918-001"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2024-44918-001</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib58">Maki D, Lempp H, Critchley D (2022) An exploration of experiences and beliefs about low back pain with Arab Muslim patients. Disabil Rehabil 44(18):5171–5183. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2021.1928301">https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2021.1928301</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2021.1928301">https://doi.org/10.1080/09638288.2021.1928301</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=34167415">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib59">Mansour R, Al-Ani A, Al-Hussaini M, Abdel-Razeq H, Al-Ibraheem A, Mansour AH (2024) Modifiable risk factors for cancer in the middle East and North Africa: a scoping review. BMC Public Health 24(1):223. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-17787-5">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-17787-5</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-17787-5">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12889-024-17787-5</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38238708">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10797965">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib60">Manzanero AL, Aroztegui J, Fernández J, Guarch-Rubio M, Álvarez MÁ, El-Astal S, Hemaid F (2024) War, torture and trauma in preadolescents from Gaza Strip. Two different modalities of PTSD. Anuario de Psicologia Juridica 34(1):1–12. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.copmadrid.org/apj/art/apj2024a6"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.copmadrid.org/apj/art/apj2024a 6</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.5093/apj2024a6">https://doi.org/10.5093/apj2024a6</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib61">Masoud MS, Yakout SM, Al-Attas OS, Alokail MS, Al-Daghri NM (2020) The association between iron and vitamin D status in Arab adolescents. Public Health Nutr 23(7):1208–1213. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/association-between-iron-and-vitamin-d-status-in-arab-adolescents/5F7C822F9FC6EC2A2BACBD957D52098A"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/public-health-nutrition/article/association-between-iron-and-vitamin-d-status-in-arab-adolescents/5F7C822F9 FC6 EC2A2 BACBD957D52098A</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980019001113">https://doi.org/10.1017/S1368980019001113</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31097054">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib62">Mekkodathil A, El-Menyar A, Sathian B, Singh R, Al-Thani H (2020) Knowledge and willingness for organ donation in the middle eastern region: a meta-analysis. J Relig Health 59(4):1810–1823. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-019-00883-x">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-019-00883-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-019-00883-x">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10943-019-00883-x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31309441">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib63">Mohsin K, Mula-Hussain L, Gilson R (2024) Health Care Access Barrier (HCAB) framework for the barriers to cancer care during conflicts: perspective from Iraq. BMJ Oncol 3(1) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://bmjoncology.bmj.com/content/3/1/e000252.abstract"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://bmjoncology.bmj.com/content/3/1/e000252.abstract</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib64">Mostafavi E, Ghasemian A, Abdinasir A, Mahani SAN, Rawaf S, Vaziri MS, Gouya MM, Nguyen TMN, Al Awaidy S, Al Ariqi L (2022) Emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases in the WHO Eastern Mediterranean region, 2001-2018. Int J Health Policy Manag 11(8):1286. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9808364/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9808364/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=33904695">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib65">Mpofu E (2018) How religion frames health norms: a structural theory approach. Religions 9(4):119. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.lib.umb.edu/10.3390/rel9040119">http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.lib.umb.edu/10.3390/rel9040119</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/rel9040119">https://doi.org/10.3390/rel9040119</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib66">Nisar M, Benedict SM (2024) Exploring gender equality: a comparative study of contemporary feminism, Islamic perspective, and feminism in Sufism. Islamic Perspective, and Feminism in Sufism (9 Jan 2024). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4721634"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol 3/papers.cfm? abstract_id=4721634</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib67">Olimat S, Altawalbeh SM, Maabreh RS, Basheti IA (2024) Asthma–COPD overlap syndrome among smoker subjects with asthma: a cross-sectional study. J Appl Pharm Sci 14(4):72–80. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://japsonline.com/abstract.php?article_id=4194&amp;sts=2"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://japsonline.com/abstract.php? article_id=4194&amp;sts=2</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib68">Pampati S, Alattar Z, Cordoba E, Tariq M, Mendes De Leon C (2018) Mental health outcomes among Arab refugees, immigrants, and U. S. born Arab Americans in Southeast Michigan: a cross-sectional study. BMC Psychiatry 18(1):379. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-018-1948-8">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-018-1948-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-018-1948-8">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-018-1948-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=30514261">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6280467">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib69">Raghavan D, Natarajan J, Seshan V, Alsaraireh A (2024) Impact of recurrent pregnancy loss on depression, anxiety and fertility related stress in Omani women: a cross sectional survey. Afr J Reprod Health 28(1):13–21. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ajol.info/index.php/ajrh/article/view/266139"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ajol.info/index.php/ajrh/article/view/266139</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38308521">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib70">Rashidi M-M, Saeedi Moghaddam S, Azadnajafabad S, Mohammadi E, Khalaji A, Malekpour M-R, Keykhaei M, Rezaei N, Esfahani Z, Rezaei N (2024) Mortality and disability-adjusted life years in North Africa and Middle East attributed to kidney dysfunction: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2019. Clin Kidney J 17(1): sfad279. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://academic.oup.com/ckj/article-abstract/17/1/sfad279/7425645"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://academic.oup.com/ckj/article-abstract/17/1/sfad279/7425645</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/ckj/sfad279">https://doi.org/10.1093/ckj/sfad279</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38288035">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib71">Rezki K, Fateh D (2024). The reality of health development in Algeria in light of the current challenges. Accessed 20 Apr 2024<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.asjp.cerist.dz/en/downArticle/512/7/1/239629"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.asjp.cerist.dz/en/down Article/512/7/1/239629</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib72">Rostam-Abadi Y, Gholami J, Shadloo B, Mohammad Aghaei A, Mardaneh Jobehdar M, Ardeshir M, Sangchooli A, Amin-Esmaeili M, Taj M, Saeed K, Rahimi-Movaghar A (2024) Alcohol use, alcohol use disorder and heavy episodic drinking in the Eastern Mediterranean region: a systematic review. Addiction 119:984. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/add.16444">https://doi.org/10.1111/add.16444</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/add.16444">https://doi.org/10.1111/add.16444</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38356084">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib73">Saadi A, Taleghani S, Dillard A, Ryan G, Heilemann M, Eisenman D (2023) Nurses’ experiences with racial, ethnic, cultural, and religious discrimination in the workplace: a qualitative study. AJN Am J Nurs 123(5):24–34. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/ajnonline/fulltext/2023/05000/Original_Research__Nurses__Experiences_with.18.aspx?casa_token=oJElk1fppTEAAAAA:k-lzMcwd080yHCf4NWqvQNy_qwEIK6xZKimt_jfdzfc1zHygIrOmVOHXUGdM1Tj5kCj9KdZyK0RLrB7oA45RNr8"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/ajnonline/fulltext/2023/05000/Original_Research__Nurses__Experiences_with.18.aspx? casa_token=oJElk 1fppTEAAAAA: k-lz Mcwd080yHCf4 NWqvQNy_qwEIK6xZKimt_jfdzfc 1zHygIrOmVOHXUGdM1 Tj5kCj9 KdZyK0 RLrB7oA45 RNr8</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/01.NAJ.0000931892.39368.e1">https://doi.org/10.1097/01.NAJ.0000931892.39368.e1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37021974">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib74">Safadi R (2024) The liver in Greco-Arabic and Islamic medicine. Clin Liver Dis 23(1): e0137. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/cld/fulltext/2024/01010/the_liver_in_greco_arabic_and_islamic_medicine.36.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/cld/fulltext/2024/01010/the_liver_in_greco_arabic_and_islamic_medicine.36.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/CLD.0000000000000137">https://doi.org/10.1097/CLD.0000000000000137</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib75">Saliba B, Kang M, Wells N, Mao L, Prestage G, Hammoud MA (2024) Hiding in plain sight: highlighting the research gap on access to HIV and other sexual health services for underrepresented gay men in developed Western countries–insights from a scoping review with a focus on Arab men. Sex Health. 21<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.publish.csiro.au/SH/SH23131"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.publish.csiro.au/SH/SH23131</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib76">Sharkia SA, Taubman-Ben-Ari O (2024) Personal growth and life satisfaction among Arab mothers after fertility treatment–the role of stress and optimism. J Happiness Stud 25(1):6. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa?redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10902-024-00712-3&amp;casa_token=mgfv7uN1X1AAAAAA:rq1XsnFSBlxsrsrTOZlo9tZ2-O3LnT3wJdW3F5Tkg24eD1SA7jtn9RT4mAc6C0Id-F6H7RKVFLFUxuymlA"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://idp.springer.com/authorize/casa? redirect_uri=https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10902-024-00712-3&amp;casa_token=mgfv 7uN1X1 AAAAAA: rq 1 XsnFSBlxsrsrTOZlo 9tZ2-O3 LnT3wJdW3F5 Tkg24eD1 SA7jtn 9 RT4mAc6C0 Id-F6H7 RKVFLFUxuymlA</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10902-024-00712-3">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10902-024-00712-3</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib77">Suleiman Y (2019) Arabic language and national identity: a study in ideology. Edinburgh University Press. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=eacxEAAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR5&amp;dq=arabic+language&amp;ots=G7hx5uGDbm&amp;sig=0vqKkbLXagVCywGebXAadyzJ1d0"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://books.google.com/books? hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=eacxEAAAQBAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR5&amp;dq=arabic+language&amp;ots=G7hx 5uGDbm&amp;sig=0vqKkbLXagVCywGebXAadyzJ1d 0</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib78">Sweileh W (2024) Stigma research in Arab countries: a rapid review. Ment Health Soc Incl. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/MHSI-10-2023-0111/full/html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/MHSI-10-2023-0111/full/html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib79">Tarabay J, Golm D (2024) The transmission of intergenerational trauma and protective factors in survivors of the Lebanese Civil War and their adult offspring. Int J Intercult Relat 99:101952. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014717672400021X"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014717672400021X</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2024.101952">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijintrel.2024.101952</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib80">Vahidniya N, Hasani Z, Kamali SM (2024) Effect of warfare and forced displacement on mental health of children. Int J Travel Med Glob Health 12(1) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ijtmgh.com/article_188419.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ijtmgh.com/article_188419.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib81">Veronese G, Mahamid F, Bdier D, Obaid H, Cavazzoni F (2024) The development and validation of the Palestinian children’s traumatic events checklist in a war-torn environment. BMC Psychiatry 24(1):254. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-024-05731-1">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-024-05731-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-024-05731-1">https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-024-05731-1</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38570753">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10988932">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib82">Wehbe-Alamah H, Doumit MAA, Bernstein J, Aboul-Enein BH (2024) Nursing research in Arab countries: current status, trends, challenges, and opportunities. SAGE Open Nurs 10:23779608241246871. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608241246871">https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608241246871</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608241246871">https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608241246871</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38628620">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC11020728">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0008s0004bib83">Zimmerman MS, Shaw G Jr (2020) Health information seeking behaviour: a concept analysis. Health Info Libr J 37(3):173–191. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/hir.12287">https://doi.org/10.1111/hir.12287</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/hir.12287">https://doi.org/10.1111/hir.12287</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32052549">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
