<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0027" label="27">
  <title>27. People of Mexican Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0027s0004">
    <title>27. People of Mexican Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_27">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_27</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rick Zoucha</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0027">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Anelise Zamarripa-Zoucha</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0027">2</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Duquesne University School of Nursing, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Central Outreach Wellness Center, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Rick Zoucha</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:zoucha@duq.edu">zoucha@duq.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Migration and associated economic factors, Dominant language and dialects, Temporal relationships, Format for names, Death rituals, Spirituality, Machismo and marianismo, Biocultural ecology, Diseases and health conditions, Nutrition and food rituals, Traditional health practices, Folk practitioners</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0027s0001" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para">Great variations exist among people of Mexican heritage, depending on acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001"><emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>. However, a core of commonly held beliefs and practices is shared by those who self-identify as Mexican, Mexican American, <emphasis role="bold">Latino</emphasis>, Latinx, Latin@, Chicano, or <emphasis role="bold">Hispanic</emphasis>. Hispanic and Latino are historically used interchangeably; however, Latino includes Brazilians who are not Hispanic. Contemporary verbiage to include gender variant and gender non-conforming people of Latin American heritage is becoming more common. This includes the use of Latinx and Latin@ to promote gender inclusivity. In addition, some who identify as Mexican have no Hispanic heritage because they are from indigenous native groups who have never mixed with/married people from Spanish backgrounds; however, they are still considered Mexican.</para>
    <para role="Para">Mexican Americans include newer immigrants and people who have been in the United States for six or seven generations. Some originate from high mountains and plateaus, some from low-lying swamp areas, and others from sea- and ocean-side communities. The topography of the region of origin in Mexico may be the key to accurate health assessments for dietary preferences, illnesses, and disease. Many Mexicans come to the United States because of the high poverty rate of over 20.2% in Mexico.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Great diversity exists in the Spanish language; many dialects are spoken in Mexico. Although most Mexicans use Spanish as their primary language, some speak only English, some speak both English and Spanish, and some speak only an indigenous native language.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Significant importance is placed on verbal communication. Conversants may stand very close, even with people who are not well known to them. Loud voice volume in formal settings may connote anger.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Whereas more traditional and older individuals do not maintain eye contact, acculturated and more educated people usually do maintain eye contact.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Mexicans tend to be present-oriented. Time is relative, not categorically imperative; thus, many arrive late for appointments and delay seeking health care until the condition is more serious. Offer flexibility in scheduling health care appointments if possible in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Touch is common between people of the same sex. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity and ask permission before touching during a physical examination.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Formal names may be extensive and include a middle name and the mother’s and father’s surnames. A married woman may take her husband’s surname, thereby having three surnames. <emphasis role="bold">Greet adults formally with Señor, Señora, or Señorita unless told to do otherwise. Ask which name is preferred as well as which name is used for legal purposes.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In traditional families, men are expected to provide financial support for the family. However, this is changing due to economic challenges in the United States.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The stereotype of “ <emphasis role="bold">machismo</emphasis>,” in which men are the primary decision-makers in the household, is not accurate for all people of Mexican heritage. <emphasis role="bold">Do not stereotype machismo.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women care for children and maintain the home. In most homes where the man and woman both work outside the home, they tend to share household chores and child-rearing responsibilities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some households are patriarchal, some are matriarchal, and some are egalitarian. Regardless of who makes the decision, the male traditionally is expected to be the spokesperson for the family. <emphasis role="bold">Ask specifically who makes which decisions for the family.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Priorities for children are getting an education, having good manners, and respecting older people and people in high-status positions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children born out of wedlock are loved regardless of the parents’ marital status. Men usually remain involved with their children who are born out of wedlock.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When possible, extended family members prefer living close to each other. The elderly frequently live with their children when self-care becomes a concern; in addition, the elderly are always respected for their wisdom.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Extended family members are a good resource for home care.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Social status is gained through formal academic education, having a respected position, and having children and family members with good manners.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">As of December 2022, all states in Mexico have sanctioned same-sex marriages and Mexico’s Supreme Court has ruled that all 31 states must recognize same-sex marriages. Many continue to be stigmatized. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose sexual orientation status to family members.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">People educated in Mexico are likely to have been exposed to pedagogical approaches that include rote memorization and an emphasis on theory with little practical application. American educational systems usually emphasize an analytical approach, practical applications, and a narrow, in-depth specialization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Teach practical application of knowledge during orientation and ongoing.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Because family is a first priority for most Mexicans, activities that involve family members usually take priority over work issues. <emphasis role="bold">Be flexible with work hours when feasible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Mexican Americans tend to shun confrontation for fear of losing face. Many are very sensitive to differences of opinion, which are perceived as disrupting harmony in the workplace.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Truth is tempered by diplomacy and tact. When a service is promised for tomorrow, even when they know the service will not be completed tomorrow, it is promised to please, not to deceive. Truth is seen as a relative concept, not an absolute value, and people are expected to give direct yes and no answers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain the value of “absolute” truth in the American workforce.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For most Mexicans, titles and positions may be more important than money.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Mexicans believe that time is relative and elastic, with flexible deadlines, rather than stressing punctuality and timeliness. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the expectation of punctuality in the American workforce and repercussions for chronic tardiness.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many are used to having traditional autocratic managers who assign tasks but not authority. A Mexican worker who is not accustomed to responsibility may have difficulty assuming accountability for decisions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">More traditional and some older individuals do not maintain eye contact, whereas acculturated and more educated people usually do maintain eye contact. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that the lack of eye contact means the person is not listening, does not care, or is being less than truthful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Mexicans have dark hair and dark eyes, but some may have blond hair and blue eyes. Many have a diverse gene pool that includes indigenous Native groups.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assess for cyanosis and jaundice in those with dark skin by observing the sclera and conjunctiva, palms of the hands, soles of the feet, and buccal mucosa and tongue rather than relying on skin tone.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0027s0001ta01">27.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Mexicans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assessments need to include exposure to pesticides, parasitic diseases, and illnesses that are common in their home country.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mexicans may require lower doses of antidepressants and experience more intense side effects than non-Hispanic white populations. Many are also poor metabolizers of debrisoquine. <emphasis role="bold">Observe for side effects of antidepressants.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0027s0001ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 27.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Mexicans</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Parasitic diseases</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Dengue fever</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cleft lip/palate</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Dental caries</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Hypertension</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Sickle cell anemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">HIV/AIDS</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Pesticide/herbicide poisoning</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Smoking is more common among the more acculturated, but they smoke fewer cigarettes than European Americans when they do smoke. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation beginning in elementary schools.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Mexicans use alcohol to make them emotionally and socially extroverted and are more likely to engage in binge drinking than other groups. <emphasis role="bold">Assess alcohol consumption by determining the amount of alcohol used both daily and during celebrations.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many newer immigrants may be reluctant to use seat belts and helmets because they are not used in their home country. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the legal requirements of using seat belts and helmets.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Men may object to condom use because it decreases sensitivity. Women may object to the use of condoms because of the suggestion that the woman is “dirty.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Explain that condoms help prevent pregnancy and decrease the incidence of HIV/AIDS (SIDA) and other sexually transmitted infections.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Food choices vary widely, depending on the region of Mexico from which the person comes. Rice, beans, and tortillas are food staples.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Determine preparation practices because some people use coconut oil and animal fat for flavoring. Determine flavorings and ingredients as well as the major food choices because these can add significant calories to the diet. Encourage use of corn tortillas instead of flour tortillas, leafy green vegetables, and soups and stews that use bones in them to increase calcium content in the diet and avoid side effects with lactose intolerance.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Being overweight according to the US height/weight tables is seen as positive. <emphasis role="bold">Patients should be co-participants in deciding an acceptable weight.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Sweetened fruit drinks are popular, and adding sugar to fresh fruit juice is common.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Discouraging the use of sweetened fruit drinks and encouraging the use of natural juices without added sugar is one means of reducing calorie and carbohydrate consumption.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mealtimes may not coincide with the dominant American schedule. For many, the noontime meal is the largest meal of the day, and the evening meal may be served very late in the evening. <emphasis role="bold">Determine the individual’s and family’s mealtimes, and adjust medication schedules accordingly.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many individuals balance food choices according to the “ <emphasis role="bold">hot” and “cold</emphasis>” theory. Variations occur in the assignment of different foods for hot and cold properties. Herbal teas are commonly used to maintain health and treat illnesses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Determine the patient’s use of the hot and cold theory of food choices, which herbs and teas are used, how frequently they are used, and the amount used each time. Nonharmful practices should be incorporated into the plan of care.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Fertility practices are primarily connected with religious beliefs usually associated with the Catholic Church. The church discourages the use of condoms, believing they promote promiscuity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The rhythm method or Norplant is usually deemed acceptable because they are more natural means of helping to prevent an unwanted pregnancy. Foams, creams, and intrauterine devices may not be acceptable because women are not supposed to touch their genitals except for purposes of bathing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Abortion is decriminalized in Mexico, but the social and cultural stigma remains. A few individuals may see sterilization and other methods of birth control as acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Determine on an individual basis acceptable methods of birth control. Refer to planned parenthood if appropriate.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Multiple births are more common among Mexicans. Pregnancy is considered a natural condition, with most advice for health care coming from family members; this may deter prenatal care. <emphasis role="bold">Stress that medical evaluation during pregnancy is necessary to help ensure the health of both the mother and the baby. Encouraging female relatives to accompany the pregnant woman for prenatal checkups may be helpful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For many, the delivery room is not a place for men, and many believe that allowing the father to see the woman or baby during the delivery may harm the mother or baby. <emphasis role="bold">However, with acculturation this cultural view may be changing. Ask the mother who they would prefer in the delivery room.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Various cultural customs and beliefs are included in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0027s0001ta02">27.2</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0027s0001ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 27.2</emphasis> Common cultural beliefs and customs</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Walking in the moonlight while pregnant may cause birth defects</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Safety pins, metal keys, or other metal amulets are worn to prevent birth deformities</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Raising one’s arms over the head while pregnant will cause the cord to wrap around the infant’s neck</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Postpartum women are discouraged from taking baths, sitting in a bathtub, taking sitz baths, or washing their hair for 6 weeks</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Bathing with a cloth, including the hair, is acceptable. Encourage use of warm compresses instead of sitz baths</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Cutting the baby’s hair or nails in the first 3 months is believed to cause blindness and deafness in the baby. Ask permission before cutting an infant’s nails or hair</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Placing a key, coin, or other metal object on the infant’s umbilicus is believed to promote healing. Teach how to clean the object to prevent infection</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Wearing an abdominal binder can prevent air from entering the uterus in postpartum women</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Covering their ears, head, shoulders, and feet can prevent blindness, mastitis, frigidity, or sterility in women</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Recognize which practices are harmless, and respect the woman’s beliefs as appropriate</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Using videos and literature in Spanish and with pictures of Hispanics may help compliance with health interventions</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Death is an extended family affair, and members are obligated to visit in the hospital or long-term care facility. Expect many visitors in the inpatient setting. Among more traditional Mexicans, a family member must remain with the dying person.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Find a place where family members can be together, preferably in the unit with the dying person. In alternative settings, find another quiet place where the family can gather. Elicit a family spokesperson to assist with crowd control.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some families may want to have lighted candles in the room of the dying patient. Although inpatient facilities will not permit open candle flames because of fire safety, electric candles are acceptable to most.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Death is considered part of life, and some, especially men, may approach death stoically.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Just because someone does not openly display emotions about death does not mean the person does not care about the deceased.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some, especially women, may have an <emphasis>ataque de nervios</emphasis> on hearing about the death of a loved one. In this culture-bound syndrome, the person exhibits hyperkinetic and seizure-like activity that releases strong emotions. <emphasis role="bold">This is a normal reaction, and treatment is usually not necessary except to remain with the person and provide emotional support. Use family members for assistance when possible.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">When a person dies, family and friends gather for a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">velorio</emphasis></emphasis>, a festive occasion to celebrate the person’s life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Burial practices vary, but the more traditional do not practice cremation. Autopsy is not welcomed. <emphasis role="bold">Explaining the legalities of autopsy is conducive to having the family accept an autopsy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Although many other religions are practiced, the predominant religion is Roman Catholicism. However, do not assume that the practice of the Catholic religion is the same for all people. Each person’s religious practices must be assessed on an individual basis. Many families have altars in their homes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family is foremost. The individual’s source of strength comes from being with family members. Priests and other religious leaders are major sources of emotional strength and support for most Mexicans. <emphasis role="bold">On admission to the health-care facility, inform the patient and family of the availability of referral for pastoral care and support.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family is considered the most credible source of health-care information among Mexicans. This practice can impede health-seeking behaviors. For many, good health means being free of pain and is largely due to the “will of God.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many migrant workers are not aware of the necessity of protecting themselves from pesticides and herbicide poisoning because they are not common in Mexico.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Health teaching on herbicides and pesticides should be a family affair.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Mexicans use herbal medicines and teas. The specific herbs and teas vary among families. Most of these teas and herbs are beneficial or at least not harmful. A few can be harmful by themselves, whereas others may be harmful when included with prescription and over-the-counter medications. <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain if patients are using over-the-counter medicines and explain the hazards of excessive use of over-the-counter medications as well as using medicines that were originally intended for use by another family member.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Assess for use of herbs and teas. Two herbs commonly used by Mexican Americans are</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="bold">azarcon</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
              <emphasis role="bold">greta</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">, which are used for colic and stomach conditions in children. Both of these herbs contain lead and can be toxic, especially in children.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Mexicans practice the hot and cold theory, according to which many diseases and illnesses are caused by a disruption in the hot and cold balance of the body. Thus, if too many cold forces in the body cause an illness, treatment is aimed at balancing the condition by introducing hot treatments and foods that are considered hot. <emphasis>Hot and cold do not always coincide with temperature</emphasis> but perceived metabolic properties.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Hot conditions include infection, diarrhea, and sore throats and, therefore, are treated with such cold foods as fruits, vegetables, and dairy products. Cold conditions, such as cancer, malaria, and earaches, are treated with such hot foods as liquor, beef, pork, and spicy foods. Tremendous variations exist between and among hot and cold conditions, depending on the family.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Include the entire family in health promotion and health teaching to increase compliance with health prescriptions and interaction.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Frequently seen cultural illnesses or conditions are shown in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0027s0001ta03">27.3</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Perform an individual pain assessment, determine usual treatment modalities used for pain, ask what the patient thinks caused the pain, and determine what the patient usually does to relieve pain. Have pain scales in Spanish as well as visual scales for those who do not read Spanish or English. <emphasis role="bold">Explaining that pain medication will promote healing may encourage the patient to accept pain medication.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The sick role is easy to enter without personal feelings of inadequacy or blame. Family members readily take on the sick person’s responsibilities. Family members usually care for the ill family member at home, if at all possible. <emphasis role="bold">Query the family to determine if they have the resources to care for a member at home. Not all Mexicans in the United States have the extended family to care for relatives at home.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Because long-term care facilities are either nonexistent or are of very poor quality in Mexico, family members may be very reluctant to place family members in such a facility. Suggesting a visit to one may be an option.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Extraordinary means being used to preserve life are frequently frowned upon and are often determined by finances, education, and availability of services.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Family members who are documented are more likely to seek and receive health care versus those who are undocumented. In some families, several members may be documented and others are undocumented, potentially resulting in inequitable care.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Blood transfusions are acceptable, but some may be reluctant to accept transfusion or blood products for fear of HIV/AIDS ( <emphasis>SIDA</emphasis>)<emphasis>.</emphasis> The belief that the body must be buried whole deters organ donation. Organ transplantation may not be acceptable because of the belief that <emphasis>mal aire</emphasis>, bad air, will enter the body and increase one’s risk for developing cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Dispel myths related to organ donation and organ transplantation. Eliciting the assistance of a priest may be helpful.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0027s0001ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 27.3</emphasis> Common cultural illnesses among Mexicans</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Empacho</emphasis></emphasis> (blocked intestines) may result from an incorrect balance of hot and cold foods causing a lump of food to stick in the gastrointestinal tract. Treatment includes massaging the stomach and back to dislodge the food bolus</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Mal de ojo</emphasis></emphasis> (evil eye) occurs when an older person looks at a younger person in an admiring fashion. Such eye contact can be voluntary or involuntary. Symptoms are numerous, including fever, anorexia and vomiting, or irritability. The spell can be broken if the person doing the admiring touches the person while admiring him or her. Allopathic health-care providers are usually unable to cure <emphasis>mal de ojo</emphasis>. Making a referral to a folk health-care provider is advisable</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Caida de mollera</emphasis></emphasis> (fallen fontanel) has numerous causes, which may include removing a nursing infant too harshly from the nipple or handling an infant too roughly. Symptoms vary from failure to thrive to irritability. The usual treatment is to hold the infant upside down by the feet. Assess for dehydration. A referral to a folk health-care provider is also recommended</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Susto</emphasis></emphasis> (magical fright or soul loss) is associated with epilepsy, tuberculosis, and other infectious diseases as well as “overwhelming feelings of loss.” Symptoms may be physical or psychological in nature and may also be consistent with depression. Gear treatment to the underlying causes, and treat physical and psychological symptoms</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0027s0001s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Mexicans use a number of folk health-care providers who are usually well known to the patient. See Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0027s0001ta04">27.4</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Health-care providers with the right qualities are well respected by Mexicans.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Important qualities include addressing the patient formally unless told to do otherwise, showing respect by asking questions, accepting the patient’s ideas, taking an interest in the entire family, and being well groomed. Promoting confianca in the caring relationship. Always ask permission, and explain the reason for the necessity of touching the patient during a physical examination.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0027s0001ta04">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 27.4</emphasis> Major Mexican folk health-care providers</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Curanderos</emphasis></emphasis> receive their gift from God or serve an apprenticeship. Some even prescribe over-the-counter medications. They usually treat traditional illnesses not caused by witchcraft</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Espiritistas</emphasis></emphasis> (spiritualists) treat conditions caused by witchcraft. Amulets and prayer are a large part of the treatment. Seeing an <emphasis>espiritista</emphasis> may carry a stigma among some Hispanics</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Yerberos</emphasis></emphasis> or <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Jerberos</emphasis></emphasis> use herbs, teas, and roots to prevent or treat illnesses. Patients usually purchase the herbs from a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">botanica</emphasis></emphasis>, a specialist herb shop that also sells religious figurines</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Sobadores</emphasis> treat muscle and joint problems using massage and manipulation; usually they do not have formal training</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Ask patients if they are using folk health-care providers and the reasons why they are using them, and have them fully disclose all treatments prescribed</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0027s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">27.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe the extensive name format for Mexican women. How would you address her? What is her legal name?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe eye contact protocol among traditional Mexicans.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>How do you assess for jaundice and cyanosis among dark-skinned Mexicans?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>List three common health conditions of Mexican that have a lifestyle component.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe Mexican folk healers and describe their treatment modalities.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the deciding factors for treating Mexicans with extraordinary illnesses?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe the “hot” and “cold” theory of illnesses among Mexicans.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Describe the “hot” and “cold” theory of food among Mexicans. If you are unfamiliar with foods in each category, what are your resources for finding out more?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Two herbs commonly used by Mexican Americans are <emphasis>azarcon</emphasis> and <emphasis>greta</emphasis>, which are used for colic and stomach conditions in children. What are the hazards of giving them to children?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is the folk illness <emphasis>ataque de nervios</emphasis>. What are its symptoms? How would you treat it?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0027s0003" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0027s0003bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib01">Benito-Gomez M, Williams KN, Mc Curdy A, Fletcher AC (2020) Autonomy-supportive parenting in adolescence: cultural variability in the contemporary United States. J Fam Theory Rev 12(1):7–26. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jftr.12362">https://doi.org/10.1111/jftr.12362</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jftr.12362">https://doi.org/10.1111/jftr.12362</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib02">Dame-Griff EC (2022) What do we mean when we say “Latinx?”: definitional power, the limits of inclusivity, and the (un/re)constitution of an identity category. J Int Intercult Commun 15(2):119. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/17513057.2021.1901957">https://doi.org/10.1080/17513057.2021.1901957</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/17513057.2021.1901957">https://doi.org/10.1080/17513057.2021.1901957</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib03">Gonzalez N, Méndez-Pounds J (2017) The impact of acculturation and cultural values on Hispanic immigrants’ parenting. Contemp Fam Ther 40(1):56–67. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-017-9428-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-017-9428-8</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-017-9428-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10591-017-9428-8</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib04">Hendy HM, Can SH, Heep H (2022) Machismo and caballerismo linked with perceived social discrimination and powerlessness in U. S. Latino men. J Cross-Cult Psychol 53(1):109–121. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00220221211054206">https://doi.org/10.1177/00220221211054206</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/00220221211054206">https://doi.org/10.1177/00220221211054206</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib05">Outright International (2024) Country overview: Mexico. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://outrightinternational.org"><emphasis role="RefSource">Outrightinternational.org</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://outrightinternational.org/our-work/americas/mexico"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://outrightinternational.org/our-work/americas/mexico</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib06">Planned Parenthood Global (2024) Mexico | Planned Parenthood Global. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nam02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%253A%252F%252Fwww.plannedparenthood.org%252Fabout-us%252Fplanned-parenthood-global%252Fwhere-we-work%252Fmexico&amp;data=05%7C02%7Czoucha%2540duq.edu%7C0a90abb2c61640c35f2308dc64cae697%7C12c44311cf844e4195c38df690b1eb61%7C0%7C0%7C638496069819022861%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%253D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=iF79UmQzc4NDG1689nvM3U5xeEhSQ%252F0pcu%252FUt8dKFqs%253D&amp;reserved=0"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.plannedparenthood.org/about-us/planned-parenthood-global/where-we-work/mexico</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib07">Romero Morales A, Consoli AJ (2020) Mexican/Mexican-American siblings: the impact of undocumented status on the family, the sibling relationship, and the self. J Latinx Psychol 8(2):112–126. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/lat0000133">https://doi.org/10.1037/lat0000133</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/lat0000133">https://doi.org/10.1037/lat0000133</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib08">Son D, Updegraff KA, Umaña-Taylor AJ (2022) Familism values and Mexican-origin adolescents’ disclosure and secrecy with fathers and mothers. J Fam Psychol 36(8):1296–1305. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/fam0000986">https://doi.org/10.1037/fam0000986</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/fam0000986">https://doi.org/10.1037/fam0000986</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=35324249">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib09">Updegraff KA, Umaña-Taylor AJ (2015) What can we learn from the study of Mexican-origin families in the United States? Fam Process 54(2):205–216. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/famp.12135">https://doi.org/10.1111/famp.12135</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/famp.12135">https://doi.org/10.1111/famp.12135</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=25675994">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4615713">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib10">Zoucha R, Zamarripa-Zoucha A (2020a) People of Mexican heritage. In: Purnell LD, Fenkl EA (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach. Springer, Cham, pp 613–636</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0027s0003bib11">Zoucha R, Zamarripa-Zoucha A (2020b) Health and health care in Mexico. In: Holtz C (ed) Global health care: issues and policies, 4th edn. Jones and Bartlett, Burlington, pp 599–610</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
