<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0025" label="25">
  <title>25. People of Jewish Heritage</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0025s0005">
    <title>25. People of Jewish Heritage</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2024</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">E. A. Fenkl, L. D. Purnell<emphasis role="CollaboratorDesignation"> (eds.)</emphasis></para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_25">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_25</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Teri Aronowitz</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0025">1</link></superscript> and </emphasis>
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Polly Zavadivker</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0025">2</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Tan Chingfen Graduate School of Nursing, University of Massachusetts, Boston, MA, USA</para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Department of History and Program in Jewish Studies, University of Delaware, Newark, DE, USA</para>
    <para role="Contact"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Teri Aronowitz</emphasis> (Corresponding author)<?lb ?><emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis><ulink url="mailto:terese.aronowitz@umassmed.edu">terese.aronowitz@umassmed.edu</ulink></para>
    <para role="Contact">
      <emphasis role="AuthorName">Polly Zavadivker</emphasis>
      <?lb ?>
      <emphasis role="ContactType">Email: </emphasis>
      <ulink url="mailto:pollyz@udel.edu">pollyz@udel.edu</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="keywords">Heritage, Communication, Family roles, Nutrition, Spirituality</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0025s0001">
    <title>25. People of Jewish Heritage</title>
    <sidebar id="ch0025s0001ad01">
      <title>The original version of the chapter has been revised. A correction to this chapter can be found at https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5_36</title>
      <para>No content</para>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0025s0002" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis>Jewish</emphasis> people, or Jews, are a group who share a common cultural, ethnic, and religious background. Individual Jewish communities are diasporic, or globally dispersed, and vary widely in their distinct practices and customs. This chapter focuses on the needs of religiously observant individuals and their families, or Orthodox Jews, but also provides an overview of widely shared forms of Jewish heritage.</para>
    <para role="Para">The central sacred scripture in Judaism is the Torah or the Five Books of Moses (Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy). In the Torah, Jews are referred to variously as <emphasis>Hebrews</emphasis>, <emphasis>Israelites</emphasis>, or the <emphasis>children of Israel</emphasis>. Jews regard Abraham and Sarah as their first ancestors. Abraham’s grandson, Jacob, was renamed by God as Israel (in Hebrew, “struggles with God”), and his 12 sons and their descendants became known as the children of Israel. The later terms <emphasis>Jew</emphasis> and Jewish were derived from the name Judah, one of Jacob’s sons.</para>
    <para role="Para">Distinct Jewish communities practice the religion along a wide continuum in the observance of Jewish law, or <emphasis role="bold">halakhah</emphasis>. There are three main branches of Judaism in the United States: liberal Reform, Conservative (a mix of tradition and reform), and Orthodoxy (observance of all Jewish law). Some individuals in Orthodox or ultra-Orthodox communities may choose to consult their rabbi before making important decisions regarding their lives and health, such as fertility treatment, abortion, and organ transplants. Religious observance and beliefs can be determining factors for Jews of various subgroups. For example, according to Jewish law, a child born to a Jewish mother is identified as being Jewish. However, a child born from the union of a Jewish father and a non-Jewish mother would be recognized as a Jew only by the Reform movement but not by the Conservative or Orthodox movements. Reform Judaism approves of intermarriage between Jews and Judaism, whereas the Conservative and Orthodox movements tend to oppose it.</para>
    <para role="Para">The population of Jews in the United States as of 2020 was estimated at 7.5 million people. The size of the American Jewish population grew rapidly between the mid-nineteenth and early twentieth centuries as a result of mass migration from Central and Eastern Europe. The greatest influx occurred between 1880 and 1920. Many Jews came from Russia and Eastern Europe, primarily to escape poverty, and because of legal inequality and <emphasis>pogroms</emphasis> (anti-Jewish riots or mob violence). Most families in America today are descendants of those Eastern European and Russian immigrants and are referred to as <emphasis role="bold">Ashkenazi</emphasis> Jews. <emphasis role="bold">Sephardic</emphasis> Jews, however, trace their origins to Spain, Portugal, the Mediterranean, and North Africa. <emphasis>Israelis</emphasis> are citizens of the state of Israel, which has a Jewish majority and Muslim and Christian Arab minority. Jews who trace their family roots to Middle Eastern countries, including Iraq, Yemen, and Iran are sometimes called <emphasis role="bold">Mizrahi</emphasis>, or “Eastern” Jews. <emphasis>Falasha</emphasis> are black Jews who originated in Ethiopia, most of whom emigrated to Israel starting in the mid-1980s.</para>
    <para role="Para">Throughout their history, Jews have placed a major emphasis on education and social justice through social action. American Jews support a wide range of political causes from liberal to conservative. They often have strong ties to the state of Israel and worry about the rise of anti-Jewish hostility (antisemitism). In general, this population is well educated, and a high percentage obtain higher education and pursue professional vocations.</para>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0001" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">English is the primary language of Jewish Americans. Although Hebrew is used for prayers and Torah study, it is generally not used for conversation. Many elderly Ashkenazi Jews who immigrated early in the twentieth century or who are first-generation Americans might speak <emphasis role="bold">Yiddish</emphasis>, a hybrid language with Hebrew and Germanic elements written in Hebrew characters. In many ultra-Orthodox communities, Yiddish is a living spoken and written language.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Many Yiddish terms have worked their way into English, such as <emphasis>kvetch</emphasis> (someone who complains a lot); <emphasis>chutzpah</emphasis> (audacity or nerve); <emphasis>bagel</emphasis> (round rolls with a hole in the middle); <emphasis>tush</emphasis>, <emphasis>tushie</emphasis>, or <emphasis>tuchus</emphasis> (buttocks); <emphasis>ghetto</emphasis> (a densely settled and often poor urban neighborhood); <emphasis>klutz</emphasis> (a clumsy person); <emphasis>shlep</emphasis> (drag or carry); <emphasis>kosher</emphasis> (legal or okay); and <emphasis>oy vey</emphasis> (oh my). For Orthodox Jews, other important terms in Yiddish include <emphasis>davenn</emphasis> (pray); <emphasis>Shabbos</emphasis> (Sabbath); <emphasis>kashrus</emphasis> (kosher food); and <emphasis>rebbe</emphasis> (rabbi).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common expressions include <emphasis>l’chaim</emphasis> (to life), which is said on joyful occasions and/or as a toast; <emphasis>shalom aleichem</emphasis> (peace be with you), a traditional salutation; <emphasis>mazel tov</emphasis> (congratulations); and <emphasis>shabbat shalom</emphasis> (a good and peaceful Sabbath), which is said from Friday evening at sunset until Saturday at sunset. Yiddish pronunciation differs slightly from Hebrew: for example, not Shabbat but Shabbos.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Hebrew is read from right to left, and books are opened accordingly, with the spine on the right.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Jews frequently use humor to communicate and as a coping mechanism. However, jokes that use mainstream stereotypes about Jews, such as implying that Jews are cheap, powerful, or pampered (e.g., Jewish American princess), are culturally offensive. <emphasis role="bold">Any jokes that refer to the Holocaust or concentration camps are also inappropriate.</emphasis> However, self-criticism through humor is acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Modesty, which involves humility, is a primary value, especially among Orthodox communities. It is seen in the Orthodox style of dress and culture.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Orthodox Jews observe the custom known as “guarding touch” ( <emphasis>shomer negiyeh</emphasis>), by restricting touch of persons of the opposite sex to their children, spouses, and other close family members. Some Orthodox men and women may refuse to shake hands or have other physical contact with adults of the opposite sex, <emphasis role="bold">and their failure to do so when one’s hand is extended should not be interpreted as a sign of rudeness.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some Orthodox men and women may have limited social contact with persons of the opposite sex, including conversation and eye contact. <emphasis role="bold">In such cases, Orthodox men and women should only be touched when providing direct care. “Therapeutic touch” is not appropriate.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While most Jews live for today and plan for and worry about tomorrow, history is very important in Judaism, especially of the Holocaust. They are warned to “never forget,” lest history be repeated. Therefore, their time orientation is simultaneously to the past, the present, and the future.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Jewish format for names follows the Western tradition. The given name comes first and is followed by the family surname. Only the given name is used with friends and in informal situations. <emphasis role="bold">In more formal situations, the surname is preceded by the appropriate title of Mr., Miss, Ms., Mrs., Rabbi, or Dr. In Orthodox circles, children are not referred to by their names until after the</emphasis><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">bris</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">or</emphasis><emphasis><emphasis role="bold">brit milah</emphasis></emphasis><emphasis role="bold">(circumcision) (bris and brit milah are also glossary terms).</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0002" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The family is the core of society, and the needs of all family members are respected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Conservative and Reform Jews typically send school-age children to Hebrew school at least two afternoons a week after public school throughout the school year. Most Orthodox families send their children to private Jewish schools.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Children play an active role in holiday celebrations and services. Respecting and honoring one’s parents is one of the Ten Commandments. Children are expected to show gratitude to their parents for giving them the gift of life.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In Judaism, the age of majority is 13 years for a boy and 12 for a girl, at which age children are deemed capable of differentiating right from wrong and of committing themselves to performing the commandments. Recognition of adulthood occurs during a religious ceremony called a <emphasis>bar</emphasis> or <emphasis>bat mitzvah</emphasis> (son or daughter of the commandment). This rite of passage is usually accompanied by a celebration.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The goal of the Orthodox family is to observe and raise children to observe <emphasis>halakhah</emphasis> (Code of Jewish Law), which emphasizes maintaining health, promoting education, and helping others.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Women who follow the Jewish laws of family purity must physically separate themselves from all men during their menstrual periods and for 7 days after, at which time they visit <emphasis>mikveh</emphasis>, a ritual bath. No man may touch a woman or sit where she sat until she has been to the <emphasis>mikveh</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Older people receive respect, especially for the wisdom they must share. Honoring one’s parents is a lifelong endeavor; one is obligated to maintain their dignity by feeding, clothing, and sheltering them, even if they experience senility.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Bible, as interpreted by Orthodox Jews, prohibits intercourse between men but says nothing about sex between women. Some of the objections to gay and lesbian lifestyles include the inability of these unions to fulfill the commandment of procreation and the possibility that acting on the recognition of one’s homosexuality could ruin a marriage. The liberal movements within Judaism support legal and social equality for lesbians and gays, and welcome them as members of the community. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to others.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0003" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Jews who observe the Sabbath will not work from Friday evening to Saturday evening. The definition of “work” in Jewish law includes driving and using phones and many other forms of technology.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">They may work on the Sabbath in critical jobs such as health care when needed. They may work on Sundays.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Jewish staff should be allowed to request off the major Jewish holidays. <emphasis role="bold">Be sensitive to the needs of Jewish staff and recognize the holiness of the Sabbath, taking into account current US Equal Employment Opportunity Commission laws.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Judaism’s beliefs are consistent with the values that American society places on the individual and family. For some newer Jewish immigrants, especially the elderly, English may pose a challenge. <emphasis role="bold">Speak clearly and ask for clarification of understanding from those for whom English is a second language.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Jews believe in autonomy and willingly take leadership positions in the workforce when the need arises.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0004" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Skin coloring for Ashkenazi Jews ranges from fair skin and blonde or red hair to darker skin and brunette hair. Sephardic Jews have slightly darker skin tones and hair coloring, similar to people from the Mediterranean area. There also are Jewish groups throughout Africa who are black, most notably the <emphasis>Falasha</emphasis> from Ethiopia.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Genetic risk factors vary based on whether the family emigrated from Ashkenazi or Sephardic areas. There is a greater incidence of some genetic disorders among Ashkenazi individuals. Most of these disorders are autosomal recessive, meaning that both parents carry the affected gene.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0025s0002ta01">25.1</link></emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Jews in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Ashkenazi Jews have a higher rate of side effects with clozapine; 20% develop agranulocytosis.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Test for agranulocytosis when Jewish patients are prescribed clozapine.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0025s0002ta01">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 25.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Jews</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Tay-Sachs disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Gaucher’s disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Canavan’s disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Familial dysautonomia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Torsion dystonia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Niemann–Pick disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Bloom syndrome</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Fanconi’s anemia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Mucolipidosis IV</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Werdnig–Hoffmann disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Kaposi sarcoma</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Phenylketonuria</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Ataxia-telangiectasia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Metachromatic leukodystrophy</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Myopia</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Polycythemia vera</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Breast cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Ovarian cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Inflammatory bowel disease</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Colorectal cancer</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0005" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Any substance or act that harms the body is not allowed. This includes smoking, suicide, illegal medications, and permanent tattooing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Most Jews are health-conscious and practice preventive health care, with routine physical, dental, and vision screening. This is also a well-immunized population. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage these positive health-promotion and disease-prevention practices.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0006" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For those who follow the dietary laws, much attention is given to the slaughter, preparation, and consumption of food.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Perhaps the food identified as culturally “Jewish” that receives the most attention is chicken soup, which has frequently been referred to as “Jewish penicillin” and is often served with <emphasis>knaidle</emphasis> balls in it (dumplings made of <emphasis>matzoh</emphasis> meal). Although it has no intrinsic meaning or religious value, it is a staple in religious homes, especially on Friday evenings to usher in the Sabbath and during times of illness. It is frequently associated with a mother’s warmth and love.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Common Ashkenazi foods include <emphasis>gefilte</emphasis> fish (ground freshwater fish molded into oblong balls and served cold with horseradish); <emphasis>challah</emphasis> (braided white bread); <emphasis>kugel</emphasis> (noodle pudding); blintzes (crepes filled with sweet cottage cheese); chopped liver (served cold); <emphasis>hamentashen</emphasis> (a triangular pastry with different types of filling); and lox and bagel sandwiches. Lox is cold smoked salmon, served with cream cheese and salad vegetables, on a bagel.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Religious laws regarding permissible foods are referred to as <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kashrut</emphasis></emphasis>. The term <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kosher</emphasis></emphasis> means “fit to eat.” Foods are divided into those that are considered <emphasis>kosher</emphasis> (permitted or clean) and those considered <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">treyf</emphasis></emphasis> (forbidden or unclean). A permitted animal may be rendered <emphasis>treyf</emphasis> if it is not slaughtered, cooked, or served properly. All blood is drained from the animal before eating it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Milk and meat may not be mixed together in cooking, serving, or eating. To avoid mixing foods, utensils used to prepare foods and the plates used to serve them are separated, requiring two sets of dishes, pots, and utensils: one set for milk products and the other for meat. Because glass is not absorbent, it can be used for either meat or milk products, although religious households still usually have two sets. Therefore, cheeseburgers, lasagna made with meat, and grated cheese on meatballs and spaghetti are unacceptable. Milk cannot be used in coffee if served with a meat meal. Non-dairy creamers can be used instead, as long as they do not contain sodium caseinate, which is derived from milk.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some foods are <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">pareve</emphasis></emphasis> (neutral) and may be used with either dairy or meat dishes. These include fish, eggs, anything grown in the soil (vegetables, fruits, coffee, sugar, and spices), and some chemically produced goods.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mammals are considered kosher if they meet the other requirements for their slaughter and consumption and have split (cloven) hooves and chew their cud. These animals include buffalo, cattle, goats, deer, and sheep. The pig is an example of an animal that does not meet these criteria. Although liberal Jews decide for themselves which dietary laws they will follow, many still avoid pork and pork products out of a sense of tradition and symbolism.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Serving pork products to a Jewish patient, unless specifically requested, is insensitive.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Poultry is acceptable as well as fish if it has both fins and scales. Nothing that crawls on its belly is allowed, including shellfish, tortoises, and frogs.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">People who keep kosher will buy kosher-certified products, including meats and cheeses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A <emphasis role="bold">U</emphasis> with a circle around it is the seal of the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America and is used on food products to indicate that they are kosher. A circled K and other symbols may also be found on the packaging to indicate that a product is kosher. <emphasis role="bold">Do not bring food into a patient’s home without knowing whether they adhere to kosher standards. If the patient keeps a kosher home, do not use any cooking items, dishes, or silverware without knowing which are used for meat and which are used for dairy products.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Health-care providers must fully understand the dietary laws so they do not offend the patient and can plan medication times accordingly.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Care must be taken in serving cheese to ensure that no animal substances are served at the same time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Breads and cakes made with lard are <emphasis>treyf</emphasis>, and breads made with milk or milk by-products (for example, casein) cannot be served with meat meals.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Eggs from non-kosher birds, milk from non-kosher animals, and oil from non-kosher fish are not permitted.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Butter substitutes are used with meat meals. Honey is allowed because it is produced from the nectar of flowers.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Kosher meals are available in most hospitals. They arrive on paper plates and with sealed plastic utensils. For in-patient facilities that do not have readily available kosher capabilities, frozen meals can be ordered online from a number of places.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Do not unwrap the utensils or change the foodstuffs to another serving dish. If health-care providers have difficulty locating a supplier of kosher foods, they should contact a local rabbi. Determining a patient’s dietary preferences and practices regarding dietary laws should be done during the admission assessment. Frozen kosher meals can be ordered online if the health-care facility does not have a kosher kitchen.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Religious Jews wash their hands and say a blessing before eating bread. <emphasis role="bold">Make facilities for patients to wash their hands before eating.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">During the week of Passover, no bread or product with yeast may be eaten. <emphasis>Matzoh</emphasis> (unleavened bread) is eaten instead. Any product that is fermented or that can cause fermentation (souring) may not be eaten. Rather than attend synagogue, the Jewish house of worship, the family conducts the service, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">seder</emphasis></emphasis>, around the dinner table during the first two nights and incorporates dinner into a service that includes all participants and retells the story of Moses and the exodus from Egypt.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Jewish calendar has several fast days. The most widely observed fast falls on the holiest day of the year, <emphasis>Yom Kippur</emphasis> (Day of Atonement). Jews abstain from food and drink as they pray to God for forgiveness for the sins they have committed during the past year. They eat an early dinner on the evening the holiday begins and then fast until after sunset the following day.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Ill people, the elderly, the young, pregnant, and nursing women, and the physically incapacitated are absolved from fasting and may need to be reminded of this exception to Jewish law.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">If concerns arise about fasting, a consultation with the patient’s rabbi may be necessary.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Schedule appointments and treatment to avoid religious days.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0007" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Couples who are unable to conceive should try all possible means to have children, including infertility counseling and interventions and egg and sperm donation. Orthodox opinion is virtually unanimous in prohibiting artificial insemination when the semen donor is not the woman’s husband. When all-natural attempts have been made, adoption may be pursued.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Unless pregnancy jeopardizes the life or health of the mother, contraception is not looked on favorably among the ultra-Orthodox. Condom use is supported, especially when unprotected sexual intercourse poses a medical risk to either spouse.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">To the Orthodox, barrier techniques are not acceptable because they interfere with the full mobility of the sperm in its natural course. The birth control pill does not result in any permanent sterilization nor does it prevent semen from traveling its normal route. Therefore, the use of this method is the least objectionable to most branches of Judaism. Sterilization implies permanence, and Orthodox Jews probably oppose this practice, unless the life of the mother is in danger. <emphasis role="bold">Reform Judaism allows free choice in fertility control.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The fetus is not considered a living soul or person until it has been born. Birth is determined when the head or “greater part” is born. If the physical or mental health of a pregnant woman is endangered by the fetus, all branches of Judaism consider the fetus an aggressor and require an abortion. Abortion in cases where the mother’s health is not compromised is not permitted by the Orthodox branch because the fetus is regarded as part of the mother’s body according to Jewish law and one must not do harm to one’s body. The liberal branches of Judaism hold that a woman maintains control over her own body and that it is up to her whether to abort a fetus.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A Hasidic husband may not touch his wife during labor and may choose not to attend the delivery because he is not permitted to view his wife’s genitals. These behaviors should never be interpreted as insensitivity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">During the delivery of a baby in an ultra-Orthodox family, initiate the following interventions: give the mother a hospital gown that covers her in the front and back to the greatest extent possible. Provide a surgical cap so that her head remains covered (because the hair is considered a private part of her body). Give the father the opportunity to leave during procedures and during the birth or, if he chooses to stay, drape the mother so that the husband may sit by his wife without viewing her perineum, including by way of mirrors or other means.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Pain medication during delivery is acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">For male infants, circumcision ( <emphasis>bris</emphasis>), which is both a medical procedure and a religious rite, is performed on the eighth day of life by a <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">mohel</emphasis></emphasis>, an individual trained in the circumcision procedure, asepsis, and the religious ceremony. Although a rabbi is not necessary, it is also possible to have the procedure completed by a physician with a rabbi present to say the blessings.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Attending a <emphasis>bris</emphasis> is the only mitzvah for which religious Jews may violate the Sabbath so that it can be completed at the proper time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Provide a space for a family celebration if the circumcision is done in the hospital.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0008" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Traditional Judaism believes in an afterlife where the soul continues to flourish, although many dispute this interpretation. A dying person is considered a living person in all respects.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Active euthanasia is forbidden for religious Jews. Passive euthanasia may be allowed depending on its interpretation. Nothing may be used or initiated that prevents a person from dying naturally or that prolongs the dying process. <emphasis role="bold">However, anything that artificially prevents death (cardiopulmonary resuscitation, ventilators, and so forth) may possibly be withheld, depending on the wishes of the patient and his or her religious views. The dying person should not be left alone.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Taking one’s own life is prohibited. To the ultra-religious, suicide removes all possibility of repentance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Any Jew may ask God’s forgiveness for his or her sins; no confessor is needed. Some Jews feel solace in saying the <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">Sh’ma</emphasis></emphasis> in Hebrew or English. This prayer confirms one’s belief in one God. At the time of death, the nearest relative can gently close the eyes and mouth, and the face is covered with a sheet.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The body is treated with respect and revered for the function it once filled. <emphasis role="bold">Ask the closest relative of the deceased specifically about the family’s preferred practices to follow after death.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Autopsy is usually not permitted among religious Jews because it results in desecration of the body, and it is important that the body be interred whole. Allowing an autopsy might also delay the burial, something that is not recommended. Conversely, autopsy is allowed if its results would save the life of another patient who is immediately at hand. Many branches of Judaism currently allow an autopsy if (a) it is required by law; (b) the deceased person has willed it; or (c) it saves the life of another, especially an offspring. <emphasis role="bold">Explain legal requirements for an autopsy.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Cremation is prohibited because it unnaturally speeds the disposal of the dead body. Embalming is prohibited because it preserves the dead. However, in circumstances when the funeral must be delayed, some embalming may be approved. Cosmetic restoration for the funeral is discouraged.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Funerals and burials usually occur within 24–48 h after the death. The funeral service is directed at honoring the departed by only speaking well of him or her. It is not customary to have flowers either at the funeral or at the cemetery. The casket should be made of wood with no ornamentation. The body may be wrapped only in a shroud to ensure that the body and casket decay at the same rate. There is no wake or viewing. The prayer said for the dead, <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kaddish</emphasis></emphasis>, is usually not said alone.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In cases where the body cannot be removed to a funeral home, many Jewish communities have volunteers that care for the dead (Kaevra Kodusha) who are contacted and practice the custom of watching the body around the clock and prepare the body for burial by washing and wrapping in linen. This work is considered the holiest of all mitzvahs (good deeds).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After the funeral, mourners are welcomed at the home of the closest relative. Outside the front door is water to wash one’s hands before entering, which is symbolic of cleansing the impurities associated with contact with the dead. The water is not passed from person to person, just as it is hoped that the tragedy is not passed. At the home, a meal is served to all the guests. This “meal of condolence” or “meal of consolation” is traditionally provided by the neighbors and friends.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para"><emphasis>Shiva</emphasis> (Hebrew for “seven”) is the 7-day period that begins with the burial. <emphasis>Shiva</emphasis> helps the surviving individuals face the actuality of the death of the loved one. During this period when the mourners are “sitting <emphasis>shiva</emphasis>,” they do not work. When health-care providers are the ones experiencing the loss, it is important for supervisors to understand the mourning customs. In some homes, mirrors are covered to decrease the focus on one’s appearance; no activity is permitted to divert attention from thinking about the deceased. Evening and morning services may be conducted in the closest relative’s home. Condolence calls and the giving of consolation are appropriate.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Crying, anger, and talking about the deceased person’s life are acceptable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A common sign of grief is the tearing of the garment that one is wearing before the funeral service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In liberal congregations, a black ribbon with a tear in it is a symbolic representation of mourning. During <emphasis>shiva</emphasis>, the mourner sets the tone and initiates the conversation. Because there are such discrete periods of mourning and an emphasis on the needs of the living, Jewish tradition holds that it is wrong to mourn more than 30 days for a relative and for more than 1 year for parents.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Mourning is not required for a fetus that is miscarried or stillborn. This is also true of any premature infant who dies within 30 days of birth. However, parents are required to mourn for full-term infants who die at birth or shortly thereafter.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Within Orthodoxy, when a limb is amputated before death, the amputated limb and blood-soaked clothing are buried in the person’s future gravesite because the blood and limb were part of the person. No mourning rites are required. <emphasis role="bold">In the case of an amputation, assist with arrangement for the burial of the body part as needed.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0009" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Jewish scripture, or the Hebrew Bible, includes 24 books in 3 sections (Torah, Prophets, and Writings). This body of scripture is what Christians refer to as the Old Testament. Judaism is a monotheistic faith that believes in one God as the creator of the universe. No physical qualities are attributed to God; making and praying to statues or graven images are forbidden.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The spiritual leader is the rabbi (teacher). He (or she, in liberal branches) is the interpreter of Jewish law. All Jews pray directly to God. They do not need the rabbi to intercede, to hear confession, or to grant atonement. However, ultra-Orthodox groups venerate their most important rabbis as spiritual intercessors to God.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Some of the major principles that guide Judaic bioethics are shown in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0025s0002ta02">25.2</link></emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The practice of Judaism spans a wide spectrum. Although there is only one religion, there are three main branches or denominations of Judaism in the United States. The Orthodox are the most traditional. They adhere most strictly to the <emphasis>halakhah</emphasis> and try to follow as many of the laws as possible while also taking part in American society. They observe the Sabbath by abstaining from work, spending money, and driving, and many attend synagogue on Friday evening and Saturday morning. Orthodox Jews observe the Jewish dietary laws at home and when eating out; men always wear a yarmulke or kippah (head covering) in reverence to God. Women wear long sleeves and modest dress and cover their hair with scarves, hats, or wigs. In many Orthodox synagogues, the services are conducted primarily in Hebrew, and men and women sit separately.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Ultra-Orthodox men wear a special garment with strings under their shirts every day ( <emphasis>tzitzit</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A <emphasis>mezuzah</emphasis> is a small container with a small piece of scripture inside. Many Jews will affix a mezuzah to all the doorways of their home. Some Jews wear a mezuzah as a necklace. Other religious symbols include the Star of David, a six-pointed star that has been a symbol of the Jewish community, and the <emphasis>menorah</emphasis> (candelabrum).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">While some Conservative Jews observe most of the <emphasis>halakhah</emphasis>, they do make concessions to modern society. Many drive to the synagogue on the Sabbath, and men and women sit together during services. Many keep a kosher home, but they may or may not follow all of the dietary laws outside the home. Women can be ordained as rabbis and unlike in Orthodox Judaism, they are counted in a <emphasis>minyan</emphasis>, the minimum number of 10 people that is required for a prayer quorum. While head coverings are required in the Conservative synagogue, they are optional outside of that environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The liberal or progressive movement is called Reform. Reform Jews claim that only the moral laws of the <emphasis role="bold">Torah</emphasis> are binding. They observe fewer rituals and laws, although they frequently have a mezuzah on the doorpost of their homes, celebrate the holidays, have their children circumcised, and have an ethnic and cultural identity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">Reform Jews may or may not follow the Jewish dietary laws, but they may have specific unacceptable foods (for example, pork or shellfish), which they abstain from eating.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Of the many small groups of Orthodox Jews, <emphasis role="bold">Hasidic</emphasis> (sometimes spelled <emphasis role="bold">Chasidic</emphasis>) Jews are perhaps the most recognizable. They usually live, work, and study within close-knit urban communities. Men typically have full beards, uncut hair around the ears ( <emphasis>payos</emphasis>), black hats or fur <emphasis><emphasis role="bold">streimels</emphasis></emphasis>, dark clothing, and no exposed extremities.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Like other Orthodox women, Hasidic women dress modestly; in addition, married women will cover their hair completely with scarves, wigs, and sometimes a hat.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">A relatively new denomination, <emphasis role="bold">Reconstructionism</emphasis>, is a mosaic of the three main branches. It views Judaism as an evolving religion of the Jewish people and seeks to adapt Jewish beliefs and practices to the needs of the contemporary world.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Jewish house of prayer is called a synagogue, temple, or <emphasis>shul</emphasis>. Jews may pray alone, in small groups, or as part of a minyan (ten Jews over the age of 13 who have had their bar/bat mitzvah). Many Jews will wear a large prayer shawl ( <emphasis>tallit</emphasis>) during prayer. Orthodox Jews pray three times a day: morning, late afternoon, and evening. They wash their hands and say a prayer on awakening in the morning and before meals. Men will wrap <emphasis>tefillin</emphasis> (phylacteries) around their arms during morning prayers. Religious patients in hospitals may want their prayer items ( <emphasis>yarmulke</emphasis> or <emphasis>kippah</emphasis>, <emphasis>tallit</emphasis>, <emphasis>tefillin</emphasis>) and may request a minyan. <emphasis role="bold">Disregard hospital policies regarding the number of visitors in the sick person’s room in such instances.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The Sabbath begins 18 min before sunset on Friday. During this time, religious Jews do no manner of work, including answering the telephone, operating any electrical appliance, driving, or operating a call bell from a hospital bed. If an Orthodox patient’s condition is not life-threatening, medical and surgical procedures should not be performed on the Sabbath or holy days. A gravely ill person and the work of those who need to save him or her are exempted from following the commandments regarding the Sabbath. <emphasis role="bold">Because Orthodox Jews cannot summon an elevator, patient care facilities with a Jewish population should consider installing a “Sabbath elevator” that automatically stops on every floor.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef"><link linkend="ch0025s0002ta03">25.3</link></emphasis> provides a list of Jewish holidays for the years from 2024 to 2028.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table id="ch0025s0002ta02">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 25.2</emphasis> Principles of Judaic bioethics</title>
        <tgroup cols="1">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Humanity’s purpose on earth is to live according to certain God-given guidelines, the highest of which are to sanctify and repair all aspects of life on earth. In addition, Jews must follow God’s laws as part of a covenant</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Life possesses infinite value. The obligation to preserve and save human life (known as <emphasis>pikuakh nefesh</emphasis>) is the guiding principle for Jewish law and bioethics. If a patient’s life is in danger, all medical treatment that can potentially avert the threat to life must be carried out, overriding all other religious considerations</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• All human beings are created equal and in God’s image</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• Our lives are not our own exclusive private possessions but “on loan” from the Creator and must be treated with dignity and care for that reason. Accordingly, Judaism accords great importance to medicine and medical treatment</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• The first five books of the Hebrew Bible, also known as the Five Books of Moses, make up the Torah. They are handwritten in Hebrew on parchment scrolls, kept in the “Holy Ark” within each synagogue under an “eternal light,” and read aloud in the community on the Sabbath, holidays, and other occasions. The Torah’s commandments instruct Jews how they should live their lives in relation to other human beings and to God</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">• The commandments stated in the Torah and the oral law that was derived from the biblical commands are the basis of all codes of Jewish law. These commandments demand certain actions and ethical commitments. Observant Jews believe that the commandments reflect the will of God, and it is their duty to carry them out to fulfill their covenant with God</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table id="ch0025s0002ta03">
        <title><emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 25.3</emphasis> Jewish holidays: 2024–2028</title>
        <tgroup cols="6">
          <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
          <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
          <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
          <colspec colname="c6" colnum="6"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry namest="c1" nameend="c6">
                <para role="SimplePara">Jewish holidays begin at sundown the evening before the date recorded on this type of calendar; holidays end at sundown on the date shown</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Holiday</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2024</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2025</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2026</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2027</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">2028</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Rosh Hashanah</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/2–4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/22–24</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/11–13</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/1–3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/20–22</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Yom Kippur</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/11–12</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/1–2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/20–21</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/10–11</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/29–30</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Sukkot</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/16–18</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/6–8</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">9/24–26</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/15–17</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">10/4–6</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Chanukah</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12/25–1/2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12/14–22</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12/4–12</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12/24–31</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">12/12–19</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Passover</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4/22–30</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4/12–20</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4/1–9</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4/21–29</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">4/10–18</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">Shavuot</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6/11–13</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6/1–3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">5/21–23</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">6/10–12</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para role="SimplePara">5/30–6/1</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para role="SimplePara">A calendar of all Jewish holidays with start and end times can be found at <emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="https://www.hebcal.com/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.hebcal.com/</emphasis></ulink></emphasis></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0010" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">All denominations recognize that religious requirements may be laid aside if a life is at stake or if an individual has a life-threatening illness. <emphasis role="bold">Hospice and palliative care are fully consonant with Jewish beliefs.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">In ultra-Orthodox denominations of Judaism, taking medication on the Sabbath that is not necessary to preserve life may be viewed as “work” and is unacceptable. This belief may result in some people with conditions such as asthma not recognizing the severity of their condition; they may also be unaware of the laws that allow them to take their necessary medications. <emphasis role="bold">Teach patients about the potential life-threatening sequelae of their condition as well as the exceptions to Jewish law that permits them to take their medications.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The verbalization of pain is acceptable and common. Individuals want to know the reason for the pain, which they consider just as important as obtaining relief from pain.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The sick role for Jews is highly individualized and may vary among individuals according to the severity of symptoms.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Judaism opposes discrimination against people with physical, mental, and developmental conditions. The maintenance of one’s mental health is considered just as important as the maintenance of one’s physical health. Mental incapacity has always been recognized as grounds for exemption from all obligations under Jewish law.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Jewish law considers organ transplants from four perspectives: those of the recipient, the living donor, the cadaver donor, and the dying donor. Because life is sacred, if the recipient’s life can be prolonged without considerable risk, then transplant is ordained. For a living donor to be approved, the risk to the life of the donor must be considered. One is not obligated to donate a bodily part unless the risk is small. Examples include kidney and bone marrow donations. Organ donation at the time of death is acceptable if it saves a person’s life. <emphasis role="bold">Conservative</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Reform</emphasis> Judaism approve using the flat EEG as the determination of death so that organs, such as the heart, can be viable for transplant. Burial may be delayed if organ harvesting is the cause of the delay. <emphasis role="bold">Assist patients in finding a rabbi if they desire to consult one when making a decision regarding organ donation or transplant.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">The use of a cadaver for transplant is usually approved if it is to save a life. No one may derive economic benefit from the corpse. Use of skin for burns is also acceptable, although no agreement has been reached on the use of cadaver corneas.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="ch0025s0002s0011" role="Heading">
      <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Physicians are held in high regard. Although physicians must do everything in their power to prolong life, they are prohibited from initiating measures that prolong the act of dying.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Only supportive care is required while the patient is dying and includes such care as food and water, good nursing care, and maximal psychosocial support.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis role="bold">More traditional Orthodox patients prefer that care be delivered by a same-sex health-care provider.</emphasis>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0025s0003" role="Heading">
    <title><emphasis role="HeadingNumber">25.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is meant by<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">halakhah</emphasis></emphasis> and what does it emphasize?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Name and describe at least three genetic conditions common among Jews.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is meant by<emphasis><emphasis role="bold">kashrut</emphasis></emphasis>? Distinguish between kosher and <emphasis>treyf.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are the tenets of the four broad branches of Judaism? What are the primary differences among them?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>When does Sabbath begin and end?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Under what conditions are observant Jews able to work?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What are some of the major principles that guide Judaic bioethics?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>What is meant by <emphasis>shiva</emphasis>? Describe its practices.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>An orthodox Jewish couple is expecting their first child. The expectant father wants to be in the delivery room with his wife. What preparations do you need to make for this to occur?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>The hospital where you work does not have a kosher kitchen. Where might you purchase kosher meals? Once you have a kosher meal, how do you handle the food?</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0025s0004" role="bibliography">
    <title>Bibliography</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0025s0004bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib01">Ben Ben-Tzion Halevi HY, Lavine JB (2008) The thirteen principles of Jewish medical ethics. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.science.co.il/jewish-studies/articles/Medical-ethics.php"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.science.co.il/jewish-studies/articles/Medical-ethics.php</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib02">Death and mourning: Jewish customs, traditions, and practices (2016) <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.shiva.com/learning-center/death-and-mourning/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.shiva.com/learning-center/death-and-mourning/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib03">Guidelines for health care providers interacting with Jewish patients and their families (2002). <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.advocatehealth.com/assets/documents/faith/cgjewish.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.advocatehealth.com/assets/documents/faith/cgjewish.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib04">Jewish perspectives on the birthing experience (2016) <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.mikvah.org/article/jewish_perspectives_on_the_birthing_experience"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.mikvah.org/article/jewish_perspectives_on_the_birthing_experience</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib05">National Foundation for Jewish Genetic Diseases (2012) <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.mazornet.com/genetics/"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.mazornet.com/genetics/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib06">Pew Research Center (2021) Jewish Americans in 2021. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2021/05/11/jewish-americans-in-2020/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.pewresearch.org/religion/2021/05/11/jewish-americans-in-2020/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib07">Satlow M (2006) Creating Judaism: history, tradition, practice. Columbia University Press, New York</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib08">Selekman J, Zavadivker P (2020) People of Jewish heritage. In: Fenkel E, Purnell L (eds) Textbook for transcultural health care: a population approach. Cultural competence in nursing care, 5th edn. Springer, Cham</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0025s0004bib09">U. S. Equal Opportunity Commission (2016) <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.eeoc.gov/"><emphasis role="RefSource">www.eeoc.gov/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
