<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<preface id="pr0002"><title>Handbook for Culturally Competent Care</title><para>Editors</para><para>Eric A. Fenkl</para><para>and</para><para>Larry D. Purnell</para><para>Second Edition 2024</para><figure id="pr0002s0001fg01" role="Figure"><title/><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="Prefacef01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure><para>Editors</para><para>Eric A. Fenkl</para><para role="AffiliationText">Nicole Wertheim College of Nursing and Health Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, FL, USA</para><para>Larry D. Purnell</para><para role="AffiliationText">College of Health and Nursing Sciences, Excelsior University, Albany, NY, USA</para><para role="CopyrightPageISBNs">ISBN 978-3-031-70491-8<?lb ?>e-ISBN 978-3-031-70492-5</para><para><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-70492-5</ulink></para><para>© The Editor(s) (if applicable) and The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2019, 2024</para><para>corrected publication</para><para>2024</para><para>This work is subject to copyright. All rights are solely and exclusively licensed by the Publisher, whether the whole or part of the material is concerned, specifically the rights of translation, reprinting, reuse of illustrations, recitation, broadcasting, reproduction on microfilms or in any other physical way, and transmission or information storage and retrieval, electronic adaptation, computer software, or by similar or dissimilar methodology now known or hereafter developed.</para><para>The use of general descriptive names, registered names, trademarks, service marks, etc. in this publication does not imply, even in the absence of a specific statement, that such names are exempt from the relevant protective laws and regulations and therefore free for general use.</para><para>The publisher, the authors and the editors are safe to assume that the advice and information in this book are believed to be true and accurate at the date of publication. Neither the publisher nor the authors or the editors give a warranty, expressed or implied, with respect to the material contained herein or for any errors or omissions that may have been made. The publisher remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</para><para role="SimplePara">This Springer imprint is published by the registered company Springer Nature Switzerland AG</para><para role="SimplePara">The registered company address is: Gewerbestrasse 11, 6330 Cham, Switzerland</para><para>Preface</para><para role="Para">The usefulness of the Purnell Model for Cultural Competence, its organizing framework, and comprehensive assessment guide has been established globally. They are being used worldwide for individual and family health-care assessment and planning and intervention in health promotion and wellness; illness, disease, and injury prevention; and health maintenance and restoration.</para><para role="Para">In the second edition of this handbook, chapters from the first edition were updated to reflect the most current information available on each cultural heritage. Many of the chapters were revised and updated by new corresponding authors, providing a fresh perspective of the chapter content. The chapter on “People of Hindu Heritage” was expanded to specifically include people who identify as Sikh, thus resulting in a new chapter title: “People of Hindu and Sikh Heritage.” The second edition also includes two completely new chapters not previously published: “People of Jamaican Heritage” and “People of Ukrainian Heritage.” Both of which are beneficial to readers seeking culturally competent information for those two groups. Additionally, three consolidated chapters from the more comprehensive <emphasis>Textbook for Transcultural Health Care: A Population Approach</emphasis> were added to the handbook including “People of Greek Heritage,” “People of Italian Heritage,” and “People of Thai Heritage.”</para><para role="Para">The reader will find it helpful that the second edition is organized in the same manner as the first edition. For this second edition, as in the first edition, the aggregate data, a research principle, in culturally specific chapters is meant as a guide. The content may not apply to every individual in that culture depending on individual preferences, acculturation, and assimilation into the dominant culture. The variant cultural characteristics on the model help prevent stereotyping, assuring patients are individuals within their culture.</para><para role="Para">As in the first edition, each chapter is organized by the model’s 12 domains of culturally competent care and provides key approaches and interventions highlighted in bold type, providing a quick reference for working with each individual. Thus, recommended approaches and interventions may need to be adapted based on patient’s and family’s personal perspectives and circumstances. The health-care provider must make a concerted effort to set aside any ingrained personal biases and prejudices.</para><para role="Para">With increased worldwide migration, health-care providers are caring for patients whose cultures are foreign to them, making care more complex. Given the worldwide diversity, and the diversity within cultural groups, it is impossible to include the beliefs and practices of all cultures and subcultures.</para><para role="Para">Specific criteria are used for identifying the groups represented in the guide and were selected based on a variety of the following criteria:</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet"><listitem><para role="Para">The group has a large population in North America, such as people of African American, Appalachian, Cuban, Jamaican, Jewish, and Mexican heritages.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The group is relatively new in its migration status, such as people of Arab, Bosnian, Hmong, Somali, Ukrainian, and Vietnamese heritages.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The group is widely dispersed throughout the world, such as people of Chinese, Cuban, Greek, Filipino, Hindu, Iranian, Italian, Puerto Rican, and Thai heritages.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The group has little written about it in the health-care literature, such as people of Brazilian, Haitian, Japanese, Korean, Russian, Sikh, and Turkish heritages.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para">The group was of particular interest to the readers, such as people from Amish, Hmong, and Somali heritages.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para>Eric A. Fenkl</para><para>Larry D. Purnell</para><para>Miami, FL, USA</para><para>Albany, NY, USA</para><para>Introduction</para><para role="Para">Caring for culturally diverse patients and families has become commonplace throughout most of North America and worldwide. Geographical areas that previously were largely homogenous, with the exception of possibly one or two culturally diverse groups, no longer exist. This multicultural mosaic being created is adding richness to our communities and societies at large.</para><para role="Para">Many cultural groups fall into the category of vulnerable populations with increased health and health-care disparities. Even when disparities are not a concern, patient satisfaction may be of concern. If we are to decrease health and health-care disparities and increase patient satisfaction, more attention must be paid to cultural values, beliefs, and practices, which include spirituality and complementary and alternative therapies. If health-care providers and health-care delivery systems do not adapt and include diverse practices, patient and family care are compromised, resulting in not only poorer health outcomes but also an increase in cost. Recent efforts to promote global recognition of multiculturalism have encouraged health-care providers to become more aware of their own cultures and to the cultural differences among their patients in order to provide effective, acceptable, and safe health care. Each provider and organization must make a strong commitment to providing culturally competent care, regardless of the setting in which the care is provided and the backgrounds of the participants in care. As a result of this commitment, health-care organizations and educational programs have begun to recognize the need to prepare health-care professionals with the knowledge, skills, and resources essential to the provision of culturally competent care.</para><para role="Para">Culturally competent providers value diversity and respect individual differences regardless of one’s race, religious beliefs, or ethnocultural background. The goal of this guide is to provide a framework to promote culturally competent care that respects each person’s right to be understood and treated as a unique individual.</para><para role="Para">Educational programs and access to resources necessary for cultural competence are not always readily available in a format that is concise and easy to use. This guide has been developed to be used in a manner that can be easily accessed and understood. This approach to gaining essential knowledge using aggregate data is designed to help health-care professionals provide the highest quality care for patients and families of all backgrounds. Respect is essential to the development of dynamic interpersonal relationships that promote a positive influence on each person’s interpretation of, and responses to, health care in a multicultural environment.</para><para role="Para">The real challenge for health-care providers is gaining timely access to concise information that facilitates an accurate understanding of cultural beliefs from the perspective of both the patient and the provider. This concise guide uses the Purnell Model as a framework to simplify health assessments and interventions accurately while enabling culturally relevant care. Although the primary focus of the handbook is on the needs of health-care providers in the United States, the organizing framework and major concepts presented in each chapter are relevant to multicultural health care throughout the world. The small size of this guide and the outline format of its presentation with recommended highlighted culturally relevant interventions make it an essential resource for all health-care providers who are committed to providing culturally competent care, regardless of their practice setting.</para><bridgehead role="Heading">Contents</bridgehead><para><ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">1 Transcultural Diversity and Health Care</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0002#ch0002">2 The Purnell Model for Cultural Competence</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0003#ch0003">3 Barriers to Culturally Competent Health Care</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0004#ch0004">4 People of African American Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Mattie Geneva Caldwell</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Myra Michelle De Bose</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0005#ch0005">5 People of American Indian/Alaskan Native Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Kathy Prue-Owens</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0006#ch0006">6 The Amish</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Christine Nelson-Tuttle</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0007#ch0007">7 People of Appalachian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Mary Lou Clark Fornehed</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0008#ch0008">8 People of Arab Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Suha Ballout</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0009#ch0009">9 People of Brazilian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Thaís Moreira São João</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0010#ch0010">10 People of Chinese Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Hsiu-Min Tsai</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tsung-Lan Chu</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Wen-Pin Yu</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Ruoh-Lih Lei</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0011#ch0011">11 People of Cuban Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Jorge A. Valdés</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Victor Delgado</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0012#ch0012">12 People of European American Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Larry D. Purnell</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0013#ch0013">13 People of Filipino Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Nelson Tuazon</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0014#ch0014">14 People of German Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0015#ch0015">15 People of Greek Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Irena Papadopoulos</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0016#ch0016">16 People of Guatemalan Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cory Salcedo</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0017#ch0017">17 People of Haitian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Jessie M. Colin</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0018#ch0018">18 People of Hindu and Sikh Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Arvinder Singh</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0019#ch0019">19 People of Hmong Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Jennifer Kue</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0020#ch0020">20 People of Iranian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eric A. Fenkl</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0021#ch0021">21 People of Irish Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Francisco Brenes</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosa Roche</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0022#ch0022">22 People of Italian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Alessandro Stievano</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rosario Caruso</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Gennaro Rocco</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0023#ch0023">23 People of Jamaican Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Audrey P. Miller</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Chanadra Young-Whiting</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Yasmine Campbell</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Valerie J. Diaz</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0024#ch0024">24 People of Japanese Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Ivette M. Hidalgo</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Carmen Rizzetto Duque</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0025#ch0025">25 People of Jewish Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Teri Aronowitz</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Polly Zavadivker</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0026#ch0026">26 People of Korean Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Eun-Ok Im</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Yaelim Lee</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0027#ch0027">27 People of Mexican Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Rick Zoucha</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Anelise Zamarripa-Zoucha</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0028#ch0028">28 People of Polish Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Latisha Barfield</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Nola Holness</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0029#ch0029">29 People of Puerto Rican Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Mariceli Comellas-Quinones</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0030#ch0030">30 People of Russian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tatayana Maltseva</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Irina Rozenfeld</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0031#ch0031">31 People of Somali Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Trudy Gaillard</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tamara La Croix</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0032#ch0032">32 People of Thai Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Ratchneewan Ross</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0033#ch0033">33 People of Turkish Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Marshelle Thobaben</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Sema Kuguoglu</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0034#ch0034">34 People of Ukrainian Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tatayana Maltseva</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Irina Rozenfeld</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0035#ch0035">35 People of Vietnamese Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Carol O. Long</emphasis>, </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Tracy Tram Tran</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Timothy Minh Tran</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0036#ch0036">Correction to: People of Jewish Heritage</ulink></para><para role="TocAuthors"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Teri Aronowitz</emphasis> and </emphasis><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Polly Zavadivker</emphasis></emphasis></para><para><ulink url="ch0037#ch0037">Glossary</ulink></para></preface>
