<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0012s0005" role="Heading">
         <title>Personal Growth</title>
         <para role="Para">Personal growth can occur after a person experiences bullying within the workplace.</para>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Personal growth</emphasis> occurs when a person seeks to understand themselves and the people in their lives, finds meaning in their relationships and careers, and has found personal fulfillment in their spiritual life. Personal growth occurs when an individual decides that being stagnant in life is not living life to the fullest.</para>
         <para role="Para">Roberts Morgan et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib13">2019</link>
            </emphasis>) found in their research using the tool they developed entitled Reflected Best Self Exercise (RBSE) in 2005, that when people receive positive feedback about their contributions and strengths, they become more emotionally healthy. Emotionally healthy people tend to have good relationships with their colleagues, family, and friends and are resourceful and build personal agency. Presumptively, these are people, who in the workplace environment will have an increase in job satisfaction.</para>
         <para role="Para">Roberts Morgan et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib13">2019</link>
            </emphasis>) identified five practices that can enhance personal growth through the development of your <emphasis>best self</emphasis>. These five practices are:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Notice positive feedback</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Ask questions</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Study your successes</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Practice enacting your best self</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Pay it forward</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
         <para role="Para">When an individual makes a point to listen to the positive feedback of others and not just focus on the negative comments of a few people, they can become their best self. By asking questions to learn more and demonstrate a genuine interest in the lives and work of others, a person can become their best self. Taking the time to reflect on one’s own successes in their professional and personal life makes one thankful. Each day, making the decision to begin and end your day by recognizing your contributions not only within the work environment but at church or perhaps a place that you do volunteer work in the community, makes your workplace small and your personal world larger. Hence, you have accomplishments outside of the workplace and do not define yourself solely by your job. Lastly, always remember the importance of honoring the accomplishments of others. Everyone has the potential to do great work at work and beyond!</para>
      </sect1>
      
