<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0008" role="Heading">
         <title>Heal Thyself</title>
         <para role="Para">The Cambridge Dictionary defines a <emphasis>healer</emphasis> as “a person who has the power to cure ill people without using ordinary medicines: a spiritual healer” and also as “a person or thing that heals: time is a great healer” (Cambridge Dictionary, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib03">2023</link>
            </emphasis>). Traditionally, nursing has had a historical background of religious and spiritual connections. During the pre-Christian era, the care of the ill was associated with the ability to nourish the souls of others with prayer and was a noble act (Timmins &amp; Mc Sherry, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib08">2012</link>
            </emphasis>). The embodiment of the spiritual is how nursing was viewed in Celtic ancient writings, and the nurse was referred to as a “soul friend” to the ill to whom they provided care to, or “anam cara” (Grove &amp; Klauser, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib05">2005</link>
            </emphasis>). Foundationally, nursing is a profession of faith and carries with it the foundational belief that healing is a gift of compassion directed toward others who are in need of nurses’ delivery of physical, emotional, and spiritual healing.</para>
         <para role="Para">Nurses are professional healers. Nurses learn to heal through the recognition of symptomatology associated with different disease processes. However, for nurses when scars turn inward, the nurse as healer experiences emotional wounds that unattended to, manifest as physical and mental illness. To heal thyself is often not possible. Therefore, nurses will require someone to listen, maintaining confidentiality, to their story and situation related to bullying and help them to identify, processes, develop, and plan approaches to heal their pain so that they can move toward action and, ultimately, forgiveness. Because in absence of forgiveness, nurses affected by The Hollow give power to those who bully.</para>
      </sect1>
      
