<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0004s0009" role="Heading">
         <title>Interpersonal Theory</title>
         <para role="Para">Peplau (1952) examined the nurse-patient relationship with regard to the importance of the effectiveness of that which is being communicated and the clarity of the communication.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0009s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>The Value of Effective Communication</title>
            <para role="Para">Effective communication is invaluable because it constitutes the mutual listening, comprehension, and understanding of another person. Nurses, in their communication with patients, must demonstrate professionalism but most importantly, empathy and respect while nonjudgmentally gathering healthcare history and performing an assessment on their patients. Communication is necessary in the formation of therapeutic nurse-patient alliances that lead to diagnostic collaborations with healthcare providers and other disciplines in ensuring that patients are accurately diagnosed.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0009s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>The Angry Patient</title>
            <para role="Para">Patients enter healthcare environments under duress. Unexpected illnesses that require the intervention of healthcare workers place ill persons in a position of vulnerability and powerlessness as they wait in waiting rooms to be evaluated and undergo diagnostic tests. Patients are also asked to tell their “health decline” stories over and over again the moment they enter healthcare environments. While it is imperative that patients’ past health histories be known in order for disease processes and illnesses to be identified, the repetition of “health decline” stories can heighten anxiety, increase fear, and frustrate patients. As a result of the latter, patients can become angry in their communications with nurses and other healthcare workers and professionals.</para>
            <para role="Para">Workplace violence involving nurses is often perpetuated against them by patients, their families, or significant others. According to Lim et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib06">2022</link>
               </emphasis>), violence in the workplace can include threats and acts of violence such as harassment, verbal abuse, physical assault, homicide, or bullying. Physical violence incurred in the workplace can include slapping, kicking, gun violence, biting, stabbing, and pushing. Harassment is used as a way to verbally insult, bully, irritate, humiliate, intimidate, and degrade another person, while psychological violence involves the targeted use of power and threat of physical harm to impair the social, spiritual, physical, moral, and mental development of another person or persons. Approximately 73% of nonfatal illnesses and injuries in the workplace occurred due to workplace violence (United States Bureau of Labor Statistics, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib14">2018</link>
               </emphasis>). Over the course of their careers, 8–38% of healthcare workers are likely to experience physical violence (World Health Organization, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib15">2022</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
