<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0007s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>The Danger of Workplace Bullying</title>
         <para role="Para">Workplace bullying is dangerous to affected persons because the emotionally injured person is not within a silo. The bullied person leaves work and returns to a family, friendships, church, marriages, intimate relationships, other jobs, and activities of daily living (e.g., going to the bank or grocery shopping). Hence, the bullied person reciprocally interacts with society and the organization in which the bullying is occurring (Tuckey &amp; Neall, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib20">2014</link>
            </emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">Emotional injury</emphasis> occurs when someone has been repeatedly attacked verbally and either withdraws or projects their suppressed feelings on others in their immediate environments and within random encounters. Emotionally injured persons may verbally abuse others or could potentially physically harm another, as suppressed anger, hostility, and a perceived need to protect oneself from bullying, envelopes the affected person.</para>
         <para role="Para">For nurses working within healthcare organizations, the immediate environment constitutes the healthcare environment and the patients to whom they are providing nursing care. Because the patient is the primary focus of nurses in their work within healthcare organizations, it is the patient(s) that can become the unintended target of the bullied nurses’ emotional injury. Therefore, verbal abuse, being ignored, speaking abruptly and walking away, and making medication or treatment errors may occur to patients being cared for by bullied nurses.</para>
         <para role="Para">According to Johnson and Benham-Hutchins (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib13">2020</link>
            </emphasis>), nursing errors are more likely to occur within the context of bullying. Arnetz et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib05">2020</link>
            </emphasis>) found that nurse work environments that were associated with poor nurse health and bullying could result in adverse patient events (e.g., central-line associated bloodstream infections). Therefore, workplaces that permit or choose to ignore occurrences and reports of bullying may have more errors impacting patients. It is important to note that nursing teams where bullying is allowed will likely have impaired communication barriers amongst team members because the team consists of nurses who bully and nurses who are recipients of their uncivil conduct.</para>
      </sect1>
      
