<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0007s0005" role="Heading">
         <title>Quiet Quitting</title>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Quiet Quitting</emphasis> occurs when an employee who is dissatisfied with their employer begins to gradually reduce their work productivity and overall performance, rather than submitting a resignation letter. During the coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, employees took to social media platforms such as TikTok to share how they were quietly quitting their jobs (Harter, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link>
            </emphasis>; Lord, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib15">2022</link>
            </emphasis>; Scheyett, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib19">2022</link>
            </emphasis>). Debatably, quiet quitting is believed not to be a new phenomenon, but one that has been practiced in industry for several years (Lord, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib15">2022</link>
            </emphasis>). Harter (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link>
            </emphasis>), upon review of US Gallup noted that it is estimated that at least 50% of workers make up “quiet quitters.” Engaged workers make up (Harter, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link>
            </emphasis>) 32% with 18% of employees actively disengaging. In healthcare settings, studies on quiet quitting have found that over 50% of healthcare employees engage in quiet quitting (Galanis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib06">2023</link>
            </emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib07">2024a</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">Nurses who experience The Hollow have experienced bullying. Bullying is a type of workplace violence. Nurses subjected to bullying, unless provided support at the unit level from peers and managers, will likely leave their jobs. Experiencing post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), physical health problems, stress, anxiety, decrease in work productivity and work quality, depression, burnout, low self-esteem, and job dissatisfaction, nurses’ turnover intentions increase (Al Muharraq et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib02">2022</link>
            </emphasis>; Galanis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib08">2024b</link>
            </emphasis>; Goh et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib09">2022</link>
            </emphasis>; Karatuna et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib14">2020</link>
            </emphasis>). Younger and older nurses are impacted by bullying. However, it is often the newer nurse that receives the unhealthy initiation of bullying and dysfunctional behaviors associated with bullying (Anusiewicz et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib04">2019</link>
            </emphasis>; Karatuna et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib14">2020</link>
            </emphasis>) from the experienced nurse(s).</para>
      </sect1>
      
