<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0007s0007" role="Heading">
         <title>Summary: Unearthing Forgetfulness</title>
         <para role="Para">In order for healthcare organizations to end bullying and retain nurses, training must be initiated at the staff level all the way up to managerial, administrative, and senior level leadership on the dangers of ignoring bullying. Current research (and articles) on workplace bullying has shown that patients’ health outcomes are impacted and affected nurses’ mental and physical health, and nurse suicide (Ahc Media, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib01">2020</link>
            </emphasis>; Mental Health Practice, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib18">2018</link>
            </emphasis>) can occur as a result of prolonged exposure to toxic workplaces. While organizations would like to forget that bullying has occurred because acknowledgment of bullying behaviors is viewed as bad publicity, the bullied nurse suffers alone in isolation and their patients are unintentionally harmed.</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0007s0007ad02">
            <title>Putting Forgiveness into Practice</title>
            <bridgehead>A Personal Activity</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Forgiveness is a process. Sometimes in relationships, only one party forgives the other. And, sometimes, forgiveness can occur between two or more persons, resulting in peace and complete resolution of the problem. In the latter case, persons can walk away without bitterness. It is important to remember that forgiveness is an individual process that allows those impacted by negative situations, to positively move forward in absence of the burden of unforgiveness. In this activity, select and discuss a personal action that involves forgiveness. Consider how your personal reaction may impact the situation.</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #1 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A co-worker constantly interrupts you during meetings when you are contributing to a group discussion. Does this warrant a one-to-one conversation, or should the co-worker’s behavior be dismissed and forgiven?</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #2 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A manager steals your ideas and presents them as their own during a corporate presentation. Taken aback, you feel hurt and betrayed and decide to leave the meeting early. As you return to your office, your manager requests you to return to the meeting immediately because they would like one of your ideas “explained in more detail to the team.” You pause and decide to return to the meeting. The manager acknowledges your presence and kindly asks you to share your ideas.</para>
            <para role="Para">Did this manager betray you? Are the manager’s actions forgivable?</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #3 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">You are at a corporate compliance training event with colleagues. The lead trainer provides the opportunity for participants to take a 50-min break to eat their lunch. During lunch, two co-workers from another department sit at the table that you have already begun to eat lunch at with two other colleagues. As a friendly conversation ensues, one of the colleagues from a different department states directly to you, “You are really nice. You are nothing like we heard you were.” Unsure as to what this meant, you continue to eat your lunch quietly. Should you address this comment after the training event? Ignore the comment? Or inquire, why the comment was asked and who shared that you were difficult to communicate with?</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #4 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Loneliness is isolating, makes a person feel depressed, and have a yearning to belong. As a young biracial executive who practices Judaism, I have openly experienced discrimination within the workplace. My director is aware and has said very little to my co-workers, or supported me. It has been 1 year since my employment in my current position. I am not quite certain how to address my co-workers’ and director’s intentional disregard for discrimination in the workplace. Should I report what is happening to Human Resources or the Vice President of the division? Or, both?</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #5 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">The bullying has impacted my life negatively, more than I care to admit. Most days I do not want to go to work. I feel alone, sad, detached, and cry most of the work day intermittently. I am not certain what my next steps should be because I have been working in this environment for 8 years, and it appears to only be getting worse. My personality has changed. I am not as confident as I use to be and I know it. I need to make a change, but I am not certain of what my next steps should be and where I should go after so many years working at the same company. What should I do? How should I proceed?</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #6 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Lately, I have been just thinking about ending my life. I have gone to Human Resources and spoken numerous times with my manager and director, and nothing has improved in my work situation. The bullying has worsened. Sometimes I wake up and dread going to work. I argue with family members over very simple things and isolate myself when I am at work. I am starting to have thoughts of just ending it all. I am just not happy with my life. What should I do? Should I talk to someone? What should be my next steps?</para>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
