<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0009s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>Work-Life Balance</title>
         <para role="Para">To maintain a <emphasis role="bold">work-life balance is to ensure that your work and home life seldom intermingle</emphasis>. For example, a work-related problem may be discussed within the home or within a personal situation with a friend or colleague, but the problem is not the predominant factor nor focus. When work-life balance is managed, care of one’s self is prioritized, health and well-being is important, and time and energy is balanced. Often, it is when a person does not balance their time and energy toward their home life being one of contentment that toxic work environments can strangulate the mind and body causing mental fatigue and physical strain (Gragnano et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib03">2020</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">An unhealthy work-life balance, according to Cook-Campbell (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib01">2023</link>
            </emphasis>) includes burnout, constant overwork, lack of self-care, strained relationships, and neglected personal life. Persons who overwork, tend to have higher incidences of physical illness and depression and anxiety (el Batawi, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib02">1984</link>
            </emphasis>; Kivimäki et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib04">2015</link>
            </emphasis>; Virtanen et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib06">2011</link>
            </emphasis>). Symptomatology suggestive of a poor work-life balance according to Cook-Campbell (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0009s0010bib01">2023</link>
            </emphasis>) is lack of energy, constantly thinking about work, unexplained aches and pains, restlessness when not at work, struggling to take time off or a vacation, and money that is spent trying to outsource home chores (e.g., laundry, house cleaning, etc.) due to lack of time at home.</para>
      </sect1>
      
