<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0009" role="Heading">
         <title>Moving Forward</title>
         <para role="Para">The purpose of “moving forward” in name, theme, and goal is to inspire others who have encountered bullying and thrived. Mental health, spiritual wellness, and physical heath are protective factors against bullying. When one maintains a work-life balance, they are already proactive in their understanding of the importance of health maintenance and wellness promotion.</para>
         <para role="Para">The next steps in the acceleration of health and wellness “moving forward” are the following:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Acknowledgment that bullying can be an emotional and physical insult to one’s body and mind.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>The spiritual health of persons who are bullied is challenged when the act of harming another mentally and physically is intentionally ignored by others in an attempt to provide an image of unity and belonging.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Supporting of plans of change at the micro- and macro-system level in promoting nursing wellness and addressing incivility and bullying within the workplace can easily become stagnant when organizations fear a “reveal” of employees sharing their discontentment with the status quo.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Positive change can occur within any work environment. All that is needed is the empowerment of all nursing staff to correct that which is dysfunctional in environments that have historically tolerated bullying and incivility.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
         <para role="Para">Bullying is a painful, often unprovoked act of treating a person unjustly and without cause. For the bully or bullies, they believe that their intentional actions taken to shame, lie, cause doubt, and physically or emotionally harm their targets are warranted because of their own need to self-protect. Bullies view their targets as a potential or actual threat to the exposure of their own deficits. Hence, when exposed by their targets, bullies may attempt to either increase their attack or retreat in fear. The process of the target making the decision to move forward beyond the experience of the bully or bullies is a conscious one that can only be empowered with a counter move to expose the act of incivility and the perpetrators involved.</para>
      </sect1>
      
