<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0004s0008" role="Heading">
         <title>Forms of Communication</title>
         <para role="Para">Communication involves the sending and receiving of both verbal and nonverbal communication by nurses and the patients in their care. Within verbal communication, language must be interpreted if the two persons do not share the same cultural and or geographic background. For nonverbal communication, the concepts of time and space will vary among persons of different cultures. Additionally, the way one moves their body, makes eye contact, and maintains boundaries are all impacted by their personal life experiences, culture, and any deficits in kinesthetic, auditory, or visual transmission (Andrews et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib03">2020</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">In the process of applying the <emphasis>nursing process</emphasis> to clinical practice, nurses are taught during their undergraduate education to formulate patient care plans. One of the tools used in several academic settings is the nursing diagnosis applying the North American Nursing Diagnosis Association-International (NANDA-I). The NANDA-I provides a formal definition and defining characteristics of identified patient’s risk factors (Ackley et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib01">2022</link>
            </emphasis>), related factors, potential outcomes, and evidenced-based and clinically appropriate nursing interventions with rationales that support the reason for and necessity of implementation of interventions in the provision of quality and safe nursing care.</para>
         <para role="Para">Current communication nursing diagnoses include communication and communication problems that are defined based upon specific patient needs, deficits, and disease factors or illnesses contributing to lack of communication or an inability to communicate suggestive of an impairment. The latter is determined by the clinical and critical thinking of the nursing professional, in the context of exercising clinical judgment. The following are two areas of communication to be addressed:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Impaired verbal communication.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Readiness for enhanced communication.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
         <para role="Para">Readiness for enhanced communication involves the verbal exchange of information with others. The exchange of information includes comprehension of another’s thoughts, feelings, and objectives in the message they are delivering to another person. Communication, in absence of a language barrier or speech impediment, is understood by both parties. Impaired verbal communication is the absence, delay, or decrease in an individual’s ability to use a system of symbols, transmit, receive, or process information. Characteristically, examples of impairment in verbal communication can include slurred speech associated with a brain injury, stroke, facial paralysis, selective inattention, absence of eye contact, hearing impairment, or muteness (Ackley et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib01">2022</link>
            </emphasis>; Newton &amp; Shah, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib08">2013</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
      </sect1>
      
