<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0011s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>Achievable</title>
         <para role="Para">When something is <emphasis role="bold">achievable</emphasis>, it is soon to be completed. Although peace and calm seem unachievable in the midst of The Hollow, both can be accomplished. For persons affected by The Hollow, with counseling and the support of family and friends, the reestablishment of a work-life balance can be achieved. While immediate forgiveness can be difficult, releasing oneself from the perceived power of the bully or bullies comes when the affected person recognizes their personal value and worth as priceless and perseveration on a bully or bullies in their life, a waste of their time. Calm will be sustained post bullying when affected persons use the experience to empower themselves and others as they educate about bullying prevention and consequences.</para>
         <para role="Para">Ultimately, change will occur, but it may or may not be in the workplace the bullying occurred but in the person affected themselves. Persons affected by The Hollow never maneuver nor experience their daily interactions inside and outside of the workplace the same. They are more aware of other’s dysfunction, and their own physiological and psychological responses to potential displays of bullying.</para>
         <figure float="0" id="ch0011s0004fg01" role="Figure">
            <title>Calm</title>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="Ch0011f01.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>
         <sidebar id="ch0011s0004ad02">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>The Use of Mindfulness in Healing from The Hollow</bridgehead>
            <para role="Para">Williams and Penman (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0011s0005bib03">2011</link>
               </emphasis>) describe mindfulness as being simple and worthwhile because mindfulness exercises can prevent spiraling periods of sadness accompanied by prolonged periods of exhaustion and unhappiness—clinical depression, stress, and anxiety.</para>
            <para role="Para">With the business of daily lives, a 1-min mindful meditation can provide a brief relief from unplanned disruptions that can temporarily exhaust and cause feelings of stress. Here are three 1-min mediations below.</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> One-Minute Meditation </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Number 1. Basic Start of the Day</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Standing upright, take a deep breath, and raise both arms as if stretching to touch the ceiling (or sky if outdoors).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Close your eyes. As you close your eyes, take a deep breath.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>The breath you take is needed to sustain life. Your life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Listen to your breath. Feel your breath. Become aware of your own breathing and how it sounds.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Place you left and right hands on your chest. Slow your breathing down. Be aware of the rise and fall of your chest.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Stretch your hands toward the ceiling (or sky if outdoors). Reach as if attempting to touch the ceiling (or sky). Lower your hands and relax.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Be thankful for the moment and the pause you took to care for yourself.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Resume your day.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> One-Minute Meditation </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Number 2. Thankful Breath</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Allow for privacy and quiet.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Sit in a chair.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Ground yourself. Feet flat on the floor with shoes removed. Lower back against the chair. Sit erect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Close your eyes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Take a deep breath. Place your hands on your abdomen. Pull in your abdomen inward as you take a deep breath. Hold the breath and count to three--- 1---2---3.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Slowly release the breath.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>At the end of the breath quietly state the word “Thankful.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Repeat this exercise three times.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Our breath honors our very existence. Our breath represents life. Our verbalization of the word “Thankful” is a reminder to appreciate our own existence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>When we honor our existence, we can begin to appreciate not only ourselves but also our fellow human beings (e.g., co-workers) who exist and have breath as we do.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> One-Minute Meditation </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Number 3. Calming Break with Visualization</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Obtain a pen or pencil with one blank piece of paper.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Place the writing utensil and blank piece of paper on a desk or table.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Sit in front of the desk or table.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Sit erect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Feet grounded: shoes on or off.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Close your eyes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Count to six----1---2---3---4---5---6.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Open your eyes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Fix your eyes on the writing utensil and blank piece of paper.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Close your eyes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Think of a quiet place that you would like to visit. The place could be a beach, your home, a favorite chair, or a favorite restaurant eating a tasty meal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Mentally draw the picture using your imagination where you would like to visit.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Open your eyes and write down the place you visited and how it made you feel.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>As you resume your day, select a date on your calendar to visit the place you selected.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Remember to take time to create mini vacations to rest, renew, and refresh.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0011s0004ad03">
            <title>Counseling</title>
            <para role="Para">When a person experiences workplace bullying, they may feel anxious, paranoid, betrayed, fearful, sad, lonely, isolated, and depressed. Episodes of tearfulness are not out of the ordinary. Unfortunately, the feelings associated with the workplace-based bullying are not solely manifested at work. Affected persons bring these feelings home and marriages and relationships with family members and friends are impacted as well. Hence, it is imperative that persons affected by The Hollow receive counseling.</para>
            <para role="Para">By securing the services of a professional counselor or therapist, affected persons are providing themselves the opportunity to process their feelings and the emotional pain and turmoil they felt while being bullied within a safe and confidential setting. The processing of these varied emotions is necessary to deter the development of psychiatric disorders such as posttraumatic stress disorder, anxiety disorders, panic disorders, eating disorders, obsessive compulsive disorders, or depressive disorders (Halter Jordan, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0011s0005bib01">2022</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
