<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0008s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>The Targets</title>
         <para role="Para">Bullies target nurses who tend to be focused on their jobs, have potential for promotion, introduce cultural innovation or change, are culturally (e.g., religion, linguistics, etc.) and racially different, show no interest in joining their clicks, and present as free thinkers. Bullies tend to be stagnant in their approach to change and prefer to maintain the status quo. Typically, underperformer bullies target those who they perceive may threaten their (the bully’s) personal or professional success(es) by exposing who they really are and the knowledge they have or do not have. While the target may not understand this and only sees the meanness, lies, and covert actions of the bully or bullies at work, many bullies are very insecure people who hide behind a pompous personality façade.</para>
         <para role="Para">Targets tend to suffer from imposter syndrome. <emphasis role="bold">Imposter syndrome</emphasis> occurs when, persons, despite their intellectual accomplishments (e.g., education level attainment, career success, etc.) and personal and professional successes, feel undeserving and that their successes may have occurred for other reasons outside of their own work and determination. Nursing is a profession that involves emotional and physical connectiveness to patients (families and significant others) that are known for very short or long periods of time by the nurse. Hence, because nurses are providing healthcare to others, a level of vulnerability occurs, whether the nurse positively or negatively connects with patients in their care. For nurses, their care of patients and their loved ones on a routine basis can contribute to the development of burnout, compassion satisfaction, or compassion fatigue (Cetrano et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib04">2017</link>
            </emphasis>; Clark et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib05">2022</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">The vulnerability of the nurse experiencing The Hollow, because of being targeted by a bully or bullies, can cause nurses to consider leaving the profession of nursing and or resigning from their job. Needless to say, becoming the target of another when striving to maintain health and well-being in the workplace is fatiguing. However, consequentially, bullying, reframed, is a workplace occurrence that is a nuisance. And that which is a nuisance is an annoyance that may or may not cause a person harm. It is the decision to approach bullying as illogical foolishness that is a waste of time and emotional and physical energy that can help affected persons survive incidences of bullying.</para>
      </sect1>
      
