<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0008s0009" role="Heading">
         <title>Navigating Workplace Change in Real Time</title>
         <para role="Para">Work cultures are complex and not easily changed. On average, it can take 3–5 years to change a workplace culture. Within the profession of nursing, healthy workplace cultures are imperative for the maintenance of patient safety in healthcare environments. Classically, the view that a <emphasis>just culture</emphasis> can contribute to increased patient safety in healthcare promotes the ideology of systems thinking. In just <emphasis>cultures</emphasis>, emphasis is placed on the systems’ failures to address dysfunction and promote healthy and sustained organizational change, rather than the errors of individuals working within the system (Alashram et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib01">2024</link>
            </emphasis>). While the latter is true and applicable to nurse bullying if the system has intentionally ignored malfunctioning unit cultures for years that have bullying problems, the responsibility must also be placed on the bullies themselves as well.</para>
         <para role="Para">The allowance of The Hollow to remain active on known clinical units and in departments within healthcare organizations is often a failure of systems to openly address incivility and take a stance for zero tolerance of workplace bullying. Imboden (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib08">2024</link>
            </emphasis>) explored the value and health benefits of people having a sense of belonging in organizations. Belonging is an essential human need in order to function in social situations. Absence of connectivity to others leads to isolation, impacts well-being and trust, and affects employees’ health (Imboden, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib08">2024</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">In order to change workplace cultures, systems have to change. In order for systems to change, administration has to acknowledge problems that exist within their organization. In order for problems to be discovered, directors and managers have to ask for and receive openly the feedback from their direct patient care staff. For nurses, united, they must reach out for support to one another and to their American Nurses Association so that they have a clear understanding of the Code of Ethics for Nurses (American Nurses Association, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib02">n.d.</link>
            </emphasis>) and how these codes apply to their daily nursing practice.</para>
         <para role="Para">Nurses must realize that they have the unique gift as healthcare professionals working directly with patients and spending the greatest amount of direct clinical practice hours with patients daily and are best positioned to promote organizational change. No longer can bedside nurse leaders say, “I am just the nurse.” Know that your critical thinking and clinical judgment saves the lives of human beings that you interface with as you practice each day you enter the workplace. You have more power than you think. Discover your power, own it, share it, and do not let others attempt to take what is yours on their terms.</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0008s0009ad02">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>Change</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each scenario and identify if change is needed in the workplace. Write down the steps you would take to make this change happen.</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #1 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A new night nurse is abrupt and curses at her co-workers when they are not “immediately” ready to provide handoff report to so she can “go home.”</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #2 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A manager announces that they have selected two nurses to attend a research conference to represent the hospital.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #3 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A director announces that nurses on a 40-bed medical-surgical unit will be penalized via a new point system if they do not take their required 30-min break each time they work. A cumulation of a total of five points will lead to a negative write up related to the affected nurses poor time management. The unit is currently hiring for six full-time registered nurse positions.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #4 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse observes one of her nurse colleagues being screamed at by a fellow co-worker. The altercation occurs outside of a patient’s hospital room.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #5 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A patient throws a picture of water on a Latino nurse. The patient yells, “Go back to your country and take care of people that look like you, not me!”</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #6 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse manager informs an African American nurse that she “may not fit in” on the new hospital campus that she has transferred to and recommends she returns to her former “inner city hospital.”</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #7 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse is walking into the hospital garage when he is approached by three other nurses. The nurses begin to push and shove the nurse. One of the three nurses proceeds to spit in the nurse’s face. You are sitting in your car preparing to leave work when you observe this situation.</para>
            <para role="Para">
               <emphasis role="bold">Consider this:</emphasis>
            </para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is the nurse in a safe situation?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is the nurse able to safely leave the situation.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #8 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse receives an award for providing life-saving care to a fellow hospital employee in the parking lot.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #9 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Two nurses have been known bullies on a unit for the past 8 years. A newly hired nurse observes these nurses’ bullying behaviors and immediately reports them to the manager and Human Resources. The new nurse is now being bullied each time she enters the workplace. The nurse has become depressed and withdrawn.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario #10 </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A nurse confides in you that as a result of being bullied for 9 months, she has recently contemplated suicide.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Why is change needed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">How can you make this change happen?</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0008s0009ad03">
            <title>A Contemplation Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>Regret</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each statement or question and discuss how regret likely impacted the outcome.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>A nurse informs their nurse manager that they are resigning from their career of 20 years sharing, “I just cannot take this toxic environment anymore.” The nurse is 2 months away from retirement.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>A manager is hospitalized after a severe emotional break following an argument with her director. The manager’s director had been sarcastic and belittling to him for the last 4 years.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Lonely, a nurse contemplates self-harm after an incident of bullying with a night shift nurse. A co-worker observes the nurse taking pills out of her locker and quietly placing them in a small plastic bag. The co-worker stops the nurse and asks if everything is o.k.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>A nursing professor presenting a research project to a group of colleagues is questioned harshly post presentation as to the credibility of the research findings. The professor leaves the room in silence and returns to their office, closes the door, and cries.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>A nurse, after being bullied on their clinical unit for 9 months, obtains the new position of unit educator. Very much aware of the bullying problem on the unit, the nurse initiates a series of lectures and activities on the unit that address bullying and the consequences for retaliation.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
