<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0004s0006" role="Heading">
         <title>The Assumption of Sick Role</title>
         <para role="Para">Talcott Parsons, a sociologist practicing within the United States, developed the theory of social systems. The social systems theory (Parsons, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib09">1951</link>
            </emphasis>) explores the various roles held in society and the expectations placed on these roles and the persons who assume them in varied situations. The <emphasis>sick role</emphasis>, one of the roles identified by Parsons (Parsons, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0011bib10">1975</link>
            </emphasis>), is assumed by persons once labeled with an illness or diagnosis.</para>
         <para role="Para">The assumption of the sick role often begins by the person acknowledging that their health status has changed. Physical and or mental symptomatology overcomes the affected person’s mind and body. The affected person will either present to a healthcare facility such as an urgent care center, a doctor’s office, community-based clinic, or emergency department within an acute care hospital setting to seek help.</para>
         <para role="Para">Stripped of one’s own clothing, the sick person is welcomed into the health system with the changing into a disposable or cloth gown. The gown allows for ease of access for healthcare providers and healthcare workers to examine and assess the sick person using devices such as a stethoscope, the accessing of the veins (or arteries) to obtain blood specimens, ultrasounds, X-rays, or computed tomography (CT) scans. The process of diagnosis ensues as data is gathered via procedures, assessments, and evaluations. Ultimately, with critical analysis of gathered historical and past medical and surgical information, a diagnosis or diagnoses are made.</para>
         <para role="Para">Lastly, with a known cause of illness or disease origination, the person in the sick role either accepts the proposed treatment or denies help. The engagement or disengagement with the healthcare system is the choice of the affected person. Their decision can have either lifesaving results, stabilization with cure, or the acceptance of a poor prognosis depending upon the diagnostic outcome projection made by healthcare providers, hence, the acceptance of death.</para>
      </sect1>
      
