<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>The Bewilderment of Gaslighting</title>
         <para role="Para">The term <emphasis>gaslighting</emphasis> comes from a 1938 play entitled, “Angel Street” that was set in the year 1880 in London. The play was written by the playwright and British novelist, Patrick Hamilton. In the play, a married man uses subtle tricks to make his new wife gradually feel like she is going insane (Hamilton, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib06">1966</link>
            </emphasis>). The namesake of the tormenting trickery used by the spouse originates as he gradually dims the lights in their home that were “gas-fueled,” hence, the origin of the term “gaslighting.” The unsuspecting wife initially notices that the lights in the home have become dim, but as her seemingly innocent and well-intended husband denies that the gas-fueled lights have not dimmed, the wife begins to think she is losing her mind. Ironically, the story takes place on a street called Angel Street, which further alludes to the innocence and trust in angelic heavenly beings. Metaphorically, the person who gaslights is one who appears innocent and caring to others, while those that are being tricked by them are unaware of the gaslighter’s trickery.</para>
         <para role="Para">According to Feilding-Singh and Dmowska (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib04">2022</link>
            </emphasis>), the goal of the gaslighter is to gradually cause the person they are targeting to develop self-doubt. The act of perpetuating self-doubt is implemented by the gaslighter through carefully crafting stories about the person that they are targeting that undermine their skillset and ability to perform their job. For example, a supervisor who is a gaslighter may say to an employee who has been excelling within their position at work, “I was talking to some of your peers and one of them said that your performance on the last project was not up to par like it has been in the past. Is something going on with you at home or work?” The gaslighter’s inquiry about the target’s personal and professional life is inappropriate and has no basis. However, the gaslighter uses this type of inquiry to create doubt and to cause the target to share private information that the gaslighter can strategically use to further undermine the target’s performance at work.</para>
         <para role="Para">The more frequent the incidences of gaslighting, the more the targeted person is psychologically impacted and begins to question their own abilities. However, targeted persons can experience a one-time incident with a gaslighter and be impacted (Johnson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib07">2021</link>
            </emphasis>). The good news is that once the targeted person can recognize that they are being gaslighted, healing can begin.</para>
      </sect1>
      
