<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0010" role="Heading">
         <title>Summary</title>
         <para role="Para">Moving forward for the nurse affected by The Hollow is the process of exposing the acts of the bully and making the conscious decision to forgive and resume their own lives before the bully existed. The positive event that occurs post the exposure of the bully or bullies and their acts of incivility is that the affected nurse emerges stronger in character, moral clarity, and an undefeatable resolve. The process of moving forward is one of rebuilding.</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0005s0010ad02">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>Adult Drawing for Healing and Clarity of Situation</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Drawing pictures and coloring can be very relaxing and also thought provoking for adults. When a person draws a picture of how they are feeling, of someone close to them, or a picture of their immediate environment, both consciously and unconsciously, the person(s) is sharing how they are feeling about a particular situation and how they perceive what is occurring. Draw a picture that describes your feelings as you are presently experiencing them now and when recalling an event.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of yourself.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a part of your body that you are pleased with.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Write two words that describe what makes you happy. Draw a picture representing the two words.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your family.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your best friend.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of how you feel working as a nurse on a good day.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of how you feel working in another role (e.g., mother, wife, son, brother, daughter, etc.).</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your face as you prepare to go to work.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your face upon arrival to work.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your face when interacting with patients.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your face and body when interacting with family members.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of your face and body when interacting with your co-workers.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of yourself if you have ever experienced bullying.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Draw a picture of yourself free from the hold of The Hollow.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para role="Para">Upon completion of the drawing activity, consider this:</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After completing your drawings, examine them closely.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Are you surprised at how your drawings look?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">What do your drawings reveal about you and your current life situation?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If there is an area in need of improvement, what will be your next steps?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Identify a person or person (e.g., disclosure to a friend, co-worker, manager, director, spouse, counselor, or therapist) that can help you with you next steps.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0005s0010ad03">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>The Act of Moving Forward</bridgehead>
            <para role="Para">The act of moving forward is an exercise in accepting the past and the future to come, as being negotiable. The negotiability is either positive or negative. The decision to no longer be stagnant but to change one’s position in life warrants that one be presented with options. With this activity, participants will be asked to “move forward” when they perceive that there is no threat to their safety; physically, emotionally, or spiritually.</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Moving Forward Scenarios </bridgehead>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>You are invited to meet with a co-work and another peer. No agenda has been provided. Would you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis>? Yes or No. What is the reason for the rationale you provided?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>A colleague during a work-related meeting makes a side comment to another colleague about how you handled a situation. What would you do? Should you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> with initiating a conversation about what was said or ignore the conversation as ridiculous and nonsensible?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>If your story is true, then no one can argue with you about your story not being true. To do the latter means that the person in which you are engaged in a conversation with is lying. What would you do if someone is obviously lying about you in front of others. Do you remain quiet or <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> and address the person or persons engaged in the act of lying?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>To be kind involves being genuine of heart. Knowingly and respectfully acknowledging one’s truth or the truth of another. How would you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> knowing that the standard of organizational acceptance is not being kind nor genuine? Should you consider leaving the organization or help promote change by increasing awareness?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
