<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0009s0009" role="Heading">
         <title>And So, I Recall: Learning from the Past</title>
         <para role="Para">If your organizational culture was affected by The Hollow in the past, this does not mean that there cannot be a reoccurrence of workplace bullying. A reoccurrence of bullying is always one employee hire away of a person with anger, integrity, manipulation, insecurity, or prior bullying issues. Hence, it is important that managers learn to ask questions and explore work history indicative of bullying behaviors. For example, a hiring manager could inquire about team-building skills and approaches to resolutions of conflict in the workplace and create scenarios whereby in writing, future employees must address a challenging fellow employee or client. Also, include a scenario, whereby the employee is a witness to an actual incident of bullying in the workplace, and ask the employee to explain how they would react and why they chose to react the way they did.</para>
         <para role="Para">Pre-employment Screening: Two Scenario Examples:</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0009s0009ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
            <title>Scenario 1: Addressing a Challenging PatientThe nurse enters the hospital room of a patient the nurse has been providing care to for the last 8 h of a 12-h shift. The nurse who answered the patient’s call bell asks, “How may I help you.” The patient shares, “I’ve decided that I want to change hospitals. I am not pleased with my care you provided me today. You are not a very good nurse, and you have a horrible bedside manner. I have already notified Patient Relations and your Manager. I am calling to ask you to pack my belongings and complete my discharge. I am ready to go!”</title>
            <para role="Para">Answer the following questions:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What would be your first response?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Do you need to contact anyone?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is there a need for follow-up with patient relations and the manager?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What education, if any, is necessary for the patient?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What education, if any, is necessary for you?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What is your greatest fear or concern after this verbal interaction with your patient?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Have you ever experienced a situation similar to the scenario? If yes, how did you handle it?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is it common for patients to have complaints?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What is your motto in the care of patients that have shared that they are not pleased with their healthcare?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What would be your tone of voice, physical approach, proximity, and comfort level in engaging this patient in determining what could be done differently to ensure continuity of care and that they complete their healthcare treatment?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0009s0009ad03" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
            <title>Scenario 2: Observing an Employee Being BulliedAt 7:45 p.m., you have just completed your 12-h day to evening shift and begin walking toward the fifth level of the garage where you parked earlier. As you walk toward your car, you hear arguing, and someone whispering, “If you tell anyone, I will deny it and you’ll look like the fool. They will believe me over you any day.” Standing quietly behind a truck in a darkened area of the garage, you observe that it is the female assistant nurse manager and a male nurse from your unit. You hear the male nurse say, “I am back with my wife and our child. I am ending this relationship that should have never begun in the first place. I made a mistake. My wife forgives me and I am moving on.”</title>
            <para role="Para">The female assist nurse manager slaps the male nurse on his left cheek and begins to walk away stating, “I will get you fired. If I have to lie about your character, I will get you fired.”</para>
            <para role="Para">Answer the following questions:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What would you do?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Should you make your presence known to your two co-workers in the garage?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is it necessary to approach either party to explain what you heard them discuss?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Would you disclose what you heard to another employee you work with?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Whom should the information you heard be shared with within the organization?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is employee confidentiality important in this situation?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What is your role here, if any?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Who are you advocating for in this situation?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What type of situation is this?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Have you ever participated within or observed workplace bullying before? If yes, what was the outcome?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <para role="Para">Hiring managers should review the scenario and responses with the future employee to provide an opportunity for him or her to explain their thought processes in answering the questions and also to determine how they interpreted the scenario itself. Include their feedback and your discussion with the future employee as part of their scenario write-up. The latter is an opportunity to provide future hires with insight on the importance of healthy workplace environments. With regard to whether the individual is hired or not, an opportunity to promote healthy workplace ideals has been provided.</para>
      </sect1>
      
