<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0001s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>Questions to Contemplate: Let’s Get to Work!</title>
         <sidebar id="ch0001s0004ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle1">
            <title>Directions</title>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read and discuss the following questions about dysfunction within the profession of nursing. Consider what you can do to help improve work environments for nurses. Contemplate immediate reparative responses that can be made by nurses, professional organizations, and the healthcare systems and organizations which employee nurses:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Why would a profession based on caritas be so stressful?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>How early should nurse bullying be intervened upon?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is there a pattern of bullying within the nursing profession?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Can nurses be given support earlier by their organizations with bullying prevention?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Should nursing leadership be held responsible for knowingly allowing bullying to occur in the workplace?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Should human resources be held accountable if consistent patterns of bullying on a particular clinical unit or other healthcare workplace setting are permitted or not addressed directly at all?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is it possible for nurses to be insulated from factors contributing to nurse suicide?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What other actions could be taken to address nurse suicide?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is nurse suicide a public health issue?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What does it mean to the nursing profession to experience another nursing death by suicide? What are the implications?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
