<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0007" role="Heading">
         <title>Overexposed</title>
         <para role="Para">Overexposure to workplaces that ignore bullying can be dangerous to one’s health. When bullying is accepted and ignored, organizations leave themselves open to lawsuits. Nurses are more at risk for physical and mental illness development after days, weeks, months, and years of dealing with toxic workplace interactions. Of concern is that organizations are often well aware that there is a problem with bullying but fear having to change a culture. This can be a large undertaking, and to do so requires the organization to admit to its employees that a problem exists.</para>
         <para role="Para">The public admission of a bullying problem is a brave undertaking which employers believe will leave them legally vulnerable to employees that have had past complaints of experiencing bullying and incivility in the workplace. To the contrary, the admittance of a problem and the resolution to identify and address the problems at hand can also absolve the company of being known for acceptance of “bad” behaviors in the workplace and not responding to employees’ complaints. In essence, proof of attempting to absolve the culture of bullying is better than having not tried to at all.</para>
         <para role="Para">It may bring some comfort to organizations experiencing employee bullying within the workplace that the problem of bullying is international. Germany reports having 17% of their workforce report bullying. In the United States, 30% of the workforce report having experienced bullying; 30% translates to an estimation of 48.6 million working adults. India has an estimated 46% to 55% of workplace bullying (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0006s0012bib05">2022</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">Creating a work environment that not only educates its employees about bullying but discusses the consequences of intentionally physically and mentally harming a fellow employee such as progressive action (verbal and written) discipline that can lead to termination of employment is imperative. Workplaces that demonstrate the valuing of each employee and focus on employee safety are more likely to be healthier places to work. The latter are also workplaces that are less likely to demonize and then ostracize the person reporting having experienced bullying within the organization.</para>
      </sect1>
      
