<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0002s0005" role="Heading">
         <title>Organizational Impact of Bullying</title>
         <para role="Para">Organizations are impacted by bullying as well. Employees will leave an organization that does not have a healthy work environment (WBI, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib09">2021</link>
            </emphasis>). Hence, turnover intentions are likely to be higher and employee absences from the workplace increase. The reputation of the organization will be impacted over time and lawsuits may occur. As a result of poor branding and reputation, the organization will be unable to attract nor sustain talented workers. Because employees experience a disruption in their work as a result of the bullying and also a lack of confidence, productivity is impacted. Ultimately, the quality of customer service declines as costs to manage the organization and product(s) increase.</para>
         <figure float="0" id="ch0002s0005fg01" role="Figure">
            <title>Cold</title>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="Ch0002f01.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>
         <sidebar id="ch0002s0005ad03">
            <title>Cold Communications</title>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">For many people, responding to a rude or demeaning comment can be uncomfortable. However, at times, unaddressed untrue or negative behaviors can affect the health of the person being bullied. Additionally, addressing the unprofessional behaviors of a coworker(s) can help in the unit-based and organizational initiatives to create healthy work environments for all people. Read each statement and decide if you will respond, not respond, or be undecided. Answers will vary and depend upon an individual’s personality and personal life experiences. Hence, below the questions are possible considerations only when responding.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 1.</emphasis> “Sometimes I wonder if you really have a brain.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 1.</emphasis> “I am certain that I do. I met the qualifications to work here just like you.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(a) Respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(b) Not respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(c) Undecided.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. It is important to set clear boundaries as to who you are and do not allow the bully to define you or your abilities.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 2.</emphasis> “Let me explain how this works to ensure you understand.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 2.</emphasis> No response.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(a) Respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(b) Not respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(c) Undecided.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Not respond. This statement does not warrant a response. Some comments by people attempting to be rude or belittling to you are just not worth your energy. Maintain direct eye contact for a few moments with a neutral expression and drop your gaze. The latter demonstrates that their statement was meaningless to you and that you have already moved on to the next best thing.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 3.</emphasis> (Insert name) “It looks like ______ is the last pick for project teams again. Anyone interested in ________ joining your team? What? Afraid of having to do “extra” work?”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 2.</emphasis> “I enjoy working in teams and will do my best to help my team succeed. My work ethic is to arrive early and stay late.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(a) Respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(b) Not respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(c) Undecided.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. Reframe the negative statement with a positive one.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 4.</emphasis> “That hairstyle you are wearing is very unprofessional. Braids and afros do not belong in the workplace.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 4.</emphasis> “Have you ever heard of the Crown Act. You may want to read about this Act before you decide to make any more comments about my hair. Not appropriate.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(a) Respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(b) Not respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(c) Undecided.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Respond. It is important to recognize your own uniqueness and beauty as being valuable. No one has the right to disrespect who you are and how you choose to present yourself.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Statement (bully) 5.</emphasis> “Do you really think they will believe you… that all this was your idea. Look at me and then look at you?”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Response (affected person) 5.</emphasis> No response.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Select your response:</emphasis>
                  </para>
                  <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(a) Respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(b) Not respond.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem role="ListItem">
                        <para>(c) Undecided.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Answer:</emphasis> Not respond. No response is necessary to the bully; instead follow up with substantiating the origins of your work. It is your work and no one has the right to take credit for it but you.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0002s0005ad04">
            <title>Activity: Poof!</title>
            <bridgehead>Meditation for Contemplation.</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead>Poof!</bridgehead>
            <para role="Para">Quietly lying in bed again but wide awake, I meditate on the failures of my own interventions to stop the bullying.</para>
            <para role="Para">Tossing and turning. Repetition of words said and words I wish I could unsay; the determination of assigned fault seems relentless.</para>
            <para role="Para">Scarred more than I care to admit I ruminate.</para>
            <para role="Para">I ruminate over words said to me and words said about me.</para>
            <para role="Para">The strength now emerging is not one of fantasy but of reality. This is my reality.</para>
            <para role="Para">Mood uplifted and strength renewed, I awake to peace. What happened?</para>
            <para role="Para">Poof!</para>
            <para role="Para">I awoke from my toil. Tired of the endless and relentless nonsense of the bullies, I arose.</para>
            <para role="Para">Stronger and unscathed.</para>
            <para role="Para">Poof!</para>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Meditation and Contemplation </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">After reading the poetic meditation entitled “Poof!,” consider how it made you feel. Answer the questions below.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What is the meaning of the title “Poof!”?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Why does the person in the poem have sleepless nights?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What made the person in the poem meditate on their own failures?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What causes a person to ruminate?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What causes a person to have their strength renewed?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
