<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0012s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>Emotional Support</title>
         <para role="Para">Emotional support involves the skill of silently listening to the sorrows or burdens of another. Vaclavikova et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib18">2022</link>
            </emphasis>) conducted a scoping review of 573 articles on mobbing. A review of the articles that included Scopus, Ovid Nursing, Taylor and Francis, and EBSCOhost yielded a total of 23 articles that were reviewed on the topic of mobbing occurring with nurses in the workplace. Mobbing is a type of workplace bullying that involves behaviors such as constant criticism, ignoring, discrediting, humiliation, gossiping, and isolation (Efe &amp; Ayaz, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib06">2010</link>
            </emphasis>; Leymann, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib11">1996</link>
            </emphasis>; Suárez García, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib17">2021</link>
            </emphasis>) as a means to psychologically exhaust the affected person with the goal of facilitating the person’s departure from the workplace. Nurses impacted by mobbing require <emphasis role="bold">emotional support</emphasis> due to their having experienced intentionally planned abusive behaviors within their work environment.</para>
         <para role="Para">Vaclavikova et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib18">2022</link>
            </emphasis>), after completing a scoping review of the literature, identified the following mobbing prevention interventions that were effective in the workplace: clear rules and sanctions (Kim &amp; Sim, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib10">2021</link>
            </emphasis>), adequate awareness (Castronovo et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib04">2016</link>
            </emphasis>; Pai &amp; Lee, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib12">2011</link>
            </emphasis>; Stagg et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib16">2013</link>
            </emphasis>), cooperative team leadership (Bortoluzzi et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib03">2014</link>
            </emphasis>; Johnson, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib08">2015</link>
            </emphasis>; Ruíz-González et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib14">2020</link>
            </emphasis>), and good communication skills (Asi Karakaş &amp; Okanli, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib02">2015</link>
            </emphasis>; Keller et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0012s0007bib09">2016</link>
            </emphasis>). From an organizational perspective, mobbing is a serious issue because it can lead to nursing turnover and creates an environment whereby uncivil conduct is allowed to proliferate at the expense of the mental health of nurses. Hence it is imperative that all staff working within healthcare organizations be provided training on mobbing behaviors, how to identify them, skills to effectively intervene when a colleague is experiencing bullying via mobbing, and how to report persons perpetuating mobbing behaviors against the affected person(s). In the case of mobbing, having knowledge is having the power to prevent this bullying behavior.</para>
      </sect1>
      
