<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0004s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">African Americans (Black People) comprise 45.4 million residents in the United Stated (U. S. Census Bureau 2022). They are the descendants of Africans who were unwillingly brought to America as designated enslaved people to serve a large population of the white race. This event caused the separation of many families who never saw their relatives again.</para>
         <para role="Para">Their color identity was African, Negro, colored, and less respectful names, such as niggers, and darkies. The external labels transitioned into various shades by the sexual mixing of the races, which produced a wide variation in skin colors (mullato) but was still viewed as beautiful.</para>
         <para role="Para">Owners usually assigned lighter-skinned persons duties in the “House.” Naturally, these enslaved persons learned some of the eclectic ways. The darker-skinned person was assigned duties outside in the fields. The native names of the enslaved persons were abolished and renamed. These names were unfamiliar, and they could not pronounce them. Their status in America was considered the lowest. They were separated, even more so, by a language they could not speak, nor was it interpreted. However, they demonstrated tremendous courage and pride to survive such treatment.</para>
         <para role="Para">Today, African Americans primarily identify themselves as Black people because they were born in America. Although they are descendants of Africans, they do not know the African landscape or cultural practices. These African Americans built this country from strength based on faith that God would make it possible to free them. The many inventions that Americans enjoy today were ideas conceived by the Africans. In terms of culture and their ways of living, they transformed America in many ways.</para>
         <para role="Para">Most families place a high priority on self-identification. To deny the African heritage or self as of the Black race is most offensive. The experiences of the Black race have improved in that more of them are college educated, employed in white collar positions, business owners, and live in the upper echelon of neighborhoods. Despite these improvements, African Americans remain in the “blue collar” segment of the working class. Nevertheless, they are mindful of where they came from by celebrating their African American (Black) heritage every year in February. But if you ask a Black person about the celebration, they will say, “Every day of the year should be celebrated by each person who is of the Black race” (Satterfield <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0004s0002bib19">2023</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            <emphasis>All information presented in this chapter represents aggregate information and may not represent anyone identifying as an African American or Black.</emphasis>
         </para>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans have been plagued with labels to identify themselves as well as labels over language. Many scholars who research language have determined Black English, Ebonics, African American English (AAE), African American Vernacular English (AAVE), and most recently, African American Language (AAL), are means by which African Americans may communicate.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many believe there is a common vernacular and language among US African Americans regardless of where they live. However, the vocabulary and pronunciation of words can be very different. Speech patterns are fundamental to family culture and history. Storytelling has been a means by which African Americans pass on their history. This means of communication helps people learn and hear the stories of African American ancestors.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many agree that African-American Vernacular (AAVE) is the most commonly spoken language of many middle-class African Americans.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The dominant language of African Americans is English. However, many refer to an informal language called Black or African American English (AAE) or Ebonics. For example, some may pronounce “th” as “d”. Therefore, the word these may be pronounced <emphasis role="bold">dese</emphasis>. Do not stereotype African Americans as speaking only in Black English because most African Americans are articulate and competent in formal English.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African American English is a credible authentic dialect suitable for respect. Its origins can be found in the Atlantic slave trade. The development of dialects created “first and second language varieties” developed by African Americans. The vibrant English language is mainly due to the distinct features of African American language.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">What transpires within the family is considered private and inappropriate for discussion with strangers. A common phrase that reflects this perspective is, “Don’t air your dirty laundry.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">An example of when withholding “dirty laundry” may harm families is when someone in the family becomes unemployed. Historically, men have traditionally been the providers and if they lose their jobs, it can be detrimental to the family. Families are reluctant to discuss job loss, as it is considered a private family matter. Churches often encourage prayer to help resolve these situations. If unemployment goes for too long, additional family struggles may arise.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Speech is dynamic and expressive and the volume is often loud compared with other cultural groups. Body movements are usually involved when communicating with others and facial expressions can be very demonstrative. This audible voice volume does not necessarily reflect anger; it is merely a dynamic expression.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals are comfortable with a close personal space. However, be aware that maintaining prolonged direct eye contact may be misinterpreted as aggressive behavior by some. A few older African Americans may avoid eye, a carry-over from the past where direct eye contact was avoided.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Nonverbal communication can be seen as a respectful greeting. Tilting the head up acknowledges another’s presence, and tilting the head down shows respect. Hugs can be given when you are familiar with the person; however, asking if it is okay to hug may go further than assuming it is OK.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Body language can send direct messages where words are not required. Therefore, it is essential to determine what messages a person tries to convey through body movement, facial expressions, and gestures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Generally, most individuals are more present- than past- or future-oriented. Younger and middle-aged people may be more future-oriented, as indicated by the value placed on education. Some are more relaxed about time, believing that making an appointment is more important than being on time. Flexibility in timing appointments may be necessary for those with a circular rather than a linear sense of time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans require effective communication and this begins with building trust. Healthcare providers must be aware of their own biases and prejudices. If providers are not consciously aware of them, this can hinder positive healthcare outcomes for this population.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Showing respect with formality in names may be a first step in gaining trust. Most prefer to be greeted formally as Mr., Mrs., Ms., or Miss with the use of their surname because the “family name” is highly respected and connotes pride in their family heritage. Greet patients formally as Mr., Mrs., Ms., Dr., or Rev. and the last name until told to do otherwise.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organizations</title>
            <para role="Para">African Americans have faced a long history of racism in laws, policies, and practices throughout the United States. This has led to the creation of racist institutions and a system of structural racism that favors White people while systematically disadvantaging Black Americans. The impact of this inequality is felt deeply by African Americans in nearly every aspect of their lives, from where they live, the quality of education they receive to their job opportunities. Access to childcare, health care, and mental and physical health outcomes can be affected. Furthermore, their political standing, power, and treatment in law and justice systems have been affected. The color of their skin has influenced virtually every aspect of African Americans’ lives, regardless of their socioeconomic status or social standing.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The African American community has a distinctive family structure that prioritizes the significance of extended families. Grandmothers, aunts, and other relatives often play a pivotal role in providing emotional and physical support to children. This approach ensures that children receive the necessary care, even when nuclear families are unable to provide it.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Education and self-reliance are highly valued in the community, and parents work hard to shield their children from the outside world. Because of discrimination and violence in some areas, parents act as a buffer, protecting their children from danger. They instill respect, obedience, and good behavior to ensure children grow up in a safe and secure environment. Adolescents are assigned household chores to teach them responsibility and survival skills.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older individuals, particularly grandmothers, are respected for their wisdom and are frequently essential in childcare. Healthcare professionals, such as doctors, nurses, and dentists are highly regarded and social status is significant within the community.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">However, the community faces challenges in some areas, such as teen pregnancy. While premarital teenage pregnancy is not approved, it is accepted after the fact. The extended family provides a robust support system and the adolescent mother assumes primary responsibility for her child. Sometimes, someone other than the mother may become the primary caregiver.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">It is crucial to recognize that acceptance of same-sex relationships is different among families. Revealing these relationships may have unfavorable consequences. Therefore, it is best not to disclose same-sex relationships to others.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In conclusion, the African American community has a unique family structure emphasizing the importance of extended families, education, and self-reliance. Despite difficulties, the community values respect, obedience, and good behavior, ensuring children grow up in a secure and nurturing environment. Acknowledging and honoring these values when working with the community is essential.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Acknowledging the struggles many African Americans face in the workforce is essential. Unfortunately, prejudicial attitudes and cultural tension can create a hostile workplace atmosphere that makes it difficult for them to succeed. Employers must address these issues and create an inclusive environment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The racial wealth gap is another challenge that many African American families face. The persistent disparity in income and wealth between African American and white families highlights the ongoing impact of discrimination and inequality. Addressing this wealth gap could not only benefit African American families but also have a positive effect on the economy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">It is essential to recognize that African American employees are often underrepresented in leadership positions and overrepresented in low-wage entry-level roles. Seeing African American leadership in the workplace can be encouraging, but there is still work to provide equal opportunities.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ignoring African American culture in the work environment can have significant adverse health consequences. Microaggressions and implicit biases can lead to physical and mental health challenges that can result in increased absences from work and decreased productivity. Employers must commit to addressing these issues and implementing policies and processes that promote a healthy and inclusive work environment for all employees.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Research and genetics companies, such as <emphasis role="bold">23andMe</emphasis>, have genetic profiles that provide historical records tracing African Americans as far as the transatlantic slave trade. It shows tens of thousands of genetic profiles tracing modern-day African American ancestry.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">DNA was extracted from the remains of individuals at the historic site of Catoctin Furnace in Maryland and individuals clustered into numerous family groups. These enslaved individuals carried out domestic and agricultural tasks and operated the furnace. These enslaved individuals brought with them skills of iron technology and iron artistry.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans’ gene pool of racial strains is attributed to their skin color which may vary from light to very dark. Lighter-skinned people appear more yellowish brown, whereas darker-skinned African Americans appear ashen.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pallor in dark-skinned people can be observed by the absence of the underlying red tones that give brown and black skin its “glow” or “living color.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To assess conditions such as inflammation, cyanosis, jaundice, and petechiae, palpate the skin for warmth, edema, tightness, or induration.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To assess for cyanosis in dark-skinned people, observe the oral mucosa or conjunctiva.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Jaundice is assessed more accurately by observing the sclera of the eyes, the palms of the hands, and the soles of the feet which may have a yellow discoloration.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Keloid formation, common among dark-skinned people, is one example of the tendency toward overgrowth of connective tissue.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans have a greater bone density than European Americans, Asians, and Hispanics, resulting in a lower incidence of osteoporosis.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because of the darker skin color of most African Americans, the early stages of pressure ulcers are more difficult to observe.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pseudofolliculitis (“razor bumps”) is more common among males, whereas melasma (“mask of pregnancy”) is more common among darker-skinned females during pregnancy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many experience a disproportionate amount of pigment discoloration with vitiligo being the most common. This is an autoimmune disease that causes skin discoloration and is associated with diabetes and thyroid disorders. If left untreated, it can cause skin cancer. Some erroneously believe that dark-skinned people are not at risk for skin cancer or sunburn because of their higher concentration of melanin.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dispel myths that darker-skinned people are not at risk for skin cancer and sunburn.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Birthmarks are more common in this population. Mongolian spots, found more often in newborns, disappear over time. Reassure the family that most Mongolian spots will fade over time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some women have alopecia related to the use of chemicals to straighten/relax the hair or braid. Provide information on the causes of alopecia.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The pathophysiology of hypertension in African Americans is most frequently related to volume expansion, decreased renin, and increased intracellular concentration of sodium and calcium, making African Americans more genetically prone than whites to retain sodium.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is evidence of breast cancer disparities among African Americans; however, there is little consideration of the genomic risk of recurrence by breast cancer subtype. Women with early high-risk breast cancer where there is no evidence of residual invasive cancer have similarly good outcomes regardless of race. However, African American women with HR-positive/ <emphasis>ERBB2</emphasis>-negative tumors without surrogate biomarkers may have worse outcomes than White women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Gene variants and alcohol consumption have been associated with an increased risk of breast cancer in women. There is a correlation between the consumption of over seven or more drinks per week and invasive breast cancer as well as ER (estrogen-positive) and PR (progesterone-receptor) or breast cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Researchers must develop and test biomarker therapy in African American women.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although there has been a decline in leading causes of death such as accidents, cancer, infant mortality, and cardiovascular diseases, the adjusted death rates for African Americans are higher than for whites. Other causes of death are homicide, cirrhosis, malnutrition, chemical dependency, and diabetes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans are at a higher risk of misdiagnosis for psychiatric disorders and therefore may be treated inappropriately with drugs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans respond to or metabolize alcohol, antihypertensives, beta blockers, psychotropic drugs, and caffeine differently than European Americans. Psychiatric patients experience a higher incidence of extrapyramidal effects with haloperidol decanoate than European Americans. They are more susceptible to tricyclic antidepressant delirium, showing higher blood levels and a faster therapeutic response.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As a result, they experience more toxic side effects. <emphasis role="bold">It is crucial to observe African American patients closely for side effects related to tricyclics and other psychotropic medications.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Finally, it is essential to keep in mind that light eyes dilate wider in response to mydriatic drugs than dark eyes and must be taken into consideration when treating African Americans.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">High-risk health behaviors are causing significant challenges for African Americans. These behaviors have been linked to structural and economic disparities that are rooted in racism. The increased risk of disease or injury that comes along with these behaviors can be detrimental and often lead to disability, death, or social problems. Addressing these issues and creating a more equitable and just society for all is crucial.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Addressing health equity, particularly in the African American community, should involve addressing behaviors such as alcoholism, eating disorders, risky sexual behaviors, tobacco use, and violence. These severe issues affect individuals and families, and we must prioritize efforts to prevent and address them. By raising awareness and providing support and resources, we can work toward healthier communities for all.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The prevention of high-risk health behaviors is essential to improve the overall health and well-being of African Americans who are affected by chronic diseases. The COVID-19 pandemic has highlighted the lack of access to healthcare for many African Americans living in poor, inner-city neighborhoods. In such situations, families had to rely on each other to survive, and the fear of the healthcare system prevented many African Americans from seeking care. Unfortunately, this mistrust in the healthcare system still exists, and the COVID-19 pandemic has only added to it. Healthcare professionals must address these issues and build trust in the healthcare system.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">It is essential to acknowledge that some health conditions disproportionately impact African Americans. For instance, they have a higher rate of mortality and morbidity in cardiovascular disease, all cancers, diabetes, obesity, and HIV.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cardiovascular disease is the top cause of death among all adults in the United States. Among the most common conditions related to cardiovascular disease are heart disease and stroke. Heart disease has several disorders; two briefly discussed here are hypertension and heart attack. Although a stroke is like a heart attack, its damage is caused in the brain. It can be a prominent factor in disability. Unfortunately, these risks are even higher for African Americans due in part to historical and systemic factors that continue to play a significant role in current health outcomes. For instance, adverse social determinants of health—such as lack of access to healthcare and healthy foods, among other societal issues—are significant contributors to this disparity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hypertension (high blood pressure), if uncontrolled in African Americans, can significantly increase their risk of heart disease and stroke. Irreversible heart damage can even lead to sudden death. That’s why early screening for heart disease is crucial for promoting longevity and overall health among this population. Knowing your family history of heart disease is vital. Younger African Americans are developing some form of heart disease.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Heart attacks can be seen differently in many patients. Some people will experience tightness between their shoulders, pain in their arms or chest, and pain in their upper abdomen. The key to surviving a heart attack is knowledge. They are knowing the symptoms of a heart attack, not being alone, being with someone who knows CPR, and understanding heart disease risk factors.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Interestingly, despite smoking about the same amount as other racial and ethnic groups, African Americans have an increased risk for cancer deaths overall. Unfortunately, the survival rate following a 5-year diagnosis is lower for African Americans and they are likely to be diagnosed with all cancers at a later disease stage. This makes it more difficult to treat cancer, mainly if it has already spread to other parts of the body.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To address this issue, it is crucial to inform African Americans that many cancers are preventable. Healthcare providers should make cancer prevention information a standard part of their care plan during every visit. Community engagement is also essential for educating African Americans about their health. Churches are a common place for educating African Americans about their health and they can be used as a platform to share information about cancer prevention. Limiting alcohol use, maintaining a healthy weight, and staying away from tobacco can lower cancer risk. Additionally, committing to regular diagnostic screening for cancer is another way to catch cancer early.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sixty percent of African Americans are more likely to be diagnosed with diabetes than white Americans. It is essential to be aware of the risks associated with diabetes, especially for African Americans who are more likely to receive a diabetes diagnosis than white Americans. Diabetes can lead to a narrowing and hardening of blood vessels, which can cause serious complications such as stroke and heart disease. However, some steps can be taken to manage diabetes and reduce the risk of complications such as adopting a healthy diet, engaging in regular exercise, and being knowledgeable about the symptoms of diabetes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Obesity has a disproportionate impact on African Americans. This condition of being overweight can lead to hypertension, diabetes, and high levels of cholesterol in the blood, all of which can have serious health consequences. Food deserts contribute to this issue, as people may not have access to healthy food options. Additionally, a lack of exercise and understanding of the value of physical activity can contribute to obesity as well. Raising awareness about these issues and promoting healthy habits is essential to improve the African American community’s overall health and well-being.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sexually transmitted infections are another high-risk health behavior that has been shown to impact life expectancy among African Americans. Therefore, it is recommended that health screening programs in the community and church activities be initiated where the entire family is present. Health prevention strategies and safe sex practices should be taught at every opportunity with individual patients and families during community events and at churches. It is unfortunate but true that sexually transmitted infections (STIs) can have a significant impact on the life expectancy of African Americans. It is essential to practice safe sex and get tested regularly to prevent the spread of STIs and maintain good health.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many foods that African Americans consumed were called “soul foods.” African Americans commonly used this term to describe the foods they enjoyed from their African homeland and later became staples of the American culture. Many of the fruits and vegetables from Africa grew well in America so the enslaved Africans planted them. America is known as the “melting pot,” and many foods from new and old American crops and European and Native American cultures have influenced African food preparation traditions. The cuisine became known as “soul food.” African Americans had to adapt to the foods/spices that were available and therefore compromised on some nutritional properties that is referred to as unhealthy dietary patterns.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A large majority of these unhealthy adaptations have persisted through many generations of African Americans which contributed to the chronic diseases that are present in African Americans today. Today’s foods originated from the south (New Orleans, LA.) which contained okra and was used in gumbo.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The story of the heirloom rice has been lost to history—the rice, which was grown in the Southern uplands after it was brought from West Africa more than 200 years ago, disappeared from the South by World War I in large part because black farmers who grew it found themselves pushed from the lands they farmed. The rice’s legacy in the United States was erased like so many other contributions that the millions of enslaved African Americans made to southern history, culture, and, of course, cuisine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many of the deviations from African food preparation practices decreased nutritional value. They consumed meat and parts of vegetables that Americans did not want. These foods were frequently called “scraps” (fat trimmed from meats, animal organ meat, liver, gizzards, pig intestines, etc.). Some green leafy vegetables had bulbs that were boiled/seasoned to provide a substance that was filling to them and diminished hunger. Yams were a staple in the African culture and can be prepared in various ways. Sweet potatoes and yams are different. Sweet potatoes are primarily used to make pies. They are baked, boiled, and seasoned with extra sugar and butter which can be very filling but is unhealthy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rice and wheat were challenging to grow in some areas (because they were pushed from their farms). The enslaved Africans preferred foods such as millet, sorghum, and cereal grain plants rich in nutrition. Millet and sorghum lacked gluten and unleavened substances and were called “flatbread.” Hot water cornbread originated from these products and was used to scoop up food which replaced utensils. Early African Americans used their fingers to eat food because enslaved individuals were forbidden to use utensils for cooking and eating. They were afraid they would use them as weapons.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Nutrition is a critical social issue as well as a cultural tradition. African Americans came from a rich history of creating cuisine that had great taste and has transformed into the idea of food that promoted health and healing. Access to healthy, affordable, and culturally significant foods for African Americans is now a means for helping them to become healthier and more productive within their communities. Since the Black Panther days (in the 1960s), lack of access to fresh and nutritious foods has become a social justice issue. They believed African Americans (Blacks) had a right to food and started the first “Feed the Children Breakfast Movement “in Los Angeles, CA.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although many African Americans view access to food as a right, the lack of access for some people below the poverty level remains an issue. To minimize this problem, people plant gardens, plant seeds in flowerpots, get food from food pantries and receive food stamps to purchase fresh fruits, vegetables, meats, and dairy products.</para>
                  <para role="Para">Other sources may include food pantries/voluntary groups in which donated foods are free. Hunger and chronic diseases are never-ending problems for most Americans. However, political parties struggle to provide food to those in poverty. Republicans would abolish this measure if they could garner political support.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African American women’s preparations for childbirth come from a long history of older women teaching their young girls how to be wives and mothers. This teaching comes from the biblical influence of older women who teach and set an example for younger women <emphasis>(Titus 2:4–5). “The older women teach the younger women to be sober, love their husbands, and their children.”</emphasis> Also, refraining from premarital sex, although not often followed, is one of the many guidelines that African Americans regard as an essential rule to follow to avoid becoming pregnant. Women who live in poverty usually feel they are unable to prevent pregnancy and or see this to procure food and better living conditions through support from the government or the father of the child. They may also experience low self-esteem and surrender to the male who promises to care for them. Over the last two decades, African American women have become more independent and open to being a single parent and perceptions of what others think of them have fallen by the wayside.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African American females rarely seek abortions. Biblical and societal teachings guide the moral compass in deciding to abort a child. Biblical beliefs are that one is killing a human being, which is one of the great sins against God. “Thou shall not kill” is the sixth commandment of God. When others find out they aborted a child, family and community members will view abortion as shameful for the family. However, over the past decade, abortions have increased in the African American population, accounting for 39% of abortions nationally.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Preparing for childbirth is a celebrated time in life for most African American women. The new mother transitions from being obsessed with herself to being obsessed with caring for her child. This transition is an essential phase of maturity and a significant motherhood priority.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In recent years, African American women have become more comfortable in preventing pregnancy by taking oral contraceptives. However, contraceptives are known to serve as precursors for developing breast, ovarian, and uterine cancers. And for that reason, they only take them for a short time until they feel ready to have a baby.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Once a young woman becomes pregnant, the African American family is thrilled that a new member will join them. However, depending on the age of the female, it may be perceived as an adverse event if the person is less than 18 years of age, unmarried, financially poor, and in a less-than-optimal environment to rear a child. Nevertheless, older African American women remain close to advising and assisting the expectant mother.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The family network guides many of the childbirth practices. The grandmother (if still alive) is the most influential, followed by the mother and other females who have had a child. Grandma dictates the daily routines, including eating healthy foods and drinking plenty of water. Over many decades, the baby has been believed to dictate what the mother should eat. Cravings for pickles, ice cream, corn starch, and nonfood-white clay (an “iffy today”). Eating clay in substantial amounts can cause constipation and dirt may be contaminated with pollutants from chemical plants and waste disposal systems; this practice has diminished in the culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Preparing for the child’s arrival is another essential and fun activity. The sex of the child determines what items may be purchased. Decorating the baby’s room and buying clothes and other care items follows a specific color scheme.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Very little information is documented in the literature about African American women‘s preparation for childbirth. Most often, they are made to feel marginalized and stereotyped because of the racism against them. So, their perspective on preparing for childbirth is based on what they see Caucasian women do. Participating in childbirth classes is also one of the things only a few of them join in due to a lack of funds and other activities that leave very little time to do so.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The ideas and rituals of African Americans about death stem from their Christian education and beliefs about God the Father and Creator of all humanity. Most have affiliations with Baptist, Methodist, Catholic, and Muslim churches and beliefs with <emphasis role="bold">Baptist and Methodist being the most preferred</emphasis>. Baptists and Methodists have the same spiritual beliefs; however, their organizational structures/processes may differ. Others may not be members of either of the traditional spiritualities. It is also believed that life does not end when death occurs. The decedent transitions to another phase of life, waiting to be awakened again to live in Heaven or hell.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans display their emotions/feelings upon hearing about the death of a loved one by fainting or lowering their bodies to sit on the floor or chair and, most often, crying out loud. This emotional response to the death may not require medical attention. However, if the family member has a medical condition when a severe emotional reaction occurs, they may need medical attention. Episodes of crying/grieving that can last for an undetermined amount of time. Some people don’t show their grief in public, which can sometimes result in a severely mentally delayed response, requiring treatment. Family members may need education and counseling at any time following the death of family members or friends.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African American families have a variety of rituals that comprise their way of mourning and grieving for their loved ones. The death and burial of a family member do not end the connection with that person. And it is not just a funeral, but rather a “homegoing.” The dead person is believed to have returned home to God, the Father and Creator of life. Most quote the scripture: “We are confident, I say and willing, to be absent from the body is to be present with the Lord (II Corinthians 5:8). When the person dies, their physical body should be buried but the soul returns to God. It is believed that when Jesus Christ, the Son of God, returns, the physical body and the soul will be joined together and be transformed to look like Jesus Christ. They also believe that the body should be kept intact and embalmed for preservation and are less likely to volunteer as an organ donor. Some situations require autopsies to be performed for legal reasons<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis> Family members will need education on rationales for autopsies. However, the family sometimes requests autopsies if they believe something went wrong during hospitalization or foul play. Understanding “why” the decedent can no longer live ushers in closure and acceptance of their demise.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans don’t rush to bury their loved ones. The funeral is customarily held within 7 days after death. They give family members and friends time to prepare for the funeral. COVID-19 pandemic deaths from 2020 to 2022 changed this practice because Mortuaries were overloaded with many deaths, and funerals were scheduled as far out as 2–3 weeks.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is a variation in what occurs during the “homegoing celebration.” The ceremony must reflect the love and emotions of the family members. So, they select the most elaborate casket and floral arrangements and plan the homegoing celebration to provide a healing and calming effect to the family. It also communicates love and respect for the decedent. The most significant pain associated with loss can last for a while. Still, the homegoing celebration brings closure to the fact that the decedent is in a better place and no longer suffers, which lessens the pain.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The actual homegoing celebration follows a specific cultural order. The processional order follows in a two-by-two fashion: the Minister, Church Leaders, Pallbearers, Family (the closest relative is first in line), and all others follow.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The casket is usually left open for attendees to view the decedent before the service begins. Persons in the processional may view the decedent as they come in and sit down. Once everyone has entered the chapel, the casket is closed. The casket is usually not left open unless it is a graveside service but may be opened upon request.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The order of the funeral service is culturally driven. It is as follows: musical prelude, processional, scriptures for the Old and New Testaments (read by a minister), prayer, a song by the choir or soloist and words of the song encouraging family/friends or it may provoke public display of grief. The obituary is read in silence. Special tributes by family/friends and coworkers or a video presentation of the decedent’s life may be displayed. A church member reads the resolution. The choir or soloist performs another song. The Pastor eulogizes the deceased. At the end of the service, the Recessional allows the persons in the processional and attendees to leave the church in the same order as they entered the church.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The descendant’s casket is moved to the burial site in a processional style consisting of a fleet of cars. The burial site may be in the ground or a mausoleum, symbolizing that the body has been returned to the Earth. Cremations have increased and the ashes are contained in a pleasant urn and are given to the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The repast is when family and friends gather to remember, reflect, and rejoice in positivity, strength, and support. It focuses on food and fellowship, which signifies the realization of life anew for their loved one without the physical presence of the decedent.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most African Americans (Blacks) identify as Christians from religious traditions or beliefs. Most worshippers see the role of religion in fighting racial injustice and gaining respect within society. This belief is changing as racial and injustice events continue to occur. The younger generation views it as a way to fight back and gain equality/equity and respect for diversity through nonviolent events. They are less likely to grow up in mostly Black congregations. Three percent of black Americans identify as atheists or agnostics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fifteen attributes of God encourage African Americans to believe in God’s deity, to serve Him, and to believe they will eventually return to Him in heaven.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">They believe in the attributes of God with earthly affairs and three dimensions of deity: God the Father (resides in Heaven), the Son (resides in Heaven but walked the earth for 33 years and is now residing in Heaven)<emphasis role="bold">,</emphasis> and the Holy Spirit (reside in each believer and is on earth). God presents as an apparition of a human being (ghost-like), but man is not allowed to look upon Him, or he will die. The Trinity, as it is called, has 15 attributes: (1) God is infinite, self exists and without origin (all three forms of God exist from the beginning of time), (2) God is immutable—He never changes, (3) God is self-sufficient—He has no needs, (4) God is Omnipotent—He is all-powerful, (5) God is Omniscient—He is all-knowing, (6) God is Omnipresent—He is always everywhere, (7) God is Wise—He is perfect, unchanging wisdom, (8) God is Faithful—He is infinitely and unchangingly true, (9) God is Good<emphasis role="bold">—</emphasis>He is infinitely, unchangingly, kind, and full of Good Will, (10) God is Just—He is infinitely, unchangeably right, and perfect in All He does, (11) God is Merciful—He is infinitely, unchangeably compassionate and kind. (12) God is Gracious—Infinitely inclined to spare the guilty, (13) God is Loving<emphasis role="bold">-</emphasis>God is infinitely unchanging and loves humans, (14) God is Holy—He is infinitely, unchangingly perfect, (15) God is Glorious—He is infinitely beautiful and great. These attributes have shaped the moral compass for medicine, nursing, and other business operations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Son was conceived by the works of the Holy Spirit overcoming Mary, not by a human being. Jesus presented Himself as a human without sin. The Holy Spirit is the third dimension of God, who resides on earth (in each believer) to comfort and serve as man’s consciousness to do good in life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Regarding Christian affiliation, most African Americans affiliate with Baptist and Methodist denominations. Other religious denominations include African Episcopal, Jehovah’s Witness, Church of God in Christ, Seventh Day Adventist, Pentecostal, Apostolic, Presbyterian, Lutheran, Roman Catholic, Nation of Islam, and other Islamic sectors. Determine the religious affiliation during the intake interview and respecting their beliefs is prudent.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most people take their spiritual beliefs seriously and expect to receive messages through preaching, prayer, and waiting on God’s providential intervention. Speaking in tongues is primarily done in the Church of Christ congregations. Baptist churches adhere to the biblical scripture that says if a person speaks in a tongue, it must be to God or where two or at most three persons are present. Also, there must be someone who can interpret it. The Holy Spirit will give them an utterance. If not, the person speaks to himself and not God. If there is no interpreter, he builds himself up, not the church, because no one understands what is being said.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Prayer is an essential part of their daily routines. It gives them hope and belief that God will be with them and see them through tough times. He may not remove the current situation but will strengthen them to overcome it. Support and allow time for praying for individuals who desire to do so.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Laying on hands while praying to facilitate healing is discouraged in today’s church practices. Biblical teachings explain that healing occurs through God’s divine interventions by answering the person’s prayer. Healing does not come from the person who touches the sick. It is a symbol of God touching the sick. Healing is also facilitated by trained groups who are considered an extension of God or His chosen people to perform interventions that promote healing. This healing process can be explained by scientific knowledge. But remember, there are still miraculous healings that no one can explain. The reaction is, “Oh, but God.” This phrase does not mean that individuals do not care about their health or are unwilling to practice illness-prevention measures. Sickness can occur through heredity and exposure to agents present in the environment. Recognize and support spiritual beliefs and practices that provide comfort, coping, and support.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Since biblical times, illness has represented sin. However, in current society, biblical teachings of this belief are supported by scriptures that say sinful acts can cause their family to experience an illness over many generations. Jesus healed the sick when He was present on earth, and He explained that some were not sick because of sin and did not provide a reason. His concern was to demonstrate His powers through healing. Partnering with hospital chaplains or community church clergy is an excellent strategy to promote the patient’s beliefs about healing. Most churches have healthcare ministries and emergency response teams to encourage a healthy lifestyle through preventive education.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practice</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Healthcare practices among African Americans have changed over the past decade. Many improvements have been achieved by increasing access to care, making insurance more affordable, maximizing government insurance coverage (Medicare/Medicaid), increasing outpatient clinics in rural areas, increasing nurse practitioner clinics, telehealth medicine, and collaborative practices with family practice physicians. Therefore, better access means people can seek healthcare more often when needed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although African Americans continue to have suspicions about healthcare providers, it has improved over the past two decades. The reasons are that more information about the best healthcare screenings, diagnosis, and treatment is available via television, online, mailing reminders, community health fairs, health fairs at Black churches, healthcare ministries, and family support. Much emphasis has been placed on the most common health problems in the Black patient population, so preventive, maintenance, and treatment guidelines are readily available to patients via online and medical offices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans most often experience more than two chronic illnesses simultaneously. This usually creates a stressful situation regarding the cost of medical care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thirty percent of African Americans believe that their health is dependent upon fate or destiny, and only about 50% feel that health is a high priority. Reception and utilization of health information are well-known significant factors in disease prevention.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sometimes African Americans are less likely to follow prescribed medication directions due to a lack of understanding of how medications work and the importance of taking them for a specified time to control or cure medical disorders. For example, when prescribed antihypertensives, the individual may stop taking the medication as soon as the blood pressure normalizes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans are sometimes reluctant to follow prescribed medication regimes related to unwillingness to tolerate side effects. For example, men usually deviate from prescribed directions when taking antihypertensives because of decreased libido and sexual functioning. More and more of them are beginning to take this matter more seriously due to the number of heart attacks that occur among family members. Unlike any other tactic, this phenomenon will likely make believers out of them. This has been the number one thing that increased their participation in getting annual physical exams. Ask about the family history of diseases commonly occurring in their family and encourage them to seek screening, preventive care, and medical treatment as early as possible.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although access to healthcare has improved among African Americans, sharing medications is a common practice among males and females. For example, blood pressure medications, prescribed analgesics, and antibiotics are frequently given to people with similar complaints, especially if they forget to take their medications or are experiencing symptoms. They are also likely to discontinue medications once the discomforts subside. This habit could explain why some diseases become resistant to treatment or worsen. Discourage patients from sharing medications because they can be more dangerous and cause side effects in one person that may not occur in another.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">African Americans once believed that some diseases/ailments caused by unnatural forces could not be mitigated by routine medical procedures and resorted to seeking help from Voo Doo doctors or people who practiced witchcraft. However, since many people who grew up being exposed to these practices have died, much of this philosophy and belief has been lost.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Homeopathic medical care has been around for years since the enslaved populations. They did not have access to medical care and, therefore, had to use whatever was thought to relieve discomfort. For example, a paste of clay and vinegar treated cuts and injuries from rusty metals. Some of these practices remain in use today when someone cannot afford healthcare.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Apple cider vinegar is used to treat other health conditions. African American women frequently use apple cider vinegar to treat yeast infections and vaginal irritations. Most African Americans, male and female, believe apple cider vinegar can control high blood pressure by mixing a teaspoon of vinegar in a small amount of water. Vinegar mixed with sugar, lemon, and honey is used for weight loss. White vinegar is often used to treat skin irritations and discomforts.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Baking soda, mixed in water, is ingested to treat indigestion or stomachache. Some people mix baking soda, syrup of Black Draught, aspirin, or vinegar. It is also used topically to relieve skin irritations such as burns, insect bites, and rashes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lemons frequently treat sore throat, colds, and flu-like symptoms. They boil the lemons to make tea by adding honey and peppermint. Some gargle to relieve symptoms and others suck on a slice of lemon. Mixing lemon and syrup is also used as a cough syrup and is believed to be as effective as commercial cough syrup. Any combination of these ingredients is believed to relieve symptoms of a cold.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Salt is used primarily as a topical agent to treat mouth, throat, and sinus tissues. Commercial products using salt are available to treat sinusitis. Salt mixed with water is also used to treat bleeding gums, sore throats, and mouth sores after dental procedures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental health issues have existed in the African American patient population. However, their perspective of mental health stigmatizes their existence. It is a significant reminder of being made to feel “less than” and is a reminder of the effects of racism (limited mobility and progress). They do not trust the healthcare system for fear of being put away and deprived of a “normal life.” Also, there is a fear of being abused by family members and caregivers. Encourage patients and family members to seek professional help as soon as possible. Select a family member the patient trusts to engage in therapy and care.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0004s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">4.1.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Black Americans have mixed ideas about the progress made in improving healthcare experiences and outcomes for Black patients. Forty-seven percent say it has been enhanced over the last 20 years, 31% say it stayed about the same, and 20% feel it is worse.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When asked about their personal experiences, about 55% said they had a positive experience. They contribute to better care by speaking up and advocating for appropriate treatment. Still, there are perceptions of being treated with less respect than other patients.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Social determinates contributing to lower quality health outcomes include less access to quality care, living in communities with more environmental problems, healthcare providers being more likely to provide advanced care, working in jobs with risks for health problems, hospitals, and medical centers giving lower priorities to well-being, and more communication issues such as language and cultural differences.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although most African Americans say healthcare has improved overall, there are some negative aspects to interacting with providers. Examples include having to speak up and ask for care, the pain they were experiencing not being taken seriously, feeling rushed by healthcare providers, feeling they were treated with less respect, and feeling they received lower quality of care. They were looked down on because of their weight.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Black adults with higher education are more likely to point to healthcare disparities than those with lower educational levels.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thirty-one percent of Blacks prefer to see black providers, 14% somewhat prefer, and 17% see a black doctor or other healthcare provider for routine health care. Encourage patients to discuss their concerns with healthcare providers. If they continue to feel uncomfortable when interacting with the provider, they can choose to find someone else.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
