<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0010s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">China is the second most populous country in Asia and the second most populous country in the world, with a population of 1.409 billion, dispersed over 3.7 million square miles of land (Wikipedia <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0010s0003bib11">2024</link>
            </emphasis>). Ninety-two percent of the population is Han; the remaining 8% is a mixture of 56 different nationalities, religions, and ethnic groups. Chinese people who live in the “Chinatowns” in the United States maintain many of their cultural beliefs and values and insist that health-care providers respect these values and beliefs with their interventions. In the United States, over two million people identify themselves as Chinese, with the largest communities residing in California, New York, Hawaii, and Texas. This aggregate profile of Chinese in the United States may not fit any one person due to individuality, acculturation, and other variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">A university education is highly valued; however, few have the opportunity to achieve this life goal because of limited enrollment opportunities. Often, young adults come to Western countries to attend universities seeking more advanced prestigious educations. Many newer immigrants are professionals from Hong Kong who moved to Canada, the United States, and other Western countries to avoid the repatriation in 1997.</para>
         <para role="Para">Ideals based on the teachings of Confucius play an important part in their values and beliefs, emphasize the importance of family, and reinforce the idea that all relationships embody power and rule. Other important values are filial piety, industry, patriotism, deference to those in hierarchal positions, tolerance of others, loyalty to superiors, respect for rites and social rituals, knowledge, benevolent authority, thrift, patience, courtesy, and respect for tradition.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The official language of China is Mandarin (<emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">pu tong hua</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>), which is spoken by about 70% of the population. Other distinct dialects such as Cantonese, Fujianese, Shanghainese, Toishanese, and Hunanese are so different that often two groups cannot understand one another verbally. However, the written language is the same throughout the country, and consists of over 50,000 ideographs (about 5000 common ones).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">If unable to obtain a dialect-specific interpreter, the interpreter should try writing the question.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Chinese people speak in a moderate to low voice tone and consider Americans to be loud. <emphasis role="bold">Be cautious about tone of voice when interacting with Chinese patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When asked whether they understand what was just said, the Chinese invariably answer yes to avoid loss of face. <emphasis role="bold">Obtain information in a manner that does not require a “yes” or “no” answer.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Negative queries are difficult to understand. <emphasis role="bold">Place instructions in a specific order, such as “First, at nine o’clock every morning get the medicine bottle. Second, take two tablets out of the bottle. Third, get your warm water. Fourth, swallow the pills with the water.”</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not use complex sentences with “ands” and “buts.” Have patients demonstrate instructions to ensure that they are understood.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Despite their reputation for not openly displaying emotion with strangers, among family and friends they are open and demonstrative. The Chinese share information freely once a trusting relationship has developed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals maintain a formal distance with each other as a form of respect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When touching is necessary, provide an explanation and ask permission.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Chinese people are uncomfortable with face-to-face communications, especially when there is direct eye contact. Most prefer to sit next to others. <emphasis role="bold">Arrange seating to promote positive communication.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Titles are important to Chinese people. The family name is stated first and then the given name. Calling an individual by any name except his/her family name is impolite.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women do not use their husband’s name after they get married. Therefore, unless the woman is from Hong Kong or Taiwan or has lived in a Western country for a long time, do not assume that her last name is the same as her husband’s. Her family name comes first, followed by her given names and finally by her title. Many take an English name as an additional given name because Chinese names are often difficult for Westerners to pronounce. Some give permission to use only the English name. In addition, some switch the order of their names to be the same as those of Westerners, with the family name last. This practice can be confusing. <emphasis role="bold">Ask the patient which is his/her family name and which is the given name. Address patients by their family name and title. Ask persons how they wish to be addressed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Kinship has traditionally been organized around the male lines. Each family maintains a recognized head who has great authority and assumes all major responsibilities for the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Chinese culture, based on Confucianism, is known for its patriarchal traditions. Traditionally, women have often taken on the role of homemakers, overseeing all domestic responsibilities, while husbands have assumed the roles of family leaders and primary breadwinners (Zhong and Guo <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0003bib16">2018</link>
                     </emphasis>). In recent times, some men include housework, cooking, and cleaning as their responsibilities when their spouses work. Most believe that the family is most important and, thus, each family member assumes changes in roles to achieve this harmony.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are highly valued in China because of the government’s past mandate that each married couple may only have one child, although there are exceptions to this rule: e.g., if the first born is a female in rural areas or where the only child of a couple is disabled or dies in infancy. Resources are lavished on the child. Independence is not fostered. The entire family makes decisions for the child even into young adulthood.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children born in Western countries tend to adopt the Western culture easily while their parents and grandparents may to maintain traditional Chinese culture in varying degrees. Adolescents maintain their respect for elders even when they disagree with them. Teenagers value a strong and happy family life and seldom do things that jeopardize that unanimity. Adolescents question affairs of life and make great efforts to see at least two sides of every issue.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children feel pressure to succeed to help improve the future of the family; thus, most children and adolescents value studying over playing and peer relationships. Children are taught to curb their expression of feelings because individuals who do not stand out are successful. <emphasis role="bold">With an increase in cultural adaptation, children are becoming more outspoken, and they engage in more reading of media from the Western world, as well as watching television and movies.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The perception of family is developed through the concept of relationships. Each person is identified in relation to others in the family. The individual is not lost, just defined differently from individuals in Western cultures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Young men and women enter the workforce immediately after high school if they are unable to continue their education. Many continue to live with their parents and contribute to the family even after marriage (in their 20 s) and the birth of a child (in their 30 s).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Extended families are important. Children may live with their grandparents or aunts and uncles so individual family members can obtain a better education or reduce financial burdens.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Teenage pregnancy is not common among the Chinese but it is increasing among Chinese in America.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older people are venerated and viewed as very wise. Children are expected to care for their parents when self-care becomes a concern; in China, law mandates this.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When Chinese immigrants need additional assistance, call on local Chinese organizations to obtain help.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Maintaining reputation is accomplished by adhering to the rules of society. True equality does not exist in the Chinese mind; if more than one person is in power, then consensus is important. If the person in power is not present at decision making meetings, barriers are raised, and any decisions made are negated unless the person in power agrees. <emphasis role="bold">Ensure that key decision-makers within the family attend patient conferences or other times when health-care decisions need to be made.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The word for “privacy” in Chinese has a negative connotation and means something underhanded, secret, and furtive. People grow up in crowded conditions; they live and work in small areas. The value of group support does not place a high value on privacy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Offer to make arrangements for the family to remain with the patient 24 h a day if needed.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Chinese may ask many personal questions about salary, life at home, age, and children. Refusal to answer personal questions is accepted as long as it is done with care and feeling. The one subject that is taboo is sex and anything related to sex. This may create a barrier for a Western health-care provider who is trying to assess a Chinese patient with sexuality concerns. <emphasis role="bold">Approach issues of sexuality tactfully and indirectly and only after trust is obtained.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In China, homosexuality has been legal since 1997. In 2019, same-sex marriage officially became legal in Taiwan (Executive Yuan <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0003bib15">2022</link>
                     </emphasis>), making it the first country in Asia and the 27th country in the world to recognize same-sex marriage. This granted equal marriage rights to both same-sex and heterosexual couples. However, the LGBT community still faces stigmatization in society, with gay relationships largely criticized at the national level and continuing to bear a stigma. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Chinese adapt to the culture in the workplace quickly. They frequently call on other Chinese people to teach them and to discuss how to fit into the new culture more quickly. <emphasis role="bold">Assign a Chinese as a mentor if available.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Chinese are accustomed to giving co-workers small gifts of appreciation for helping them acculturate and adapt to the American workforce. Often, Americans seek opportunities to reciprocate with a gift, such as at a birthday party, farewell party, or other occasion. Some gifts are not appropriate. <emphasis role="bold">Do not give gifts that are culturally inappropriate; for example, giving an umbrella means that you wish to have the recipient’s family dispersed; giving a gift that is white in color or wrapped in white could be interpreted as meaning the giver wishes the recipient dead; and giving a clock could be interpreted as never wanting to see the person again or wishing the person’s life to end. If other Chinese are available, seek their advice for gift giving.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Autonomy is limited and is based on functioning for the good of the group. When a situation arises that requires independent decision making, many times the Chinese know what should be done but do not take action until the leader or superior gives permission.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Teach the U. S. expectations for assertiveness and autonomy to Chinese employees.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Language may be a barrier for some Chinese. The Chinese language does not have verbs that denote tense, as in Western languages. Intonation in Chinese is in the words themselves, rather than in the sentence. Chinese people who have taken English lessons can usually read and write English competently, but they may have difficulty in understanding and speaking it. <emphasis role="bold">Ask for a demonstration of the activity to ensure understanding.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Chinese speak in a moderate to low voice tone and consider Americans to be loud. <emphasis role="bold">Be cautious about tone of voice when interacting with Chinese employees.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When asked whether they understand what was just said, the Chinese invariably answer yes to avoid loss of face. <emphasis role="bold">Collect information in a manner that cannot be answered with a “yes” or “no” answer.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Negative queries are difficult to understand. <emphasis role="bold">Place instructions in a specific order such as “First, gather your supplies.” Second, explain the procedure, etc. Do not use complex sentences with “ands” and “buts.” Have employees demonstrate instructions to ensure that they are understood.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Skin color among Chinese is varied. Many have skin color with pink undertones; some have yellow tones, and others are very dark. Hair is generally black and straight, but some have naturally curly hair. Most men do not have much facial or chest hair.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mongolian spots—dark bluish spots over the lower back and buttocks—are present in about 80% of infants.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Bilirubin levels are usually higher in Chinese newborns, with the highest levels occurring on the fifth or sixth day after birth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The ulna is longer than the radius. Hip measurements are significantly smaller than Westerners (Seidel et al. <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0003bib08">1994</link>
                     </emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">Provide instruction on adequate calcium consumption to prevent osteoporosis and fractures. Ensure diet is low in lactose. Assess patients for genetic conditions before medications are prescribed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Rh-negative blood group is rare.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poor metabolism of mephenytoin occurs in 15–20% of Chinese. Sensitivity to beta blockers, such as propranolol, is evidenced by a decrease in overall blood levels accompanied by a more profound response. Atropine sensitivity is evidenced by an increased heart rate. Increased responses to antidepressants and neuroleptics occur at lower doses. Analgesics have been found to cause increased gastrointestinal side effects, despite a decreased sensitivity to them. Chinese people generally have an increased sensitivity to the effects of alcohol (Levy <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0003bib05">1993</link>
                     </emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">Carefully monitor Chinese patients on medications such as propranolol, atropine, antidepressants, and neuroleptics.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0001ta01">10.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists the commonly occurring health conditions for Chinese in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0010s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 10.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to people of Chinese heritage</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactose intolerance</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis B</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pancreatic cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Nasopharyngeal cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle, unknown?</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis B</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Smoking is a high-risk behavior for many men and teenagers. <emphasis role="bold">Partner with schools to teach hazards of smoking and substance misuse.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Chinese women do not smoke, but recently the numbers Chinese women who smoke is increasing among males, as much as 68% smoke. <emphasis role="bold">Screen newer immigrants for smoking-related health conditions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food habits are important, and food is offered to guests at any time of the day or night. Foods served at meals have a specific order, with a focus on a balance for a healthy body.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The typical diet is difficult to describe; each region in China has its own traditional diet. Traditional Chinese medicine frequently uses food and food derivatives to prevent and cure diseases and illnesses and to increase strength in weak and older people.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Peanuts and soybeans are popular. Common grains include wheat, sorghum, and maize (a type of corn). Rice is usually steamed but can be fried with eggs, vegetables, and meats as well. Many Chinese eat beans or noodles instead of rice. Meat choices include pork (the most common), chicken, beef, duck, shrimp, fish, scallops, and mussels. Tofu, an excellent source of protein, is a staple of the Chinese diet and is fried, boiled, or served cold like ice cream. Bean products are another source of protein. Many desserts or sweets are prepared with red beans.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fruits and vegetables may be peeled and eaten raw. Vegetables are lightly stir-fried in oil with salt and spice. Salt, oil, and oil products are important parts of the Chinese diet. Their healthy selection of green vegetables limits the incidence of calcium deficiencies.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Drinks with dinner include tea, soft drinks, juice, and beer. Foreign-born and older people may not like ice in their drinks. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients if they want ice in their drinks.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Foods that are considered <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">yin</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> and <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">yang</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> prevent sudden imbalances and indigestion. A balanced diet is considered essential for physical and emotional harmony. <emphasis role="bold">Provide special instructions regarding risk factors associated with diets that are high in fats and salt.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Chopsticks should never be stuck in the food upright because that is considered bad luck.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Heavy use of salted fish increases the risk for nasopharyngeal, esophageal, and stomach cancers. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage low use of salty fish.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because of the previous “one couple, one child” law in China, abortions are common in China. Most Chinese families see pregnancy as positive and important in the immediate and extended family. Pregnancy is seen as women’s business, although men are beginning to demonstrate an active interest in pregnancy and the welfare of the mother and baby. Women are usually very modest and may insist on a female midwife or obstetrician. Some agree to use a male physician when an emergency arises. <emphasis role="bold">Respect different views on involving men in pregnancy issues.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women usually increase meat in their diets because their blood needs to be stronger for the fetus. Pregnant women may avoid shellfish during the first trimester because it causes allergies. Some may be unwilling to take iron because they believe that it makes the delivery more difficult. <emphasis role="bold">Explain factual necessity about taking iron preparations and dispel myths.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional postpartum care includes 1 month of recovery, with the mother eating foods that decrease the yin (cold) energy. <emphasis role="bold">Ask what foods the mother plans to eat postpartum and dispel myths.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many mothers do not expose themselves to the cold air and do not go outside or bathe for the first month postpartum because cold air can enter the body and cause health problems. Some postpartum women wear many layers of clothes and are covered from head to toe, even in the summer, to keep the air away from their bodies.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Drinking and touching cold water are taboo for women in the postpartum period.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Raw fruits and vegetables are avoided because they are considered “cold” foods. They must be cooked and be warm. Mothers eat 5–6 meals a day with high-nutritional ingredients including rice, soups, and 7–8 eggs. Brown sugar is commonly used because it helps rebuild blood loss. Drinking rice wine is encouraged to increase the mother’s breast-milk production. <emphasis role="bold">Caution mothers that rice wine may prolong the postpartum bleeding time.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death is viewed as a part of the natural cycle of life; some believe that something good happens to them after they die. Death and bereavement traditions are centered on ancestor worship, a form of paying respect. Many believe that their spirits will never rest unless living descendants provide care for the grave and worship the memory of the deceased.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The dead are honored by placing food, money for the person’s spirit, or articles made of paper around the coffin.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The belief that the Chinese greet death with stoicism and fatalism is a myth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The number 4 is considered unlucky because it is pronounced like the Chinese word for death; this is similar to the bad luck associated with the number 13 in many Western societies. The color white is associated with death and is also considered bad luck. Black is a bad luck color. Red is the ultimate good-luck color. Mourners are recognized by black armbands on their left arm and white strips of cloth tied around their heads.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The purchase of life insurance may be avoided because of a fear that it is inviting death.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Chinese do not overtly express emotions to strangers. <emphasis role="bold">Accept and be non-judgmental with a wide range of bereavement practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The main religions in China are Buddhism, Catholicism, Protestantism, Taoism, and Islam. Prayer is generally a source of comfort. Some Chinese people do not acknowledge a religion such as Buddhism, but if they go to a shrine, they burn incense and offer prayers. As immigration increases, many who practice Christian religions have become more visible.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">“Life forces” are sources of strength. These forces come from within the individual, the environment, and the past and the future of the individual and society.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The individual may use meditation, exercise, massage, and prayer. Drugs, herbs, food, good air, and artistic expression may also be used. Good-luck charms are cherished and traditional and nontraditional medicines are used.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The family is usually a source of strength. Individuals draw on family resources and are expected to provide resources to strengthen the family. Resources may be defined as financial, emotional, physical, mental, or spiritual. Calling on ancestors to provide strength as a resource requires giving back to the ancestors when necessary.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the United States, churches play an important role in the local Chinese community by providing support to immigrants, students, scholars, and their families. <emphasis role="bold">Network and partner with churches to provide additional support for Chinese patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">While many Chinese people have made the transition to Western medicine, others maintain their roots in traditional Chinese medicine, and still others practice both types of medicine. Younger people usually do not hesitate to seek allopathic health-care providers when necessary unless they believe that it does not work for them; then they use traditional Chinese medicine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older people may try traditional Chinese medicine first and only seek Western medicine when traditional medicine does not seem to work. Even after seeking Western medical care, older people may continue to practice traditional Chinese medicine in some form. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients in a non-judgmental manner if they are using traditional Chinese medicine. Impress upon them the importance of disclosing all treatments because some may have antagonistic effects.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Chinese medical treatments are discussed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0010s0001ta02">10.2</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Chinese tend to describe their pain in terms of more diverse body symptoms, whereas Westerners tend to describe pain locally. The Western description includes words like “stabbing” and “localized,” whereas the Chinese describe pain as “dull” and more “diffuse.” They tend to use explanations of pain from the traditional Chinese influence of imbalances in the yin and yang combined with location and cause.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Chinese cope with pain by applying oils and massage, using warmth, sleeping on the area of pain, relaxation, and aspirin.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The balance between yin and yang is used to explain mental as well as physical health. Because a stigma is associated with having a family member who is mentally ill, many families initially seek the help of a folk healer. Many Chinese still view mental and physical disabilities as a part of life that should be hidden. Traditionally, an ill person is viewed as passive and accepting of illness. Illness is expected as a part of the life cycle.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many individuals feel uncomfortable touching their own bodies, which may be problematic when they need to provide their own health care, for example, with breast self-examinations and scrotal exams. People of the same sex may use touch if they are close friends or family. Men and women do not touch each other, and even couples who have been married for a long time do not show physical affection in public. Most women feel uncomfortable being touched by male health-care providers and tend to seek female providers. <emphasis role="bold">Always ask permission, and explain the necessity for touching patients during examinations and treatments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families may be reluctant to allow autopsies because of their fear of being “cut up.” Most accept blood transfusions, organ donations, and organ transplants.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0010s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 10.2</emphasis> Traditional Chinese medical treatments</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Traditional Chinese medicine has many facets, including the five basic substances ( <emphasis>qi</emphasis>, energy; <emphasis>xue</emphasis>, blood; <emphasis>jing</emphasis>, essence; <emphasis>shen</emphasis>, spirit; and <emphasis>jing ye</emphasis>, body fluids); the pulses and vessels for the flow of energetic forces ( <emphasis>mai</emphasis>); the energy pathways ( <emphasis>jing</emphasis>); the channels and collaterals, including the 14 meridians for acupuncture, moxibustion, and massage ( <emphasis>jing luo</emphasis>); the organ systems ( <emphasis>zang fu</emphasis>); and the tissues of the bones, tendons, flesh, blood vessels, and skin. The scope of traditional Chinese medicine is vast and should be studied carefully by professionals who provide health care to Chinese patients</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Acupuncture and moxibustion are used in many treatments. Acupuncture is the insertion of needles into precise points along the channel system of flow of the <emphasis>qi</emphasis> called the 14 meridians. The system has over 400 points. Many of the same points can be used in applying pressure (acupressure) and massage (acumassage) to achieve relief from imbalances in the system. The same systems approach is used to produce localized anesthesia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Moxibustion is the application of heat from different sources to various points. For example, one source, such as garlic, is placed on the distal end of the needle after it is inserted through the skin, and the garlic is set on fire. Sometimes the substance is burned directly over the point without a needle insertion. Localized erythema occurs with the heat from the burning substance, and the medicine is absorbed through the skin</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Cupping is another common practice. A heated cup or glass jar is put on the skin creating a vacuum, which causes the skin to be drawn into the cup. The heat that is generated is used to treat joint pain</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Herbal therapy is integral to traditional Chinese medicine. Herbs fall into four categories of energy (cold, hot, warm, and cool), five categories of taste (sour, bitter, sweet, pungent, and salty), and a neutral category. Different methods are used to administer the herbs, including drinking and eating, applying topically, and wearing on the body</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0010s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">10.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Chinese medicine health-care providers are shown great respect by the Chinese. In many instances, they are shown equal, if not more, respect than Western health-care providers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some distrust Western health-care providers because of the pain and invasiveness of their treatments.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older health-care providers receive more respect than younger providers, and men usually receive more respect than women. Physicians receive the highest respect, followed closely by nurses with a university education. Other nurses with limited education are next in the hierarchy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If Chinese patients disagree with the health-care provider, they may not follow instructions. Moreover, they may not verbally confront the health-care provider because they fear that either they or the provider will suffer a loss of face.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
