<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0002s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise</title>
         <para role="Para">Communication is probably the most import aspect of obtaining a good assessment. The onus of effective communication primarily lies with the health-care provider. Thus, providers must understand their own communication styles. When your personal communication practices differ from what is in the scholarly literature, posit why. See the variant cultural characteristics as a guide. Speak to each one of the following points:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify your cultural ancestry. If you have more than one cultural ancestry, chose the one with which you most closely associate.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Explore the willingness of individuals in your culture to share thoughts, feelings, and ideas. Identify any area of discussion that would be considered taboo?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Explore the practice and meaning of touch in your culture. Include information regarding touch between family members, friends, members of the opposite sex, and health-care providers.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify personal spatial and distancing strategies used when communicating with others in your culture. Discuss differences between friends and families versus strangers.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss your culture’s use of eye contact. Include information regarding practices between family members, friends, strangers, and persons of different age groups.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Explore the meaning of gestures and facial expressions in your culture. Do specific gestures or facial expressions have special meanings? How are emotions displayed?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Are there acceptable ways of standing and greeting people in your culture?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss the prevailing temporal relation of your culture. Is the culture’s worldview past, present, or future oriented? Temporality also include punctuality.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss the impact of your culture on your nursing and/or health care. Be specific, not something that is very general.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
   
