<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0023s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">23.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Describe the language and/or dialect spoken by native Jamaicans.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Compare and contrast communication styles between men and women of Jamaican Heritage.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Name two folklore that will identify if a woman is pregnant.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What rituals are displayed and adhered to in the post-partum period of pregnancy?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What scale was used to describe varied skin colors?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>In terms of biological features, the vast majority of Jamaicans fall into what racial category?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Fill in the blank: Currently Jamaicans are experiencing a ______epidemic fueled by changes in diet and behaviors?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What is the most concerning communicable condition which remains a top 10 cause of death in Jamaica?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Jamaicans perceive the meaning of food in ways that extend beyond its nutritional aspect. Many foods are used to treat health conditions and are therefore viewed as medicinal as well. TRUE OR FALSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>List five foods commonly consumed regularly.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Jamaicans have a strong focus on the use of fruits for healing and for wellness. TRUE OR FALSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Vitamin D levels are deficient in as many as half of children under 5 years of age and in roughly a fifth of older children. TRUE OR FALSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Due to cultural beliefs and practices as well as health education limitations, medication adherence is often low among Jamaican patients? TRUE OR FALSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Statistics show that 73% of all Jamaicans self-medicate with plants and herbs with many being home sourced. TRUE OR FALSE</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Jamaicans currently experience how many healthcare systems?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Describe three family values in the Jamaican culture.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss several death rituals and their significance in Jamaican culture.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How is spirituality displayed in the Jamaican culture?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss the use of Patois in the workplace.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify social determinants of healthcare in the rural sector.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Discuss the reason for herbal medicine being the first choice for healthcare in the Jamaican culture.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
