<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are your concerns regarding access and quality care for an Amish family?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>During your assessment of a 60-year-old Amish woman with a breast lump, she reinforces that she does not want to be “cut upon” at her age. What health teaching and advice might you give to her?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How might health-care providers use the Amish values of the three-generational family and their visiting patterns in promoting health in the Amish community?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What elements would you include for an Amish patient wanting to lose weight and prepare healthier meals for her family?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>A 42-year-old Amish woman has just delivered her tenth baby. She tells the nurse that with ten children, she just does not want any more. What approach might the nurse take to discuss contraception with her?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>An Amish family comes to the clinic with a chronically sick 4-year-old boy. They tell you that they have been seeing a folk healer but the child has not improved over the last year. What approach should the nurse take in determining care?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Name at least three common genetic disorders among the Amish. Describe conventional treatment. How might an Amish person react if you encouraged genetic counseling?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Distinguish the terms <emphasis>aagwachse</emphasis>, <emphasis>agnemme</emphasis>, and <emphasis>abwarde</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What language would you use to provide discharge instruction to an Amish family?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What is meant by “warm hands”?</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
