<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0020s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">The number of Iranians in the United States is difficult to determine, with estimates ranging from 400,000 to over one million with half of them living in California. Of the 83 million people living in Iran, over 99% are Muslim. Iranians vary enormously, from highly traditional to highly acculturated, in their reasons for leaving Iran, as well as in the variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>) and individuality. The terms <emphasis>Persian</emphasis> and <emphasis>Iranian</emphasis> are used interchangeably in this chapter because some people call themselves Persian for historical and political reasons. In 1935, the country’s name was changed from Persia to Iran to present an image of progress and in an attempt to unify into one nation the enormous diversity of urban dwellers and rural tribes, ethnic groups, and social classes.</para>
         <para role="Para">Between 1930 and 1970, women were allowed to go unveiled and gained access to university education. After conservative Moslem protests that led to the 1978 violence, martial law was declared and an Islamic government was established. Since then, Iran resembles the more conservative Muslim countries.</para>
         <para role="Para">Iranians are among the most highly educated immigrant group in the United States. Education is greatly valued, and advanced degrees are highly respected. Children are expected to do well in school and to attend college. Many middle-aged physicians, engineers, professors, army generals, and government officials who were unable to find comparable work in the United States have gone into business for themselves. Jobs that require manual labor are not respected, and some cannot accept taking such menial jobs often because of their limited skills in English.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Farsi</emphasis> (Persian) is the national language of Iran. Nearly half the population speaks different languages: Turkish, Kurdish, Armenian, Baluchi, or other Iranian dialects. Well-educated and well-traveled immigrants may speak three or more languages, often using French as a cultural language or English in business settings.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many foreign invasions and strict control by each ensuing government have influenced Iranians’ interaction with outsiders, making them suspicious of foreigners. The disclosure of personal thoughts to strangers is generally perceived to have detrimental consequences. Not verbalizing one’s thoughts is considered a customary and useful defense; overt expressions of emotions to strangers may be culturally stigmatized.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Establish trust before asking questions of a highly personal nature.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among women, patterns of speech may appear restrained or refined to avoid too much self-disclosure or to prevent loss of face. Most women give considerable detail rather than use blunt and succinct messages.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Iranians are very concerned with respectability, a good appearance of the home, and a good reputation. They are embarrassed by financial troubles and even conceal such problems from relatives. <emphasis>Zerangi</emphasis> (cleverness) is valued but only among non-intimates; it means knowing how to manipulate bureaucratic structures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The influence of intimate versus public spheres and hierarchical social relationships is seen clearly in the practice of <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">ta’arof</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (ritual expressed courtesy), which is not practiced with intimates. <emphasis>Ta’arof</emphasis> expresses the public face, with its respectful forms of speech and behavior, and is used when dealing with individuals whose status is unequal to one’s own.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Communication is structured by social hierarchy and varies according to <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">baten</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> and <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">zaher</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>. <emphasis>Baten</emphasis> (inner self) is the true vulnerable self, a collection of freely expressed personal feelings. In contrast, <emphasis>zaher</emphasis> is proper and controlled behavior, a public face to protect and buffer the vulnerable world of the <emphasis>baten</emphasis> within. Silence is used to guard confidential matters and to manage impressions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Iranians refrain from showing anger or other strong emotions to outsiders because self-control is valued; showing anger can produce embarrassment, shame the family, or damage someone’s reputation. To avoid embarrassment and to save face, they may agree or say that they understand an outsider, whether they do or not.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Because politeness and saving face prevail, do not assume that a positive response means a definite “yes.”</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">At the beginning of any health-care encounter, the provider should take time to “warm up” with social conversation if possible before “getting down to business.” Any kind of bad news must be handled carefully by revealing it gently and gradually, in several meetings if possible, or only to the family spokesperson. A person should never be given bad news alone; for example, being informed of a death or serious diagnosis.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among the more traditional, men and women do not hold hands or show affection toward each other in public. However, women often show affection for women and men for men by walking hand in hand or greeting each other with a kiss on each cheek.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Strangers and health-care providers are greeted with both arms held at the sides or with a handshake. A slight bow or nod while shaking hands shows respect. <emphasis role="bold">Offer something, e.g., a prescription, with both hands, shows respect.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Slouching in a chair or stretching one’s legs toward another person is considered offensive. It is considered rude to show the sole of one’s foot. Beckoning is done by waving the fingers with the palm down. <emphasis role="bold">Do not beckon patients; call them formally by name.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Tilting the head up quickly means “no.” Tilting the head to the side means “what?” and tilting it down means “yes.” Extending the thumb (as in “thumbs up”) is considered a vulgar sign. <emphasis role="bold">Refrain from using nonverbal behaviors that may be offensive.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Personal distance is generally closer than that of European Americans. Respect for a provider’s role and education might be demonstrated by keeping a wide distance.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense at patients who stand closer to you than you wish.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals maintain intense eye contact between intimates and equals of the same gender, but the traditional tend to avoid eye contact. Younger people and those of lower status do not sustain eye contact with those they perceive as being older or of higher status.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Temporal relationships are a combination of present and future orientation. <emphasis role="bold">The future orientation enhances the effectiveness of health education.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranians are not clock-watchers; rather, they are mood- and feeling-oriented. While social time is flexible, Iranians meet the expectations for timeliness in work and appointments. <emphasis role="bold">Stress the importance of timeliness for appointments in the United States.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In highly traditional families, privacy demands that husbands do not mention their wife’s first name to other men.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Close friends and children may be called by their first name by family members, but others should not do so. Shaking hands with a child shows respect to the parents.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">A man should wait for a woman to extend her hand first. One is expected to greet every member of the family with a handshake. Heed nonverbal cues when greeting Iranians.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranian culture is patriarchal. The father rules the family and expects obedience and submission from family members. In the father’s absence, the oldest son has authority.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families were traditionally large in Iran, with male children being highly desirable. In more traditional families, older male siblings have the authority to make decisions about younger siblings, even in the father’s presence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Never underestimate the power of this hierarchy or of the family in general in decision-making. Traditional individuals usually cannot or will not make decisions.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men see their role as protecting and providing for the family, managing the finances, and dealing with matters outside the home. Women maintain the home; even working women may place their priorities on the family and home.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In traditional families, both daughters and sons stay at home until married, and in rural areas marriages are often arranged. In the United States, young people are free to select their own marriage partners, but families usually want to approve because of the importance of marriage alliances between families.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are expected to be loyal to their families and behave respectfully toward older people. Manners are considered important even outside the home, where children are expected to be clean, well behaved, and refrain from rowdiness.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Girls are expected to behave and dress more modestly than boys, especially as they approach adolescence. Children and teens are usually included in adult gatherings. Young children are rarely left with babysitters.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Taboo behaviors for teens include smoking, drugs, alcohol, and sex, in that order.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Young women are expected to remain virgins until they marry, but sexual activity by men outside marriage is tolerated.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family members often live close to each other so they can visit whenever possible. Most maintain strong intergenerational involvement with grandmothers, mothers, and children in the domestic sphere and with male family members. <emphasis role="bold">Take advantage of this living situation when health care becomes a concern for Iranians.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranians often remove their shoes at the door and wear slippers. Outside the home, they tend to dress conservatively, but more traditional or religious women avoid bright colors, cover their arms and legs, and conceal their heads with head covers or scarves (<emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">hijab</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>). In Iran, these coverings are mandatory.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Age is a sign of experience, worldliness, and knowledge. Regardless of kinship or relationship, an older person is treated with respect. When grandparents reach an age when they can no longer care for themselves, they live with and are cared for by the family. Caring for older people is an obligation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older and more traditional Iranians may be uncomfortable with unrelated members of the opposite sex. Although divorce is viewed negatively, its rate has been increasing among Iranians in the United States. Cultural mores also advocate ignoring or denying minor marital discord and accepting suffering for the sake of maintaining family stability.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Iran, out-of-wedlock teen pregnancy is neither talked about nor prevalent, and it can have a devastating outcome. If it happens in the United States, it may be taken care of quietly to preserve the face of the family. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose pregnancy outside of marriage to family members.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Homosexuality is highly stigmatized and not discussed; gays and lesbians remain “in the closet.” Since 1979, when the legal and religious systems became synonymous, homosexuality, which is considered unnatural and sacrilegious, has been a capital offense punishable by death. <emphasis role="bold">Do not expose lesbian and gay relationships to family members or others.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranians may perceive and actually experience a degree of bias at work. More acculturated immigrant professionals respond flexibly in the workplace. Most newcomers may not be familiar with American vernacular or slang. <emphasis role="bold">Do not use idiomatic expressions and slang with Iranian employees.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To avoid embarrassment and to save face, they may agree or say that they understand an outsider, whether they do or not. <emphasis role="bold">Because politeness and saving face prevail, do not assume that a positive response means a definite “yes.”</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Personal distance is generally closer than that of Americans or northern Europeans.</para>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense if spatial distancing is closer than what you are accustomed to</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals maintain intense eye contact between intimates and equals of the same gender, but the traditional tend to avoid eye contact. Younger people and those of lower status do not sustain eye contact with those they perceive as being older or of higher status.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that intense eye contact is anger or that avoiding eye contact means that the person is not listening, does not care, or is being less than truthful.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As white Indo-Europeans, coloring ranges from blue or green eyes, light-brown hair, and fair skin to nearly black eyes, black hair, and brown skin. <emphasis role="bold">Because of the variations in skin color, assess jaundice and anemia in Iranians by examining the sclera and oral mucosa rather than by relying solely on skin assessments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0020s0001ta01">20.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Iranians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0002#ch0002">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Screen newer immigrants for cholera, malaria, and parasitic disease. Screen for glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase before administering primaquine. Avoid fava beans, which can cause a hemolytic crisis.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0020s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 20.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Iranians</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Bacterial meningitis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hookworm/parasites</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cholera</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ischemic heart disease</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Birth defects</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hemophilia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dubin-Johnson syndrome</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Smoking is more prevalent in Iran than in the United States among both men and women. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage decreasing or stopping smoking and network with elementary school teachers to teach smoking hazards at a young age.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some alcohol and street-drug misuse occur in the immigrant population, but the rate is no higher than that of the population at large.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alcohol is prohibited by the Qur’an (Holy Book), although many are not religious and drink socially, a few to excess. In some, years of opium use in Iran can create both psychological and physical addiction. Family responses to drug use range from complete support of the family member to disownment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most comply with seat-belt and child-restraint laws, valuing the safety of their children.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food is a symbol of hospitality. Iranian food is flavorful and takes hours to prepare. Presentation is important.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food is classified into two categories, <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">garm</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (hot) and <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">sard</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (cold), which sometimes corresponds to high-calorie and low-calorie foods. The key is balance. At any given table, there is usually a pleasing mixture of foods of different colors and ingredients, composed of a balance of <emphasis>garm</emphasis> and <emphasis>sard</emphasis>. Too much of one category can cause symptoms of being “overheated” or “chilled.” Symptoms are treated by eating food from the opposite group. Becoming overheated, sweating, itching, and rashes may result from eating too many hot foods, such as walnuts, onions, garlic, spices, honey, or candy. The stomach may become chilled, causing dizziness, weakness, and vomiting, after eating too many cold foods, such as grapes, rhubarb, plums, or yogurt. <emphasis role="bold">Seek assistance from family members in selecting foods while in an inpatient facility.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranians prefer to use only the freshest foods, although in some cases cost is a factor in their using some dried herbs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hot tea is the most popular drink among Iranians. The most common starchy foods are rice and wheat bread. Bread is usually baked flat like pita. Corn and potatoes are used but less favored. Beans and legumes, for example, lentils, pinto, mung, kidney, lima and green beans, and split and black-eyed peas make up a fairly high proportion of the dietary intake and are commonly used in rice mixtures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dairy products are dietary staples, particularly eggs, milk, yogurt, and feta cheese as well as dairy by-products, such as <emphasis>doog</emphasis> (yogurt soda) and <emphasis>kashk</emphasis> (milk by-product).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Favorite meats are beef, chicken, fish, and lamb. Shellfish is sometimes eaten. Fresh fruit is always found in Iranian houses.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Green leafy vegetables are used in cooking, and herbs such as parsley, cilantro (coriander), dill, fenugreek, tarragon, mint, savory, and green onions are served fresh at a meal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Islam has a strict set of dietary prescriptions <emphasis>(halal)</emphasis> and proscriptions <emphasis>(haram)</emphasis>. Slaughter of poultry, beef, and lamb must be done ritually to make the meat <emphasis>halal</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">Strict Muslims avoid pork and alcoholic beverages; a few avoid shellfish.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food is eaten with the right hand, and foods or objects are passed with the right hand alone or with both hands. <emphasis role="bold">Make adjustments to accommodate traditional food practices; make provisions for the family to bring food from home if the patient prefers. Incorporate Iranian foods and dietary practices into health teaching to improve compliance with special dietary restrictions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Menstrual blood is believed to be ritually unclean and physically polluting to the body. Menstruating women are not allowed to touch holy objects or to have intercourse. Menstruation is also considered a time of great fragility when a woman should not exercise or shower excessively, because these activities might cause a hemorrhage. At the end of the menses, the woman must wash and purify herself thoroughly before partaking in any religious rituals.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Birth control methods used by Iranians include the pill, intrauterine devices, and natural methods. Vasectomies are beginning to gain acceptance.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A woman’s prestige is at its height when she delivers her first child, particularly if the child is a boy. Delivering the first child gives the young wife a more respected and cherished position with her in-laws. <emphasis role="bold">Providing factual information regarding family planning is one area in which health-care providers can improve family care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food cravings must be satisfied lest a miscarriage occurs from not meeting the fetus’s needs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women avoid fried foods and foods that cause gas; fruits and vegetables are recommended, with special attention to the balance of hot <emphasis>(garm)</emphasis> and cold <emphasis>(sard)</emphasis> foods.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In more traditional families, the father is usually not present at the birth. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make the father feel guilty if he chooses not to be at the delivery.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To strengthen the postpartum woman, a <emphasis>ghorse kamar</emphasis> (a brown, flat disk of dried herbs) is mixed with eggs and placed on her lower back a few hours before bathing.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">New mothers avoid cold water for bathing, ablutions, or cleaning, although they now bathe sooner than the traditional first 30 days.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Baby boys are considered “hotter” than baby girls, and mothers of sons are considered to have hotter bodies, hotter milk, and hotter temperaments than mothers of girls.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mothers of girls are given a mixture of honey and other nutrients, an herbal extract called <emphasis>taranjebin</emphasis>, to raise their bodily heat to ensure that the next child is a boy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some families keep an infant home for the first 40 days, at which time the baby is strong enough to fight off environmental pathogens.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The baby is given a ritual bath between the tenth and 40th days.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask the childbearing family about prescriptive, restrictive, and taboo cultural practices that they customarily follow, and incorporate nonharmful practices.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Muslims may need only a gentle reminder that death is not a termination of life but rather the beginning of a new and better life. <emphasis role="bold">To discuss termination of life support with a practicing Muslim, begin the conversation by noting God’s will for human beings and His power over our destiny, followed by a dialog about life and death as necessary steps toward immortal life in heaven.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some individuals may oppose stopping life support, viewing it as “playing God,” even though they may have no objection to beginning life support, viewing it as the “gift” of medical technology. Some families may demand that strenuous efforts be made to prolong life. <emphasis role="bold">Assess each patient and family individually about life-prolonging medical treatments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among religious Muslims, the deathbed should be turned to face Mecca so family members can read prayers from the Qur’an to ensure that the dying person hears this at the time of death. <emphasis role="bold">Determine the direction of Mecca so that the dying person can face Mecca.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After death, another Muslim should wash the body in a ritual manner, using soap and water and proceeding from head to toe and front to back. All body orifices must be closed and slightly packed with cotton to prevent leakage of bodily fluids (considered unclean). The final rinse is performed with water. The body is then wrapped in a special white cotton shroud. Prayers and verses from the Qur’an are read during the procedure.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">A non-Muslim health-care provider should wear gloves when touching the body.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cremation is not practiced in Iran; it is unlikely to practice in the United States.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">No specific religious rules exist against autopsy. However, the body of the dead is to be respected. <emphasis role="bold">The reason for the autopsy must be made clear, and some may still refuse. Explain legal requirement of autopsy in the</emphasis> United States<emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Iranians may express their grief over the death of a loved one by crying, wailing loudly, or even striking themselves or an object.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Specific Muslim practices include prayers, read in the name of one of the 12 imams, to provide peace of mind or to plead for a miracle. Devout Muslims pray five times daily and need privacy and water for ritual washing. <emphasis role="bold">Assist the patient to make arrangements for praying.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Muslims fast from sunrise to sundown during Ramadan, although pregnant women and the ill are exempt from fasting. <emphasis role="bold">Arrange meals and medications to accommodate Ramadan. See Chap.</emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0008#ch0008">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">
                              <emphasis role="bold">8</emphasis>
                           </emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">for Ramadan celebration dates through 2021.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family relationships and friendships are sources of strength and meaning in life for many individuals. <emphasis role="bold">Adjust visiting policies to accommodate family and friends.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death is not a finalization; rather, it is a graduation to a higher level of being.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional health beliefs and therapeutic processes are a combination of Galenic (humoral), Islamic (sacred), and modern biomedicine. In classic humoral theory, illness arises from an imbalance (excess or deficiency) in the basic qualities such as hot/cold or wet/dry. The purpose of treatment is to restore balance.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Galenic-Islamic thought, every individual has a distinctive balance of four humors, resulting in a unique temperament.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sacred medicine is from the Qur’an and <emphasis>hadith</emphasis>, and holy men are considered able to heal. The sacred tradition includes beliefs in the “evil eye” and <emphasis>jinns</emphasis> as disease agents as well as healing by means of manipulating impurity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Narahati</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> is a general term used to express a wide range of undifferentiated, unpleasant emotional or physical feelings, such as feeling depressed, uneasy, nervous, disappointed, or not fully well. Many individuals somaticize in a subconscious effort to communicate <emphasis>narahati</emphasis> or distress that cannot be otherwise expressed verbally.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">By somaticizing, they construct an illness that is culturally sanctioned and socially understood.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When <emphasis>narahati</emphasis> is caused by fright, the evil eye, or <emphasis>jinns</emphasis>, it may be treated with religious cures. If it is considered caused by problems of blood, nerves, or humoral imbalance, it is treated with herbs or biomedicine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Ghalbam gerefteh (narahatiye qalb)</emphasis> or distress of the heart may be expressed as a feeling that the heart is being squeezed and can range in severity from mild excitation of the heart or palpitations to fainting and heart attack.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A sudden ailment or symptom of puzzling origin may be attributed to the evil eye, or <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">cheshm-i-bad</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, which is the belief that the eyes of another person can cause illness. <emphasis>Cheshm-i-bad</emphasis> can be unintentional (enthusiastically complimenting someone without saying “In the name of God”) or intentional (cast out due to jealousy or enmity).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals expect immediate relief or cure from the health-care system and may shop around until they find a provider they like. At the same time, they may seek advice from those who can suggest herbal remedies. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the dangers of “shopping around” and not disclosing all treatments and home therapies used.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Iranians practice self-medication and use prescription and over-the-counter medications as well as homemade herbal remedies. Antibiotics, codeine-based analgesics, mood-altering drugs in the benzodiazepine family, and intramuscular vitamins are available over-the-counter in Iran, and immigrants often bring these medications with them to the United States.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients in a nonjudgmental manner about full disclosure of prescription and nonprescription medicines and herbal treatments.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Self-adjusting dosage of prescribed medications is common. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the dangers of self-adjusting medications.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When ill, most individuals are inclined to be passive and cared for by health-care providers and family members.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When an individual is hospitalized, family members are expected to visit frequently or to be present continuously until the patient is discharged from the hospital or is fully functioning again. <emphasis role="bold">Self-care should be implemented by encouraging family members to assist with care of the sick person.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common herbal remedies include dried flowers, seeds, leaves, and berries, steeped in hot or cold water and drunk for a variety of purposes, such as digestive problems, “cleaning the blood or kidneys,” coughs, aches and pains, fevers, nerves, or fear. Some common herbal medications include <emphasis>gol-i-gov zabon</emphasis> (dried foxglove flowers) for an imbalance in the digestive system or nervous upsets, which is sometimes taken with <emphasis>nabat</emphasis>, a concentrated sugar. <emphasis>Khakshir</emphasis> (flat, brown rocket seed) is used for stomach problems and “dirty blood”; <emphasis>razianeh</emphasis> is used for halitosis; quince seeds are sucked for sore throats; and <emphasis>sedr</emphasis> prevents and treats dandruff. <emphasis>Neshasteh</emphasis> (wheat starch) is combined with boiling water and drunk for sore throats or coughs and is also used to stop diarrhea. Mint extracts are used to relieve excess stomach gas. <emphasis>Shatareh</emphasis> is thought to cure fever.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Iranians are expressive about their pain. Some justify suffering in light of later rewards.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental illness is highly stigmatized and is thought to be genetic. If a family member has a mental illness, it is likely to be called a “neurological disorder” to avoid stigmatizing the family. Psychotherapeutic help may be avoided either because of stigma or because it is perceived as irrelevant.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rehabilitation, such as physical therapy and music therapy, is embraced as the way to bring the disabled into the mainstream.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Blood transfusions, organ donations, and organ transplants are widely practiced. In Iran, donation of organs is often a business transaction—if a kidney is needed, it is purchased.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0020s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">20.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many immigrants think that Iranian doctors make more authoritative and quicker diagnoses, using minimal technology, even if they may be uncertain or wrong. American physicians, who are tentative, ask the patient to describe the problem, or order too many tests may be viewed as incompetent.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Iranians prefer to be cared for by providers of the same sex. Iranian women are modest in front of men. Some very traditional families may consider taking a female patient elsewhere or avoid care until the situation is acute, if only male providers are available. <emphasis role="bold">Male health-care providers should not ask women to undress fully for an examination or procedure.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The most respected health-care provider is an experienced, middle-aged to elderly male physician, with several degrees, and preferably with a high position in the hospital or university. He is considered the authority and is expected to act like one, making diagnoses quickly and prescribing remedies that cure the patient.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Male nurses or women who have gray hair and positions of authority are accorded more respect than young, single, female nurses. Nurses who encourage self-care may be perceived as uncaring or even incompetent. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about the benefits of self-care as a method of rehabilitation.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
