<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0028s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Poland was conceived near the middle of the tenth century and reached its golden age in the sixteenth century. In a series of agreements between 1772 and 1795, Russia, Prussia, and Austria partitioned Poland among themselves. Poland regained its independence in 1918 only to be overrun by Germany and the Soviet Union in World War II. It became a Soviet satellite state following the war, but its government was comparatively tolerant and progressive. Labor turmoil in 1980 led to the formation of the first independent free trade union in Eastern Europe, <emphasis>Solidarnosc</emphasis> (Solidarity) that over time became a political force and by 1990 had swept parliamentary elections and the presidency. Poland borders with neighboring countries Belarus, Czechia, Germany, Lithuania, Russia, Slovakia, and Ukraine.</para>
         <para role="Para">In 1988, formal negotiations between the Polish Communist Party leaders and the unofficial opposition, called the “Round Table talks,” resulted in partially free Parliamentary elections. Solidarity won a landslide victory in the 1989 elections and the newly elected Parliament changed the country’s name and constitution establishing the Third Republic of Poland.</para>
         <para role="Para">Polish and their descendants who have immigrated to the United States and elsewhere for many generations have maintained their ethnic heritage by promoting their culture, attending Catholic churches, attending parades and festivals, maintaining ethnic food traditions, speaking the Polish language, and promoting interest in their home country through media events as well as economic and political channels. For newer immigrant Poles, maintaining ethnic heritage means learning English and obtaining a good job. Newer immigrants are less concerned with raising consciousness over Polish American issues than they are with financially helping families who remain in Poland and raising concerns over the political and economic climate in their homeland.</para>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">Polonia</emphasis>
            </emphasis> is the name given to Polish communities in the United States. Poles are a heterogeneous group. Much of the diversity within this ethnic group is due to the degree of acculturation, individuality, and variant cultural characteristics as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>.</para>
         <para role="Para">The coronavirus (COVID-19) caused by severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) spread throughout Europe, reaching Poland in 2020. The pandemic had a significant impact on Poland’s health system, the health of its citizens, and social, economic, political, and cultural services even after the disease diminished. Social interactions among Polish citizens and travel restrictions severely affected tourism to the country.</para>
         <para role="Para">Another humanitarian crisis challenged Poland. The Russian military invaded Ukraine on February 24, 2022, which resulted in an unprecedented influx of Ukrainian war refugees into Poland. As of September 2023, 15.4 million people have fled Ukraine. One major factor for this influx is Poland’s geographical location adjacent to Russia. Since the war began, Poland received over 1.7 million refugees, mostly women and children. Poland is a major destination in Western Europe. As of February 2023, there are over eight million Ukrainian refugees residing in Poland. The current refugee crisis caused by this conflict has resulted in additional challenges with Poland’s healthcare system and social services.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The dominant language of people living in Poland is Polish, although there are some regional dialects and differences.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Polish language was influenced by the countries surrounding Poland and by the Latin of eleventh- and twelfth-century kings. Depending on the regional and cultural background of the speaker, Polish may sound German, Russian, or French.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles are an animated group, and facial expressions generally convey the tone of the conversation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles use touch as a form of personal expression of caring. Touch is common among family members and friends, but Poles may be quite formal with strangers and healthcare providers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Handshaking is considered polite. In fact, failing to shake hands with everyone present may be considered rude. <emphasis role="bold">Greet patients formally and with a handshake.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Poles feel comfortable with close personal space, but distances increase when interacting with strangers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">First-generation Poles commonly kiss “Polish style,” that is once on each cheek and then once again on each cheek.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Two women may walk together arm in arm, or two men may greet each other with an embrace, a hug, and a kiss on both cheeks.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Polish Americans consider the use of spoken second-person familiarity rude. Polish people speak in the third person. For example, they might ask, “Would Martin like some coffee?” rather than “Would you like some coffee?” Although the first expression might sound awkward, the latter expression may be considered impolite and too informal, especially if the person being asked is older.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish people use direct eye contact when interacting with others. Many Americans and elsewhere may feel uncomfortable with this sustained eye contact and feel it is quite close to staring, but to Poles, it is considered ordinary. <emphasis role="bold">Sustained eye contact does not necessarily mean anger.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles, as a group, tend to share thoughts and ideas freely.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality is important to Polish people. To be late is a sign of bad manners. Even in social situations, people are expected to arrive on time and stay late.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish people are both past and future-oriented. The past is very much a part of Polish culture with the families passing on their memories of World War II, which still haunt them in some way. A strong work ethic encourages Poles to plan for the future.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Polish names are difficult to pronounce to outsiders. Even though a name may be mispronounced, a high value is placed on the attempt to pronounce it correctly.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some examples of common Polish names include <emphasis>Kowal</emphasis>, meaning “blacksmith.” Numerous suffixes, such as “icz,” “czyk,” “iak,” and “czak,” which mean “son of,” can be added. Two of the most common suffixes are “ski” for male and “ska” for female, which originally were added to many names because they were associated with nobility. The suffix “cki” became the phonetic version of “ski.” Surnames ending in “y,” “ow,” “owo,” and “owa” are usually derived from names of places. The “ak” suffix is typical of western Poland, whereas “uk” is found in the east.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish culture centers on family. Each member has a certain position, role, and related responsibilities. All members are expected to work, make contributions, and strive to enhance the entire family’s reputation and social and economic position.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In most families, the father is perceived as the head of the household. Depending on the degree of assimilation, the father may rule with absolute authority in first-, second-, and even third-generation Polish families. However, among some third- and fourth-generation Polish and second- and third-wave immigrants, more egalitarian gender roles are becoming the norm.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Determine the spokesperson and decision maker for healthcare decisions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Historically, large families were expected and common among Poles, with women often experiencing between 5 and 10 pregnancies.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The most valued behavior for children is obedience. Taboo child behaviors include anything that undermines parental authority. Parents are quite demonstrative with young children, but they resist showing much affection toward them once they are older than toddler age. This is the parents’ way of teaching children to be strong and resilient.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many parents praise children for self-control and completing chores. Little sympathy is wasted on failure, but doing well is openly praised. Children are taught to resist feelings of helplessness, fragility, or dependence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional family values and loyalty are strong in most households. The elderly are highly respected. They attend church regularly and carry on Polish traditions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The elderly play an active role in helping grandchildren learn Polish customs and in assisting adult children in their daily routine with families.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For some families, one of the worst disgraces, as seen through the eyes of the Polish community, is to put an aged family member in a nursing home. Third- and fourth-generation Polish may consider an extended-care or assisted-living facility because of work schedules and demands of care, but first-generation immigrants rarely perceive this as an option.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Extended family, consisting of aunts, uncles, and godparents, is very important to Poles. Long-time friends become aunts or uncles to Polish children.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alternative lifestyles are seen as part of assimilation into the blended cultures. Same-sex couples are frowned upon and may even be ostracized, depending on the level of assimilation. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to others.</emphasis> Poland is very conservative. In Poland, there is still no legal acknowledgment of marital or family relationships for same-sex couples. Compared to Western countries, recognition of LGBTQ+ families is faced with many legal and social obstacles that play a role in how same-sex family structures are constructed, viewed, and practiced. Polish law opposes adoption and artificial reproductive technologies for same-sex couples.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When divorce occurs, single heads of households are accepted in the Polish American community.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Polish immigrants are underemployed and may have difficulty working with authority figures who are less educated. Poles quietly comment that they are disrespected for their educational background and that they must endure decreased status to stay in America and elsewhere.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Polish characteristic of praising people for their work makes Poles strong managers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because Poles learn deference to authority at home, in the church, and in parochial schools, some may be less well suited for the rigors of a highly individualistic, competitive market.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The strong Polish work ethic, exhibited as volunteering for overtime, being punctual, and rarely taking sick days, is valued by employers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Native-born Polish Americans have little, if any, difficulty with the English language. Foreign-born Poles frequently have some difficulty understanding the subtle nuances of humor. Recent Polish immigrants, who had experience working under a Communist bureaucratic hierarchy, may have some difficulty with the structure, subtleties, and culture of the American workplace. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain workforce rules and expectations.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The pandemic impacted the workforce in Poland by increasing unemployment rates by 5.8–6.3% from April to December 2020 due to decreased employment opportunities. Employment opportunities decreased by 25% compared to 2019. The main areas impacted by the pandemic were the healthcare industry, hospitality, retail, human services, cultural activities, and religious and family observances. Initially, the Polish government acted on prevention and management strategies to control the transmission of COVID, aiding employees and preventing companies from claiming bankruptcy. The pandemic also resulted in the advancement of technology and working remotely.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Before the Russian invasion of Ukraine, there were an estimated 1.35 million Ukrainian immigrants (mostly men) working and residing in Poland. Due to the continuing conflict and destruction of Ukraine’s infrastructure, 46.7% of Ukrainians came to Poland. More Ukrainians will continue to reside in Poland compared to before the war. The outlook of Poland’s economy is expected to be challenged as labor migration will increase. In the long term, tensions may increase between Polish and Ukrainian refugees because of increased use of social services and in the labor market.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Poles are of medium height with a medium-to-large bone structure. As a result of foreign invasions over the centuries, Polish people may be dark and Mongol-looking or fair with delicate features, blue eyes, and blonde hair. Those with fair complexions are predisposed to skin cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Teach patients about protecting themselves from sun exposure and cancer.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Polish culture, a common belief is that enduring pain without complaining or asking for relief demonstrates virility in men and self-control in women. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage acceptance of pain medication, explaining that it will promote healing.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Risk factors for newer Polish immigrants relate to their employment in industries in their homeland. Heavy industry in Poland produced prolonged, significant air pollution and environmental neglect. Living in polluted environments led to an increase in premature deliveries, low-birth-weight children, diseases of the pulmonary and circulatory systems, and various forms of cancer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Poland, air pollution remains a serious problem because of sulfur dioxide emissions from coal-fired power plants. In 1986, the Chernobyl incident in Russia contaminated the land and water systems of eastern Poland.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assess new immigrant Poles for respiratory conditions and cancer resulting from radiation exposure.</emphasis> Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0028s0001ta01">28.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Poles in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The first case of COVID was recorded on March 4, 2020 in Poland. There were 6.4 million confirmed cases of COVID in Poland from 2020 to 2023. The impact of COVID caused the Minister of Health to declare a state of emergency on March 20, 2020, and social restriction protocols were enacted. Mood disorders were on the rise among young Poles because of social isolation. The number of deaths significantly increased. In January 2023, the number of deaths due to COVID was greater than 118,000. COVID restrictions and travel advisories in Poland were lifted in March 2022. The vaccination rate doses are 145 per 100 people in Poland.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The war began in the third year of the COVID pandemic. The war has caused a humanitarian crisis with the influx of refugees. The increased transmission of infectious diseases places challenges to public health in Poland. Since the war, the COVID vaccination rate among Ukrainians is 38% in comparison to 56% of Polish citizens coming out of the pandemic.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">It is estimated that up to 8000 Ukrainian refugees are unaware of their HIV status and up to 18,000 will need treatment for HIV disease, which will lead to increased HIV cases reported in Poland. Before the war, HIV screening in Poland singled out drug users and men who have sex with men.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0028s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 28.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Polish people</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Alcohol misuse</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pulmonary disorders</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles have had a long history of excessive smoking. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage anti-smoking beginning in elementary school.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Poland, a high rate of alcoholic psychosis, cirrhosis of the liver, and acute alcohol poisoning exists. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage socially responsible alcohol intake and refer patients to support groups for those with alcohol misuse.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Children of immigrants should especially be targeted for counseling regarding the health effects of smoking and alcohol consumption.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Screen Polish immigrants for diseases common in their home country: hypertension, CVDs, respiratory conditions, cancer (particularly leukemia), and thyroid disorders.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Meats and vegetables are cooked for a very long time, resulting in destruction of B and other vitamins.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The strong Catholic influence is evidenced by attending many food-laden celebrations, festivals, and rituals, each of which has its own traditional high-calorie foods.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Complete a dietary assessment on admission. Help patients structure a diet that is culturally acceptable, promotes healthy food choices, and is sustainable.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Staples of the Polish diet are millet, barley, potatoes, onions, radishes, turnips, beets, beans, cabbage, carrots, cucumbers, tomatoes, apples, and wild mushrooms.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common meats are chicken, beef, and pork. Traditional high-fat entrees include pigs’ knuckles and organ meats such as liver, tripe, and tongue. <emphasis>Kapusta</emphasis> (sauerkraut), <emphasis>golabki</emphasis> (stuffed cabbage), <emphasis>babka</emphasis> (coffee cake), <emphasis>pierogi</emphasis> (dumplings), and <emphasis>chrusciki</emphasis> (deep-fried bowtie pastries) are common ethnic foods. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0028s0001ta02">28.2</link>
                     </emphasis> lists a variety of traditional Polish foods.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0028s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 28.2</emphasis> Polish foods</title>
               <tgroup cols="3">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Common name</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Description</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ingredients</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Babka</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Coffee cake</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Yeast bread</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Barszcz</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Beet soup</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Served plain or with sour cream</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Bigos</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hunter’s stew</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stew with game, sausage, sauerkraut</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Chrusciki</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Polish bowties</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Fried egg dough</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Golabki</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cabbage rolls</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cooked cabbage stuffed with chopped meat and rice in tomato sauce</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Kielbasa</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Sausage</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ground pork and spices</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Ogorki smietanie</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Sour cream and cucumbers</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Sour cream, cucumbers</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Pierogi</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Boiled dumplings</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dumplings filled with potatoes, cheese, or sauerkraut</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Sledzie</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Herring</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pickled fish</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because family is very important, most Poles want children. In Poland, the Catholic Church strongly opposes abortion, which is the prevailing attitude of many Poles in the United States and elsewhere.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fertility practices are balanced between the needs of the family and the laws of the Church. Polish women believe in the power of prayer to guarantee a successful pregnancy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant Polish women are expected to seek preventive health care, eat well, and get adequate rest to ensure a healthy pregnancy and baby. Pregnant women usually follow the physician’s orders carefully.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">They depend on intuition and believe in “evil eye” powers, causing the mother and baby harm. Polish women hang a red ribbon on the baby carriage to protect the infant.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The emphasis on food and “eating for two” is a common philosophy. <emphasis role="bold">Counsel pregnant Polish women on weight gain and the long-term hazards.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many consider it bad luck to have a baby shower. Even now, many Polish grandmothers may be reluctant to give gifts until after the baby is born.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The birthing process is considered the domain of women. During labor, movement is an important method to hasten childbirth. Polish women believe massage is important to deliver the placenta. Newer Polish immigrants may feel uncomfortable with men in the birthing area or with family-centered care. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make men feel guilty if they do not wish to be in the delivery room.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women are expected to rest for the first few weeks after delivery. For many, breast-feeding is important for postpartum recovery. <emphasis role="bold">Lactation education during breast-feeding helps the woman understand the balance between diet, rest, and exercise after delivery.</emphasis> Polish women believe in traditional personal hygiene practices to prevent infections after childbirth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fertility trends are declining in Poland due to postponed childbearing related to advanced age, low socioeconomic status, scarceness or instability of partners, cost of childrearing, infertility, and uncertain future. Delayed childbearing increases the risk of infertility and other pregnancy complications.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Poles have a stoic acceptance of death as part of the life process.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family and friends stay with the dying person to negate any feelings of abandonment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Make arrangements for the family to remain with the dying patient.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Home hospice care is acceptable to most Poles.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Healthcare providers may encounter difficulty in convincing the family that the dying member may choose to refuse food as a result of the illness. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about end-of-life care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish American family members follow a funeral custom of having a wake for 1–3 days followed by a Mass and religious burial.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Catholic Church, with its required attendance at Mass on Sundays and holy days, is an integral part of the lives of most Polish people.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish people have had a renewed interest in their ethnic roots. For example, their attendance at language classes, festivals, and Polish Catholic churches has become very widespread.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Primary spiritual sources are God and Jesus Christ, with many Polish immigrants praying to the Virgin Mary, saints, and angels to ward off evil and danger. <emphasis role="bold">Contact a chaplain if the patient wishes.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Honor and special attention are paid to the Black Madonna or Our Lady of Czestochowa. During times of illness and serious family concerns, one might hear a Pole evoking <emphasis>Matka Boska</emphasis>, which translates literally to “Mother of God.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many older Polish people believe in the special properties of prayer books, rosary beads, medals, and consecrated objects. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove religious items and amulets from patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish Americans commonly exhibit devotions to God, such as crucifixes and pictures of the Virgin Mary, the Black Madonna, and Pope John Paul II, in their homes.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Poles place a high value on stoicism and doing what needs to be done. Many go to healthcare providers only when symptoms interfere with function; then they may carefully consider the advice provided before complying.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Poles are reluctant to discuss their treatment options and concerns with healthcare providers and routinely accept the proposed care plan.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If Poles believe they are unable to pay the medical bill, they may refuse treatment unless the condition is life-threatening. Many have a strong fear of becoming dependent and resist relying on charity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because many Poles consider Medicare, Medicaid, and managed care as forms of social charity, they are reluctant to apply for them. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients and families and help them access social services when needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles usually look for a physical cause of disease before considering a mental disorder. If mental health problems exist, home visits are preferred. Few Poles turn to psychiatrists or mental health providers for help. Those who seek help from mental health providers do so as a last resort. Many individuals choose their priest or seek assistance from a Polish volunteer-run agency before going to a health provider for psychiatric help.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Talk-oriented interventions and therapies without pharmaceutical or suitable psychosocial strategies are dismissed unless interventions are action-oriented. In addition, Poles consult other family members and the community to assess the appropriateness of treatments. The role of exercise and increased intake of vegetables have minimal impact on reducing overweight, obesity rates, and lifestyle changes. Many Poles do not make the connection that weight reduction prevents cardiovascular diseases.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish people often seek self-help groups such as Alcoholics Anonymous before seeing a healthcare provider.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Assimilated Poles respect the healthcare system and tend to seek specialized care when necessary.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Given the continuation of limited access to care and the strong work population, health promotion practices are often undervalued by Polish.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Explain the benefits of health promotion activities and wellness checkups.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Breast self-examination and Pap smear tests are poorly understood by many newer female immigrants. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the benefits of breast self-examination and the necessity of Pap smears.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Polish ethic of stoicism discourages the use of over-the-counter medications unless a symptom persists.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles may use certain remedies to cure an illness, such as tea with honey and spirits to “sweat out” a cold. Herbs and rubbing compounds may also be used for problems associated with aches, pains, and inflammation from overworked joints and muscles. Some additional common cultural practices included treating the symptoms of colds with herbs or poultices made from goose grease or fat. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically, ask about the use of home remedies and over-the-counter medications.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When a Pole is asked to undress for a physical examination, pay special attention to any medals pinned to the patient’s undergarments. Most of these medals have special religious significance to the wearer. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove medals from clothing without asking permission from the patient or family.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Being unable to speak and understand a foreign language and the cost of healthcare and its complexity are the greatest barriers to health care for newer Polish immigrants. <emphasis role="bold">Obtain interpreters when needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Poles are polite to authority figures and avoid offending a healthcare worker by disagreeing with them. Thus, they may be reluctant to ask for clarifications on questionable issues.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Owing to their strong sense of stoicism and fear of being dependent upon others, many Polish Americans use inadequate pain medication and choose distraction as a means of coping with pain and discomfort. Many Poles either deny or minimize their pain or level of discomfort. Poles with chronic illnesses may have similar attitudes; thus, persevering with pain is common. <emphasis role="bold">Explain that pain medicine will promote healing. Use a visual analog scale to assess pain and assist patients with distraction techniques.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The ethic of being useful, independent, and a good Catholic influences one to refrain from using extraordinary means to keep people alive. The individual or family determines what means are considered extraordinary. Receiving blood transfusions or undergoing organ transplantation is acceptable.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0028s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">28.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Immigrant Poles often assess healthcare providers by their demeanor, warmth, and show of respect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Health advice may be sought from chiropractors and local pharmacists as well as neighbors and extended family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">When caring for Polish patients, particularly older adults, make every attempt to address individuals by their surname. Attempting to pronounce the name demonstrates respect for the patient.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Polish women are modest and self-conscious and may refuse health care when asked to disrobe in front of a male healthcare provider. <emphasis role="bold">Provide a same-sex healthcare provider when possible.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Physicians are held in high regard in Polish communities. Poles may change physicians if they believe their recovery is too slow or if a second opinion is needed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Immigrant Poles may be unfamiliar with the advanced roles of nurses who are expected to know about, plan, and be directly involved in the patients’ care. Thus, many Poles may still want only the physician to explain all aspects of their care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In 2020, the number of physician and dental practices was 3.7 per 1000 population, a 46% decrease compared to 2010. The number of nurses increased to 236.4 thousand in 2022 compared to 2021. The number of practicing midwives increased marginally to 29.4 thousand in 2022.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Since the beginning of the war, the Polish healthcare system faced many challenges. There is an increased need for mental and public health services in Poland. Many of Ukraine’s healthcare facilities were destroyed such as hospitals, ambulatory clinics, and pharmacies. As a result, many Ukrainian healthcare providers became refugees and fled to Poland. Poland’s Ministry of Health made provisions for Ukrainian healthcare workers to be able to receive temporary medical licenses to practice. There is also a language barrier with Ukrainian healthcare workers. Poland offered a free e-learning course in Polish medical language to remove barriers of communication in the medical community. The Ministry of Health and WHO Europe initiated the Organization of Healthcare course in Poland. Due to the damage to the Ukrainian infrastructure, Polish medical students attending Ukrainian universities returned and continued their education at Polish universities.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
