<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0015s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What do the terms philotimo and endropi mean and how are they displayed among Greeks?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are typical nonverbal communication practices among traditional Greeks?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>The core values of philotimo and endropi set the pattern for the family and for the enactment of gender roles. How are they displayed among men, women, and children in the family context?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>List some genetic conditions common among Greeks. What dietary implications do they have?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify two high-risk health behaviors common among Greeks. What might you do to help decrease them?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Traditional Greeks fast for a number of religious holidays. What implications does fasting have for medication administration?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Under what conditions is an abortion acceptable for most Greeks?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>The Greek Orthodox Church is important for Greeks. For what health problems might you use the church for health teaching?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Describe three folk illnesses. What is the treatment for each? What implications are there for the healthcare provider?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Hospitals are a particular source of mistrust for some Greeks. What might you do to gain their trust?</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
