<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0001s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">1.2 </emphasis> Variant Characteristics of Culture</title>
         <para role="Para">Major attributes that shape peoples’ worldview and the extent to which people identify with their cultural group of origin are called variant characteristics of culture. Some characteristics may change while others remain stable over life. Variant characteristics include:</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">nationality,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">race,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">skin color,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">gender,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">age,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">religious affiliation,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">educational status,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">socioeconomic status,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">occupation,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">military experience,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">political beliefs,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">urban versus rural residence,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">enclave identity,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">marital status,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">parental status,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">physical characteristics,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">sexual orientation,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">gender issues,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">health literacy,</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">length of time away from the country of origin, and</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">reason for migration (sojourner, immigrant, or undocumented status).</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">Immigration status influences a person’s worldview. For example, people who voluntarily immigrate generally acculturate and assimilate more easily. Sojourners who immigrate with the intention of remaining in their new homeland for only a short time or refugees who think they may return to their home country may not have the need or desire to acculturate or assimilate. Additionally, undocumented individuals (illegal immigrants) may have a different worldview from those who have arrived legally. Some variant characteristics of culture may be fluid and should not be seen as categorically imperative.</para>
         <para role="Para">The literature reports many definitions for the terms <emphasis>cultural awareness, cultural sensitivity</emphasis>, and <emphasis>cultural competence</emphasis>. Sometimes, these definitions are used interchangeably. However, cultural awareness has more to do with an appreciation of the external or material signs of diversity, such as the arts, music, dress, or physical characteristics. Cultural sensitivity has more to do with personal attitudes and not saying things that might be offensive to someone from a cultural or ethnic background different from that of the health-care provider. Increasing one’s consciousness of cultural diversity improves the possibilities for health-care providers to provide culturally competent care. Cultural competence, as used in this book, means:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Developing an awareness of one’s own existence, sensations, thoughts, and environment without letting them have an undue influence on those from other backgrounds.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Demonstrating knowledge and understanding of the patient’s culture, health-related needs, and culturally specific meanings of health and illness.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Continuing to learn about cultures of patients to whom one provides care.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Recognizing that the variant cultural characteristics determine the degree to which patients adhere to the beliefs, values, and practices of their dominant culture.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Accepting and respecting cultural differences in a manner that facilitates the patient’s and family’s abilities to make decisions to meet their needs and beliefs.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Not assuming that the health-care provider’s beliefs and values are the same as the patient’s.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Resisting judgmental attitudes such as “different is not as good.”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Being open to cultural encounters.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Being comfortable with cultural encounters.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Adapting care to be congruent with the patient’s culture.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Engaging in cultural competence is a conscious process and not necessarily a linear one.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Accepting responsibility for one’s own education in cultural competence by attending conferences, reading professional literature, and observing cultural practices.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
         <para role="Para">As of April 2020, the census recorded a resident population of 331,449,281 in the 50 states and the national capital of Washington, D. C., reflecting an increase of 7.4%, or 22,703,743, over that of 2010 (U. S. Department of Commerce: U. S. Census Bureau <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0001s0004bib01">2022</link>
            </emphasis>). Also, as of 2022, nearly 46.2 million immigrants lived in the United States, the most in U. S. history.</para>
         <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
               <link linkend="ch0001s0002ta01">1.1</link>
            </emphasis> presents the diversity of the U. S. population.</para>
         <table id="ch0001s0002ta01">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 1.1</emphasis> Diversity of the U. S. population as of 2021</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
               <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
               <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">White</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">59.3%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Hispanic or Latino origin</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">18.9%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Black and African American</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">12.6%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Asian</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">5.9%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Persons with two or more races</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">2.3%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">American Indian/Alaskan Native</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">0.7%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Some other race</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">0.5%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">Native Hawaiian and other Pacific Islanders</para>
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
                        <para role="SimplePara">0.2%</para>
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <para role="SimplePara">Data from “US population by year, race, age, ethnicity, &amp; more”. USAFacts. May 18, 2023. Retrieved June 4, 2024 from <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">https://usafacts.org/data/topics/people-society/population-and-demographics/our-changing-population/</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>
         </para>
         <para role="Para">The census collects data on two categories: race and ethnicity; therefore, these numbers total more than 100%. Race and Hispanic origin are two separate and distinct categories. Race categories as used in Census 2020 include the following:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>1. <emphasis>White</emphasis> refers to people having origins in any of the original peoples of Europe, the Near East, the Middle East, and North Africa. This category includes Irish, German, Italian, Lebanese, Turkish, Arab, and Polish.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>2. <emphasis>Black</emphasis> and <emphasis>African American</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the black racial groups of Africa and include Nigerians and Haitians and any person who self-designated this category regardless of origin.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>3. <emphasis>American Indian</emphasis> and <emphasis>Alaskan Native</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the original peoples of North, South, and Central America and who maintain tribal affiliation or community attachment.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>4. <emphasis>Asian</emphasis> refers to people having origins in any of the original peoples of the Far East, Southeast Asia, and the Indian subcontinent. This category includes the terms <emphasis>Asian Indian, Chinese, Filipino, Korean, Japanese, Vietnamese, Burmese, Hmong, Pakistani</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Thai</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>5. <emphasis>Native Hawaiian</emphasis> and other <emphasis>Pacific Islander</emphasis> refer to people having origins in any of the original peoples of Hawaii, Guam, Samoa, Tahiti, the Mariana Islands, and Chuuk.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>6. <emphasis>Some other race</emphasis> was included for people who are unable to identify with the other categories. Additionally, the respondent could identify, as a write-in, with two races (U. S. Department of Commerce: U. S. Census Bureau <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                     <link linkend="ch0001s0004bib01">2022</link>
                  </emphasis>).</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
