<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0026s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The dominant Korean language, <emphasis>han’gul</emphasis>, was the first phonetic alphabet in East Asia.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Koreans in America can speak, read, write, and understand English to some extent. However, some Americans may have difficulty understanding their English, especially those who learned English from Koreans who spoke with their native intonations and pronunciations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A high value is placed on harmony and the maintenance of a peaceful environment. Most are comfortable with silence. Small talk may appear senseless and insincere.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Touch in the realm of health care is readily accepted. Touching among friends and social equals is common and does not carry a sexual connotation, as it might in Western societies. Hugging and kissing are uncommon among parents and children as well as among children and older aunts or uncles.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Age, gender, and social status determine the use of eye contact. Respect for those in senior positions is shown by not looking them directly in the eye.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Feelings are infrequently communicated in facial expressions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Koreans prefer indirect communication because they perceive direct communication as an indication of intention or opinions as rude. Koreans may agree with the healthcare provider in order to avoid conflict. <emphasis role="bold">A response of “yes” may not have the same connotation as it does in European American cultures.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">More traditional Koreans are past-oriented. Much attention is paid to the ancestry of a family. Yearly, during the Harvest Moon in Korea, <emphasis>chusok</emphasis> (respect) is paid to ancestors by bringing fresh fruits from the autumn harvest, dry fish, and rice wine to gravesites.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The younger and more educated generation is more futuristic and achievement-oriented.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Punctuality is the norm for keeping important appointments, making transportation connections, and reporting to work.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The number of surnames in Korea is limited, with the most common ones being Kim, Lee, Park, Choi, and Jung. Korean names contain two Chinese characters, one of which describes the generation and the other the person’s given name. However, some younger generations do not use Chinese characters in their names.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The surname comes first; however, because this may be confusing to many Americans, some Koreans in the United States follow the Western tradition of using the given name first, followed by the surname. <emphasis role="bold">Address Koreans by their surname, with the title Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., Dr., or Minister, unless otherwise indicated. Determine Korean clients’ language ability, comfort level with silence, use of eye contact, and spatial distancing practices when completing health assessments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">While speaking to someone directly, you use the appellation “Hoching,” and while referring to someone to a third party, you use the designation “Jiching.” They are collectively known as “Chingho (title).”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In South Korea, using just one hand to receive something can be seen as rude. Therefore, use both hands to receive something, or you can accept it with your right hand while holding your right wrist with your left.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para role="Para">Younger individuals do not typically initiate a handshake with older people, whereas older people usually do.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men used to be the primary financial providers. Women used to stay home and care for the children and house choirs unless they were professionals (e.g., medical doctors, lawyers, teachers) or needed to work for financial purposes. Today, however, most men and women are both economically active, and the rate of economically active women population is increasing. Women have long been degraded in Korean society and seen as appendages of males. In earlier times, a woman’s identity was determined by her role as someone’s daughter, wife, or mother. Although many still practice these gender relationships, more educated women and men no longer adhere to these Confucian values.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Parenting in Korea is authoritative, although class differences play a more influential role in determining parenting styles and family roles.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are expected to be well-behaved because the whole family is disgraced if a child behaves in an embarrassing manner.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Discussing domestic violence violates Korean cultural norms. <emphasis role="bold">When family violence is suspected, approach the topic in an indirect manner.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dating is common among high schoolers. More than half of high schoolers have dating experience.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Once young adults have entered a university, they receive their freedom and are permitted to make their own decisions about personal and study time. Group outings are common for meeting the opposite sex.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">With rapid acculturation, children often take on the values of the dominant society or culture, challenging parents who support traditional values and ideals. <emphasis role="bold">Assist parents in exploring alternative parenting practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Parents expect their children to care for them in old age. <emphasis>Hyo</emphasis> (filial piety) is the obligation to respect and obey parents, care for them in old age, give them a good funeral, and worship them after death. The obligation to care for one’s parents is written into the civil code in Korea.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older people are frequently consulted on important family matters as a sign of respect for their life experiences.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Old age begins when one reaches the age of 65 years.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women who divorce may suffer social stigma. Living together before marriage is not customary in Korea. If pregnancy occurs outside marriage, it may be taken care of quietly and without family and friends being aware of the situation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the past, status was customarily assigned, but presently achieved status is more common.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lesbian and gay relationships are frowned upon. Personal disclosure to friends and family jeopardizes the family name and may lead to ostracism. The negative perception of homosexuality is now slightly improving.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The skills and work experiences Koreans bring from their home country are often not accepted in the American workforce, forcing them to take jobs in which they may be over-skilled.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Orientation programs need to address language skills, practice differences, and communication and interpersonal relationships to help Koreans adjust to the workforce.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A supervisor is treated with much respect in work and social settings. Informalities and small talk may be difficult for Korean immigrants.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For an employee to refuse a request of an employer is unacceptable, even if the employee does not want or feel qualified to complete the request. <emphasis role="bold">Asking Korean employees to demonstrate procedures is better than asking them if they know how to perform them.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Slang and colloquial language are difficult for Koreans to understand. <emphasis role="bold">Be clear in your communication style and refrain from using slang and idiomatic expressions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most stand close when conversing. <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense if a Korean stands closer than how you are accustomed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Age, gender, and social status determine the use of eye contact. Respect for those in senior positions is shown by not looking them directly in the eye. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that lack of eye contact means the person is not listening, does not care, or is being less than truthful.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The foundation of the Korean leadership style is <emphasis>jeong</emphasis> and <emphasis>woori</emphasis>. <emphasis>Jeong</emphasis> is a fostered inner condition of filial compassion, intimacy, and empathy in relationships that break down interpersonal barriers. <emphasis>Woori</emphasis> is a powerful sense of belonging to a group in which incomplete, interdependent people come together to form a whole.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">South Korea is a highly hierarchical society with a large power gap.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common physical characteristics include dark hair and dark eyes, with variations in skin color and hair darkness. Skin color ranges from fair to light brown, with those residing in the southern part of South Korea being darker.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Epicanthal skin folds create the distinctive appearance of Asian eyes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0026s0001ta01">26.1</link>
                     </emphasis> presents commonly occurring health conditions for Koreans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assess for stomach and liver cancer, tuberculosis, hepatitis, renal impairment, hypertension, parasites, and asbestos-related health problems.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Be aware that many Koreans require lower dosages of psychotropic drugs.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In newborn Korean children, a salmon patch is the most prevalent vascular birthmark and a Mongolian spot is the most prevalent pigmentary birthmark.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0026s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 26.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Koreans</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Schistosomiasis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Renal failure</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Asbestosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hypertension</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Osteoporosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Peptic ulcer disease</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Insulin autoimmune deficiency disease</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Smoking by women in public is taboo, but some women smoke at home.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men have a high incidence of alcohol consumption.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Seat belts are required for all car seats in Korea. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage moderate alcohol intake and smoking cessation. Explain the legal mandates of seat belt and child restraint laws in the United States.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Teenagers in South Korea sleep less than those in other Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) (on average). The rate of women’s smoking was reported to be low in the past because women’s smoking was taboo. However, as the negative perception of female smokers has decreased, the smoking rate among females has increased (higher than before).</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The traditional Korean diet includes steamed rice; hot soup; <emphasis>kimchee</emphasis>; and side dishes of fish, meat, or vegetables served in some variations for breakfast, lunch, and dinner. Breakfast is traditionally considered the most important meal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rice is served with 5–20 small side dishes of mostly vegetables and some fish and meats.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food is flavorful and spicy. Cooking includes a variety of seasonings such as red and black pepper, garlic, green onion, ginger, soy sauce, and sesame seed oil.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Korean Americans are at high risk for calcium deficiencies due to lactose intolerance. <emphasis role="bold">Determine individual cultural food choices that are high in calcium.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A cultural treatment for the common cold is a soup made from bean sprouts, anchovies, garlic, and other hot spices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The saying, “foods are the best medicine,” gave rise to the long-held belief that foods and medications have the same effect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fermentation, a biological process that helps food mature so it can be preserved longer, is one of the important concepts for understanding traditional Korean cuisine. Kimchi, soy sauce, red pepper paste, salted fish, and soybean paste are the foods that most closely exemplify the Korean fermented culinary culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common Korean American dishes are listed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0026s0001ta02">26.2</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0026s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 26.2</emphasis> Common Korean American dishes</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Kimchi</emphasis>: A spicy fermented cabbage made from a variety of vegetables but made primarily from a Chinese, or Napa, cabbage. Spices and herbs are added to the previously salted cabbage, which is allowed to ferment over time, and it is served with every meal in a variety of forms</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Bibimbap</emphasis>: Rice, finely chopped mixed vegetables, and a fried egg served in a hot pottery bowl. Hot pepper paste is usually added</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Bulgolgi</emphasis>: Thinly sliced pieces of beef marinated in soy sauce, sesame oil, green onions, garlic, and sugar and served after being barbecued</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Japchae</emphasis>: Clear noodles mixed with lightly stir-fried vegetables and meats</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Adapt health teaching to Korean American food choices and practices</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnancy is a highly protected time for women. Both pregnancy and the postpartum period are ritualized. See Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0026s0001ta03">26.3</link>
                     </emphasis> for some possible rituals.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Once a woman is pregnant, she starts practicing <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Tae-Kyo</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, which literally means “fetus education.” The objective of <emphasis>Tae-Kyo</emphasis> is to promote the health and well-being of the fetus and mother by having the mother focus on art and beautiful objects.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Advice on prenatal care from the husband’s family may seem like an invasion of privacy and can be a stressor to pregnant women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women who practice <emphasis>Tae-Kyo</emphasis> well before giving birth are believed to have better maternal–fetal attachment and lower the risk of postpartum depression.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0026s0001ta03">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 26.3</emphasis> Pregnancy beliefs</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Pregnant women who handle unclean objects or kill a living creature may experience a difficult birth</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Women wear tight abdominal binders beginning at 20 weeks gestation or work physically hard toward the end of the pregnancy to increase the chance of having a small baby</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Expectant mothers should avoid chicken, fish with scales, squid, or crab because eating these foods may affect the child’s appearance. For example, eating duck may cause the baby to be born with webbed feet</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Women attribute a variety of complaints to <emphasis>naeng</emphasis> (chill), a cold imbalance of the womb that brings on a heavy vaginal discharge and can cause women who experience it to become sterile</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Eating blemished fruit can cause a skin disease in the infant or result in an unpleasant face</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Women commonly labor and deliver in the supine position. After the delivery, women are traditionally served seaweed soup, a rich source of iron, which is believed to facilitate lactation and promote the healing of the mother</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Bed rest is encouraged after delivery for 7–90 days</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Women are encouraged to keep warm by avoiding showers, baths, and cold fluids or foods in order to prevent chronic illnesses such as arthritis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• The baby should be wrapped in warm blankets to prevent harm from cold winds</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Postpartum women should care for their bodies by augmenting heat and avoiding cold, resting without working, eating well, protecting the body from harmful strains, and keeping clean. To improve postpartum care, develop bilingual pamphlets that include medical terms used in the US health-care system</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death and dying are fairly well accepted in Korean culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Prolonging life may not be highly regarded in the face of modern technology. Families are expected to stay with family members and assist in feeding and personal care around the clock. <emphasis role="bold">Include family in caring for their hospitalized family member.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many believe that patients should not be told they have a terminal illness. <emphasis role="bold">Take cues from the patient and, if necessary, disclose terminal illnesses to the oldest son or designated family spokesperson, who will inform the patient when the family deems it necessary.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Crying and open displays of grief are common and signify respect for the dead.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Relatives and friends pay respect by viewing photographs of the deceased instead of viewing the body.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">An ancestral burial ceremony follows death, with the body being placed in the ground facing south or north. Rice wine is sprinkled around the gravesite.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The eldest son or male family member sits by the deceased, sometimes holds a cane, and makes a moaning noise to display his grief. The cane is a symbol of needing support.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide a private room so the family may grieve in culturally congruent ways.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The deceased wears special clothing, and the deceased’s family prepares mourning garments for the funeral. In general, clothing for the dead is prepared while they are still alive. This clothing might be different depending on the location, including hemp clothing in either black or white.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guests at <emphasis>Munsang</emphasis>, which is a visit to the family of the deceased to express condolences, are advised to dress in black or white rather than bright colors. It is important to show respect and pray with the family at <emphasis>Munsang</emphasis>. As an additional expression of consolation, money is given to the family.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Organized religions include Christianity, Buddhism, and <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Chondokyo</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>. The church is a powerful social support group for Korean immigrants.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Christians believe the spirit goes to heaven; Buddhists believe the spirit starts a new life as a person or an animal. <emphasis role="bold">Individually assess each patient’s spiritual practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family and education are central themes that give meaning to life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In South Korea, Christianity is the most prevalent religion.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Different religions, philosophical systems, and lifestyles have left their marks on Korean history, and these varied religions are harmonious with people’s daily lives.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many prescription drugs in the United States, such as anti-inflammatory and cardiac medications, as well as certain pain-control medications, can be purchased over-the-counter in Korea.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Herbal medicine may be used in conjunction with Western biomedicine. Herbal remedies include ginseng, seaweed soup, and <emphasis>haigefen</emphasis> (clamshell powder), which contains high levels of lead, causing abdominal colic, muscle pain, and fatigue.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask about the use of traditional medicine, and include nonharmful practices in prescriptions.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Hanbang</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> is the traditional Korean medical care system and works on the principle of restored energy. Complementary health practices include acupuncture, acumassage, acupressure, and moxibustion therapy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Korean Americans are stoic and are slow to express emotional distress from pain. Others are expressive and discuss their smallest discomforts.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Monitor nonverbal cues and facial expressions for pain.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental illness may be stigmatized. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Hwa-Byung</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, a traditional Korean illness, occurs from the suppression of anger or other emotions. These emotions are expressed as physical complaints, ranging from headaches and poor appetite to insomnia and lack of energy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Disability may carry a stigma, especially for older, more traditional Koreans.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assist families to access resources to care for parents and children with disabilities.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Whereas blood donation and transfusions are acceptable, organ donation and organ transplantation are rare, reflecting traditional attitudes toward integrity and purity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Korean men smoke a lot. In addition, Korean men and young women use a lot of alcohol at least once a month, and “binge drinking” is a common and growing health problem.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The inability to express their feelings openly could lead to a condition known as <emphasis>Hwa-byung</emphasis> (literally, “fire illness”), which could be attributed to illnesses.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0026s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">26.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Practitioners</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">More traditional individuals frequently prefer health-care providers who speak Korean and are older.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because of modesty, women prefer women for performing Pap smears, mammography, and breast examinations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide a same-gender health-care provider for intimate care whenever possible.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The appearance of symptoms can be interpreted as bad luck, misfortune, or “karma,” which means retribution for wrongdoing in the past.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When asked about unpleasant things, Koreans try to keep their emotions under control.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
