<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0008s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3 </emphasis> Case Studies</title>
         <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.1 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2</title>
            <para role="Para">Suha Abul Mona, an unmarried 23-year-old Arab woman, visits the clinic accompanied by her Middle Eastern parents and older brother. Suha complains of left lower quadrant abdominal pain and spotting, causing concern for her family. Despite feeling visibly uncomfortable and anxious, Suha’s family expresses worry about her condition.</para>
            <para role="Para">Describing a persistent, dull pain in her left lower abdomen, Suha rates it as a 6 out of 10 on the pain scale, noting it began a day ago and has since worsened. She mentions experiencing light vaginal spotting for the past 2 days, which is unusual for her menstrual cycle. Suha denies any history of irregular periods or recent changes in menstrual pattern, attributing her intermittent nausea to the abdominal discomfort. Having no significant medical history, surgeries, or chronic conditions, Suha denies recent illnesses, travel, or exposure to infectious diseases. She is not currently taking any medications, including contraceptives.</para>
            <para role="Para">The family actively participates in Suha’s healthcare decisions, expressing deep concern for her well-being. The nurse observes how traditional gender roles and familial expectations influence communication dynamics with Suha’s mother taking the lead in expressing health concerns while her father and older brother provide support. The nurse acknowledges the influence of Suha’s unmarried status on discussions about reproductive health and sexual activity within the family, respecting cultural norms and societal expectations.</para>
            <para role="Para">Performing a thorough physical examination, the nurse evaluates Suha’s abdominal pain and vaginal bleeding ordering laboratory tests like a complete blood count and urinalysis to assess for underlying causes. Maintaining confidentiality regarding sensitive health information, particularly related to sexual health and reproductive issues, is essential for Suha’s privacy and comfort.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What steps should the nurse take in this situation?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>How can the nurse employ culturally sensitive approaches to effectively address the needs of the Abul Muna family?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>How can the nurse ensure the best care for Suha?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Is it appropriate for the nurse to discuss the possibility of pregnancy with Suha when her parents are not present?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2.1</title>
            <para role="Para">Latif, a 75-year-old man diagnosed with end-stage liver cancer, is undergoing chemotherapy treatment. Experiencing constant nausea and decreased appetite as side effects of his cytotoxic medications, Latif often refuses to eat the food provided to him.</para>
            <para role="Para">Recognizing Latif’s eating difficulties, the nurse arranges for the dietician to assess his dietary preferences and provide personalized recommendations. During the visit, Latif expresses concern about the halal status of the meat in his meals, indicating his discomfort with consuming non-halal food. Despite the nurse’s explanation that the food was selected based on his dietary agreement, Latif remains uneasy about the meat’s halal status. Also, he voices dissatisfaction with the lack of vegetables and salads in his meals, believing them to be essential for nutrition.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Drawing from insights into Arab cultural norms, what steps could the nurse take in response to Latif’s concerns?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>How can the nurse and the dietician collaborate to improve Latif’s dietary intake in a culturally sensitive manner?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What strategies can the nurse employ to prevent similar situations from occurring in the future?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0008s0003s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">8.3.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercise 8.2.3</title>
            <para role="Para">Ms. Al-Mansoori is a 32-year-old pregnant woman who arrives at the delivery suite experiencing contractions. As the nurses assist Ms. Al-Mansoori to her bed, her husband contacts the nurse and expresses his preference for no men to enter his wife’s room. He insists that all nurses, doctors, and other staff attending to his wife be female. Also, he requests that no male personnel enter the room during the night as his wife will have her veil removed while she sleeps. The nurse faces a dilemma as the doctor on duty in the delivery suite is male and Ms. Al-Mansoori is fully dilated and prepared to deliver imminently. In response, the nurse places a note outside the Al-Mansoori family’s room, indicating that males are not permitted inside based on the patient’s preference.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Assess the nurse’s reaction based on your nursing education.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Interpret the cultural significance behind Mr. Al-Mansoori’s actions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>What actions can the nurse take in this scenario?</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
