<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0003s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.1 </emphasis> Introduction</title>
         <para role="Para">Barriers to culturally competent health care are defined as obstacles or hindrances that make it difficult to obtain or access good health or health care. Despite efforts and goals in the United States and many other countries around the world to reduce or eliminate obstacles, significant disparities continue, especially with what the professional literature refers to as vulnerable populations. Vulnerable populations include the following:</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">the economically disadvantaged</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">racial and ethnic minorities (including those of mixed race or ethnicities)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">the uninsured and underinsured</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">older adults</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">children</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">the homeless</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">people with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">people who are stigmatized for whatever reason, which includes substance misuse</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">people with chronic health conditions and severe mental illness</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">rural populations</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">people with low acculturation and low levels of education</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">gender disparities</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">refugees and undocumented immigrants</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">distance to a health-care facility</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">language difficulties, and an interpreter is not available.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">Overall, these disparities are due to environmental, psychological, and social factors; maldistribution or shortage of human and fiscal resources; and lack of access to health-care systems. From this list, it seems clear that under the right set of circumstances, any group or individual can be vulnerable.</para>
         <para role="Para">Barriers can be categorized in several domains that are presented in this chapter: language and health literacy, availability, accessibility, affordability, appropriateness, accountability, adaptability, acceptability, awareness, attitudes, approachability, alternative practices, and additional services. It should be noted that these domains are not categorically imperative or perfectly distinct categories; they can overlap.</para>
      </sect1>
      
