<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0031s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Somalia is approximately 246,200 miles <superscript>2</superscript> (637,658 km <superscript>2</superscript>) and has a population of over 17 million. Somalia occupies the “horn” of Africa, a large land mass jutting into the Indian Ocean just south of the Arabian Peninsula, wrapping around Ethiopia and Kenya to the west. With a long coastline on the Indian Ocean and the Gulf of Aden, which leads into the Red Sea and Suez Canal, Somalia has a long trade and interaction with other cultures. Most of the country is arid and sparsely settled by nomadic herders. The southern part has a tropical climate supporting agriculture, and cultivators settled in urban communities, including Mogadishu, the large capital city.</para>
         <para role="Para">The Somali Democratic Republic is the formal name of this African country, also known as Somalia in short form. Somali is the predominant language with several dialects in different coastal regions. English and Italian are used in small urban areas. Arabic is used in religious contexts. Introduced by the Arabs in the seventeenth century, the official religion is Islamic with an overwhelming majority of Sunni Muslims, less than 1% of the population are Christians. Arabic neighbors greatly influence the culture in Somalia. However, as in many countries, tribal allegiance is primary. Social stratification is based on classes and castes. The Samaal clan-family believes that they are superior to the Saab. In turn, the Saab developed a caste system that awards status to different groups according to their heritage or occupation. In the twentieth century, education, income, and the ability to speak foreign languages were the standards by which status was attained in urban Somalia.</para>
         <para role="Para">After the collapse of the Somali government in 1991, at least one million Somali people fled to neighboring counties such as Ethiopia, Djibouti, Yemen, and especially Kenya. Many refugees have resettled in the United States (US), Canada, the United Kingdom, Holland, Sweden, Denmark, Germany, Australia, and New Zealand.</para>
         <para role="Para">Immigrants to Western countries were initially scattered, but many have joined family and clan members in urban centers throughout the US, especially Minneapolis–St. Paul, Minnesota. Many have built prosperous lives, opened businesses, and taken advantage of educational opportunities. In some Minnesota high schools and community colleges, more than half the students are Somali. Residual conflict persists in their new homes between members of different clans still at war in Somalia. Diversity among Somalis varies according to acculturation and the variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0002#ch0002">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali is the universal language understood by all Somali people despite minor differences in dialect. Many people speak Arabic. A few older and educated Somalis speak Italian or English, depending on experiences with former colonial powers. In 1972, during a literacy campaign, the Somali language began to be written using phonetic spelling and the European alphabet and taught in primary schools. Older Somalis are generally not able to read this language. <emphasis role="bold">Upon admission, determine language preference, Somali, Arabic, or English, and obtain an interpreter if necessary.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somalis are polite and appreciate complete introductions of everyone in the room, including interpreters and family members. <emphasis role="bold">Formally introduce yourself by title and purpose.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women and men are not shy about obtaining medical care and often ask detailed questions until satisfied. This may include challenging questions like “Why is this medicine not working?” However, they are almost always respectful and usually conclude a medical or nursing interaction by expressing thanks.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Explain the purpose of every intervention.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somalis dress up for medical appointments. Women and female children as young as 7 or 8 generally wear the Muslim headscarf and dress discreetly, often with a strong sense of color and fashion. Men dress in slacks and shirts with good-quality leather belts and shoes. One rarely encounters sloppy or worn clothing. <emphasis role="bold">Sloppy or worn clothing may be a symptom of other problems besides the reason for the appointment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Somalis follow Muslim traditions regarding social touching. A man or woman may not touch someone of the opposite sex except for spouses or close relatives. However, Somalis are practical people; in the exam room, it is understood that touching is permitted for a specific reason. <emphasis role="bold">Because shaking hands when greeting a patient of the opposite sex is inappropriate, saying hello while putting your hands in your pocket or clasping them together puts a patient at ease.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Somali patients are uncomfortable having a genital exam by a provider of the opposite sex. <emphasis role="bold">Provide a same-sex provider for intimate exams.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Eye contact and voice volume are not noticeably different from the European American cultural norms. If a patient is timid and soft-spoken, the explanation may be depression or post-traumatic stress disorder rather than culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Smiling, informality, expressing friendship, and engaging in humor by the healthcare provider are acceptable.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Naming is by the usual Muslim patronymic system. Both girls and boys are given a specific name at birth. This is followed by the name of their father (for both sexes) and then the name of their grandfather. Jibrill Ibrahim Mohamud would be a boy named Jibrill whose father was Ibrahim and grandfather was Mohamud.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality is not expected in a social context. Still, Somali people are generally quick to adapt to new cultures and learn that they are expected to be on time for appointments. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of being on time for appointments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A Somali nuclear family includes a father, mother, children, and grandchildren. The father heads the family and makes the final decision in family affairs. Family relations are based on hierarchal respect, as the <emphasis role="bold">Qur’an</emphasis> expects children to obey their parents unconditionally. Children are also likely to care for their parents when needed, especially during sickness, aging, or financial hardship. There was no social security or pension back home in Somalia. <emphasis role="bold">Accept family dynamics and hierarchy without judgment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The father is the leading income producer and manager of family finances. Other family members, including his wife, their grown children, and sometimes grandchildren work and help as they can. The mother is a homemaker in cooking, cleaning, shopping, and caring for children. She is revered and respected in this role, even more so than the father. <emphasis role="bold">Accept gender roles without judgment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When children reach the age of marriage, the father has the final say regarding whom and when his daughters marry. When a son matches, his father participates in decision-making and the marriage ceremony but does not have the same level of authority as the bride’s father.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Marriage in Somalia was an entirely religious ceremony conducted by a religious official versed in <emphasis>Sharia</emphasis> law with two male witnesses and male members of the bride’s family. Civil authorities sometimes issued certificates of marriage, but these were not essential.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The husband can declare divorce under Sharia in the presence of two male witnesses. A wife must apply to a court for judgment if she wishes to divorce. In rural areas, she may be represented by her male relatives instead. Grounds for divorce include lack of financial support or sexual impotence. These traditions do not coincide with Western civil law. Confusion and misunderstanding can occur, especially among newly arrived immigrants. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain the legalities of divorce in the US and elsewhere.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Extended families are critical. Most Somalis in the US help support their family members in Somalia or refugee camps in neighboring countries.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Include extended family in health teaching.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Clan relationships are essential. Wealthy and productive clan members are expected to help others, especially in the event of significant illness or legal trouble. The clan leader administers it and persists in Western countries.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The family is becoming less cohesive in the US. Adolescents are less obedient to their parents. Fathers may believe they are losing their traditional positions as providers and heads of the family when two incomes are needed to survive. Mothers may feel long work hours interfere with their role as homemakers. Large families add to financial stress. These factors and the American culture of individualism are loosening the tight relationships and traditional roles characteristic of the collectivistic Somali family for generations. <emphasis role="bold">Assist the family in understanding the dominant culture and refer for appropriate parenting skills.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Same-sex relationships are hidden and not discussed. Marrying and producing children is the expectation. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to family or outsiders.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In general, Somali culture values practicality and assimilation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sometimes Somali employees will join each other and speak Somali, but they are generally polite about switching to English to comfort English-speaking co-workers. <emphasis role="bold">Explain organizational policies as to when English only is required.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali culture also values hard work, self-reliance, and entrepreneurship. Conflict may ensue when employers fail to permit prayer at times prescribed by the Qur’an (imagine an assembly line). <emphasis role="bold">Employers may not be aware that worship at these times is mandatory and not something that can be done when convenient.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Conflict between Somali and African American teenagers occurs in some high schools and may carry over into the workplace.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the US, Somali immigrants are generally quick to learn American culture and the English language. Keeping apart from mainstream culture and language, as seen in some immigrant communities, is distinctly unusual.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali people tend to have thin frames and light skin. Men and women tend to vary in appearance once settled in America. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0031s0001ta01">31.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists common Somali health conditions in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Tuberculosis is by far the most important infectious disease among Somali immigrants. Providers should not assume that testing for this has been accomplished during the immigration process. Extrapulmonary tuberculosis, especially in lymph nodes, is more common than pulmonary tuberculosis and often presents with fever alone or vague other symptoms. <emphasis role="bold">A tuberculin skin test should be performed unless the patient gives a history of a previously positive test. Screen every Somali patient for tuberculosis.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Other common infectious diseases are hepatitis B, <emphasis>Helicobacter pylori</emphasis>, intestinal parasites, and malaria. Many arrivals come from refugee camps in countries other than Somalia. HIV and hepatitis C are relatively uncommon. Almost all Somali immigrants have antibodies to hepatitis A and do not need vaccination against this disease.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>H. pylori</emphasis> infection is common, although it has an uncertain relationship to common upper gastrointestinal symptoms. <emphasis role="bold">Antibodies to</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">H. pylori</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">in the blood do not indicate current condition. A better indicator is the presence of</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">H. pylori</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">DNA in the stool. Screen Somali refugees for hepatitis B,</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">H. pylori</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">, intestinal parasites, and malaria.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Intestinal parasites may persist for years after immigration. Usually, these do not cause symptoms but should be treated for public health reasons. Common infections involve <emphasis>Trichuris trichiura, Enterobius vermicularis, Entamoeba histolytica, Dientamoeba fragilis, Ascaris lumbricoides,</emphasis> and <emphasis>Schistosoma mansoni.</emphasis> Stool tests will also reveal many nonpathogenic organisms, such as <emphasis>Endolimax nana, Entamoeba coli, Entamoeba hartmanni, Iodamoeba buetschlii,</emphasis> and <emphasis>Chilomastix mesnili.</emphasis> These do not need treatment. There is controversy about whether <emphasis>Blastocystis hominis</emphasis> is pathogenic; generally, treatment is recommended only if the patient is symptomatic or immunosuppressed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Little is written about drug metabolism specific to Somali. Lactase deficiency occurs in adulthood. <emphasis role="bold">Assess for lactose intolerance on intake interviews.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0031s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 31.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Somalis</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health condition</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Depression, post-traumatic stress disorder</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis B</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Helicobacter pylori,</emphasis> intestinal parasites, and malaria</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Trichuris trichuriasis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Enterobius vermicularis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Entamoeba histolytica</emphasis>, <emphasis>Dientamoeba fragilis</emphasis>, <emphasis>Ascaris lumbricoides</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Schistosoma mansoni</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rates of obesity and diabetes have increased dramatically, especially among women adjusting to food availability in Western countries and decreased physical activity climates. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage indoor physical activities such as swimming, working out at gyms, and dancing when appropriate.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Muslim religion prohibits alcohol consumption and few Somali immigrants use alcohol. <emphasis role="bold">If you ask about alcohol, explain, “We ask these questions of everybody.”</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">More of a problem is <emphasis>khat or qat</emphasis>, a vegetable stimulant chewed like tobacco or drunk as an infusion that produces euphoria. <emphasis>Khat</emphasis> can be obtained from leaves, shoots, or twigs of an evergreen shrub found in Arabia, Ethiopia, Kenya, and Yemen but not in Somalia. It can cause psychosis and is classified as a controlled substance by the United Nations. Possession in the US is a felony. It loses potency within days after harvest, so imported <emphasis>khat</emphasis> must be used promptly. People who use <emphasis>khat</emphasis> regularly tend to gather in houses where they sit together for many hours, talking with each other, abandoning family and work obligations. <emphasis>Khat</emphasis> can cause loss of appetite and erectile dysfunction. In pregnancy, it is associated with low birth weight.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Promiscuity, intravenous drug use, and HIV are relatively uncommon. <emphasis role="bold">If you ask about promiscuity,</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">khat</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">, intravenous drug use, or HIV, explain, “We ask these questions of everybody.”</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Teenagers are more oriented toward school and family life and less likely to engage in premarital sex, gangs, weapons, and drugs than their American counterparts.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As in many cultures, the day’s main meal is an essential opportunity for a family to gather and talk. In urban areas, the main meal is usually in the early afternoon. In rural areas, it’s in the evening after work.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Somalia, everyday foods are rice, pasta, bread, potatoes, corn, beans, and sugar. Meat products include goat, lamb, beef, camel, and fish. Fruits include bananas, mango, papaya, grapefruit, oranges, lemons, grapes, and dates. Beverages include milk from goats, cows, and camels; tea and coffee; and soda.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A typical breakfast includes <emphasis>angela</emphasis>, a flour product resembling pizza, to which oil or sauce can be added, and tea. At mid-day, the meal is rice or pasta with sauce and vegetables, including onions and potatoes, often with goat meat and bananas. A mixture of beans, corn, oil, and sugar, with milk, is consumed for dinner.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali food is less spicy than Ethiopian, Middle Eastern, or Indian cuisine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Adapting to American culture and the ready availability of food has produced an epidemic of obesity and diabetes, especially in Somali women who were physically active in their home country and now live indoors in cold northern climates.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Initiate nutritional assessments and food preferences on intake assessments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Vitamin D deficiency may occur in winter due to lack of sunlight from indoors and wearing a headscarf.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Everyone fasts from sunup to sundown during the lunar month of <emphasis role="bold">Ramadan</emphasis>. Some religious individuals may select additional days of fasting at any time. <emphasis role="bold">Adjust medication schedules to coincide with nonfasting hours. See Chap.</emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0008#ch0008">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">
                              <emphasis role="bold">8</emphasis>
                           </emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">for Ramadan schedules.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Meat slaughtered by a butcher of faith is called <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">halal</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis>.</emphasis> The butcher is ideally Muslim, but Christianity and Judaism are respected religions, and butchers from these faiths are acceptable. Pork of any kind is forbidden. <emphasis role="bold">Provide</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">halal</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">meats when possible; otherwise, ask the patient’s family to bring food from home. Some online services have frozen</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">halal</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">foods available.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali families tend to be prominent by American and European standards. Over 60% of Somalia’s population is younger than 25 as of 2020, and the fertility rate is among the world’s highest at almost 5.5 children per woman—a rate that has decreased little since the 1970s.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somalia has the highest rate of female genital mutilation (FGM) or infibulation worldwide. Infibulation is attributed to gender inequality. Prepubertal girls aged 5–11 years can be circumcised by removing the clitoris, labia minora, and labia majora. In another variety of this practice, only the clitoris is removed. The vaginal orifice is then narrowed by sutures, leaving little room for menstruation. At the time of marriage, these sutures are removed. After childbirth, infibulation may be done. In the US, and some other countries, this practice is illegal. In response, some families arrange for their children to travel to Africa for FGM.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali women who have undergone FGM have many health concerns that should not be overlooked. These issues include pain, urinary dysfunction, sexual dysfunction, and scarring. During the birthing process, Somali women with FGM are at risk for difficult labor and neonatal complications secondary to birth. In addition, the mental health of Somali women with FGM may be compromised. Many Somali women may have depression, low self-esteem, and low self-confidence due to FGM.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain that female circumcision is illegal in the US and most other countries. Obtain permission for students, residents, and fellows’ presence during exams and birthing experiences</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children and pregnancy are invariably considered precious gifts. Infertility is a psychological burden that causes marked suffering and elicits sympathy. Abortion is prohibited.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Contraception to space children is allowed by Islam. Cesarean sections are avoided because of the fear of preventing subsequent normal pregnancy and delivery.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">During pregnancy, women must eat well and avoid heavy exertion or lifting. The custom of working until the due date seems strange to many Somali women. However, Somalis tend to be practical and adapt to new situations and expectations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate healthy traditional practices into care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After childbirth, <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">afartanbah</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> is observed, a period of 40 days during which the woman stays home, eats well, is assisted by her family and neighbors, and abstains from sexual intercourse.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Breastfeeding for as long as possible, up to 2 years, is a religious obligation. Supplementation with milk, formula, and other food as the child grows is allowed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A naming ceremony is held between 2 weeks and 40 days.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Upon learning a family member is dying, Somali families come together to support each other and the dying person. This may include many members of the extended family. A religious person, such as the <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">imam</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> from the local mosque, may visit the person in the hospital, offer prayers, and help mobilize community support. <emphasis role="bold">Assist the family to obtain an</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">imam</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">and make arrangements for the family to be at the dying patient’s bedside.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As faithful Muslims, Somalis believe that Allah will determine how long a person will live. In addition, Muslim Somalis believe the soul returns to God upon death. For this reason, discussing end-of-life care, advance directives, or efforts to prolong life may be misunderstood. In general, impending death is not concerned directly with the patient. “Allah will decide, and I will follow” is common. <emphasis role="bold">When the need arises to discuss end-of-life care, hospice, palliative care, or life-prolonging measures, approach the nearest relative to the patient. Be patient and allow time for the family to discuss this among the elders of the family.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After death, the funeral home cooperates with the mosque to prepare the body, wash it, wrap it in white cloth, and deliver it to the mosque for a prayer service. Bodies are never cremated, always buried on the right side facing Mecca. In Somalia, bodies are buried without coffins, as the belief is that being “in a box” may be uncomfortable.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Essentially, all Somalis are devout Sunni Muslims who believe that Allah cares for them in their daily lives and follow instructions in the Qur’an regarding prayer and fasting, caring for the poor, and kindness to strangers. They have a great interest in Sufi spiritualism, characterized by chanting, whirling, chewing <emphasis>khat,</emphasis> and falling into a trance to communicate with Allah. Somalis also include the veneration of Somali saints in religious worship.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Islam, no priests mediate between the believer and God, but there are religious leaders, including teachers, preachers, and mosque officials. Somalis believe that both their religious and secular leaders have the power given by Allah to bless and curse people. This power, baraka, is believed to linger on tombs of Somali saints to help cure illness and resolve other troubles upon visit to the tomb. Somalis believe that some kinds of illnesses are caused by the body being possessed by spirits. Among several religious practitioners, the Yibir from the clan of Saab is called on to exorcise spirits and restore health, good fortune, or prosperity to individuals through prayers and ceremonies, including animal sacrifice.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the US and elsewhere, Somalis attend formal services at mosques, which serve as centers of community life and religion. Prayers ( <emphasis>salat</emphasis>) are performed five times daily in any location facing Mecca. These prayers take about 3 min and involve kneeling and touching the forehead to the ground. On Fridays, men must attend the local mosque to listen to the <emphasis>khadi,</emphasis> who gives a sermon called <emphasis>khudba</emphasis>. Women may go to the mosque to pray and study the Qur’an separately from men, but attendance is not required. <emphasis role="bold">Plan care around prayer times if at all possible. Assist patients and families with prayer as necessary. Contact a chaplain for assistance.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Strict fasting occurs during the lunar month of Ramadan. Ramadan advances each year within the Western calendar. During this time, all people older than 14 refrain from taking food or drink from sunrise to sundown. Sometimes, this is interpreted to include medication, including insulin. Exceptions can occur during illness, travel, menstruation, pregnancy, etc. At the end of this month comes a feast called <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Eid al-Fidri</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, in which everyone joins to give thanks, make a special prayer, wear their best clothes, and dine out. <emphasis role="bold">Adjust meal and medication schedules to accommodate for Ramadan.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Another feast day, <emphasis>Eid al-Adha</emphasis>, coincides with the annual pilgrimage to Mecca ( <emphasis>haj</emphasis>). Every Muslim is expected to make <emphasis>haj</emphasis> once in their life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is a strong sense of sharing and being part of a faithful community. Individualism is regarded as self-centered. Somali culture does not encourage celebrating birthdays. Many refugees will give January 1 of the year they were born when confronted by immigration authorities or Western medical records systems.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somalis sometimes seek healing from traditional and religious healers first. However, they do not hesitate to go to a healthcare provider when symptoms persist or are alarming. This includes seeking care for mental health problems. Older individuals who feel well may not understand the concept of preventive medicine but usually accept advice when the reasons are explained to them. <emphasis role="bold">Integrate nonharmful traditional healthcare practices with allopathic practices and treatments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Somali patients listen, ask questions, and value medical advice. Seeking care and keeping appointments are usually not barriers to care; lack of insurance may be a barrier.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Affording prescription medication is a problem for many patients; prescribing less expensive generic drugs is a discreet way to help. Newly arrived persons will appreciate assistance in navigating the complex American healthcare system. <emphasis role="bold">Recommend generic medications when feasible and assist patients and families in navigating the healthcare system. Refer to social services and community agencies as necessary.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Somali healing practices include ritual reading or reciting of verses from the Qur’an; creating superficial skin burns on the abdomen, chest, or head; external cutting of the skin (primarily used for jaundice in children suffering from hepatitis A); <emphasis>minis</emphasis> (or <emphasis>saar</emphasis>), which consists of ceremonial drumming, singing, and dancing around the sick person, and herbs that may be consumed or used as a poultice. Such practices are guided by a traditional healer, usually an older man called an <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">alaqad</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, and may include participation by a large group of people. The patient is expected to provide food and clothing for the gathering and to pay the <emphasis>lead</emphasis> a sum of money. Some traditional healers specialize in setting fractures or trephine procedures for subdural bleeding.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Somalia, prepubertal girls are circumcised by removing the clitoris, labia minora, and labia majora. The vaginal orifice is then narrowed by sutures, leaving room for menstruation. At the time of marriage, these sutures are removed. In another variety of this practice, only the clitoris is removed. While these practices seem extreme to Western medical providers, they are accepted as expected by many Somali women who value purity and tradition. In the US and many other countries, this practice is illegal. In response, some families arrange for their children to travel to Africa for circumcision. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain that female circumcision is illegal in the US and most other countries.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There are no restrictions on accepting blood products when needed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pain is a common complaint, including the unusual pain pattern on one half of the body. Pain may be a culturally acceptable way to express sadness or social and psychological discomfort. <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain if the pain is physical or emotional in origin.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Healthcare providers should be informed of the cultural idioms of distress Somali immigrants express. One such idiom is <emphasis>jinn. Jinn</emphasis> is believed to be a spirit that causes many mental health experiences. A sudden unknown reason for the change in personality or behavior may be caused by <emphasis>jinn</emphasis> possession.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Somali immigrants have significant depression or post-traumatic stress disorder related to war, family disruption, and long years in refugee camps. This cultural term for mental distress is referred to as <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">qaracan</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis>.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Symptoms include depressed mood, insomnia, rumination, social isolation, lack of trust, and a host of somatic symptoms for which investigations do not reveal a specific cause. <emphasis role="bold">Antidepressants are generally more helpful than insight psychotherapy.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">There is a significant stigma attached to mental health among Somalis.</emphasis> Somalis may respond better to more straightforward explanations like troubled thinking, too much stress, insufficient sleep, or a reaction to the past. There is a sense that people should bear up under their symptoms, that Allah would not ask a person to bear more than they can tolerate. Poor mental health can be perceived as a weakness or lack of religious participation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Avoid using “depression” on the first encounter because it may elicit feelings of weakness or guilt. Approach mental health issues cautiously and indirectly until trust is established, unless the situation is an emergency.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0031s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">31.1.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In urban Mogadishu, Western medicine was practiced by European standards before the civil war, supplemented by traditional practices. The breakdown of the government and the destruction of most hospitals and clinics have declined Somalia’s healthcare system. This also caused the availability of few doctors and hospitals, and many unqualified persons practice a form of medicine. Most healthcare is free in Somalia and is provided by the World Health Organization and nongovernmental organizations (NGOs). Folk medicine is practiced by nomads and farmers who have no immediate access to healthcare. Somali Western medicine and classic methods are complementary. <emphasis role="bold">Integrate traditional healthcare providers and traditional treatments with Western healthcare providers and treatments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Respect for medical education and expertise is the rule. Doctors and nurses are valued as professionals. A healthcare career is a common choice for young people. Somalis integrate easily into Western medical systems, displaying medical values such as patience, tactfulness, and kindness. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage Somali children and older adults seeking a second career to think about the health professions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
