<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0034s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Ukraine is the second-largest European country by area in Eastern Europe. Ethnic Ukrainians belong to the Slavic nationality group. The capital of Ukraine is Kyiv. The national groups residing in Ukraine include Ukrainians, Russians, Belarusians, Bulgarians, Crimean Tatars, Moldovans, Jews, and Hungarians. Russians account for about a sixth of Ukraine’s population. Most of the people in the Crimean Peninsula are of Russian ethnicity. Ukraine is one of the world’s leading farming regions. During A. D. 800s, Kyiv became the center of a Slavic state that modern historians call Kievan Rus (also spelled <emphasis>Kyivan Rus)</emphasis>. Parts of Ukraine were under Polish, Lithuanian, and Austrian control until the late 1700s, when almost all of Ukraine came under Russian control. In 1922, Ukraine became one of the four original republics of the Soviet Union (USSR), but in 1991, Ukraine declared its political independence from the USSR. Ukraine has a significant history of movement for national independence with strong aspirations to join the European Union in recent years. During the post-Soviet period, some Ukrainian citizens left the country for economic reasons and have been working abroad and supporting families at home. In 2014, Maidan Revolution in Kyiv led to the removal of the Ukrainian president from office and the beginning of civilian unrest in the Eastern part of the country and Crimea. In February 2022, the Russia–Ukraine war started, contributing to millions of Ukrainian citizens escaping war zone and significant number of citizens volunteered joining military units on the front line or at the local territorial defense units. A new wave of Ukrainian immigrants to the United States comprised of younger generation Ukrainians who are usually well-educated or have good vocational skills. Many are proficient in English and can find gainful employment upon arrival in the United States. Recently immigrated Ukrainians may have higher level of medical and psychological needs due to exposure to war (Popova and Shevel, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0034s0003bib08">2024</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians tend to be relatively straightforward and use a direct communication style. They expect others to be clear and open when expressing their opinions. They may not be overly polite or use innocent words discussing sensitive topics. While being direct, they may in some cases use indirect communication. When discussing sensitive or confrontational topics, they may use euphemisms instead of addressing the issue.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians may use <emphasis role="bold">nonverbal communications</emphasis> via facial expressions, gestures, and eye contact to convey emotions and meanings. <emphasis role="bold">Maintaining eye contact during a conversation is generally seen as a sign of attentiveness and sincerity</emphasis>. Ukrainians may avoid direct eye contact in communication with authorities.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians often show respect for authority figures. They may use titles and honorifics when addressing superiors in hierarchical organizational settings. It is a sign of respect to address older person by first and middle name.</para>
                  <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkDash">
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">
                           <emphasis role="bold">Personal Relationships</emphasis>: Ukrainians often prefer to do business with people they know and trust. “<emphasis>
                              <emphasis role="bold">Small Talk</emphasis>
                           </emphasis>” or polite inquiries about one’s health, family, and general well-being are common to build rapport.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">
                           <emphasis role="bold">Language</emphasis>: Ukrainian is the official language of Ukraine, although Russian was also widely spoken in the eastern and southern regions. <emphasis role="bold">Language choice can be a sensitive issue, so it’s important to use the language preferred by your communication partner</emphasis>. Many Ukrainians do not understand medical language and have difficulty communicating abstract concepts or understanding American dialects. <emphasis role="bold">It is recommended to use a professional interpreter, speak slowly and clearly with a medium tone of voice. Refrain from a loud conversation when communicating with Ukrainian immigrants.</emphasis>
                        </para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">Ukrainians appreciate active listening. <emphasis role="bold">Provide full attention when someone is talking with you. Nodding and making affirmative sounds may show that you are engaged in the conversation and appreciate the speaker</emphasis>.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">Ukrainians may prefer to avoid confrontational or aggressive communication styles. <emphasis role="bold">It’s essential to be aware of regional and individual differences when interacting with Ukrainians</emphasis> in any setting to ensure effective communication.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">Punctuality is a cultural standard. Many Ukrainians arrive early for their scheduled appointments.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para">Ukrainians accept touch in the healthcare settings but prefer not to be hugged or kissed by strangers. A handshake is acceptable. They do not appreciate nonverbal gestures such as standing with hands inserted into pockets or arms crossed over the chest. Neither do they appreciate slouching postures when being interviewed. Ukrainians are likely to seek and follow the healthcare recommendation which may appear paternalistic in the Western healthcare system.</para>
                     </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                           <emphasis role="bold">Address Ukrainians by their last name and title such as Mr., Mrs., Miss, and Ms. You can greet patients with a handshake.</emphasis>
                        </para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <para role="Para">Ukrainian family roles are influenced by traditional and cultural norms, but there can be variation in family structures and roles depending on factors such as urban or rural living, generational differences, and individual preferences, there are some common characteristics of Ukrainian family life.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Extended families with multiple generations living together were common in Ukraine. Extended family arrangement may be less common in urban areas. Extended families provide emotional and financial support and play a role in child-rearing. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients who they want to be a healthcare surrogate and to include in the medical decisions making process. Do not disclose sexual same-sex orientation to family members.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Traditional gender roles</emphasis> are still prevalent in Ukraine. Men may be seen as the primary breadwinners, while women are expected to take care of the household and children. However, women have equal decision-making power and some families may be described as maternalistic. In urban areas among younger generations, gender roles are more equitable with women pursuing careers and men taking more domestic responsibilities.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Child-rearing</emphasis>: Children’s education is highly valued in the Ukrainian culture. Parents, grandparents, and all members of the extended family may play roles in the care and education of children. There is a strong emphasis on education. Parents invest in children’s academic success. <emphasis role="bold">Include grandparents and older family members in health education for their grandchildren.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Respect for elders</emphasis> is a fundamental aspect of Ukrainian family life. Grandparents are highly respected and are often involved in the lives of their grandchildren. Elders are often consulted for advice and play a significant role in decision-making within the family. <emphasis role="bold">Help families prevent caregiver burden. Provide resources about long-term care facilities if needed and encourage family to visit the facility before a decision is made to place a family member there.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Marriage and family values are highly valued. Many Ukrainians place a strong emphasis on the importance of a stable and loving family unit. Divorce rates, while rising, are generally lower compared to some Western countries. Families often provide financial support to their members including assistance with education, housing, or other major life events. Family dynamics are evolving in Ukraine among younger generations. There is a growing emphasis on individualism, career aspirations, and personal choices. Ongoing political and war crisis led to changes in family roles and organization as well as family structures and gender roles.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Religious institutions</emphasis> have a meaningful influence on family life. Religious ceremonies and traditions are often integrated into family events such as weddings and baptisms.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Hospitality</emphasis>: Ukrainians are known for their cheerful family gatherings with extended family members coming together for celebrations and holidays. Food plays a significant role in these gatherings with elaborate traditional meals shared with loved ones.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Emigration</emphasis>: During the last 30 years, economic and political instability have led to a significant emigration of Ukrainians in search of better opportunities abroad. This has sometimes resulted in family members being separated across borders adding emotional challenges to families.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <para role="Para">Before emigration to the United States, about 70% of the Ukrainians were living in big cities residing in apartments. About 30% of Ukrainians live in rural areas and work on farms. Western Ukraine is more rural, while Eastern Ukraine is heavily industrialized. Nevertheless, many young people leave the countryside to live and work in the cities.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians have a strong <emphasis role="bold">work ethic</emphasis> and dedication to their jobs. Ukrainians value professionalism in the workplace. This includes dressing appropriately and being respectful to colleagues. Ukrainians communicate directly with colleagues and friends, and this is considered a sign of respect and sincerity. Not showing up for work without prior notification is considered disrespectful. Ukrainians practice politeness, respect, and accountability in the workplace. They value time and support the rule of work and society.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Punctuality</emphasis> is generally expected in the workplace. Being late for meetings or appointments is considered disrespectful so it’s important to arrive on time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians may practice non-direct eye contact when speaking with government officials, a practice common in Ukraine where making eye contact with government officials could lead to questioning or even invasion of personal space or disrespect. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that the lack of eye contact means the person is not paying attention, does not care, or not providing correct information.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The tone of voice may be loud as Ukrainians prefer to prove their point of view by articulating loudly. <emphasis role="bold">Do not interpret a loud voice volume as a sign of anger.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians who have immigrated to the United States are predominately white Caucasians and have a physical structure like other white Americans, making them prone to skin cancer.</para>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Encourage the use of sunblock and instruct all family members about the dangers of skin cancer.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian immigrant may have prior exposure to tuberculosis. The burden of tuberculosis (TB) remains significant according to WHO estimates. Ukraine has the fourth highest TB incidence (new cases and relapses) among the 53 countries of the WHO European Region. Other chronic infectious diseases are hepatitis and HIV.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukraine’s population faces health risks from a poor diet, smoking, alcohol consumption, and lack of regular physical activity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men are more likely to be exposed to these behavioral risk factors than women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental health remains a significant challenge. The adult male suicide rate in Ukraine is the highest in the WHO European Region (WHO <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0034s0003bib13">2021</link>
                     </emphasis>).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Physical, psychiatric trauma, and post-traumatic stress disorder can be prevalent conditions in new Ukrainian immigrants due to war exposure and economic and healthcare destruction of the country. Fewer than 2% of Ukrainians seek specialized psychological or psychiatric help and may have impaired social functioning. <emphasis role="bold">Evaluate patients’ risk factors for depression, suicide, and post-traumatic stress disorder. Younger age, lack of social support, psychiatric co-morbidities, and substance use disorder are significant.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The government spending on health in Ukraine is the lowest compared to the European countries, leaving vulnerable groups at risk of impoverishing payments and undermining access to health services. Over half (51%) of all health spending in Ukraine in 2018 was private almost entirely consisting of out-of-pocket payments. <emphasis role="bold">Explain patient governmental resources and structure of healthcare to facilitate obtaining insurance and using healthcare services.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0034s0001ta01">34.1</link>
               </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Ukrainians in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
            <table id="ch0034s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 34.1</emphasis> Top 10 health risk factors common to Ukrainians</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health condition</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cause</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">1. High systolic blood pressure</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">2. Cardiovascular disease</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">3. Diabetes mellitus</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">4. Hyperlipidemia and obesity</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">5. Depression and anxiety</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">6. Gastrointestinal disorders</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">7. Respiratory diseases</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">8. Tuberculosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environmental, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">9. Infectious diseases</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environmental, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">10. Cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetics, environmental, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Smoking is a prevalent health risk behavior in Ukraine with a high rate among men. Smoking is a major contributor to respiratory diseases, cardiovascular diseases, and cancer. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage smoking cessation and assist with finding smoking cessation programs.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukraine has one of the highest alcohol consumption rates in the world. High levels of alcohol consumption contribute to a range of health problems, including liver disease, alcohol poisoning, accidents, and violence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian diets are high in salt, saturated fats, and sugar, which can lead to obesity, hypertension, and other diet-related diseases. Insufficient consumption of fruits and vegetables is also a concern.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A sedentary lifestyle, particularly in urban areas, can contribute to obesity and high levels of diabetes and cardiovascular diseases.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Unprotected sex and a lack of access to oral contraception as well as awareness about sexually transmitted infections (STIs) lead to the spread of STIs, including HIV/AIDS. <emphasis role="bold">Explain support services in the United States for intimate partner violence. Help patients gain an access to the services.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Injection drug use</emphasis> is a significant risk factor for the spread of HIV/AIDS and hepatitis C in Ukraine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians may have <emphasis role="bold">low vaccination rates</emphasis> for preventable diseases. Inquire about prior vaccinations, and advise about possible health risks, especially among children.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Ukrainian cities, particularly Kyiv and industrial areas, have <emphasis role="bold">high level of air pollution</emphasis> which contribute to respiratory problems and cardiovascular diseases in Ukrainians.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lack of awareness about mental health issues can deter individuals from seeking help and leading to potentially risky behaviors. <emphasis role="bold">Screen all newer immigrants for conditions common in their home country. Provide scientific information and assist in finding appropriate services and resources.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Ukrainian diet includes pork, beef, goat, lamb, rabbits, chicken, duck, fish, and various cold-cut products made from pork such as ham, sausage, and bacon. Ukrainians eat large amounts of vegetables such as potatoes, cabbage, tomatoes, cucumbers, and eggplants, cooked and pickled. Breads are among staple foods: white, sour dough, dark rye, and numerous sweetened choices. Grains are popular as a side dish. A prevalent grain is buckwheat, called <emphasis>kasha.</emphasis> Popular drinks include tea, coffee, kvas, cocoa, kefir (special soured milk drink), honey and cherry liquor, and vodka with pepper (horilka).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Ukrainian dishes include <emphasis>varenyky, borsch,</emphasis> holubtsi, and <emphasis>holushki.</emphasis> Varenyky consists of boiled dumplings filled with potatoes, sauerkraut, cheese, or cherries. Ukrainians eat dumplings with sour cream-fried onions or bacon bits. Borsch is a soup of meat, beets, carrots, tomatoes, and cabbage served with bread and sour cream. Holubtsi are stuffed cabbage rolls filled with rice, buckwheat, and meat.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <para role="Para">Pregnancy and childbearing practices are similar to the Russian culture.</para>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Contraception for Ukrainian women is allowed without sanctions or taboos. Condoms, followed by intrauterine devices and birth control pills are available. Ukrainian males do not consider vasectomies as a method of contraception. Many new immigrants may not be aware of different methods of fertility control.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Inform patients of the variety of birth control methods common in the United States.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women have regular prenatal checkups, which are mandatory in Ukraine. During pregnancy, women are encouraged to rest. They do not perform heavy lifting, hard work, and strenuous physical activities; they are also protected from bad news or unpleasant information that can be harmful to the fetus. Pregnant women are encouraged to eat foods that are high in iron, calcium, and vitamins. Strawberries, citrus fruits, peanuts, and chocolate are avoided to prevent allergies in the newborn.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As labor approaches, women take laxatives and enemas to facilitate delivery. Recently husbands in Ukraine are allowed to participate in the delivery or visit the hospital postpartum. There are no cultural restrictions for fathers or female relatives not to participate in delivery in United States. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients who they wish to be involved in the delivery.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Breastfeeding is encouraged as Ukrainians believe that breast milk will increase immune system of the newborn. Some women breast-feed until the infant reaches the toddler stage.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Peri-care with warm water is important, and a binder is worn to help the mother’s figure return to normal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Ukraine, women receive maternity leave before delivery and after newborn delivery up to the 3 years. <emphasis role="bold">Explain family medical leave practices for expectant parents in the United States.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian’ families protect the terminally ill family member. They want to be notified about imminent death first before the patient is told.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most families prefer to care for the dying family member at home.</para>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Facilitate transferring the dying person to the home if the family wishes and has the means to provide terminal care. Assist with obtaining hospice home care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian families believe that everything should be done to save a loved one and often will not agree to disconnect the life support. They will not discuss advance directive, a living will, durable power of attorney, do not resuscitate procedures, and might not sign these documents. Ukrainian Orthodox pastor may perform and institute a special prayer, hymn, and vigil over the deceased.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask permission from the family before contacting clergy for their preferences.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian rural families may not accept cremation; most prefer interment. Ukrainians living in the major cities may consider cremation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Both men and women may wear black as a sign of mourning and mirrors are covered of the deceased’s home. Expression of grief varies greatly. Ukrainian Orthodox family mourns the death of a family member for at least 40 days. <emphasis role="bold">Recognize a wide variety of grieving and bereavement practices in Ukrainian culture.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians are closely associated with the Ukrainian Orthodox Church and Catholic Church. Faith plays a role in internal spirituality. The Ukrainian government recognizes Orthodox Christianity, Buddhism, Islam, and Judaism as established religions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian Americans often practice religion and attend services in Ukrainian Churches. <emphasis role="bold">Discuss individual religious practices and spirituality with patients and family during the interview.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Ukrainians define <emphasis>health</emphasis> as the absence of disease.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainian immigrants will need to become more familiar with the healthcare insurance system in the United States as Ukraine has a public healthcare system. Some clinics and hospitals in Ukraine are private, and patients pay out of pocket for their treatment. <emphasis role="bold">Explain health reimbursement procedures in the United States and elicit assistance from case managers to obtain health insurance coverage as needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hospitalization in Ukraine lasts between 3 and 4 weeks. Some patients may expect the same in the United States. Explain the hospitalization stays in the United States. <emphasis role="bold">Refer patient to the home health care agencies if needed upon discharge and teach family how to care for recuperating family member at home.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Single females do not do Pap tests in Ukraine; only, married women perform them in women center clinics. Explain the significance of Pap tests and mammography, regardless of the woman’s marital status.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many individuals prefer staying warm to prevent colds and other illnesses. Most like to keep the temperature warm in their rooms. They may also be unwilling to add ice or drink cold drinks with ice. Explain the application of ice compress in exact terms. <emphasis role="bold">Ask if a patient wants ice in their drinks.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Ukrainians consider pain a sign of weakness or fear of side effects of opioid medications and may not ask for pain medicine. <emphasis role="bold">Offer and encourage pain medicine and explain that it will help with the healing process.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Patients are not comfortable to being told about terminal diagnoses or cancer because it is believed to make the condition worse. <emphasis role="bold">Inform patients about poor prognosis gradually on their terms and preferably in several meetings. Consult with family members first and pay attention on their verbal and nonverbal cues for readiness to hear news about a terminal illness.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cupping is a common procedure in Ukraine for treatment of a respiratory infection in healthcare settings and at home. Do not mistake circular ecchymotic areas on children or adults back as abuse. <emphasis role="bold">Ask if they have been practicing cupping.</emphasis> Alcohol-saturated cotton or other materials is introduced to a cup. The cotton or material is lighted inside the cup and removed; then, the hot cup is turned upside down on the patient’s back. The skin is drawn into the cup by vacuum. The cup is pulled off the skin within 10–15 min leaving round ecchymotic areas 1–1½ in. in diameter.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common cultural practices include using herbal remedies and tinctures available from pharmacies, soaking one’s feet in warm water for a cold, gargling with salty water for sore throat, aromatherapy for a variety of respiratory illnesses, mud and mineral baths to promote healing, and herbs and teas for fever and colds. <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate nonharmful folk practices into allopathic prescriptions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians are accustomed to seeing multiple healthcare providers. Each provider may give prescriptions. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically ask patients if they are seeing other healthcare providers and taking any prescription medications, over-the-counter medications, or traditional herbal remedies and teas.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians may not disclose any mental health issues unless they are experiencing crisis. They might present with vague somatic complaints because mental illness carries a significant stigma and is considered as a weakness. <emphasis role="bold">Screen for anxiety, depression, and post-traumatic stress disorder in immigrants.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ukrainians may have a great fear of contracting HIV from blood transfusions. <emphasis role="bold">Explain US safety procedures with blood transfusions and organ donation.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0034s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">34.1.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Healthcare providers are very well respected by Ukrainian immigrants. Because nurses’ function in higher roles in the United States, Ukrainian immigrants may not understand their independent roles. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the roles and education of nurses in the United States.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men and women are accustomed to living together in very small apartments or in communal living; thus, most do not have a problem with privacy. Healthcare professionals’ gender is not generally a concern in providing care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Always ask about gender concerns before performing breast pelvic or rectal exams on patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
