<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0001s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">1.3 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What changes in ethnic and cultural diversity have you seen in your community over the last 5 years? Over the last 10 years? Have you had the opportunity to interact with newer groups?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What health disparities have you observed in your community? To what do you attribute these disparities? What can you do as a professional to help decrease these disparities?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Who in your family had the most influence in teaching you cultural values and practices? Mother, father, grandparent?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What activities have you done to increase your cultural competence?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Given that everyone is ethnocentric to some degree, what do you do to become less ethnocentric?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How do you distinguish a stereotype from a generalization?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How have your variant characteristics of culture changed over time?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Distinguish between a stereotype and a generalization.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What ethnic and racial groups do you encounter on a regular basis? Do you see any racism or discrimination among these groups?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What does your organization do to increase diversity and cultural competence?</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
