<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0003s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.4 </emphasis> Accessibility</title>
         <para role="Para">Accessibility is defined as the ability of the patient to actually get to a service when needed. Transportation services may not be available, or challenging road conditions and rivers and mountains may make it difficult for people to obtain needed health-care services when no health-care provider is available in their immediate region. Although federal law requires public facilities to be accessible to people with disabilities, there are still private clinics where accessibility may be a problem. Extremely rural hospitals have critical access facilities receive cost-based reimbursement but access can still be a concern when the closest facility is 50+ miles away.</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Make vans available at convenient locations and at specified times to transport patients to clinics.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Provide guidance for accessing services and navigating the health-care delivery system by advertising in local newspapers, in newsletters, and on public transportation systems. Local convenience stores and restaurants are additional sites to advertising services.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Provide telephone triage systems where patients and families can talk with a nurse to determine the acuity of a health concern.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </sect1>
      
