<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0032s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Cities in the United States with sizable Thai populations include Los Angeles, New York City, Houston, and Chicago. Many Thais with graduate degrees work in the United States in professional fields such as medicine, nursing, and engineering. Others own Thai restaurants or grocery stores and provide work for other Thais. Diversity among Thais is significant according to acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as described in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis> and the region in Thailand from which they come.</para>
         <para role="Para">Some of the earliest Thai immigrants in the United States were <emphasis>Eng</emphasis> and <emphasis>Chang</emphasis>, the famous Siamese twins who captured the world’s attention because of their conjoined chests and whose career was as a public exhibition. They settled in North Carolina in 1839, later changed their Thai last name to Bunker, and married American women. However, prior to 1960, Thai immigration to the United States was largely non-existent and didn’t become more prevalent until during and after the Vietnam War. Today, it is estimated that approximately a quarter of a million Thai immigrants reside in the United States.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The official language in Thailand is Thai with English as a secondary language of the elite. Thai is derived from <emphasis>Pali</emphasis> and <emphasis>Sanskrit</emphasis> (ancient South Asian languages) and has several dialects. The three main dialects are <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">pasha dai</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">pasha issam</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, and <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">pasha nua</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Thai language is a fixed tonal language having five tones. Thus, the same phonetic sound can have different meanings depending on the tone. The written alphabet is a complicated system of 44 letters with over 33 vowels or vowel combinations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Age and status contribute greatly to how Thais communicate with one another. A younger person is expected to show respect for an older person through his or her gestures and language. A Thai female uses the word <emphasis>kah</emphasis> and a Thai male uses <emphasis>kraab</emphasis> at the end of a sentence to add politeness in a conversation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Looking into a person’s eyes and conversing quietly reflects respect and politeness. A distance of 1½–2 ft between two speakers is preferable.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thais usually greet each other with the <emphasis>wai</emphasis> motion—putting the palms of both hands together in a prayer-like gesture and bowing the head slightly. This gesture is used by both men and women of all age groups. <emphasis role="bold">Health-care providers are not expected to greet patients with the</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">wai</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">motion.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Thais have long first and long last names. A Thai is usually referred to by his or her first name, even in an official setting like school or work. The names usually have clear meanings in Thai. The first name is often given by a Buddhist monk or fortune-teller based on the date, day of the week, and time of a newborn’s birth. Often, parents name their children themselves. More recently, some parents have begun to give their children Western first names.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When a woman marries, she usually takes her husband’s last name, although this has become less prevalent in recent years. A couple’s children also take their father’s last name.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When Thai names are transcribed in English, the spelling is merely a phonetic translation from its spelling in the Thai alphabet. Because Thai is a tonal language, the correct pronunciation of names cannot be ascertained from their spelling in English. <emphasis role="bold">Ask Thai patients how to pronounce their names and do the best you can in approximating them.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Almost all Thais have a short nickname used by their family and close friends and often by colleagues at work. Nicknames normally have no relationship with first names. They are often humorous to Thais themselves. Nicknames are usually either Thai or English words. They might be derived from names of colors, body types, fruits, or any number of other things. <emphasis role="bold">Feel free to ask patients if they wish to be called by their nickname. The patient may well prefer it. Maintain the legal name for medical record keeping.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In a traditional Thai family, the man is usually the breadwinner and manages important tasks such as managing finances, making decisions on major purchases, and deciding where the family will live. Household chores and taking care of children are the woman’s responsibilities. However, more Thai families today have begun to divide household chores between men and women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older Thais generally value tranquil relationships with family and friends.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai children are taught to respect elders. Talking back to elders is discouraged.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai female adolescents have traditionally been expected to protect their virginity until marriage. Dating with a chaperone is preferable. However, more and more Thai adolescents date on their own today.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are the center of the family. Many Thai children sleep with their parents from birth until some point in time before they reach adolescence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Often, children are spoon-fed by adults until they are 4–5 years old.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Marriages used to be mainly arranged by the parents. Today, young Thais have more freedom to select a spouse. Nevertheless, sometimes parents may make the final decision as to whether or not a bride or groom is acceptable.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Gays and lesbians in Thailand are more accepted today than in the past. However, for some, being gay or lesbian continues to carry a stigma. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose a patient’s same-sex relationships to the family or others.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Thais usually try to avoid personal conflicts at work and are hard workers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although the family is deemed very important, in many circumstances, especially for economic reasons, work comes before family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In general, Thai Americans tend to socialize among themselves rather than mix with Americans or people from other cultures. Therefore, some Thai Americans may not fully understand American culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai respect their supervisors because seniority is strongly valued in their culture. Thus, they might not be assertive at work. <emphasis role="bold">Supervisors may be wise to provide open discussions and expression of opportunities for their Thai American colleagues.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">English proficiency among some Thais is low, especially among newer immigrants and older people who did not learn English in Thailand. <emphasis role="bold">The language used in the workplace should be clear.</emphasis> Avoid <emphasis role="bold">slang expressions</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">An estimated 75% of the population in Thailand are pure “Thai”; 14% are Chinese; and the rest (11%) are Malay, Lao, Mon, Cambodian, Vietnamese, Asian Indian, Caucasian, or hill-dweller tribes—Karen, Lisu, Ahka, Lahu, Mien, and Hmong.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thais from northeast Thailand ( <emphasis>Isaan</emphasis>) emigrated from Laos or Cambodia and have dark brown skin.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Thais in the north immigrated to Thailand from China or Burma and tend to have finer skin texture and lighter skin color. Their noses are a little longer and their cheekbones narrower than those of <emphasis>Isaan</emphasis> Thais.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Central Thais generally have medium skin color compared with those in the rest of the country. Their facial profile is a mixture of <emphasis>Isaan</emphasis> Thais and northern Thais.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Southern Thais, some of whom migrated from Malaysia, are likely to have a darker skin color.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Regardless of skin color or facial profile, the Thais’ size and body structure are usually much smaller than those of Caucasians.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common genetic conditions among Thais are glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency (G-6-PD) and thalassemia. Different ethnic groups may have different pharmacokinetic functions. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0032s0001ta01">32.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Thais in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0032s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 32.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Thailanders</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Major health problems among Thais in Thailand include low birth weight and perinatal asphyxia, HIV/AIDS, road traffic injuries, drug and alcohol abuse, schizophrenia, diabetes, cerebrovascular disease, emphysema, and liver cancer. It is unknown to what degree these conditions are common among Thais in the United States.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sexual promiscuity among Thai youth has also contributed to an increased risk for other sexually transmitted infections (STIs) and unwanted pregnancies. <emphasis role="bold">Teach safe sex practices at every opportunity.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In general, an individual portion of a Thai dish is about one-third to one-fifth of a typical US dish in terms of volume. Most Thais are slim owing to these smaller portions and also the types of food they eat.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A Thai balanced diet usually includes low-fat/low-meat dishes with a large percentage of vegetables and legumes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rice and fish are the main staples. Rice is the main source of carbohydrates in Thai dishes, but noodles are also found in many favorite recipes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Vegetables and meats are usually fried or grilled and prepared in many combined variations to supplement rice.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pork and chicken are eaten more than beef. All meats are consumed more sparingly in proportion to vegetables when compared with a Western diet.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fish and seafood are also regularly enjoyed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Noodle recipes are much loved by Thais and are prepared with the noodles already mixed in with meats and vegetables.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For all foods, seasonings are critical to the Thai artistry of accommodating different palettes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fish and oyster sauces are very often combined with soy sauce as a basic starting point for many recipes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai chili pepper is the basic ingredient added to control the degree of spiciness in foods. Many, but not all, Thais love very spicy food.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Tom-Yum</emphasis> is a traditional spicy Thai soup that is gaining popularity worldwide. It has been found to have positive effects on people’s health because of its ingredients, which include lemongrass, galangal roots, kaffir lime leaves, hot chilies, red onions, and garlic. The soup’s antimicrobial effects come from its chilies, onions, and garlic. Onions and garlic can function against diabetes and hypercholesterolemia.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Som-tum</emphasis> is a famous spicy Thai salad. Its ingredients include fresh shredded papaya, cut tomatoes, tamarind juice, fish sauce, salt, sugar, fresh crushed garlic, and hot chilies. Sometimes, cooked or raw fermented fish is added. <emphasis>Som-tum</emphasis> is usually served with hot <emphasis>sticky</emphasis> (sweet) rice. Fresh garlic, used as an ingredient in <emphasis>Som-tum</emphasis> and many other Thai dishes, has been identified as an antifungal, antiparasitic, and antiviral agent.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thais in the United States have changed their food intake habits. They skip more meals and consume more Western foods and snacks such as white bread, salty items, fruit juice, soft drinks, and sweets. <emphasis role="bold">Assess Thai patients’ food intake habits and encourage more fruits and vegetables.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hot or warm foods or drinks are considered healthier than cold ones.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai women view pregnancy as a special time in their lives when they need extra care, both physically and emotionally. They acknowledge that this is a time when their moods can be unstable.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Owing to modesty, especially during a vaginal examination, Thai women prefer female health-care providers. <emphasis role="bold">Provide female health-care providers for intimate care during labor and delivery and the postpartum period.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women often receive advice from their mothers and/or mothers-in-law about what to do or not do during childbearing. Pregnant women are advised not to complain or get upset so that newborns will be happy and stay happy for the rest of their lives. They may also be advised not to sit on stairs or doorsills to avoid difficult labor and delivery. It is believed that when a pregnant mother blocks other people from going up and down stairs or in and out of a doorway, the unborn baby could be blocked inside the mother’s uterus.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Astrology and animism play major roles in many Thais’ lives. In general, pregnant women are discouraged from visiting a hospitalized person, attending a funeral, or visiting a house where a death has occurred. Such practices prevent the woman and her unborn baby from catching any illness or getting haunted by a spirit or ghost.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some avoid drinking coconut juice, believing that it can cause too much vernix caseosa (fat on the newborn’s skin). Others drink a lot of the juice, believing that it will help their newborns to have smooth and beautiful skin texture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Thais view lighter skin as more favorable and that drinking chocolate milk, eating chocolate, or drinking coffee will cause newborns to have a darker skin color.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women from the central region of Thailand are often seen with a safety pin on their outfit over their belly. The pin works against a kind of ghost who always wants to steal the unborn baby from a mother’s womb. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove pins or amulets of any kind unless the patient gives permission.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After a child is born, the mother is left cold and wet. Therefore, the mother should gain some heat to dry out her body, especially her uterus. To gain heat, some Thai mothers practice <emphasis>yue fai</emphasis>, which literally means “being with fire,” a complicated process that is rarely practiced in the United States and is practiced less in Thailand.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mothers are advised to use a perineal heat light, a hot sitz bath, sauna heat belts, and warm showers. Warm and hot drinks and foods are consumed; ice chips or ice cubes are avoided.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some postpartum mothers are advised to not eat eggs, chicken, or buffalo meat, believing that the new mothers’ perineum may not heal. Some believe chicken is a taboo food for women after delivery because a chicken likes to scratch the ground to look for food. The chicken meat, therefore, could scratch open the perineum. Eggs are avoided by some, believing that they could cause a big scar on the perineum.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Vegetables include lettuce, banana flower, lemongrass, onion, ginger, cabbage, hairy melon, snake beans, chili, peppers, and bamboo shoots.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Acceptable fruits after the postpartum period include oranges, bananas, tamarind, watermelon, jack fruit, and durian, an oval fruit with a hard spiny rind.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some women drink <emphasis>ya dong</emphasis>, a Thai nonalcoholic or alcoholic drink herbs such as <emphasis>ya dong,</emphasis> ginseng, galangal, peppermint, cinnamon, spirulina, and plant roots. As perceived by many Thais, <emphasis>ya dong</emphasis> is famous for its medicinal qualities. The drink helps with blood production and drying out the uterus quickly.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fathers have begun to participate more in the childbearing experience.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Thais are Buddhists. Buddhists believe that after a person dies, the person will be reborn somewhere else based on that person’s <emphasis>karma</emphasis>, the process by which a person’s moral behavior or actions have consequences for the person’s future, either in the present or later life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In general, Thai Buddhists follow the custom of cremating the bodies of the deceased, because when the Buddha passed away, his body was cremated.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Buddha’s teaching, a funeral ceremony should be simple. In the funeral ceremony, often Buddhist monks are invited to chant verses to the dead and the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The ashes from the cremation are buried at a cemetery. Sometimes, a portion of the ashes is sprinkled in a river. If possible, when the family of the dead returns home after a sojourn away from Thailand, some of the ashes may be sprinkled again in a river or near the deceased’s hometown.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Female relatives normally wail quietly. The family members pray quietly to the dead before the cremation to ask for forgiveness and wish the dead to be reborn in a happy and peaceful home. <emphasis role="bold">Expect and accept a wide range of behaviors to occur with grieving.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Thais are Buddhist and are free to incorporate any other religious values and animism into their beliefs and practices when deemed good. Thais in all socioeconomic strata incorporate animism, fortune-telling, and astrology to some degree into their religious practice.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For most Thais, family support along with Buddhism is a crucial source of strength.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Meditation and prayer are used by many Thais to cope with an illness. Meditation is a means for Thai older people to enhance their self-awareness, peace of mind, sleep, and physical health.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For older people in the United States, meditation and prayer also help them feel peaceful, perceive life as valuable, and experience meaning and confidence in death. For Thais, health and spirituality are intertwined and are important aspects of life. <emphasis role="bold">Seek assistance from chaplain services when requested.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Health promotion and disease prevention practices among the Thais are very limited. Folk practices are common among the less educated. <emphasis role="bold">Promote healthy behaviors at every opportunity.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many believe that bad <emphasis>karma</emphasis> and negative supernatural power cause mental illness. Therefore, folk therapies from traditional healers are the first resource for many families. When such therapies do not seem to work, they go to contemporary medical facilities. Folk therapies may include healing ceremonies, using shamans (as a mediator) to converse with supernatural beings (such as black magic, evil beings, and ancient/natural spirits), and negotiating with them that the sick person might be released from his or her illness.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Stigmatization attached to mental illness and beliefs in animism and <emphasis>Karma</emphasis> tend to prevent some Thais from seeking health-care providers’ help when mental health problems arise.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Thais may appear stoic in trying to withhold expressions of pain or suffering.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Rely more on nonverbal clues for pain or psychological-emotional distress when assessing Buddhist Thai patients.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When clinical depression is diagnosed, make extra efforts to encourage patients to get help and treatment, along with assuring them that depression and psychosis are different disorders.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">No religious beliefs against blood transfusion exist for Thais.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thais who believe in rebirth might object to organ donation, believing that they might not have the organ when needed in the next life.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0032s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">32.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thais in the United States and elsewhere tend to consult their family and friends first when they feel ill or have medical problems.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Thai women usually seek female health-care providers for childbearing care and gynecological problems owing to their modesty and their culture. If female providers are not available, they are generally willing to accept male health-care providers.</para>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide a female health-care provider for female intimate care whenever possible.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Respect for seniority is a strong cultural value among Thais. In general, when comparing physicians, head nurses, and junior nurses, physicians receive the most respect, followed by head nurses and junior nurses. In some cases, very senior head nurses receive the same level of respect as physicians.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
