<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0012s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">The term European American culture in this chapter refers to the middle-class values of citizens of the mainland United States and is the world’s oldest constitutional democracy. The European American culture evolved from those of early immigrants, primarily from Northern European countries. Today, the United States includes immigrants or descendants of immigrants from almost every nation and culture of the world.</para>
         <para role="Para">Americans, and individuals from other groups who have assimilated, value individualism, free speech, freedom of choice, independence, self-reliance, confidence, “doing” rather than “being,” egalitarian relationships, non-hierarchal status of individuals, individual responsibility, achievement status over ascribed status, volunteerism, friendliness, openness, futuristic temporality, technology, and the ability to control the environment. Many emphasize material possessions and physical comfort. The extent to which people conform to this dominant culture depends on the variant characteristics of culture discussed in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-21946-8_1">http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-21946-8_1</ulink>
            </emphasis>. However, remember aggregate data are true for the group but not necessarily for the individual, so this profile may not be accurate for everyone who self-identifies with the European American culture.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The United States does not have an official language. However, the unofficial language in English and accents vary regionally but are usually understandable to all. Having well-developed verbal skills is considered important.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Voice volume is loud compared with many other cultures.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The rate of speech varies depending on location within the United States, with people from the South generally speak slower than people in the Northeast.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many individuals readily disclose personal information about themselves. Personal sharing is encouraged in a wide variety of topics, but not religion.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">People of the same sex (especially men) or opposite sex do not generally touch each other unless they are relatives or close friends. <emphasis role="bold">The low-touch culture of the</emphasis> United States <emphasis role="bold">is reinforced by sexual harassment policies.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Regardless of class or social standing of the conversant, Americans are expected to maintain direct eye contact without staring. <emphasis role="bold">Just because someone does not maintain direct eye contact does not mean they are not listening or not telling the truth.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men and women extend the right hand when greeting someone for the first time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Americans are future-oriented but try to balance the past with the present. Punctuality is valued in both business and social settings.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The usual name format is given name, middle name (optional), and family name. People known to each other use the given name, although it is common to have a nickname.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Greet patients using use Mr., Mrs., Miss, Ms., or appropriate title on first meeting someone and until told to do otherwise.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A value is placed on egalitarian relationships and decision making, although great variations exist within families. Women may have careers, and men often assist with child care, household chores, and cooking responsibilities.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Great value is placed on children, and many laws help protect children.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Autonomy is encouraged in children and teenagers. Children and teenagers are encouraged to have friends of the same and opposite sex.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Teenagers are expected to refrain from premarital sex, smoking, recreational drug use, and alcohol use until they reach the age of 18 years or until they leave home. Most teenagers move out of their parents’ home when their education is completed or when they turn age 18 years.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Social attitudes toward homosexual activity vary widely and sometimes carry a stigma. In 2015, same-sex marriage became legal in the United States and same-sex relationships have become more acceptable among many.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not to disclose patients’ same-sex relationships to family members or others. Do not assume that married individuals are necessarily in a male–female marriage. Provide an environment that is welcoming to all individuals regardless of their sexual orientation.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Terminology for the same sex relationship keep evolving.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para role="Para">Heterosexual, homophobia (fear or dislike someone based on prejudice or negative attitudes toward someone who is perceived to be bi, lesbian, or gay. Intersex: described as biological attributes of both sexes, and LGBTQIA: lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgendered, queer or questioning, intersex, and asexual.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Americans are expected to be punctual on their job, with formal meetings, and with appointments. If one is more than a few minutes late, an apology is expected.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The American workforce stresses efficiency (time is money), operational procedures on how to get things done, task accomplishment, and proactive problem-solving.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Intuitive abilities and common sense are not usually valued as much as technical abilities. The scientific method is valued and everything must be proved. Americans want to know <emphasis>why</emphasis>, not <emphasis>what</emphasis>. Many are obsessed with collecting facts and figures before they make decisions. Pragmatism is valued.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">American values expect that the needs of individuals are subservient to the needs of the organization. Most Americans place a high value on “fairness,” and rely heavily on procedures and policies in the decision-making process, a necessity in individualistic cultures in order to reach consensus.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">All professionals are expected to be assertive without being aggressive, a concept that is difficult for some non-Americans. When others speak in their native language at work, it may become a source of contention for both patients and health-care personnel.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Explain rules for foreign language use upon employment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Four generations are in the workforce in the United States: (a) Traditionalists, (b) Baby Boomers, (c) Generation X, and (d) the Millennials. Each group brings a different worldview, different perspectives, and varied strengths to the workforce.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Traditionalists were born before 1945 and are characterized as being loyal, patriotic, and hard working. Many from this group worked under “control and command” styles of management and may perceive changes in the health-care field as being too radical. They have a wealth of practical expertise to share. Most have also developed conflict resolution and negotiation skills.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Baby Boomers, born between 1945 and 1965, currently comprise almost half the workforce. Most are seen as idealistic, optimistic, competitive, and community-focused. They are also considered the “sandwich generation” because they are often caring for their children and their parents. This group also has a wealth of practical expertise to share and has developed conflict resolution and negotiation skills.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Generation Xers, born between 1966 and 1980, are characterized as being highly independent and skeptical and have a “free agent” mentality and change jobs easily to meet personal needs. Most are looking for experience rather than job security.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Millennials, born between 1981 and 1996, like new ideas and change. Technology use is a given, and most are comfortable with diversity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Generation Z, born between 1997 and 2012, the first actual digital generation, they are characterized by their assertiveness in demanding flexibility, work-life balance, and advancement in their careers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Capitalize upon the strengths of each generation. Generational descriptions may not be accurate with many newer immigrant and ethnic populations.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The leading causes of death in Americans are heart disease, cancer, chronic obstructive lung disease, unintentional injury, diabetes, and HIV.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Nearly one million people in the United States are HIV-positive or have AIDS, with the highest concentrations in large urban areas.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0012s0001ta01">12.1</link>
               </emphasis> lists commonly occurring diseases and disorders for European Americans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
            <table id="ch0012s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 12.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to European Americans</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Appendicitis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Unknown</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diverticular disease</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Colon cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hemorrhoids</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Osteoporosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Osteoarthritis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cystic fibrosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Phenylketonuria</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Skin cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular disease</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Varicose veins</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Obesity</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle, environment</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Multiple sclerosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cigarette-smoking has been declining in the United States. However, many people now vape rather than smoking cigarettes. <emphasis role="bold">Assess for vaping habits</emphasis>. Higher socioeconomic groups are more likely to drink but also more likely to drink without problems. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage responsible drinking and smoking cessation beginning in elementary school.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">High-risk sexual behavior continues with the incidence of STIs and HIV infections. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage health screening and preventive behaviors such as condoms and safer-sex practices starting in elementary school.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many traffic laws have been enacted, although they vary from state to state, requiring automobile seat belts, child restraints, and helmets for bicycle and motorcycle riders.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Encourage use of seat belts, child restraints, and helmets. Refer to state laws where they exist.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The typical diet is high in fats and cholesterol and low in fiber. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage low-fat, low-cholesterol, and high-fiber diets using the U. S. Department of Agriculture food pyramids.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Given the varied topography of the United States, there are no food shortages for a healthy diet. However, socioeconomic resources prohibit some from purchasing healthy foods. <emphasis role="bold">Teach patients about healthy foods and preparation practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Meal times and food choices vary according to ethnic background, the region of the country, urban versus rural residents, and weekdays versus weekends.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Breakfast is usually consumed between 6:00 a.m. and 9:00 a.m., depending on the person’s work schedule. The noontime meal, typically consumed by 1:00 p.m., is called lunch in urban areas and dinner in rural areas. The evening meal, dinner in urban areas or supper in rural areas, is served between 6:00 p.m. and 9:00 p.m. and is usually the largest meal of the day.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Determine meal times, and adjust medications accordingly.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Commonly used methods of fertility control include natural ovulation methods, birth control pills, foams, Norplant, the morning-after pill, intrauterine devices, condoms, abortion, and sterilization procedures such as vasectomy and tubal ligations. Sterilization in the United States is strictly voluntary. <emphasis role="bold">Abortion remains a controversial issue.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women are expected to seek preventive care, eat a well-balanced diet, and get adequate rest in order to have a healthy pregnancy and baby. Women are encouraged to breast-feed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Discourage smoking, drinking alcohol, consuming large amounts of caffeine, and taking recreational drugs during pregnancy.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Prospective fathers are encouraged to take prenatal classes with expectant mothers and provide a supportive role in the delivery process. <emphasis role="bold">Fathers who do not want to participate should not be made to feel guilty.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Respect cultural beliefs associated with pregnancy and the birthing process.</emphasis> Possible restrictive beliefs for pregnant women are listed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0012s0001ta02">12.2</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Integrate nonharmful cultural practices into preventive teaching and interventions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0012s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 12.2</emphasis> Possible restrictive beliefs for pregnant women</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Pregnant women should refrain from being around loud noises for prolonged times</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Wearing an opal ring during pregnancy can harm the baby</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Eating strawberries or being frightened by a snake cause birthmarks</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Congenital anomalies can occur if the mother sees or experiences a tragedy during her pregnancy</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Nursing mothers should eat a bland diet to avoid upsetting the baby</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• The infant should wear a band around the abdomen to prevent the umbilicus from protruding and becoming herniated</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• A coin, key, or other metal object should be put on the umbilicus to flatten it</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Cutting a baby’s hair before baptism can cause blindness</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• If the pregnant woman raises her hands over her head while pregnant, it may cause the cord to wrap around the baby’s neck</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Moving heavy items can cause a pregnant woman’s “insides” to fall out</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Children born with physical or mental abnormalities are punishment from god for acts of the parents</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death and responses to death are difficult topics for many Americans to verbalize.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The dying person should not be left alone. <emphasis role="bold">Make accommodations for a family member to be with the dying person at all times. Health-care personnel are expected to care for the family as much as for the patient during this time.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most people are buried or cremated within 3 days of death; extenuating circumstances may lengthen this period to accommodate family and friends who must travel a long distance to attend a funeral or memorial service. The family decides if the deceased will be cremated or will have an open or closed casket.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">More people are choosing to remain at home and participate in a hospice for end-of-life care to have their comfort needs met. <emphasis role="bold">One requirement for hospice care is that the patient must sign documents indicating that he or she does not want extensive life-saving measures performed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although women may be more expressive than men, most Americans demonstrate their grief conservatively. Generally, tears are shed, but loud wailing and uncontrollable sobbing rarely occur. Bereavement support strategies are listed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0012s0001ta03">12.3</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0012s0001ta03">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 12.3</emphasis> Bereavement support strategies</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Being physically present</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Acknowledging the patient’s pain</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Encouraging a reality orientation</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Openly acknowledging the family’s right to grieve</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Recognizing varied behavioral responses to grief</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Assisting the patient and family to express their feelings</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Encouraging interpersonal relationships</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Promoting interest in a new life</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Making referrals to other resources such as a priest, minister, rabbi, or pastoral care person, with the patient’s or family’s permission. Allow a family member to remain with the patient</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dominant religions in the United States are those of the Judeo-Christian faiths and include Catholicism, Protestantism, and Judaism. However, there are many other recognized religions that are consistent with religious freedom, a reason that many people immigrated to the United States. Although church and state are separate, many public events and ceremonies still open with a prayer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In times of illness, many people say prayers. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients if they need anything to say prayers. Inquire if the person wants to see a member of the clergy.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove religious symbols or statues as they provide solace to the person. Removing them may increase or cause anxiety.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0012s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">12.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The United States continues to undergo a paradigm shift from curative and restorative medical practices and sophisticated technological care to health promotion and wellness; illness, disease, and injury prevention; and health restoration. Many view good health as a divine gift from God.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Advance directives are an important part of medical care, which allow patients to specify their wishes concerning life and death decisions before entering an inpatient facility. These directives also designate the name of a family member or significant other to speak for the patient and make decisions when or if the patient is unable to do so. Some patients have a living will that outlines their wishes in terms of life-sustaining procedures in the event of a terminal illness or a serious accident. <emphasis role="bold">Each inpatient facility has these forms available and will ask the patient what his or her wishes are. Patients may sign these forms at the in-patient facility or elect to bring their own forms.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">As an adjunct to biomedical treatments, many people use acupuncture, acupressure, acumassage, herbal therapies, massage therapy, aromatherapy, and other complementary and alternative treatments. An awareness of combined practices when treating or providing health education to individuals and families helps ensure that therapies do not conflict with each other, intensify the treatment regimen, or cause an overdose.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Nonjudgmentally inquire about all therapies being used, such as foods, teas, herbal remedies, non-food substances, over-the-counter medications, and medications prescribed or loaned by others.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Often, traditional, folk, and magicoreligious non-harmful practices should be incorporated into the plan of care for patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">To help prevent contradictory or exacerbated effects of prescription medication and treatment regimens, ask patients about self-medicating practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pain is the “fifth vital sign.” Patients should be made comfortable and not have to tolerate high levels of pain. <emphasis role="bold">Offer and encourage pain medication, and explain that it will help the healing process.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Americans with Disabilities Act protects individuals with a handicap from discrimination. Rehabilitation and occupational health services focus on returning individuals with handicaps to productive lifestyles in society as soon as possible.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Traditional practice calls for fully disclosing health conditions to patients, who then disclose the information to the family.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Americans favor organ donation and transplantation and blood or blood products transfusions. <emphasis role="bold">Some people refuse blood or blood products for fear of contracting HIV.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Jehovah’s Witnesses do not receive blood or blood products. Assist patients in obtaining a religious leader to support them in making decisions regarding organ donation or transplantation if requested.</emphasis> Health-Care Providers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most people combine biomedical health-care practices with traditional practices, folk healers, and magicoreligious healers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Standard practice is to assign staff to patients regardless of gender differences.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Recognize and respect differences in gender relationships when providing care. Respect patients’ modesty by providing adequate privacy and assigning same-sex caregivers whenever the patient requests.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The advanced practice role of registered nurses is gaining respect as their numbers increase and research demonstrates and the public sees them as equal or preferable to physicians. The public holds nurses in high regard.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
