<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
      
            <emphasis role="bold">Today’s Amish live in rural areas in a band of more than 20 states, stretching westward from Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Indiana to as far west as Montana, with some scattered settlements in Florida and the province of Ontario, Canada. Recently, Amish have started new communities in six states that had not had settlements prior: Colorado, Nebraska, New Mexico, South Dakota, Vermont, and Wyoming. Population estimates of Amish in 2022 were 373,620 with an increase of approximately 12,150 since 2021. Amish communities in Canada include the provinces of Ontario, Manitoba, New Brunswick, and Prince Edward Island. As affordable land has decreased, some Amish have migrated to Argentina and Bolivia. The Old Order Amish, the so-called for their strict observance of traditional ways that distinguish them from other, more progressive “plain folk,” are the largest and most notable group. The Amish emerged after 1693, when they parted ways with the Anabaptist movement that originated in Switzerland in 1525. After experiencing severe persecution and martyrdom in Europe, the Amish and related groups immigrated to North America in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries. Some variant groups are named after their factional leaders (for example, Egli and Beachy Amish); some are called conservative Amish Mennonites; and others, New Order Amish. No Amish live in Europe today after leaving in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries due to religious persecution.</emphasis>
    
         </para>
         <para role="Para">Even though the Amish have persisted in relative social isolation, they continue to adapt and change at their own pace, accepting innovations selectively. Although most Amish homes do not have electricity and electronic labor-saving devices and appliances, that does not preclude their openness to using state-of-the-art medical technology necessary for health promotion. The Amish selectively adapt to technology when it is necessary; selected use telephones for business and health-care purposes is more commonly permitted in the more progressive orders of Amish. They also may use other technology such as electrically powered ventilators for home care when required. With the advent of technology and not being able to order from such catalogs as Sears, they have been forced to order online. In many Amish communities, local stores that cater to the Amish will place electronic orders for them.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">English is the language of school, of written and print communications, and of contact with most non-Amish outsiders.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">At home and in the immediate Amish communities, <emphasis role="bold">Deitsch/Deutsch</emphasis>, or Pennsylvania German, is used. In this highly contextual culture, less overt verbal communication is required, and more reliance is placed on implicit, often unspoken, understandings. Much of what passes for “general knowledge” in the information-rich popular culture is screened, or filtered, out of Amish awareness.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Expect all Amish patients of school age and older to be fluently bilingual. They can readily understand spoken and written directions and answer questions presented in English, although their own terms for some symptoms and illnesses may not have exact equivalents in Deitsch and English.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Amish have severely restricted their own access to print media, permitting only a few newspapers and periodicals. Most have also rejected electronic media such as radios, television, and entertainment and information applications of film and computers. Since the decline of mail order catalogs, many Amish consider alternative methods of securing necessary supplies. In some communities, the Amish are able to go to community stores where personnel will order supplies and equipment for them online.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish are clearly not outwardly demonstrative or exuberant. Fondness and love of family members is held deeply but privately. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Demut</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, humility, is a priority value, the effects of which may be observed in public as a modest and unassuming demeanor. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Hochmut</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, pride or arrogance, is avoided.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">The expression of joy and suffering is not entirely subdued by dour or stoic silence.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish present in an unpretentious, quiet manner, with modest outward dress in plain colors lacking any ornament, jewelry, or cosmetics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">They are unassertive and nonaggressive and avoid confrontational speech styles and public displays of emotion.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish self-perception is grounded in the present. In public, Amish avoid eye contact with non-Amish, but in one-on-one clinical contacts, patients can be expected to express openness and candor with unhesitating eye contact.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">They are generally punctual and conscientious about keeping appointments.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Using first names with Amish people is appropriate because there are only a limited number of surnames. For example, it is preferable to use John or Mary during personal contacts rather than Mr. or Mrs. Miller. Within Amish communities, individuals are identified further by nicknames, residence, linked with description of occupation or a spouse’s given name.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Greet Amish patients with a handshake and a smile.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask Amish if they have access to a telephone where messages may be left if needed.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">If educational videos are shown in the health-care organization, ask Amish if they wish to view them or if they prefer printed material. If preoperative or postoperative/discharge care is usually delivered via online video, they may be willing to view them in the office or health-care facility if no other reasonable options are available. If this is necessary, offer them paper and pencil to take notes for review at home.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish society is patriarchal, but women are accorded high status and respect. Practically speaking, husband and wife may share equally in decisions regarding the family farming business. In public, the wife may assume a retiring role, deferring to her husband, but in private they are typically partners. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that the spokesperson for the family is the primary decision-maker. Verify who the health-care provider has permission to share information with to facilitate health-care decision-making for the family. This should be documented in the patient chart.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish family pattern is the three-generational family. This kinship network includes consanguine relatives consisting of the parental unit and households of married children and their offspring. It is not uncommon for multi-generations to reside together.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The highest priority for parents is child rearing, a charge given them by the church.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Young people older than 16 years may experiment with non-Amish dress and behavior, but the expectation is that they will be baptized Amish before marriage. Unmarried children live in the parents’ home until marriage. Single adults are included in the social fabric of the community.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families are the units that make up church districts. The size of church districts is measured by the number of families rather than by the number of church members. When the church district increases to a size that is not manageable, a new district may be formed to splinter off.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Grandparents have respected status as elders; they provide valuable advice, material support, and services that include child care to the younger generation. Family emotional and physical proximity to older adults facilitates elder care.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Include the extended nuclear family in health educational activities.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish place a high value on hard work, with little time off for leisure or recreation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the past, the Amish have worked almost exclusively in agriculture and farm-related tasks. Amish avoidance of compromising associations with “worldly” organizations, such as labor unions, restricts them to non-union work, which often pays lower hourly rates. Work settings that rely heavily on modern technology are not open to the Amish.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Amish with carpentry and other businesses have landlines and or cell phones that are located in the shop or outside the building in a weather protected box. Several families may share one telephone. <emphasis role="bold">Ask if there is a telephone where messages may be left and what medical information is permissible to leave in a message (or would they prefer a message instructing them to call the health provider back)</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish may avoid eye contact with non-Amish, but in one-on-one contacts in the work environment, they can be expected to express openness and candor with unhesitating eye contact. <emphasis role="bold">Do not take offense at sustained eye contact.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because English is the language of instruction in schools and is used with business contacts in the outside world, there is generally no language barrier for the Amish in the workplace. <emphasis role="bold">Do not use slang or idiomatic expressions that the Amish may not understand.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish are essentially a closed population, with exogamy occurring very rarely. Most are of German and Swiss descent; therefore, their physical characteristics differ, with skin variations ranging from light to olive tones. Hair and eye colors vary accordingly.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Statistics do not exist for Amish cardiovascular and respiratory diseases and illnesses or for the incidence of cancer and diabetes mellitus. Obesity is common, especially among women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0006s0001ta01">6.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for the Amish. A description of the common genetic disorders is in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0006s0001ta02">6.2</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0006s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 6.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to the Amish</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Limb-girdle muscular dystrophy</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ellis-van Creveld syndrome</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dwarfism</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, unknown</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Polydactylism</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cartilage hair hypoplasia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Glutaric aciduria</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Manic-depressive disorder</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pyruvate kinase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hemophilia B</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Obesity</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table id="ch0006s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 6.2</emphasis> Common genetic disorders</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Dwarfism</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Ellis-van Creveld syndrome</emphasis> is characterized by short stature and an extra digit on each hand, congenital heart defects, and nervous system involvement resulting in some amount of mental deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Cartilage hair hypoplasia</emphasis>, also a dwarfism syndrome, is characterized by short stature; fine, silky hair; and deficient cell-mediated immunity that increases susceptibility to viral infections</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Pyruvate kinase anemia</emphasis>, a rare blood-cell disease with jaundice and anemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Hemophilia B</emphasis>
                           </para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Phenylketonuria</emphasis> (PKU) results in an inability to metabolize the amino acid phenylalanine, evidenced as high blood levels of the substance and eventually severe brain damage if the disorder is untreated</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis>Glutaric aciduria</emphasis>, a progressive neurologic disease, which can be prevented by screening individuals at risk, restricting dietary protein, and thus limiting protein catabolism, dehydration, and acidosis during illness episodes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Health-care providers need to plan for family and community education about genetic counseling and screening of newborns for genetic conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Farm and traffic accidents are major health concerns because of horse-drawn vehicles. Transportation-related injuries involving farm animals are the largest group. Falls from ladders and down hay holes result in numerous orthopedic injuries. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage close monitoring of children who operate farm equipment and transportation vehicles.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alcohol and recreational drug use occur at low rates among the Amish, although few statistics as to the frequency can be found. <emphasis role="bold">Teach about safety factors. Ask about alcohol and recreational drug use in a nonjudgmental approach and when family members are not present. It is important to remember that when young adults may choose to try non-Amish activities during rumspringa, they may be at increased risk for injuries due to lack of familiarity.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Amish families grow their own produce. Typical meals include meat; potatoes or noodles or both; a cooked vegetable; bread; something pickled, such as red beets; cake or pudding; and coffee.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">At mealtimes, all members of the household are expected to be present.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Snacks and meals tend to be high in fat and carbohydrates. Common snacks are large, home-baked cookies about 3 in. in diameter, ice cream, pretzels, and popcorn.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When asking about weight control, suggest reducing portion size, decreasing the amount of sugar used in baking, limiting fatty meats, offering more fresh fruits and vegetables and altering food preparation practices.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are considered gifts from God. The average number of live births per family is seven. Birth control is viewed as interfering with God’s will and thus should be avoided. Nevertheless, some Amish women do use intrauterine devices, but this practice is uncommon. <emphasis role="bold">Approaching the subject of birth control obliquely may make it possible for an Amish woman or man to sense the health-care provider’s respect for Amish values and thus encourage discussion. “When you want to learn more about birth control, I would be glad to talk to you” is a suggested approach. It is also important for health-care providers to offer education if using hormonal medication for non-contraceptive use. An Amish woman may not be aware of medicinal uses other than birth control for these medications.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women participate in prenatal classes, often with their husbands. Women are interested in learning about all aspects of perinatal care, but they may choose not to participate in sessions when videos are used. <emphasis role="bold">Prenatal class instructors should inform them ahead of time when videos or films will be used so they can decide whether to attend.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most women prefer home births and choose to use Amish or non-Amish lay midwives. The Amish have no major taboos or requirements for birthing. Men may be present, and most husbands choose to be involved; however, they are likely not to be demonstrative in showing affection verbally or physically.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The laboring woman cooperates quietly, seldom audibly expressing discomfort. Women sometimes use herbal remedies to promote labor. <emphasis role="bold">Knowledge about and respect for Amish health-care practices alert health-care providers to the possibility of simultaneous treatments that may or may not be harmful.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The postpartum mother resumes her family role managing, if not doing, all the housework, cooking, and child care within a few days after childbirth. Grandmothers or other female relatives often come to stay with the new family for several days to help with care of the infant and give support to the new mother. Older siblings are expected to help care for the younger children and to learn how to care for the newborn.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When hospitalized, the family may want the patient to spend the least allowable time in the hospital. <emphasis role="bold">Include extended nuclear family in care of the newborn. Ask the father how extensively he wants to be involved with labor and delivery.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families are expected to care for the aging and the ill in the home. However, when hospitalization is required, <emphasis role="bold">make private arrangements for family members to stay overnight in the hospital.</emphasis> A wake-like “sitting up” through the night is expected for the seriously ill and dying.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">While it is unusual for Amish to use cremation, many will utilize local funeral services for embalming. This would enable family and friends to travel for viewing and participation in funeral services. The viewing and services may occur in a family home or barn building depending on the size of gathering.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The funeral ceremony is simple and unadorned, with a plain wooden coffin and no flowers. Although grief and loss are keenly felt, verbal expression may seem muted as if to indicate stoic acceptance of suffering. No eulogy is offered.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish community will assist the family by preparing daily meals, assisting in performing farm work, business obligations or household management during the period of bereavement.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Accept varied means of grieving from Amish families. Just because grief is not overtly demonstrated does not mean that family members do not care about their loved one.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish religious and cultural values include honesty, order, personal responsibility, community welfare, humility, non-resistance or nonviolence, and obedience to parents, church, and God.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish are socialized to sustain injuries, grieve, and move on without fixing blame or seeking punishment or redress from perpetrators.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish settlements are subdivided into church districts similar to rural parishes, with 30–50 families in each district. Local male leaders are chosen from their own community and are generally untrained and unpaid. No regional or national church hierarchy exists to govern internal church affairs. To maintain harmony within a group, individuals often forgo their own wishes. In addition to Sunday services every other week, silent prayer is always observed at the beginning of a meal. A prayer may also end the meal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When choosing among health-care options, families usually seek counsel from religious leaders, friends, and extended family, but the final decision resides with the immediate family.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The body is considered to be the temple of God, and human beings are stewards of their bodies. Medicine and health care should always be used with the understanding that it is God who heals. Nothing in the Amish understanding of the Bible forbids them from using preventive or curative medical services. They are highly involved in the practices of health promotion and wellness; illness and disease prevention, and health restoration. Men are involved in major health-care decisions and often accompany the family to the chiropractor, physician, or hospital. Health-care decisions are influenced by three factors: (1) type of health problem, (2) accessibility of health-care services, and (3) perceived cost of the service. Grandparents are frequently consulted about treatment options. <emphasis role="bold">Include the extended nuclear family in health-care decision-making.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Amish do not carry health insurance. Some have formalized mutual aid, such as the Amish Aid Society. <emphasis role="bold">Ask Amish families if they have access to the Amish Aid Society and assist with contacting them if desired. Some health-care systems or hospitals in areas where there is a large Amish population, have established reduced set costs for common medical procedures when paid in cash, as preferred by the Amish.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Providers must be aware that some individuals may withhold important medical information from medical providers by neglecting to mention folk and alternative care being pursued at the same time. Health-care providers must remain open to hearing and learning more about these types of care choices.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">When the Amish use professional health-care services, they want to be partners in their health care and want to retain their right to choose from all culturally sanctioned health-care options.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Care is expressed in culturally encoded expectations, which the Amish best describe in their dialect as <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">abwaarde</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, meaning “to minister to someone by being present and serving when someone is sick in bed.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some accept medical advice regarding the need for high-technology treatments such as transplants, ventilator support, or other high-cost interventions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The patient’s family seeks prayers and advice from the bishop and deacons of the church, the extended family, and friends, but the decision is generally a personal family choice. Family members may also seek care from Amish healers and other alternative care practitioners, who may suggest nutritional supplements.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Herbal remedies include those handed down by successive generations of mothers and daughters.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common folk illnesses are described in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0006s0001ta03">6.3</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Health-care knowledge is passed from one generation to the next through women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Inquire about the full range of remedies being used. For the Amish patient to be candid, the provider must develop a context of mutual trust and respect.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Amish are unlikely to display pain and physical discomfort. <emphasis role="bold">Remind Amish patients that medication is available for pain relief if they choose to accept it.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There are no cultural or religious rules or taboos prohibiting blood transfusions or organ transplantation and donation. Some may opt for organ transplantation after the family seeks advice from church officials, extended family, and friends, but the patient or immediate family generally makes the final decision.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children with mental or physical differences are sometimes referred to as “hard learners” and are expected to go to school and be incorporated into classes with assistance from other student “scholars” and parents. The mentally ill are generally cared for at home whenever possible.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0006s0001ta03">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 6.3</emphasis> Common Amish folk illnesses</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Brauche, sometimes referred to as sympathy curing or powwowing, is referred to as “warm hands” and includes the ability to feel when a person has a headache or a baby has colic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis role="bold">Abnemme</emphasis> is a condition in which the child fails to thrive and appears small, ill, and weak. Specific treatments for the child may include incantations</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• <emphasis role="bold">Aagwachse</emphasis>, or livergrown, meaning “hide-bound” or “grown together,” includes crying and abdominal discomfort that is believed to be caused by jostling in rough buggy rides</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0006s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">6.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish hold all health-care providers in high regard. Health is integral to their religious beliefs, and care is central to their worldview. They tend to place trust in people of authority when they fit Amish values and beliefs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Amish usually refer to their own healers by name rather than by title, although some say <emphasis>brauch-doktor</emphasis> or <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">braucher</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>. In some communities, both men and women provide these services. Amish folk healers use a combination of treatment modalities, including physical manipulation, massage, <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">brauche</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, herbs and teas, and reflexology. Most prefer health-care providers who discuss health-care options, giving consideration to cost, need for transportation, family influences, and scientific information.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Because Amish are not sophisticated in their knowledge of physiology and scientific health care, health-care providers should be prepared to use educational materials that may include anatomic models or illustrations. Providers should bear in mind that the Amish respect authority and that they may unquestioningly follow orders.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
