<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0033s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">33.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Explain the Turkish language and how it might be difficult for Americans to pronounce Turkish names. What might you do to ensure you pronounce a name correctly?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Give some examples of the collectivistic Turkish family versus the individualistic culture of European American and other nationalities. What implications does this have for patient education?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify communication practices related to touch among Turkish people. How does this vary among women, men, their religion, and tradition?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify genetic conditions common among Turks. Which of them has a lifestyle component?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Describe the practices conducted during the holy month of <emphasis>Ramazan</emphasis>? How would you change your practice to accommodate a person who is conducting these practices during <emphasis>Ramazan</emphasis>?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What function does somatization have in Turkish culture? How would you address a patient who is somaticizing?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What is a <emphasis>nazar boncuk</emphasis>, and what is its function?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify two folk remedies and the conditions they are used for.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Explain why newer Turkish immigrants may easily assimilate into the dominant European American culture?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>As a nurse, you are visiting a Turkish patient in their home. What do you need to consider before entering their home?</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
