<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0015s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">This chapter presents two groups of people with Greek heritage. The first group refers to those or their ancestors who emigrated from Greece and the second group originated in Cyprus. Both groups have a common history, language, and religion. The Greek and Greek Cypriot diaspora is of considerable size and has spread to all continents and numerous countries. The largest Greek community outside Greece is in the United States, and the largest Greek Cypriot community outside Greece is in Britain.</para>
         <para role="Para">Greece, a small country in southern Europe, enjoys a climate similar to that of southern California. The characteristics of members of the Greek and Greek Cypriot communities vary according to acculturation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. 1).</para>
         <para role="Para">The core values of philotimo (honor and respect) and endropi (shame) are key when considering the experience of Greeks and Greek Cypriots. Although values of honor and shame are found in all societies, they are particularly important among Mediterranean groups. Philotimo is a Greek’s sense of honor and worth derived from one’s self-image, one’s reflected image (respect), and one’s sense of pride. Philotimo is enhanced through courage, strength, fulfilling family obligations, competition with other people, hospitality, and appropriate behavior. Shame results from any conduct that is considered deviant.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <para role="Para">All Greeks, whether in Greece, Cyprus, or the diaspora, use the same form of written language, although there are regional and country variations in spoken Greek. Greek communities regard the retention of the Greek language as an essential part of their identity; thus, much effort is expended encouraging second and subsequent generations to speak Greek. Many first-generation Greek Cypriots speak very little or no English.</para>
            <para role="Para">Obtain an interpreter when necessary; do not rely on family members who may not fully disclose information because of honor and shame.</para>
            <para role="Para">Greek and Greek Cypriots tend to be expressive in both speech and gesturing. They use their hands frequently while talking. They embrace family, friends, and others to indicate solidarity. Whereas innermost feelings, such as anxiety or depression, are often shielded from outsiders, anger is expressed freely, sometimes to the discomfort of those from less expressive groups. Eye contact is generally direct and speaking and sitting distance is closer than that of other European Americans. Do not take offense if patients stand closer to you than you are accustomed. Do not assume that prolonged eye contact is a sign of anger.</para>
            <para role="Para">Patients often appear to be compliant in the presence of the healthcare worker, but this may be only superficial to ensure a smooth relationship. Stress the importance of letting the healthcare provider know the patient’s intentions on complying with health prescriptions.</para>
            <para role="Para">Greeks are oriented to the past as they are highly conscious of the glories of ancient Greece. They are present-oriented regarding philotimia, family life, and situations involving family members. However, they tend to be future-oriented regarding educational and occupational achievements. Greek Americans differentiate between “Greek time,” which is used in family and social situations, and “American/clock time,” which is used in business situations. Greek time emphasizes participating in activities until they reach a natural breaking point, whereas American/clock time emphasizes punctuality. Reinforce the necessity of punctuality if the situation requires it.</para>
            <para role="Para">For Greeks having a Greek name is an important sign of their heritage. Honorific titles might be given to members of the community who are elders or otherwise respected. Terms such as Thia (aunt), Kyria (Mrs.), or giagia (grandma) may be used. First names come from either the Bible or from Greek mythology and history. Ideally, first daughters are named for the mother’s mother and first sons for the father’s father. Following tradition, middle names are the first name of the father.</para>
            <para role="Para">In healthcare situations, it is not appropriate to call an older woman or man by the first name. The prefix Kyria or Kyrie should be used with the first name, for example, Kyria Maria or Kyrie Alexandre. Alternatively, the preferred mode of address is using the surname preceded by Mr., Mrs., Miss, or Ms.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <para role="Para">Traditionally, the father was considered the head of the household in Greek and Greek Cypriot families. The complexity of household dynamics is noted in the well-known folk saying, “The man is the head but the wife is the neck that decides which way the head will turn.” This acknowledges the primacy of fathers in the public sphere and the strong influence of women in the private sphere. In recent years, there has been increased recognition of a trend toward more equality in decision making.</para>
            <para role="Para">The core values of philotimo and endropi set the pattern for the family and for the enactment of gender roles. The traditional roles of husband and wife are characterized by mutual respect (a partnership). However, their relationship is less significant than that of the family as a unit. Although in the past fathers were responsible for providing for the family, in modern times mothers are also providers as well as having the bigger share of responsibility for the management of the home and children. Protection of family members and maintenance of family solidarity tends to be foremost among their values. Consequently, they are often friendly but somewhat superficial and distant with those considered “outsiders.”</para>
            <para role="Para">Traditionally the cleanliness and order of the home reflect the moral character of the woman.</para>
            <para role="Para">Children are included in most family social activities and tend not to be left with babysitters. The child is the recipient of intense affection, helpful interventions, and strong admiration. The child may be disciplined through teasing, which is thought to “toughen” children and make them highly conscious of public opinion. Accept alternative forms of childrearing as long as they are not psychologically or physically abusive.</para>
            <para role="Para">Adolescents, particularly young women, tend to reside with their parents until they get married. Unlike previous generations, spouse selection is left to the adolescent, with parental approval. Girls have considerably less freedom in dating than their brothers and it is common for girls to be prohibited from dating until they are in the upper grades of high school. Adolescents in more traditional families may experience stress as the differences in family and peer values precipitate family conflict.</para>
            <para role="Para">High stress areas include extreme dependence on the family, intense pressure for school achievement, and a lack of sexual education in the home although the young generation has access to a mobile phone, a tablet, and a computer which they use to educate themselves. School nurses and counselors are in a good position to provide sex education and to discuss issues related to personal freedom. Educate teachers on early warning signs of suicide ideology.</para>
            <para role="Para">Prestige is connected to the idea that honor is collective and individual. Because a person loses honor if a family member acts improperly, the honor of each family member is a matter of concern for all family members. Older people hold positions of respect. Include the extended nuclear family in healthcare decision making.</para>
            <para role="Para">Although in the past families were obliged to care for their parents in old age, this rule is now more flexible for several reasons. Many of the older people (70–80 years) are likely to have arrived in the United States as children or young adults and were able to become fluent in English, be educated to a high level, and find employment outside the Greek community. All these factors enabled them to be take care of themselves through finding and using relevant information or seeking help from the systems operating in the area where they live. However, families continue to provide support that will ensure the comfort and dignity of their parents. Failure to do so results in a sense of dishonor and guilt for the family. Treatment of the yiayia (grandmother) and the pappou (grandfather) reflects the themes of closeness and respect emphasized in the family. Grandparents tend to participate fully in family activities. Include the family when planning to or providing services to older persons.</para>
            <para role="Para">If an older person is ill, living with the family is the first preference, followed by placement in a residential care facility. Although living alone is often the least preferred residential pattern, many older people are choosing to live alone with the support of family, friends, and healthcare providers. Help the family obtain needed support services for providing care to family members in the home setting.</para>
            <para role="Para">The basis of social status and prestige is family philotimo and cohesiveness. However, social status is also received from attributes such as wealth, educational achievement, and achievements of its members. Honor is the social worth of the family as judged by the community.</para>
            <para role="Para">Greeks tend to be relatively conservative. Consequently, alternative lifestyles encompassing premarital sex, divorce, and same-sex relationships are considered sources of concern for family members and the community. Do not disclose same-sex relationships and matters of personal privacy to family members or others.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <para role="Para">In the United States, the high achievement orientation and work ethic have resulted in Greeks serving as a “model” ethnic group. Greeks stress on self-reliance is sometimes seen as reluctance to be told what to do. Do not misinterpret self-reliance with not taking direction from superiors.</para>
            <para role="Para">Eye contact is generally direct and speaking, and sitting distance is closer than that of other European Americans. Do not take offense if Greek employees stand closer to you than to which you are accustomed. Do not assume that prolonged eye contact is a sign of anger.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <para role="Para">Greeks are most commonly of medium stature, shorter than northern Europeans but taller than other populations of southern Europe. Although some Greeks have blue eyes and blond hair, usually from the northern provinces of Greece, most Greeks have brown eyes, dark hair, and dark skin.</para>
            <para role="Para">Assess recent immigrants for health conditions such as typhoid and hepatitis A and B.</para>
            <para role="Para">Screen for glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G-6-PD) deficiency and do not administer oxidant drugs such as primaquine, quinidine, thiazolsulfone, dapsone, furazolidone, nitrofuran, naphthalene, toluidine blue, phenylhydrazine, chloramphenicol, and aspirin. Make patients aware that broad beans (fava beans) can induce hemolysis and an acute anemic crisis when ingested. Consider G-6-PD deficiency in Greek patients with unconjugated jaundice.</para>
            <para role="Para">Most Greek and Greek Cypriot women choose to have an abortion if they are found to carry a fetus with thalassemia.</para>
            <para role="Para">Screen Greek patients for thalassemia, and advise them of genetic risks.</para>
            <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0015s0001ta01">15.1</link>
               </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Greek and Greek Cypriots in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetic.</para>
            <table id="ch0015s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 15.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Greeks and Greek Cypriots</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health Condition</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Major risk factors include smoking, diet, obesity, and lack of physical activity</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cancer is one of the highest leading causes of death. Common cancers include colorectal, breast, prostate, and lung cancers</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Mental health disorders</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Mental health issues like depression, anxiety, and substance abuse are prevalent in the Greek population</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">The diabetes rates have rapidly increased along with rising obesity. Genetics and changing diets are possible factors</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Neurodegenerative diseases</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle, environment</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Alzheimer’s disease and Parkinson’s disease have rates comparable to other ethnicities. As life expectancy increases, so will age-associated neurological conditions</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6 PD</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Deficiency in G6 PD is more common in ethnic populations from regions like Africa, the Mediterranean, and Southeast Asia</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia is a blood disorder which affects Greek people. However, government initiatives in Greece and Cyprus have significantly reduced the number of people affected by it</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alcohol is most often considered a food item and is consumed with meals. However, losing control by being “under the influence” engenders considerable gossip and social disgrace, focused not only on the individual but also on the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Obesity among both sexes and smoking among men are high among Greeks. Although a high level of risk-taking appears to be part of survival, it is in fact perpetuated by the belief that “God will look after me,” meaning that God will prevent anything untoward happening and that if anything should happen, God will heal and sustain the person.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Network in elementary schools to educate about the hazards of smoking.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Greeks tend to disregard standard health promotion behaviors. Safety measures such as seat belts and helmets are often viewed as infringements on personal freedom and are frequently ignored, particularly by the older generation. Explain the legal requirements for seat belt and helmet laws, and encourage their use.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greeks describe their culture as an “eating culture.” Food is a centerpiece of everyday life as well as of social and ritual events.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fasting is an integral part of the Greek Orthodox religion. During fasts, it is forbidden to eat meat, fish, and animal products such as eggs, cheese, and milk. General fast days are Wednesdays and Fridays. At least 3 days of fasting must be observed by anyone wishing to take Holy Communion. Some first-generation Greeks observe the four major fasting periods which include the Great Fast, Lent, for 7 weeks before Easter; the Fast of the Apostles, from Monday 8 days after Pentecost to June 28; the eve of the Feast of the Saints Peter and Paul; the Assumption fast, from August 1 to August 14; and the Christmas fast, from November 15 to December 14.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Accommodate for patients to fast if it is not contradictory to their health status. People with health conditions and small children are exempt from fasting.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditionally, Greeks based their diet on cereals, pulses, lentils, vegetables, fruits, olive oil, cheese, and milk. They are also relatively high consumers of sweets and snacks. For adults, dairy products are consumed in the form of yogurt or cheeses such as feta, kopanisti, kefaloteri, kasseri, and halloumi.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Acknowledge the presence of lactose intolerance and help patients choose alternative sources of calcium.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fats are consumed in the form of olive oil, butter, and olives. Meats include chicken and lamb or, in the United States and Britain, beef adaptations. Eggs, lentils, and fish such as shrimp and other shellfish, whitefish, and anchovies are additional sources of protein.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Vegetables such as potatoes, eggplant, zucchini, spinach, garlic, onions, peas, artichokes, cucumbers, asparagus, cabbage, and cauliflower are common.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Bread choices include pita, crescent rolls, and egg breads. Other foods include rice, tabouli, macaroni, and cracked wheat (bourgouri). Fruit preferences include grapes and currants, figs, prunes, oranges, lemons, melons, watermelons, peaches, and apricots.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Common seasonings used by Greeks are anise, basil, cumin, cinnamon, citron, cloves, coriander, dill, fennel, ginger, garlic, lemon, marjoram, mint, mustard, nutmeg, oregano, parsley, rose, sage, sesame, thyme, vinegar, bay leaf, and honey.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Beverages such as coffee, tea, chocolate milk, and wine are common choices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food choices and preparation practices should be assessed on intake.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In North America, Greeks have deliberately limited family size so children can be adequately cared for and educated. A wide variety of birth control measures, such as intrauterine devices, birth control pills, and condoms are preferred. The strong pro-life Greek Orthodox Church condemns birth control while silently accepting the reality. Help patients identify acceptable birth control methods.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Abortion is condemned as an act of murder except in circumstances that threaten the life of the mother or when a young woman becomes pregnant because of rape. In practice, a few women, particularly those who are unmarried, have legal abortions because of the negative consequences of having a baby out of wedlock. Inflicting endropi on the family is believed to be more severe than the consequences of abortion. A fetus with thalassemia may also be aborted. Do not disclose abortions to family or other members of the community.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnancy is a time of great respect for women and a time when women are given special considerations. Proscriptions include not attending funerals or viewing a corpse, refraining from sinful activity as a precaution against infant deformity, and praying to Saint Simeon.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Pregnant women are encouraged to eat large quantities; foods high in iron and protein are particularly important. If a pregnant woman remarks that a food smells good or if she has a craving for a particular food, it should be offered to her; otherwise, the child may be “marked.” This is the usual explanation for birthmarks.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Factually explain the potentially harmful effects on the fetus and mother of excessive weight gain during pregnancy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After delivery, most traditional Greeks consider the mother ritually impure and particularly susceptible to illness for 40 days. During this time, she is admonished to stay at home and not attend church. At the end of the 40 days, the mother and child attend church and receive a ritual blessing. Arrange for a visiting nurse if the mother is reluctant to see healthcare providers in their offices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For breastfeeding mothers, early showering is sometimes thought to result in the infant developing diarrhea and becoming allergic to milk. Newborns are generally breastfed and solids are not introduced early.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When relatives visit an infant in the hospital, silver objects or coins may be placed in the crib for good luck. Do not remove good luck charms from the infant’s crib.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Anointing of the Sick is administered in the sacrament of Holy Communion given by a priest or occasionally by a deacon. Assist family members to contact a priest when needed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A klama (wake) is held in the family home or, more commonly in North America today, in a funeral home. All relatives and friends are expected to attend for at least a brief time. The wake ends when the priest arrives and offers prayers. Pictures and mirrors may be turned over. During the wake, women may sing dirges or chant. In some regions, people practice “screaming the dead,” the miroloyi.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Greece and Cyprus, the kidia (funeral) is held the following day at the Orthodox Church, with internment in a cemetery. After internment, family and friends gather for a meal of fish, (symbolizing Christianity), wine, cheese, and olives at the family home or a restaurant.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Based on the Orthodox belief in the physical resurrection of the body, Greeks reject cremation. The extent of adherence to this precept varies in North America, but Greeks in Britain do not practice cremation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Black is the color of mourning dress and is often worn by family members throughout the 40 days of mourning; for widows, it may be worn longer. Formerly, a widow was expected to wear black and no jewelry or makeup for the rest of her life. While black armbands are still worn in Greece and Cyprus, that custom is virtually non-existent in immigrant communities.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">After death, family and close relatives, who may stay at home, mourn for 40 days. Close male relatives do not shave as a mark of respect. A memorial service follows 40 days after burial and at 3 months, 6 months, and yearly thereafter. At the end of this service, koliva (boiled wheat, with almonds, pomegranate, sesame seeds and powdered sugar) is served to participants, and mourning is conducted with joyful reverence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Accept varied expressions of grief and rituals related to death and dying.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Greeks in America are affiliated with the Greek Orthodox Church, whereas Greeks in Britain are affiliated with the Archdiocese of Thyateira and Great Britain. The central religious experience is the Sunday morning liturgy, which is a high-church service with icons, incense, and singing or chanting by the psaltes (main singers of hymns using Byzantine musical tradition) and a few background assistant singers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Greek Orthodox religion emphasizes faith rather than specific tenets. The Greek faith does not emphasize Bible reading and study. Some parishioners attend church services weekly; others attend only a few times a year.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Easter is considered the most important of holy days and nearly all Greeks in America and Britain attempt to honor the day.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is a strong belief in miracles, even among second and subsequent generations of Greeks in America and Britain. Daily prayers may be offered to the saints. Women often consider faith an important factor in regaining health. Family members may make “bargains” with saints, such as promises to fast, be faithful, or make church donations if the saint acts on behalf of the ill family member. They may call on an individual’s namesake or a saint believed to have special affinity with healing.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Particularly in immigrant communities, the Greek Orthodox Church serves as a base for spirituality, language, social, and political organization, and an ongoing identity with Greece and Cyprus. Assist with referrals to the local Greek community and the Greek Orthodox Church.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A distinctive feature of the Greek Orthodox religion is the place it assigns to icons, such as paintings of saints, the Virgin Mary, and Christ. These icons have sacred significance as sources of connection to the spiritual world. Icons grace the walls and ceilings of churches and cathedrals and are found in personal altars in homes. In the homes, holy vigil candles are often kept burning. To ensure safety and health, many begin each day by kissing the blessed icons and making the sign of the Greek cross.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When a person is ill, the icon of the family saint or the Virgin Mary may be placed above the bed. Do not remove religious art or icons from the patient’s bedside.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Greeks may sprinkle their homes with holy water from Epiphany Day church services to protect the members of their household from evil.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The amount of acceptance and use of biomedicine is highly related to one’s level of education and generation of immigration. Although fourth-generation Greek Americans are highly traditional in many aspects of their lives such as religion, language retention, and food preferences, they have not retained many of the folk beliefs and practices concerning healthcare.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greek immigrants tended to be anxious about health, to lack trust in healthcare providers, and to rely on family and community for advice and remedies. Inquire about home treatments in a nonjudgmental manner.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">To be healthy means to feel strong, joyful, and content; to be able to take care of oneself; and to be free from pain. Greek immigrants believed that threats to health resulted from a lack of balance in life, departure from family, and failure to demonstrate right behaviors such as respect toward parents, sharing with family, upholding religious precepts, and staying out too late.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditionally Greeks believed that problems originated outside the individual’s control were attributed to God, the devil, spirits, and envy or malice of others.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The family generally assumes responsibility and care for a sick member and works to control interactions with healthcare providers. Help the family find resources to care for their family member.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greeks are extremely reluctant to use welfare services or other forms of governmental assistance to meet their healthcare needs. Reliance on public assistance might indicate that the sick person and family are not self-reliant.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Three traditional folk healing practices were particularly notable in the early immigrants: those related to matiasma (bad eye or evil eye), practika (herbal remedies), and vendousas (cupping). However, it is important to say that the current generations (particularly the fourth generation) of Greeks rarely use these methods and many do not believe in matiasma. Today, the acculturated Greeks believe in the use of modern medicine and may combine it with some of the traditional remedies.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Early immigrants believed that matiasma results from the envy or admiration of others. While the eye is able to, harm a wide variety of things including inanimate objects, children are particularly susceptible to attack. Common symptoms include headache, chills, irritability, restlessness, and lethargy; in extreme cases, matiasma has resulted in death. Greeks employ a variety of preventive mechanisms to thwart the effects of envy or evil eye, including protective charms in the form of phylactos, amulets consisting of blessed wood or incense, or blue “eye” beads, which “reflect” the eye. Do not remove protective charms from the patient or from the bedside.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When matiasma is suspected, the most common method of detection consists of placing olive oil in a glass of water. If the oil disperses, then the eye has been cast. Subsequent treatment consists of physical acts such as making the sign of the Greek cross over the glass of water or reciting ritual prayers passed on in families by members of the opposite sex. In particularly severe cases, the Orthodox priest may recite special prayers of exorcism and use incense to fumigate the afflicted person.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Practika are herbal and humoral treatments used for initial self-treatment. Chamomile, the most popular herb, is used in teas for gastric distress or abdominal pain, including infant colic and menstrual cramps. It is also used as an expectorant to treat colds.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Liquors, such as anisette, ouzo, and mestika, are used primarily for colds, sore throats, and coughs and are consumed alone or in combination with tea, lemon, honey, or sugar, either alone or in some combination. Occasionally, liquors are used for treatment of nevra (nerves). Raw garlic is used as prevention for colds and cooked garlic is used for blood pressure and heart disease.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Encourage patients to fully disclose the use of complementary and alternative practices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Vendousas, a healing practice, is used as a treatment for colds, high blood pressure, and backache. It consists of lighting a swab of cotton held on a fork, then placing the swab in an inverted glass, thereby creating a vacuum in the glass, which is then placed on the back of the ill person. The skin on the back is drawn into the glass. This procedure is repeated 8–12 times. An alternative method, for particularly serious cases, is the kofte, “cut vendousa.” Here, the same procedure is followed, except that a cut in the shape of a cross is made on the skin. When the glass is placed over this cut, blood is drawn into the glass. The therapeutic rationale for using vendousas surrounds its counterirritant effect; the technique increases and revitalizes the circulation, draws out poisons and “cold,” and prevents coagulation of blood. Fourth-generation community members rarely use vendousas.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Self-medicating behaviors are common. Herbal remedies and over-the-counter medications are used widely for specific symptoms.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Encourage full disclosure of over-the-counter drug use and folk practices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental illness is accompanied by social stigma with negative consequences for the afflicted person as well as the family and relatives. Shame originates in the notion that mental illness is hereditary; afflicted people are viewed as having lifelong conditions that “pollute” the bloodline. As a result, families place a wide variety of behaviors within the range of “normal” to delay receiving the stigmatized label.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Individuals with mental illness often present with somatic complaints such as dizziness and paraesthesia on initial visits to healthcare providers. Recent immigrants tend to have higher rates of mental disorders which perhaps result from the stress of culture and societal change.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Do not disclose emotional or psychiatric disorders to people outside the immediate family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A folk model for nevra is a socially acceptable and culturally condoned medium for the expression of otherwise unacceptable emotions. Nevra is experienced most commonly by those in positions of least power, such as women and people living in poverty. It encompasses a wide variety of symptoms and provides a metaphor for social disorders such as conflict between close kin or intergenerational conflict. Ideally, nevra are treated through medications for the relief of symptoms instead of through talk therapy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ponos (pain) is the cardinal symptom of ill health and an evil that needs eradication. The person in pain is not expected to suffer quietly or stoically in the presence of family. The family is relied on to find resources to relieve the pain or, failing that, to share in the experience of suffering. In the presence of outsiders, the lack of restraint in pain expression suggests lack of self-control, and therefore it is considered endropi.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Provide adequate pain relief to help the patient maintain control.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The key aspect of the sick role is for the sick to fully rely on the family for sustenance. When an individual is ill, it is particularly important that he or she not be left alone.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When hospitalization occurs, family members expect to stay with the individual, even during examinations and therapeutic procedures. Families are expected to ensure that sick family members are not harmed and are receiving the best care possible. Protection includes shielding the sick from a serious diagnosis such as cancer, until the family feels the individual is ready to learn about the diagnosis. Make arrangements to accommodate multiple visitors. Determine the spokesperson for the family and obtain his or her assistance in visitor control. Seek assistance from the family spokesperson or next of kin before informing the patient of a grave diagnosis.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Based on the Christian Orthodox belief in the physical resurrection of the body, some Greeks may reject the concept of autopsy and do not readily accept organ donation. However, the Greek Orthodox Church is strongly pro-life and more recently has been encouraging organ donation as an act of love. Blood transfusions are wholly acceptable and are common for people with thalassemia. Explain the legalities of autopsy.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0015s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">15.1.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A woman who cures, particularly one who cures the evil eye, is known as a magissa, which is usually translated as “witch” but means “magician”; she may also be called doctor. In the United States and Britain, “wise women” from one’s own family conduct most lay healing. Occasionally, for particularly difficult cases of matiasma, a woman with particular gifts in diagnosis and healing may be called. The priest may also be called on for advice, blessings, exorcisms, and direct healing. Assist patients and family in obtaining a priest.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Greeks display a general distrust of all healthcare providers and considerable shopping around for physicians and other professionals to obtain additional opinions is relatively common. The use of several physicians simultaneously may result in untoward drug interactions from conflicting interventions or overdoses. Encourage patients to disclose the use of all healthcare providers seen and treatments used.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hospitals are a particular source of mistrust for Greeks. When hospitalizations occur, the family may be perceived by staff as demanding or interfering as they enact their protective advocacy roles. Mothers may demand to sleep with their children and fear that the children may not receive appropriate care. There is also a fear that the sick person may be used as a subject for experimentation. Encourage family members to participate in hospital procedures. Provide factual information and dispel myths.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
