<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0003s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">3.2 </emphasis> Language and Health Literacy</title>
         <para role="Para">Language and health literacy barriers include the medical jargon used by health-care providers, inadequate reading level of the patient, or lack of fluency in English or in the patient’s mother tongue. Several studies in the United States have identified that a lack of fluency in language is the primary barrier to receiving adequate health care, and not just for people for whom English is a second language.</para>
         <para role="Para">Language barriers may involve both oral and written language. Interpretation refers to oral communication, while translation refers to written communication. Interpretation requires more than word-for-word substitution. Professional interpreters must not only demonstrate bilingual proficiency, but they must also be knowledgeable of idioms, slang, and colloquialisms as well as medical terminology. Sign language may be a concern for some because there is no standard worldwide sign language. Besides American Sign Language, there are multiple Arabic sign languages. Language and literacy barriers may result in the following:</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Language barriers can negatively affect perceptions of patient and provider care, resulting in patients not returning for follow-up care.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Language barriers may result in a patient leaving against medical advice. A patient who perceives that he or she is not understood by the health-care provider or who does not understand a provider who is using medical technology may simply leave.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Limited English proficiency (LEP) can result in unsafe situations caused by poor patient comprehension of their medical condition, treatment plan, or discharge instructions; an inaccurate and incomplete medical history being obtained by the health-care provider; ineffective or improper use of medications or serious medication errors; improper preparation for tests and procedures; and poor or inadequate informed consent.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Be alert to comments and behaviors from patients and family members that might mean they do not understand the provider. Such cues include “Can I take these forms home to complete?” or “I forgot my glasses. I’ll wait until (friend or family member) comes to help me.”</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">LEP patients who do not receive professional interpretation services at admission and discharge have longer lengths of stay and higher readmission rates compared with patients who receive professional interpretation services.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Just because someone speaks the language does not necessarily mean he or she has the skills to be successful at interpretation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Improper interpretation is prone to additions, substitutions, omissions, volunteer opinions, and sematic errors.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Compared with professional medical interpreters, ad hoc interpreters such as patients’ family members or house staff frequently make medical interpretation errors. These errors are significantly more likely to have clinical consequences.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Use only certified interpreters when at all possible.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Use dialect specific interpreters whenever possible.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Create a system for interpretation and translation.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Compile a list of commonly used words in the dominant languages of the patients using the facility. This list does not replace the need for an interpreter but may be helpful if a professional interpreter is not available.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Allow time for interpretation.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Be aware that social class differences can affect interpretation.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Maintain eye contact with both the patient and the interpreter.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Non-professional interpretation and using children or other family members can lead to a breach of confidentiality. Also, patients might not speak freely, especially regarding issues such as sexuality, drug and alcohol misuse, and domestic violence.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Do not place the patient in a precarious situation by asking the patient in front of the family if it is acceptable for a family member or friend to interpret.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Do not use family members except in nonconfidential situations such as obtaining demographic and admitting data and teaching about medication administration and dietary requirements.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Do not use individuals known to the family as interpreters due to confidentiality issues.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Language barriers may involve written as well as oral communication. It is therefore important to provide written materials in the patient’s native language.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Translate satisfaction surveys into the languages of the population served.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Translate treatment plans and medication requirements into the languages of the patients who come to the facility.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Translate pamphlets on common illnesses and diseases into the languages of the patients who come to the facility.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Ensure that translated material is at a grade 6 reading level.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Create pamphlets on high-risk behaviors and occupations that are high risk.</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </sect1>
      
