<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0021s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">21.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify four common health problems among Irish Americans. Provide a recommendation to address each problem.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are some childrearing practices common among the Irish?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How are emotions displayed among the traditional Irish?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify two high-risk behaviors common among the Irish. What health education would you provide to decrease these behaviors?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>The family of a deceased patient invites you to a wake. What might you expect from a traditional wake?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What is the dominant religion among the Irish? How might you partner with the church to improve the health of the Irish?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Most Irish speak low-contexted English. What does this mean and how might it be displayed on an intake assessment?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify at least three common traditional health-care practices.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>List at least three common traditional beliefs practiced by pregnant women.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify at least common health conditions among newborns. What health teaching would you do to decrease these conditions?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>11. <emphasis role="bold">What are some cultural differences and challenges experienced by acculturated children and their Irish immigrant parents?</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>12. <emphasis role="bold">What treatment modalities are available for pregnant women at risk for alcoholism?</emphasis>
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
