<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0019s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Hmong (pronounced “ <emphasis>Mong</emphasis>”—the “H” is silent) people lived primarily in the mountainous areas shared by China, Myanmar (Burma), Vietnam, Thailand, and Laos. Most Hmong who live in the United States (US) originate from Laos, a country with a population of more than 7.8 million, where only 9.2% identify as Hmong. The Hmong traditionally are an agrarian society that practiced “slash and burn” agriculture. Mountainous areas were cleared of underbrush, burned, and then used for crops. When the soil became depleted, they moved on, often relocating their village as well. They are believed to have originated in the Yellow River Valley of China.</para>
         <para role="Para">Hmong people began immigrating to the US and other countries in 1975 following the Vietnam War. These refugees originated from the mountainous regions of Laos, where they had fought alongside the CIA during the “secret war” in Laos. They were targeted for genocide because they opposed the communist Pathet Lao, and as a result, they fled their country. They escaped to Thailand by traversing jungles and crossing the Mekong River. Many Hmong died due to war, genocide, or while attempting to flee. Hmong immigrants in the US bear the scars of war, including bullet and shrapnel wounds, as well as the lasting effects of exposure to biological warfare, which they referred to as “yellow rain.” According to the US Census, as of 2023, there are approximately 336,000 Hmong people living in the US.</para>
         <para role="Para">While the Central Valley of California was not initially settled by the Hmong, many now reside there. California has the largest Hmong population in the US, followed by Minnesota and Wisconsin. Small groups still tend to migrate to areas where they perceive economic opportunities exist. Hmong people have settled in North Carolina, Oregon, Colorado, Michigan, and other states. In 2004, the final refugee settlement in Thailand was shut down and 15,000 new refugees were relocated to the US.</para>
         <para role="Para">The Hmong in Laos were preliterate farmers with generally limited or no access to education. They lived in very primitive and traditional circumstances and had no access to the modern world or modern medicine. When immigrating to the US, many Hmong experienced culture shock in a world that was completely unfamiliar to them. Depression, post-traumatic stress disorder, and suicide are prevalent in this population. More recent immigrants have received some education and have been exposed to the modern world. This aggregate profile may not fit well-acculturated Hmong individuals in the US based on length of time in the US and the diverse characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">Paj ntaub (</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis role="bold">pronounced</emphasis>
            <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">“pan dow”)</emphasis>
            </emphasis>, or “flower cloth,” is an art form that includes batik designs, appliqué, reverse appliqué, and cross stitch created by Hmong women. Paj ntaub are used to decorate traditional clothing and create historical story cloths. Story cloths were used to pass down family history and culture from one generation to the next. Images and patterns carry representational and symbolic meanings. One such example is the triangle pattern, which symbolizes mountains, like the ones found in Laos where the Hmong people lived. Even today, remarkable story cloths are made depicting the Hmong fighting the communists in the jungles, Hmong being killed, yellow rain falling on villages, Hmong fleeing through jungles, and Hmong floating across the Mekong River to the refugee camps of Thailand.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ensure that a professional healthcare interpreter who can speak the patient’s language is available.</emphasis> Hmong in the US speak either a dialect of White Hmong (Hmoob dawb) or Green Hmong (Hmoob ntsuab), also known as Blue Hmong. These dialects are mutually intelligible, with variations in pronunciation and vocabulary.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Avoid providing written instructions in Hmong unless someone in the household can read them. Instructions in English may be preferable, as school-aged children may be able to read them.</emphasis> The Hmong community has a rich tradition through which history, cultural knowledge, art, and ideas are passed from one generation to the next through oral communication. The Hmong did not have a written language until the 1950s, when Christian missionaries created a written form of their language. Due to the absence of a written Hmong language, many older Hmong individuals are unable to read or write in their native language.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Several medical terms do not have equivalents in the Hmong language. For example, there are no equivalent words in the Hmong language for cancer, cervix, or pancreas. Some words and phrases in Hmong may be challenging to translate into English.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Be aware that Hmong immigrants born in Laos may not have their accurate age on their documents. For Hmong people born in Laos, their ages are often unknown; immigration officials assign an age to them before they immigrate to the US.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Avoid prolonged direct eye contact. Do not rush to ask questions; engage in small talk first if the situation is not urgent.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Hmong people believe that Americans are rude because they make direct eye contact when speaking and their questions are too straightforward. Proper communication when speaking to a Hmong person involves using fleeting glances without staring. Making small talk before inquiring about someone’s health is polite and essential. Hmong people also use the word “yes” to indicate that they hear what you are saying. Saying “yes” does not necessarily indicate understanding or a commitment to follow through with your request.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">To determine if treatments are understood, request a demonstration.</emphasis> This is also known as the teach-back technique, a method used to assess and confirm whether the patient understands the provider’s instructions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">When inquiring about Hmong individuals’ adherence to treatment recommendations, it is most effective to request a demonstration of their actions.</emphasis> For example, their method for conducting blood sugar testing. To determine the amount of medication taken, check the number of pills in the vial and the date the prescription was filled. In general, the Hmong community has a strong desire to be viewed positively by people in positions of authority. This social desirability factor may lead individuals to tell the healthcare provider what they believe the provider wants to hear, rather than what is happening; this is often seen as being respectful.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Obtaining informed consent is a legal requirement in the US, but it directly contradicts Hmong traditional decision-making.</emphasis> In the Hmong culture, the male head of the family or clan is often responsible for making decisions for family members, including medical decisions.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Due to the Hmong community’s limited exposure to Western medicine and surgical procedures, they frequently experience significant fear in medical situations. They do not understand what is happening and they sometimes distrust medical personnel, especially if the person is a student. Rumors persist among the Hmong community that they are used for practice by medical students. If any treatment is labeled as experimental, this only reinforces their belief that they are being used for experiments, leading them to likely refuse the treatment. Obtaining consent from the head of a family may lead to treatment delays, as the head of the clan may live in another state.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">To successfully obtain consent, it is crucial to respect the individuals’ wishes, wait for family members to arrive, meet with the family members to explain the situation and accept their decision. If the patient’s wishes differ from those of the head of the family, most patients will defer to the head of the family’s decision.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Hmong believe that it is inappropriate to say negative things in front of sick people. Words have great power, and the Hmong believe that speaking negative words in front of an ill person can make those things happen.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">It is crucial to have a professionally trained healthcare interpreter who can work with the family to convey information in a culturally congruent manner.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Hmong individuals have attained higher education and degrees in fields such as nursing, medicine, psychology, and social work. In Western culture, attaining education and a high position commands respect and authority. In the Hmong culture, patients may not show the same deference toward Hmong healthcare providers and may treat them based on their position within the Hmong family or community hierarchy. This creates additional stressors for Hmong healthcare providers and interpreters, who may be required to prioritize the preferences of Hmong patients who have higher status in their community.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Be aware that Hmong healthcare providers and interpreters may be related to the patient, and they could be placed in an untenable situation because of a clan hierarchy that Western individuals may not fully comprehend.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Hmong people are organized into 18 clans, each with a surname that is shared by all men and children. Although wives and mothers typically retain the clan name from their birth, they are still regarded as members of their husband’s clan. Hmong people have no single leader; instead, each clan has older males who serve as leaders. If a husband has died, the oldest son is expected to make decisions for the family. Daughters are expected to marry and live with their husbands and in-laws.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Plural marriages were common in Laos, and they continue to exist today. Hmong men may marry as many women as they can afford to support. This is less common among Hmong people in the US and those who have moved away from traditional beliefs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Single Hmong individuals may find partners or spouses at the annual Hmong New Year celebrations, which are held between Christmas and New Year’s Day. Marriages are forbidden between individuals who share the same clan name, regardless of how distant their relation. Young Hmong women are still victims of “capture bride,” a practice in which a young girl is taken to her future husband’s home overnight and then declared married. This practice is being discouraged because it has led to young women escaping and reporting their kidnappings to the police.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family is considered an important part of Hmong culture, so marriage is seen as a duty. There is significant social pressure for young Hmong girls to marry, often in their early teens. These marriages are not recognized as legal marriages by Western standards, but rather as traditional Hmong ceremonies; therefore, they do not violate state laws.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditionally, Hmong men and women tend to marry young; however, this practice has changed, and it is now more acceptable to delay marriage for reasons related to socioeconomic status and shifts in cultural norms.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not reveal disgraces to family members.</emphasis> The Hmong community in the US is well-connected through telephone, e-mail, and frequent family visits. Family “disgraces” are widely known even among Hmong people living in different parts of the US. “Disgraces” are considered taboo and can cause a family to “lose face.” Examples may include birth defects, mental health issues, or a divorce in the family. Any of these “disgraces” are considered to reflect on every member of a family and, as a result, decrease their chances of forming a successful marriage.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not reveal same-sex relationships to the family members of others.</emphasis> Same-sex relationships are not widely accepted in Hmong culture.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hmong people have the highest unemployment rate among all Asians in the US. They have the lowest socioeconomic status among all Asian groups in the US. First-generation immigrants often face challenges in finding employment due to limited English language proficiency and a lack of workplace skills. Having a large family leads to lower employment rates for women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Requesting demonstrations helps to assess knowledge so that better instructions can be given in the workplace.</emphasis> Hmong individuals who acquire adequate English language skills may secure employment in low-skill occupations (e.g., factories or agriculture). Their desire for social acceptance may lead to them saying “yes” to questions about knowing how to do something, even when they do not understand.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Hmong community is rapidly attaining higher levels of education and socioeconomic status. This has led them to assist other family members in living better lives and attaining higher education. Hmong individuals are now occupying various professional roles and serving in government positions. They are hardworking and loyal to their employers.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Since resettling in the US, obesity has been rapidly increasing among children and adults. Hmong Americans are at significant risk of developing type 2 diabetes. One study found that Hmong patients were three times more likely to be diagnosed with type 2 diabetes compared to non-Hispanic White patients.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0019s0001ta01">19.1</link>
                     </emphasis> presents a list of frequently occurring health conditions for the Hmong in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. See Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0002#ch0002">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Encourage adherence to long-term mental health counseling and adherence to medication regimens.</emphasis> Common health conditions among the Hmong community include depression, anxiety, suicidal thoughts, and post-traumatic stress disorder, stemming from their experiences during the war in Laos, their treacherous flight to safety, and cultural stressors. Many Hmong people continue to have nightmares and flashbacks to the terrors they experienced in Laos. Unemployment and evolving gender roles in families contribute to additional cultural stressors.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Type 2 diabetes and hypertension are prevalent due to the rising obesity rates in both Hmong children and adults. Contributing factors to the increase in obesity rates include lifestyle and environmental changes, such as lack of physical activity and poor diet.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">When evaluating nutrition, inquire about the patient’s liquid intake;</emphasis> this information is often not disclosed unless specifically asked and may reveal high consumption of sugary juices and drinks.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Avoid teaching about diet using measurements from the Western system.</emphasis> Measuring foods in cups, tablespoons, etc., may not be understood by Hmong patients because baking is uncommon in traditional Hmong households, and they may not possess these utensils. A “cup” may refer to a drinking cup to the patient.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">It is important to instruct patients in the proper use of inhalers and other medications.</emphasis> Hmong of all ages in central California have a high prevalence of asthma. Exacerbations are frequent when air quality is poor.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Consider paragonimias in cases of pulmonary infections.</emphasis> Paragonimiasis is a parasitic infection acquired in Southeast Asia. The parasites settle in the lungs, causing a widespread infection. Some elderly Hmong individuals may experience breathing difficulties due to paragonimiasis.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">All new immigrants showing signs or symptoms of tuberculosis should undergo clinical evaluation for the disease.</emphasis> Recent immigrants have been diagnosed with tuberculosis at high rates, and some have been infected with drug-resistant strains of the disease.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hepatitis B occurs at high rates and often affects all members of a family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assist the family in complying with public health monitoring. Screen all new immigrants for hepatitis B. If one family member has hepatitis B, all family members should be screened.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Helicobacter pylori</emphasis> is also commonly associated with peptic ulcers and adenocarcinoma of the gastrointestinal tract. <emphasis>H. pylori</emphasis> transmission may be due to sociocultural and environmental factors. The Hmong traditionally have high consumption of rice and preserved foods. Differences in health belief systems and use of Western medicine as a last resort may delay early diagnosis and treatment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When individuals are ill, traditional cupping or coin rubbing is practiced by pricking the skin to release blood, as it is believed to expel bad spirits. This practice involves using non-sterilized sewing needles, which may lead to the transmission of hepatitis B within the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Teach the family how to sterilize needles and other sharp instruments before performing coining.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Hmong population has been found to have higher rates of cancers such as nasopharyngeal carcinoma, gastric cancer, hepatic cancer, and cervical cancer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cervical cancer incidence and mortality rates among Hmong women are three to four times higher than those among non-Hispanic White women. Cervical cancer screening rates are low due to a lack of awareness, limited healthcare access, and cultural and linguistic barriers to screening.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ensure that professionally trained healthcare interpreters are available at all times.</emphasis> The greatest barrier to healthcare for the Hmong community in the US is the lack of accurate and culturally appropriate communication.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0019s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 19.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to the Hmong</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cervical cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Depression, anxiety, suicidal ideation, and post-traumatic stress syndrome</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hepatitis B</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Parasitosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thalassemia</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Liver cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Trichinosis</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Nasopharyngeal cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hypertension</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle, genetic</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Asthma</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Encourage Pap smears as part of routine examinations and during other healthcare visits for women.</emphasis> Hmong women have a high incidence rate of cervical cancer, yet they are the least likely among all Asian ethnic groups to undergo screening. Contributing factors to low screening rates include lack of awareness, discomfort or pain during the procedure, embarrassment, and modesty. Failure to undergo regular gynecological examinations with Pap smears increases the risk of advanced cervical cancer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Explain the adverse effects of cigarette smoking, promote cessation, and collaborate with schools to educate about the dangers of smoking at a young age.</emphasis> Many individuals are unaware that cigarette smoking can cause cancer. E-cigarette use is the most common form of tobacco use among Hmong adolescents.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Hmong people were primarily farmers, and many have developed small farms where they sell fruits and vegetables. Even Hmong living in apartments have small plots for growing vegetables, and their homes may have chicken pens in the backyards.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rice is the primary staple of the Hmong diet. Vegetables, fish, chicken, and pork are served with the rice. Spicy peppers are used to make into a condiment that accompanies the meal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">It is advisable to avoid consuming raw pork due to the potential for serious health risks. Encourage physical activity and maintaining a balanced, healthy diet.</emphasis> Occasionally, a special dish called “ <emphasis>laub”</emphasis> is made with raw pork, vegetables, and spices. This increases the risk for trichinosis, therefore, many young Hmong people have started to prefer American diets.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are highly esteemed in Hmong families, and having large families is seen as an advantage. Hmong families tend to live in multigenerational households. Many older adults often assist in caring for their grandchildren.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">According to Hmong tradition, women are believed to be particularly susceptible to illnesses and misfortunes during the first 30 days after giving birth. Therefore, a woman must confine herself and follow strict postpartum practices, also known as <emphasis>nyo dua hli.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">New mothers may not want to eat hospital food, so allowing families to bring traditional foods from home could be beneficial.</emphasis> Women are prohibited from drinking cold beverages and spicy foods during pregnancy. Postpartum, white rice and chicken soup cooked with medicinal herbs are the traditional diet for 30 days. After giving birth, women must only consume “hot” food and drink, which is believed to help the body to expel postpartum blood.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">New mothers are expected to rest after giving birth. A woman should refrain from engaging in strenuous activities, such as lifting heavy objects or doing heavy cleaning. The mother-in-law and husband help the new mother during this period.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hmong women view regular menstruation as a sign of good health and may prefer not to use birth control methods that disrupt the regular menstrual cycle.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hmong funerals are unique and can last for several days. The older or more respected the person, the longer the funeral may be. Family members are expected to attend the funeral and stay for the duration. Specific rituals are required, including animal sacrifice, to honor the deceased. These animals are used to provide food for people attending the funeral. A proper burial enables the deceased to transition to the spirit world in a positive manner, which is believed to lead to reincarnation. Most Hmong people believe in the existence of multiple souls that reincarnate. One soul stays in the vicinity of the body, while another remains in the present world, overseeing and caring for the family. Rituals are conducted to honor deceased ancestors.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditionally, the Hmong practiced animism and ancestor worship. They use traditional or spiritual healers (i.e., shamans) to prevent and treat illnesses.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most older and more recent immigrant Hmong adhere to traditional animist beliefs, where ancestors are revered and spirits are believed to be widely distributed in the world, residing in many inanimate objects or places such as trees, rivers, and houses. Many people believe that spirits have the power to cause harm, misfortune, illness, or death, as well as to provide protection or prevent negative events from happening. The Hmong believe that good spirits are ancestors who watch over and protect them. They also believe that a person’s souls must live in harmony to maintain good health. The Hmong consider each person to have three souls. If a person’s soul(s) wanders off or becomes frightened, it can lead to illness or death. This is called “soul loss.” A shaman must perform a soul-calling ritual, known as <emphasis>hu plig</emphasis>, to guide the soul back to the person.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is also a large Christian Hmong community throughout the US. The Christian Hmong have beliefs and practices that are appropriate to their religion. Some people may denounce animist beliefs and traditional Hmong practices, such as the belief in soul loss and the performance of soul-calling ceremonies by shamans.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.10 </emphasis> Healthcare Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hmong in the US often seek Western medical care, and they may also consult traditional healers or shamans who perform rituals. They may consult herbalists and undergo multiple treatments for the same condition.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not mistake the regular patterns of coining or cupping for abuse. Encourage the sterilization of needles.</emphasis> Some people practice home remedies such as coining or cupping. These traditional practices result in distinctive bruises, which are typically elongated or round, and are usually located over the affected area. For instance, a Hmong individual with a sore throat may exhibit bruises around the neck, while someone with chest symptoms may undergo cupping on the front and back of the chest. They believe that pricking the center of the bruise releases bad spirits; and unsterilized sewing needles are typically used for this purpose.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">One cause of illness is believed to be the loss of one’s soul. Some people, such as babies and children, are believed to have souls that struggle to remain their bodies. If the soul(s) leaves for too long, the baby can become ill or die. For this reason, parents may choose to tie a string around the baby’s neck or wrist soon after birth. Older children and adults may have strings tied around their wrists, waists, or ankles. These must remain on until they fall off naturally, as removing them too soon can result in soul loss, illness, or even death. Since immigrating to the US, the traditional strings have been replaced with gold necklaces and bracelets.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Hmong people who practice shamanic ceremonies may wear amulets in small bags around their neck or waist. These contain objects that are believed to be protective against evil spirits. These should not be removed without the patient’s or family’s permission.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Inquire about patients’ herbal use upon admission.</emphasis> Some Hmong people use herbs recommended by a Hmong herbalist. Studies have shown that these herbs may possess pharmaceutical properties.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide a detailed explanation of the benefits of blood transfusions when required.</emphasis> More traditional Hmong people are opposed to blood transfusions and organ donation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Caution patients about using unfamiliar herbs.</emphasis> The traditional herbs found in Laos and Thailand are difficult or impossible to obtain in the US. Traditional herbalists sometimes use plants found in the US simply because the plant resembles a plant they had used in Laos. The efficacy of these herbs is unknown and may be harmful.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0019s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">19.1.11 </emphasis> Healthcare Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Shamanic ceremonies are used for treating severe illnesses that have not improved with other forms of treatment. Shamans do not choose to become shamans; the occupation is a calling. Shamans undergo extensive training for many years and learn through apprenticeships. Shaman ceremonies are conducted within the home with the entire family present. During these ceremonies, the shamans enter the spirit world to discover the reasons behind the loss of the soul or its journey to the spirit world. During a second ritual, the shaman may call the person’s spirit home, thereby restoring harmony. A shaman may sacrifice an animal to pay the spirit world and release the soul so it can return home. <emphasis role="bold">Amulets from the ceremony may be placed on the patient to protect them, and they should not be removed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
