<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0016s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">Individuals of Guatemalan heritage are one of many cultures grouped under the umbrella of Hispanic/LatinX populations in the United States and elsewhere. Although similarities range among language paradigms for Hispanic/LatinX individuals, this unique cultural group has an abundance of linguistic differences in addition to religious, cultural, and economic structures that must be acknowledged to adequately care for this population. Healthcare providers must be knowledgeable regarding the specific cultural characteristics and behavioral practices for Guatemalan individuals in order to provide individualized care that is sensitive to cultural necessities. Although each methodology to practice may not adequately reflect the distinctiveness encompassed within each Guatemalan profile, understanding the basis of cultural sensitivity and competence and necessity for patient healing is a core component for successful nursing practice.</para>
         <para role="Para">Guatemala, referred to as “eternal spring,” is a country in Central America with an estimated population of over 17 million. Guatemala is inhabited by Mestizo (mixed Amerindian Spanish—in local Spanish called <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">Ladino</emphasis>
            </emphasis>), K’iche, Kaqchikel, Mam, Q’eqchi, and other Mayan, and indigenous non-Mayan sub-cultural groups. Following the civil war, during the 1960s–1980s, a widespread of mortality, loss of land, community right restrictions, economic instability, and cultural disruption arose, ultimately impacting the structural archetype of everyday life for most Guatemalans. As a result, as many as one million Guatemalan natives fled north toward Mexico and the United States seeking safety and political asylum. The increased migration to the United States created increased difficulties for Guatemalan individuals in regard to cultural differences, language restrictions, and governmental policies. Although much time has passed since the cultural disruption of Guatemala, residing individuals continue to be plagued with “abject” poverty with a majority of the population living below the universal poverty level.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The primary languages spoken in Guatemala include the official language, Spanish, which is spoken by 60% of the population, and Amerindian languages, spoken by the remaining 40%. Officially, 23 Amerindian languages are recognized and primarily spoken in rural areas throughout the country.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Mayan men do not have a formal education but are able to speak Spanish because of frequent interactions with Spanish speakers. Due to the sporadicity of mayan cultural groups, these indivudials tend to adopt skills, customs, and traditions from one-another and through generational instruction. <emphasis role="bold">Obtain an interpreter when needed. Note: Interpreters are not available for many of the Amerindian languages; however, providers must attempt to use established, accredited resources to adequately communicate with this population.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although topics such as income and investments are taboo among many Guatemalans, they generally like to express their inner beliefs, feelings, and emotions once they get to know and trust a person. Meaningful conversations often become loud and seem disorganized from unfamiliar parties. To the outsider, the situation may seem stressful or hostile, but this intense emotion means the conversants are enjoying each other’s company. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that a higher voice amplitude is indicative of emotional anger.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Within the context of respect (</emphasis>
            
                     <emphasis>
              
                        <emphasis role="bold">respeto—goes on the glossary as well</emphasis>
            
                     </emphasis>
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">), encourage open communication and sharing. Develop the patient’s sense of trust by inquiring about family members and individual customs before proceeding with the usual business if the patient’s condition and situation permits.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans place great value on closeness, togetherness, and unity, including when they are in an in-patient facility and/or under stressful circumstances. This culture uses a higher degree of touch and embrace and support the involvement of relatives and significant others. Touch between men and women, between men, and between women is acceptable, including in the health-care environment. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of and ask permission before touching during a physical examination to ensure patient consent and comfortability.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional Guatemalans consider sustained eye contact when speaking directly to an older person to be rude. Direct eye contact with superiors may be interpreted as insolence. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that lack of eye contact means the patient and/or family is being less than truthful or not listening. Avoiding direct eye contact with superiors is a sign of respect.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans tend to value the past and live in the present, being more concerned with today than the future that is uncertain for many. <emphasis role="bold">Inquiring about past events in one’s life may help build a rapport and establish comfortability with Guatemalan individuals.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because work is a priority in the life of many Guatemalans, many seek healthcare only when their illness has progressed to the point of preventing them from working or carrying out their duties or roles within the family. Taking time to go to the doctor means time lost from work and loss of pay. <emphasis role="bold">Educational initiatives, follow-up care, and take-home documents may be beneficial with continuation of care among this population.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality is difficult for many because of limited transportation and unexpected family needs. <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain the necessity of timeliness in keeping appointments in the health-care system.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans who have a Hispanic heritage use the Spanish format for names. At birth, a child is given a first name (Ovidio) followed by the surname of the father (Garcia), and then the surname of the mother (Salvador), resulting in Ovidio Garcia Salvador. In referring to a male as Mr. ( <emphasis>Señor</emphasis>) it would be appropriate to use Señor Garcia. Men’s names remain the same through their lifetime. However, when a woman named Jovita Garcia Salvador marries Francisco Vasquez Gutierrez, she then becomes Jovita Garcia de Vasquez or simply Jovita Garcia Vasquez. She then becomes Mrs. ( <emphasis>Señora</emphasis>) Vasquez. <emphasis role="bold">Ask what the legal name is for medical record keeping and to ensure patient preferred name is used by interdisciplinary teams.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">To convey respect, address the Guatemalan in a formal manner unless otherwise requested by the patient.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Guatemalans shake hands softly. To give a firm handshake indicates aggressive behavior.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditionally, the man has been the head of household and is the primary decision maker, “breadwinner,” and provider for the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women’s roles have traditionally involved raising the children. <emphasis role="bold">More Guatemalan women are entering the workforce outside of the home, resulting in more egalitarian male/female roles. Inquire about the familial structure and head-of-household before assuming.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans place high value on familial unity. Most families are nuclear—comprised of a father, mother, and children. Extended family is important to Guatemalans and may include grandparents, aunts, uncles, and cousins. <emphasis role="bold">Determine the spokesperson in the family.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children are a gift from God and are highly valued in Guatemalan society. Sons are usually more valued than daughters. Children are taught to be obedient and demonstrate respect for older people.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In Mayan communities, family members and other adults take an active part in raising a child. Values include being humble, content, and respectful of others, working hard, avoiding arguments, and placing the needs of the family before one’s own individual needs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Disobedience among children in Guatemala may be handled with physical punishment. <emphasis role="bold">Explain child abuse laws in the</emphasis> United States <emphasis role="bold">and elsewhere.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Guatemalans do not believe in homosexuality, sexual activity among the unmarried, or infidelity. Persons involved in these activities must do so in secrecy. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships to the family.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Homosexuality in Guatemalan culture is considered taboo and advocates for discretion. <emphasis role="bold">Provide information on sexual care practices when necessary and with discretion.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Larger cities in the offer organizations such as <emphasis>Ellas</emphasis>, a support group for Latina lesbians; El Hotline of Hola Gay, an organization with information and referrals in Spanish, and Dignity, a gay Catholic support organization. <emphasis role="bold">Refer patients to gay support groups when requested.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">During the civil war, residents of Guatemala were permitted to migrate to the United States and apply for political asylum, allowing them to stay permanently in the United States. Political asylum allows national protection of an individual who has left their native country as a political refugee. The application of political asylum for this cultural group ensured Guatemalans were safe to migrate and protected from immigrative law upon entrance to the United States.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans who migrate today often find employment in the agricultural industry, including hand-harvesting crops and working on egg or chicken farms. Additional occupations of Guatemalan migrants include citrus processing plants, plant/flower nurseries, and construction services throughout the country.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assess patients for diseases and deficits related to farming, construction and respiratory compromise, including pesticides and inhalation debris.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Migrants are able to find additional positions in housekeeping or maintenance in businesses or academic institutions. Because punctuality is not valued in Guatemala, Guatemalan employees may arrive late for work. They might not wear a timepiece, be able to tell time, or understand the importance of punctuality.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Stress the necessity of and importance placed on punctuality. Include teaching regarding employment related requirements and community services to assist with transportation.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Those of lower socioeconomic status or with formal education and English language skills usually acquire positions with responsibility but little authority. These individuals prefer to get along well with others and not criticize or voice complaints when treated poorly. Moreover, the Guatemalan is likely to remain in a position equal to his or her peers rather than seek a promotion. <emphasis role="bold">Provide opportunities for advocacy and self-representation when caring for this population.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Guatemalan natives are culturally constructed from Spanish and Mayan Indian heritage and have adopted lifestyle practices from generational growth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">There is a small population of Guatemalans with ancestry from the Caribbean and Africa who may use cultural practices from these regions to maintain health adequacy. This accounts for variations in skin color, facial features, hair, body structure, and other biological variations. Guatemalans of Caribbean and African descent tend to have black hair, dark skin, dark eyes, and be of average <emphasis role="bold">(</emphasis>Male: 5′4; Female: 4′10<emphasis role="bold">)</emphasis> or taller based on a regional population with a medium to large build.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans who are predominantly Spanish have lighter features and produce similar characteristics to Caucasian-identifying individuals. This sub-cultural group may have blonde or brown hair, fair (white) complexion, blue eyes, and be of average or taller height based on regional population with a medium to large build.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans with predominantly Mayan Indian ancestry tend to have black hair, brown skin, dark eye color, and are of short height with a petite build.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Jaundice, cyanosis, and petechiae are difficult to detect among dark-skinned Guatemalans. <emphasis role="bold">Exam the sclera and buccal mucosa, tongue, lips, nailbeds, and palms of hands and soles of feet.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The leading causes of mortality in Guatemala are diabetes mellitus, ischemic heart disease, respiratory infections (pneumonia, influenza, COVID-19), nephritis/nephrosis, perinatal conditions, intestinal infectious diseases, and nutritional deficiencies. <emphasis role="bold">Assess newer immigrants for health conditions common in their home country. Include areas of nutrition, familial history, activity level, and occupation.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Other common health conditions include malaria or dengue fever, gastritis, intestinal worms, pulmonary tuberculosis, and diarrhea resulting from shigella, amoebas, and giardia. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0016s0001ta01">16.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Guatemalans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. <emphasis role="bold">Inquire about previous vaccinations and provide patient education regarding required/recommended vaccinations.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Eye disorders common among Guatemalan individuals include dacrocytosis and trachoma. Cataracts (even in children), congenital toxoplasmosis, toxic optic neuropathy (usually related to TB treatment), vitamin A deficiency, and actinic allergy are additional health concerns related to this population. <emphasis role="bold">Assess Guatemalans for health conditions common in their home country. Provide opportunity for visual examination(s) and address dermatologic concerns.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0016s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 16.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Guatemalans</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Respiratory infections</para>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactase deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Gastritis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Eye disorders</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alcohol products are readily available and widely abused throughout Guatemala. These products are accessible to majority of the population and are highly consumed among early to middle-aged men. Men who immigrate from Guatemala may find themselves drinking alcohol excessively, even if they did not prior to migration. This may be due to such factors as (a) migrational stress of living in another country, (b) lack of communication and increased distance from family, friends, and support systems, (c) fear of inadequate work, financial struggle, and deportation, and (d) illness and (e) being victims of violence and injury.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans of low socioeconomic status have received little health education, reduced access to healthcare and provider coverage, and often believe illness is punishment from God or a religious entity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalan families readily participate in immunization programs for their children, yet do not participate themselves. Many parental figures strive for healthier lifestyles among children when compared to oneself. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage immunizations as part of routine care and provide education for immunization rationale, timing, and accessibility.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most women do not participate in routine screening for breast and cervical cancer. Few men participate in routine screening for testicular or colon cancer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Educate Guatemalans in a family context for disease, illness, and injury prevention, assist with low-cost referrals, and provide milestone necessities for all individuals across the lifespan.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Food to Guatemalans signifies physical, spiritual, and cultural wellness and is a catalyst for familial integration and support.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Nutritional options vary among Guatemalans based on cultural traditions and accessibility. Gari’funa cuisine reflects the Caribbean coast and includes recipes from African ancestors. Common foods include sea bass, flounder, red snapper, tarpon, shrimp, pork, chicken, ceviche, coconut milk, tomato, onion, garlic, lime, and lemon.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Corn is highly valued in the Mayan culture and is the chief crop and the basis for many food products and meals. The Mayan diet primarily consists of maize (corn grain), black beans, rice, chicken, squash, tomatoes, carrots, chilies, beets, cauliflower, lettuce, cabbage, chard, leek, onion, and garlic. These foods are used to make tortillas, <emphasis>atole</emphasis> (liquid corn drink), <emphasis>pinol</emphasis> (chicken-flavored corn gruel), <emphasis>pepi’an</emphasis> (chicken stew with squash seeds, hot chilies, tomatoes, and tomatillos [small green tomato]), and <emphasis>caldos</emphasis> (soups made of chicken stock and vegetables). Green leafy plants are often added to soups and stews. Preferred beverages are Hibiscus tea, limonadas/ponche de frutas (juices), and coffee.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ladino foods reflect their Spanish ancestry and include maize, rice, black or red beans, beef, chicken, pork, milk, cheese, plantains, carrots, peppers, tomatoes, squash, avocado, cilantro, chilies, onion, garlic, lemon, lime, and chocolate. Common dishes include <emphasis>arroz con pollo</emphasis> (chicken with rice), <emphasis>chile rellenos</emphasis> (peppers stuffed with pork or beef with carrot, onion, and tomato and fried in egg batter), and <emphasis>tamales</emphasis> (chicken or pork in a corn paste steamed in banana leaves or corn husks). Additional delicacies may stem from surrounding regions of Mexico, El Salvador, and Belize, and include <emphasis>Paches</emphasis> (Maize, potato) and Dobladas (masa dough, cheese, ham and/or chicharones). Again, green leafy plants are often added to soups and stews. Foods are seasoned with toasted squash seeds ground to a powder. Guatemalan food is not served spicy; however, traditional foods tend to be rich in sodium.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Complete a nutritional assessment as part of the intake interview. Include teaching related to health concerns and provide cultural alternatives to nutrition for at-risk individuals.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For religious purposes, most Guatemalan individuals do not believe in contraception use and/or abortion practices. Women who desire contraception will not actually seek to obtain modalities for prevention due to lack of spousal, familial, and religious support. When the Guatemalan patient expresses a desire to learn more about family planning, women may request the session include her husband and supporting family members to assist with decision-making.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Arrangements should be made to accommodate the patient’s request. Health-care providers should allow autonomy in patient decision-making and provide resources for reference.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mayan women do not believe in traditional birthing processes which includes lying down to give birth and/or delivering in a hospital setting. The idea that a Guatemalan woman in the might need to deliver in the hospital may be perceived as foreign and frightening. Traditional practices of Mayan culture include ceremonial/religious environments and prefer the squatting technique when delivering offspring. <emphasis role="bold">If possible, provide a tour of the labor and delivery unit well before her due date and provide options for religious and/or midwife involvement for guidance. Allow women to guide their birthing process that is tailored in a safe and ethical structure.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If an individual eats in front of the pregnant woman without offering her food, she may believe she will have a miscarriage. Additional concerns include frequent touching of a mothers stomach during pregnancy. Instances as such may be indicative of fetal demise in Mayan culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Following delivery of a newborn, many indigenous Mayan tribes require the placenta to be burned, not buried, because it is disrespectful to the earth to do so. In contrast to this, traditional Mayan culture may support the burial of a placenta under a chosen tree to symbolize protection over the newborn. <emphasis role="bold">Inquire specific birthing practices and cultural necessities prior to, during, and following the birthing process.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalan women support breastfeeding and may continue breastfeeding until the child reaches the age of 5 years. They may also be breastfeed a new baby while continuing to breastfeed a toddler.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A bag with garlic, lime, salt, and tobacco is hung around the baby’s neck, and a red thread is used to tie the umbilical cord to protect the baby, provide strength, and to denote respect for the ancestors. Urbanized Guatemalan individuals seek to use amulets, gold, and munekitas (dolls) for newborn protection and to ward off evil spirits. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove amulets or other items that are seen as protective for the baby.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Guatemalans relate their illness or poor diagnostic outcomes to “punishment” or impending death. The notion that tragedy is a result of “God’s will” is primary and some may refuse an intervention or heroic measures to align with spiritual and cultural practice.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When a Guatemalan dies, the family may request repatriation of remains. It is important for the final resting place to be the home country. Often, immediate and extended family will pool their resources together in order to financially support the transportation of remains home.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Refer families to Social Services and funeral homes to assist with transporting the body to Guatemala. Additional resources may be available to support funding for repatriation.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans believe in burial; they do not practice cremation. <emphasis role="bold">Practices may differ in urbanized regions—include family, chaplain, and social services to support decision-making.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Yellow is the color of mourning. Yellow flowers are placed at the grave. Food is placed at the head for the spirit of the departed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ladinos mourn the dead by wearing black. Maya do not believe in this practice.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Guatemalans are Roman Catholic. When the Spanish brought Roman Catholicism to Guatemala, some Maya converted to Christianity. Others continued to practice their Mayan religion. Currently, many Guatemalans use a combination of beliefs and practices adopted through generational influence. In some cases, Guatemalans integrate aspects of Catholicism into their lives while continuing to believe in the spirituality of their ancestors in private. <emphasis role="bold">Utilize chaplain services to tailor religious practice regimines.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Two practices influenced by the Spanish are <emphasis>guachibal</emphasis> and <emphasis>cofradia</emphasis>. <emphasis>Guachibal</emphasis> involves the practice of keeping an image of a Christian saint in the home and celebrating on the particular saint’s day. <emphasis>Cofradia</emphasis> refers to a “religious brotherhood” that serves to maintain the “cult” of a particular saint. <emphasis>Cofradias</emphasis> consist of dues-paying members and elected leaders. In addition to religious activities, this population often assists with care of the underserved in the community by visiting the ill, rehabilitation centers, community kitchens, and paying for funeral services.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family provides Guatemalans with meaning in their lives. Life revolves around the nuclear and extended family. Spirituality helps to explain life and the circumstances faced by Guatemalans. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage the incorporation of familial involvement for supportive care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Whether Catholic, Protestant, or traditional Mayan, many believe that life events happen for a reason. The reason may be attributed to favor from God(s) when positive experiences occur and to punishment or disfavor from God(s) when negative events occur. Some Guatemalans feel nothing can be done to change the outcome of these experiences. This belief is referred to as <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">fatalism</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When illness occurs, many Guatemalans turn to their family and faith for strength, wisdom, and hope. <emphasis role="bold">Do not remove statues or pictures of patron saints. Contact chaplaincy for spiritual care services for the patient and family through their church or hospital resources.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The preferred mode of treatment among Ladinos is medication administered by hypodermic injection. If an infant has a cold, Ladinos believe an injection is necessary to treat conditions effectively. If someone has the flu, an IV infusion is preferred. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about allopathic medical practice.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Healthcare and provider seeking among Guatemalans generally occurs by first seeking advice from a mother, grandmother, or other respected elder. If this approach is unsuccessful, then the family usually seeks healthcare from folk healers or spiritual guiders of preference.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Several medications, including antibiotics, purchased in the United States only with a prescription are available without a prescription in Guatemala. <emphasis role="bold">Ascertain if Guatemalan patients are receiving medicines from family or friends from their home country.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Modern medical care may be the last resort. Many are fearful of hospitals. In Guatemala, when hospital care is necessary, patients are often seriously ill, resulting in death, which perpetuates the belief that “hospitals are places where patients go to die.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Guatemalans engage in folk medicinal practices and use a variety of prayers, herbal teas, and poultices to treat illness. Many of these practices are regional-specific and vary among families, sub-cultures, and generational influence. Many of these practices are harmless, however, some may contradict or potentiate therapeutic interventions. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically ask patients whether they are using folk medicine and/or what modalities to care they are currently practicing.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A common belief among this population is that numerous disorders can be attributed to an imbalance in the thermoregulatory equilibrium of the human body (hot and cold). Therefore, the consumption of foods with contrasting properties has the potential to alleviate or preempt certain ailments and disorders associated with temperature imbalances.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Physical or mental illness may be attributed to an imbalance or disconnect between a person and the environment. Influences include emotional, spiritual, and social state, as well as physical factors such as humoral imbalance expressed as either too much hot or cold.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Nonjudgmentally ask patients and families about the use of folk and traditional therapies and holistic modalities used.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Folk practitioners are consulted for several notable conditions. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Mal de ojo</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (evil eye) is a folk illness that occurs when one person (usually older) looks at another (usually a child) in an admiring fashion. Another example of <emphasis>mal de ojo</emphasis> is if a person admires something about a baby or child, such as beautiful eyes or hair. Such eye contact can be either voluntary or involuntary. Symptoms are numerous, ranging from fever, anorexia, and vomiting to irritability. The spell can be broken if the person doing the admiring touches the person admired while it is happening. Children are more susceptible to this condition than women, and women are more susceptible than men.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans often delay seeking healthcare until they are incapacitated by illness, disease, or injury. Many times, they are unaware of the dangers associated with working in agriculture. These individuals may be exposed to pesticides and dangerous equipment without proper training. Although the government has specific laws in place to protect farm workers, enforcement is limited. Companies may not disclose to workers the dangers encompassed in a specific job role or the workers may not understand instruction due to language differences. <emphasis role="bold">Be aware of the chemical exposures, laws, and resources available in order to adequately provide care for and advocate for the patient. Resources should be provided in the patient’s native language and/or via a certified interpreter.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Barriers to healthcare include <emphasis>availability, accessibility/reliability, affordability</emphasis>, a <emphasis>ppropriateness, accountability</emphasis>, a <emphasis>daptability, acceptability, awareness,</emphasis> a <emphasis>ttitudes, approachability, alternative practices and practitioners, and additional services</emphasis> (see Chap. <emphasis role="EmphasisTypeUnderline ">3</emphasis>).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans tend to view health and illness in relation to their ability to perform duties associated with their roles. As long as women are functioning in their role of caring for the home and family and men are functioning in their job, then they feel “healthy.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When an illness prevents normal functionability required for their specific role(s), then Guatemalans view this as a serious concern. The cause of debilitating illness or disease may be viewed as punishment from God rather than lack of prevention or early detection.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When symptoms persist, fear may keep the Guatemalan patient from seeking medical attention.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family members would rather care for their loved one at home if at all possible. <emphasis role="bold">Demonstrate respect for the cultural values by providing community resources that enable them to adequately care for a family member at home if they desire.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Blood transfusions and organ donation are not common in Guatemala, and with many living outside of the realm of modern medicine, residents may be uneducated regarding the indication, risks, and benefits of interventional practice. Questions related to organ donation may be puzzling and elicit fear and anxiety. <emphasis role="bold">Ensure patient/family readiness to learn when providing complex educational objectives.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some Guatemalans fear venipuncture from belief that taking blood leaves the body without enough blood to keep them strong and healthy. <emphasis role="bold">Assess the level of education and understanding of the Guatemalan patient regarding blood and blood products. Use an interpreter who is competent in the language and culture of the patient to promote successful communication.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0016s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">16.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Modern medicine</emphasis> refers to healthcare provided by educated physicians and nurses, generally in urbanized regions. <emphasis>Ladino folk medicine</emphasis> is provided by Ladino pharmacists, spiritualists, and lay healers (<emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">curanderos</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Mayan Indians</emphasis> seek medical care from Mayan <emphasis>shaman</emphasis>, <emphasis>bonesetters</emphasis>, and <emphasis>herbalists</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">When Ladinos and Mayan Indians have access to modern medicine, the utilization of these services increases. <emphasis role="bold">Provide education on accessibility to patient preferred medicinal practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the United States and elsewhere, Guatemalans use many Mexican-based traditional healers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans have great respect and admiration for health-care providers who are viewed as authority figures with clinical expertise.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalans expect their health-care provider to have the appearance and manners of a professional. When this is not the case, Guatemalans lose confidence in the provider.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many fear disclosure which may result in deportation or rejection. Patients also fear confidentiality will not be maintained in the health-care setting. <emphasis role="bold">Educate patients on disclosure laws in the related to health-care information and the ability to receive care without fear of deportation.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Guatemalan women are usually very modest. They may refuse to discuss personal issues or receive an examination by a male health-care provider. Likewise, a male Guatemalan patient may refuse a female health-care provider. <emphasis role="bold">Provide a same-sex provider when possible, especially for intimate care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because Guatemalans dislike conflict, they may not actually refuse care; yet they withhold personal information owing to discomfort with the health-care provider. <emphasis role="bold">Ensure rapport building exercises are used to provide patient comfortability and potentiate the divulgence of the reasoning for seeking health-care advisory.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
