<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">This chapter provides a general overview of American Indians and Alaskan Natives (AI/AN) followed by a more detailed description of the Navajo Nation as one exemplar. Space does not permit an extensive discourse on each tribe. The 2020 census reports 9.7 million people identified as American Indian and Alaska Native alone or in combination with another race. This is a significant increase from the 5.2 million in 2010. Around 20% live in American Indian areas/reservations or Alaska Native villages. The census report is tabulated based on an AI/AN write-in response to the 2020 census race question indicating that there is a changing demographics among AI/AN. National findings indicate that the Alaska Native alone population grew 10.9% to 133,311 while the AN alone or in any combination population increased 45.6% to 241,797. A similar increase is seen in the American Indian alone population which grew 11.6% to 2,159,802 while the alone or in any combination population nearly doubled to 6,363,796.</para>
         <para role="Para">There are more than 574 federally recognized sovereign AI/AN tribes, of which 231 are Alaskan Natives and are divided into five groups: Aleuts, Northern Eskimos (Inupiat), Southern Eskimos (Yuit), Interior Indians (Athabascans), and Southeast Coastal Indians (Tlingit and Haida). In addition, there are approximately 400 non-federally recognized tribes, each with its unique customs and beliefs. Some Alaskan Natives do not mind being called Eskimos or Indians; however, some do not like to be called Native Americans or Eskimos and prefer Alaskan Native, Alaska Indian, or Inuits. The amount of Indian blood or blood quantum necessary to include enrolment requirements is dependent on each tribe. For example, the Cherokee Nation laws are based on legal documentation that demonstrates direct ties to the tribe with no blood quantum. However, the Navajo Nation requires at least one biological parent to be enrolled with the Navajo Nation, the applicant must meet the minimum ¼ Navajo blood quantum requirement. Many of the Sioux Nations from the great plains area require ¼ blood quantum and three generations of lineal descent.</para>
         <para role="Para">Indian Health Service (HIS): The Indian Health Service (IHS) was designed to fulfill the U. S. government’s role in providing health care to American Indians and Alaskan Natives (AI/AN); however, inadequate funding has left those who depend on the IHS with only limited health care.</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Overall, AI/ANs are extremely diverse groups of people. Some are very traditional, some are highly acculturated, and some selectively combine tradition with the European American culture. Many share similar, but not exact, traditions, beliefs, and values.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">AI/ANs are a particularly vulnerable population in terms of accessing health care.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">High poverty rates, increasing suicides, individual high-risk health behaviors, social factors, low educational levels, chronic conditions and greater health disparities make it particularly important for accessing and receiving ongoing supportive and preventive care.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">One-third of AI/ANs are in families with incomes below the federal poverty line. The median household income for American Indian and Alaska Natives is $49,906.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">One in five adults has not graduated from high school; 65 % earn a high school diploma compared with 75.2% of the U. S. population. The college graduation rate is also much lower, with 9.3% compared to the national average of 20.3%.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Almost half of uninsured adults do not have a usual source of care, making it difficult to receive preventive services and timely care for acute health problems.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">The IHS is divided into 12 regions, each with either hospital, clinics, or outreach areas. The regions are listed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
               <link linkend="ch0005s0001ta01">5.1</link>
            </emphasis>. Federally recognized tribes are considered sovereign nations, giving them independent authority over their territories with the power to rule and make laws.</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Although the IHS includes access to some specialty care and has established urban Indian health clinics, shortages in funding and a lack of facilities and health-care professionals have left many eligible AI/ANs struggling to obtain timely, high-quality health care.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">The AI/AN population is a young population with a median age of 31 years compared with 37 years for the US overall.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <table id="ch0005s0001ta01">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.1</emphasis> Regions of the Indian Health Service</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
               <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
               <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
               <tbody>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Region</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Area(s) served</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Great plains area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">North Dakota, South Dakota, Iowa, and Nebraska</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Alaska area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">State of Alaska</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Albuquerque area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">New Mexico, Colorado, and Texas</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Bemidji area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Indiana, Minnesota, Michigan, and Wisconsin</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Billings area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Montana and Wyoming</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">California area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">California and Hawaii</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Nashville area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Eastern US</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Navajo area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Arizona, New Mexico, and Utah</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Oklahoma city area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Oklahoma, Kansas, and portions of Texas</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Phoenix area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Arizona, California, Nevada, and Utah</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Portland area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Oregon</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Tucson area</para>
            
                     </entry>
                     <entry>
              
                        <para role="SimplePara">Southern Arizona</para>
            
                     </entry>
                  </row>
               </tbody>
            </tgroup>
         </table>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">AI/ANs are collective cultures and avoid conflict and confrontation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Each tribe has its own language, but some languages are similar to each other.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Younger people speak English. Some older people may know only their traditional tribal language or perhaps Spanish in the southwestern part of the United States.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If needed, use professional interpreters whenever possible. Confidentiality is taken seriously. Often the younger family members will serve as interpreters.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Trust and privacy are major elements that facilitate a clearer communication.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greeting with Mr., Mrs., or Miss shows respect and is always safe. Even the use of sir or ma’am is appropriate. While use of the given name is preferred by some; wait for permission to use it.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Asking for help with pronunciation of a surname is appreciated.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greet everyone in the room and establish relationships. A light handshake is appropriate with a simple nodding of the head gestures an acknowledgment of the person.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Depending on the situation, punctuality may not be valued. Lateness is not meant as disrespect but is the result of a different sense of time. Explain the importance of timeliness if required and be flexible with appointment times whenever possible. Use of a watch is not common. Be aware that many do not have reliable transportation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Silence is a means of respect and thinking before speaking. Interrupting someone while he/she is talking is considered rude.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Strong emotions are not usually displayed verbally or nonverbally.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Direct questioning expecting an immediate answer is frowned upon. Ask questions in an indirect way, using a phrase such as “Tell me about…” or “Can you give more information…”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">One does not have the right to speak for someone else.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Directly telling someone that he/she is wrong is considered rude.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Maintaining continued eye contact with someone during a conversation is considered disrespectful. Do not maintain direct and sustained eye contact during an assessment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Singling out a specific individual for an answer is disrespectful because if the person is wrong, he/she will meet peer disapproval.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A long pause in a conversation does not necessarily mean the person is finished talking. Wait for a nonverbal gesture that says the person has finished.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Do not use idioms, colloquialisms, or abstract ideas; those unacculturated to the dominant culture might not understand them.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greet AI/ANs with a <emphasis>light</emphasis> handshake, not a firm, pumping handshake.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A nod of the head may denote “I hear you,” not necessarily agreement with what has been said.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Loudness may be interpreted as aggressiveness.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most appreciate a space greater than 2 ft during a conversation, especially with strangers, and for some maybe up to 6 ft. Take cues from the patient.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The extended family is the primary social unit in most AI/AN culture.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most define family as members made up of fictive (blood-related) and nonfictive (non-blood-related) kin, extended family, and tribal community. One is rarely alone or without family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some tribes are patriarchal and patrilocal (a social system where a married couple lives with the husband’s family); others are matriarchal and matrilocal (a social system where a married couple lives with the wife’s family) in structure. Given the individuality in any family system, determine the family spokesperson ahead of time before a decision must be made.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional women are responsible for child rearing, domestic tasks, and the overall concerns of the family. In a more modernized version women’s roles are more varied. Determine in a “simple” how and where the women’s role is. Many tribes value the matriarchal role of the women especially if she is the primary caregiver.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The goal of family and parental support, within the context of the family of origin, is to foster interdependence.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Family and parental support encompasses cultural and spiritual maintenance and satisfaction of physical and emotional needs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lifelong interdependence among members is fostered.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In traditional families, children frequently attend adult events, but they are expected to remain silent unless invited to speak.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Child rearing is a family affair that includes aunts, uncles, and cousins. While the mother bears the primary child-rearing responsibility in a traditional family, fathers, and siblings are active participants.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rather than learning from direct verbal instruction, children are expected to learn through observation and from examples.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">It is acceptable for children to be disciplined in public.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Children demonstrate their skills and knowledge by what they can do rather than what they say.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Gay and lesbian lifestyles have long been accepted in many tribes, although there are individual variations. Alternative lifestyles are accepted readily in most tribes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older people are held in high respect and are a good source for family care.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality may not be valued. Explain the importance of timeliness in reporting to work if required.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Understanding of family dynamics as it relates to transportation, child/parent care, and work is important to understand.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Do not use idioms, colloquialisms, or abstract ideas; those unacculturated with the dominant American culture might not understand them.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Greet AI/ANs with a <emphasis>light</emphasis> handshake, not a firm, pumping handshake. Introduction of others in the room is not always done so acknowledging others is important.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Do not single out a specific individual for an answer; if the person is wrong, he/she will meet peer disapproval.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Actions speak louder than words; if something is promised, make sure the promise is carried out or give an explanation as to why it could not be done.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">While some American Indians are well over 6 ft tall, others are well under 6 ft, especially Eskimos.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most have little body hair, brown skin, and epicanthal folds; however, with intermarriage, many AI/ANs have no distinct characteristic features.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Eskimos are susceptible to narrow-angle glaucoma because they have a shallow chamber and thicker lenses.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">AI/ANs have the highest rate of poverty of any racial group in the nation. They also have the highest rates of crime, suicide, alcoholism, gang membership, and sexual abuse. Suicide rates among AI/AN persons increased nearly 20% from 2015 (20.0 per 100,000) to 2020 (23.9), compared with a &lt;1% increase among the overall U. S. population (13.3 and 13.5, respectively)</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Nearly half of all Native American women (46%) have experienced rape, physical violence, or stalking by an intimate partner. One in three Indian women will, at some point in her life, experience the violence and trauma of rape.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">On some reservations, Native American women are murdered at a rate more than ten times the national average. The National Crime Information Center (2016) reported that 5712 reports of missing American Indian and Alaska Native women and girls (MMIWG) through the U. S.</para>
                  <para role="Para">This vulnerability state indicates that NA women make up a significant portion of missing and murdered cases. The murder rates are ten times higher than the national average for women living on reservations, but murder is the 3rd leading cause of death for NA women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The rate of child abuse is twice as high as the national average. For every 1000 of these cases being reported, an average of 15.2 of these cases were for American Indian/Alaska Native children.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The prevalence of diabetes mellitus is at least twice that of any other racial and ethnic group. AI/ANs have high rates of obesity.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The leading causes of death are cancer, chronic liver disease, unintentional injuries, diabetes, and heart problems. AI/ANs die at higher rates than other Americans from tuberculosis, alcoholism, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, unintentional injuries, homicide, and suicide.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Domestic violence rates are also alarming, with more than 4 in 5 American Indian and Alaska Native adults (83%) experiencing some form of violence in their lifetime. This translates to almost three million people who have experienced psychological aggression or physical violence by intimate partners, stalking, or sexual violence. Explain abuse laws at every opportunity. Educate teachers and tribal leaders on the signs and symptoms of suicide ideology.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">While bullying does not cause suicide, a stressful environment and persistent, emotional victimization can increase a person’s risk of suicide. Incorporate anti-bullying recommendations of <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="http://stopbullying.gov">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">
                              <emphasis role="bold">stopbullying.gov</emphasis>
                           </emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">More than one-quarter smoke. Partner with schools beginning in elementary school for anti-smoking campaigns.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">One in five is a binge drinker. Work with tribal leaders to develop support groups for alcohol and drug misuse. Begin teaching about alcohol and drug misuse beginning in elementary schools.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Incorporate in elementary schools in conjunction with tribal leaders “I Strengthen My Nation,” an IHS campaign that empowers Native youth to resist drugs and alcohol and motivates parents to talk openly to their children about drug and alcohol use. In addition, <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="http://wernative.org">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">we Rnative.org</emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis> offers young people information on puberty, sexual violence, suicide, cultural preservation, and other important health topics.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although great variation exists, most AI/AN diets are high in fat and sugar.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Include a dietary assessment as part of the intake interview.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Availability of fresh fruits and vegetables may be severely limited, especially during winter in cold climates and on reservations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask if any particular food is taboo, what foods are consumed for health promotion, and what foods are consumed during illness.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Birth control practices are usually an individual choice.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some do not discuss birth control with providers until significant trust is established.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Each tribe has specific foods believed to be beneficial for pregnancy. <emphasis role="bold">Ask about specific foods at each stage of the pregnancy.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women in many tribes remain active throughout their pregnancies.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe that wearing a necklace may cause the baby to be born with the umbilical cord wrapped around its neck.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe that if a pregnant woman walks through a door backward, she will have a breech delivery.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe that blowing up balloons may cause premature rupture of the membranes.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe that leaving projects unfinished may prolong labor.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Stoicism during labor and delivery is valued by some. <emphasis role="bold">Ask frequently if pain medicine is needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Younger, more urban generations may not adhere to any traditional birthing practices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For some tribes, the father is not usually present during the birth. <emphasis role="bold">Do not make the father feel guilty if he does not want to participate until after the delivery.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Delivering in a kneeling or squatting position is preferred by some.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In some tribes, the placenta is saved and buried, returning it to mother earth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Postpartum, the mother may be isolated according to the sex of her child; 1 month for a boy and 2 months for a girl. However, this is not a widespread belief.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many women resume their normal activities within a week and are expected to care for their babies as well as other family members.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women often turn to their mothers for advice after birth.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some tribes do not name the baby for a week or longer after the delivery and may include an English name along with a tribal name. <emphasis role="bold">Do not assume that not naming the baby means the parents do not care about or do not want the baby.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some tribes often name a newborn after a recently deceased respected relative.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Both sexes are seen as gifts from nature.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In general, AI/AN religions do not have precise beliefs about life after death.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe in reincarnations with rebirth as a human, as a ghost, as an animal, or as a combination of these.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Burial ceremonies vary by tribe. For example, the burial ceremony of the Zuni requires individuals to take 3 days off from work.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Autopsy is generally acceptable. <emphasis role="bold">Explain legal requirements if necessary.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Expect and respect a wide variation on bereavement.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some tribes have preserved their spiritual beliefs in writing or as an oral tradition.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some adhere to the Native North American Church. Others may be more traditional, practice mostly Christian religions, or combine the two.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Native North American Church practices have four requirements for good health: food, sleep, cleanliness, and good thoughts. The four divisions of nature are also a holistic part of spirituality: spirit, mind, body, and life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Routes of spiritual connectedness include singing, drumming, dancing, and using sweat lodges. <emphasis role="bold">Warn about dehydration when using sweat lodges.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0005s0001ta02">5.2</link>
                     </emphasis> lists the major values between AI/AN tribes and the European American culture.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0005s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 5.2</emphasis> Tribal values versus European American values</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tribal traditional cultural values</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">European American values</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Group, clan, or tribal emphasis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Individual emphasis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Present oriented</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Future oriented</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Time, always with us</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Time, use every minute</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Age</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Youth</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cooperation</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Competition</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Harmony with nature</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Conquest of nature</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Giving, sharing</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Saving</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pragmatic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Theoretical</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Mythological</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Scientific</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Patience</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Impatience</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Mystical</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Skeptical</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Shame</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Guilt</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Permissiveness</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Social coercion</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Extended family and clan</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Immediate family</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Nonaggressive</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Aggressive</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Modest</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Over confident</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Silence</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Noise</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Respect others’ religion</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Convert others to religion</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Religion, way of life</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Religion, a segment of life</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Land, water, forest</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Land, etc.</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Belong to all</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Private domains</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Beneficial, reasonable</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Avarice, greedy</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Use of resource</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Use of resource</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Religion, medicine, and healing are inseparable among AI/AN populations.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Diseases can be attributed to natural or unnatural forces, the scientific theories of illness and disease, or a combination of both.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Natural remedies are preferred, although the specific herbal remedies vary significantly by tribe and region of the country and depend on environmental influences for what is available.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients about specific herbal and tribal remedies so they do not conflict with or potentiate allopathic medicines and treatment.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Incorporate IHS programs that give general directions for health-care providers: Breastfeeding Promotion and Support, Diabetes Treatment and Prevention, Epidemiology, Elder Care Initiative, Health Weight for Life, Influenza, and HIV/AIDS (</emphasis>
            
                     <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
              
                        <ulink url="http://www.ihs.gov">
                
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">
                              <emphasis role="bold">www. IHS.gov</emphasis>
                           </emphasis>
                        </ulink>
            
                     </emphasis>
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">).</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Family conferences are appreciated with serious illness.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mental illness may be seen as violation of tribal taboos or loss of harmony with the environment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Organ donation is not usually practiced, but it is usually an individual choice.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0005s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">5.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">“Shaman” is often used refer to traditional AI/AN healer.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Spirits may be encouraged to occupy the shaman’s body during public lodge ceremonies. Drum beating and chanting aid this process.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Tribal spiritual healers may be used in combination with allopathic providers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Ask for disclosure of all treatments and explain possible complications.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Partner with traditional healers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Similar to identifying over the counter, explore possible alternative treatments.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
