<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0030s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">30.2 </emphasis> Reflective Exercises</title>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are traditional verbal and nonverbal communication practices in Russian culture?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>How do Russians value their time and punctuality?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are the decision-making practices of current Russian immigrants?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>List one health care condition in Russians in each of the three categories: environment, lifestyle, and genetics. What can you do to decrease the incidence and prevalence of these diseases?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are common high-risk health behaviors among Russian immigrants? Include some strategies for reducing them.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>What are fertility practices among Russians? What education would you provide to the family about childbirth and contraception practices?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Many Russians are afraid of having X-rays and CT scans. What is the reason for this? What can you do to decrease their fear?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify a traditional treatment that Russians use for respiratory symptoms. How would you know that this treatment is being used?</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify some practices women use during pregnancy.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Identify some cultural and traditional Russian practices. Which of them might have harmful effects?</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
