<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0018s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">More than 1.4 billion people inhabit India. Over 80% of the population are Hindus, followers of Hinduism. Other significant religious groups include Muslims (13.4%), Christians (2.3%), Sikhs (1.9%), and other (1.8%). Although different religious sectors share many common cultural beliefs and practices, they differ according to the variant characteristics of culture as presented in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>. India is divided into north and south, based primarily on Dravidian and Aryan cultural variations.</para>
         <para role="Para">Immigrants to the United States come predominantly from urban areas, including all major Indian states, and they have come in two waves. The first wave began in the early twentieth century and continued to the mid-1920s. Conditions such as racial discrimination and lack of access to economic advancement made it difficult for the first wave of Asian Indians to sustain themselves or their culture in America. The second wave of immigration began after 1965 and still continues. Most individuals from this wave are highly educated. Most come to the United States to attain a higher standard of living, better working conditions, and job opportunities. Secondary reasons include opportunities for additional education and Indian perceptions of America as a country of opportunity and freedom. Trafficking, primarily internal, of men, women, and children for the purposes of forced or bonded labor and commercial sex exploitation continues to be a major problem for Indians.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Indian state borders are reorganized in accordance with language limitations. Languages fall into two main groups: Indo-Aryan in the north and Dravidian in the south. Hindi with numerous dialects is spoken by 41% of the population and is the national language, along with English. In addition, there are 14 other official languages: Bengali, Telugu, Marathi, Tamil, Urdu, Gujarati, Malayalam, Kannada, Oriya, Punjabi, Assamese, Kashmiri, Sindhi, and Sanskrit. English is the language among the educated. <emphasis role="bold">Provide an interpreter for those who may not speak English well.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women often speak in a soft voice, making it difficult to understand or decipher what they say. Men may become intense and loud when they converse with other family members. To an onlooker, it might seem disruptive but, in general, this form of communication can be construed as meaningful when it is conducted with close friends. Although with changes in modern society, this trend is following west with women empowerment. In Sikhs, women have relatively more freedom and comparable status to men.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional women avoid direct eye contact with men. Direct eye contact with older people and authority figures may be considered a sign of disrespect. <emphasis role="bold">Do not misconstrue a lack of eye contact as not caring or not listening.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Touching and embracing are not acceptable for displaying affection. Even between spouses, a public display of affection such as hugging or kissing is frowned upon, being considered strictly a private matter.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Temporality is past-, present-, and future-oriented. Time is conceived in cycles of four ages, which start with the “age of perfection” and end with the “age of degeneration.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality in keeping scheduled appointments may not be considered important. <emphasis role="bold">Do not misconstrue being late for appointments as a sign of irresponsibility or not valuing health. Reinforce the necessity of punctuality when needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older family members are usually not addressed by name but as elder brother, sister, aunt, or uncle. A woman never addresses a man by name because the woman is not considered an equal or superior. The trend has changed in past decade where women are now addressing their spouses by name.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Strangers are greeted with folded hands and a head bow.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">No institution in India is more important than the family. The hierarchical structure of authority is the patriarchal joint family, based on the principle of superiority of men over women.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The male head of the family is legitimized and considered sacred by caste and religion, which delineate relationships. Central relationships in this system are based on the continuation and expansion of the male lineage through inheritance and ancestor worship, related to the father–son and brother–brother relationships. Due to recent changes in law, women are considered equal shareholders of parental assets; however, socially, its still frowned upon.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A matrilineal system exists in a few areas in the southwestern and northeastern regions of the country; however, power rests with the men in the woman’s family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A submissive and acquiescent role is expected of women in the first few years of married life, with little or no participation in decision-making. Strict norms govern contact and communication with the men of the family, including a woman’s husband. However, millennials are open, and women participate in decision-making.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Parents want their children to be successful and strongly encourage and emphasize scholastic achievement in fields that promise good employment and high social status. Parents in America want their children to maintain ties with their families and the Indian community.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although many parents expect and accept the Westernization of their children, the question of marriage is still a concern for parents who have opinions about how their children should be married, whether “arranged” or partly arranged. Hindu parents or Indians from all religious traditions want their children to marry other Indians. However, with western influence, cross cultural marriages are seen among Indian and Indian Americans but frowned upon socially.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Arranged marriages at a young age are considered most desirable for women. The practice of an arranged marriage continues in the United States in order to minimize the stress associated with differences in castes, lifestyles, and expectations between the male and female hierarchy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The two major types of transfer of material wealth accompanying marriage are bride price and a dowry. Bride price is payment in cash and other materials to the bride’s father in exchange for authority over the woman, which passes from her kin group to the bridegroom’s kin group.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In the joint family structure, Hindu women are considered “outsiders” and are socialized and incorporated in such a way that “jointness” and residence are not broken up; therefore, a close relationship between the husband and wife is disapproved because it induces favoring the nuclear family and dissolving the joint family. Therefore, a marriage is regarded as indissoluble. Due to westernization, trends have changed where divorces are becoming common among Indians and Indian Americans. In Sikhs, historically and religiously, women are granted similar status as men where they participate and share religious responsibilities with men.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older family members are held in reverence and cared for by their children when self-care becomes a concern.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Understand the various types of families (joint, extended, or nuclear) and determine which individual has control within the hierarchy.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Single-parent, blended, and communal families are not well accepted by Hindus. With changing trends, nuclear families are more common among Indians and American Indians.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Homosexuality may cause a social stigma. <emphasis role="bold">Refer lesbian, gay, or bisexual Hindu Americans to national support groups such as Tri Kone, a nonprofit group for lesbian, gay, and bisexual South Asians located in the San Francisco Bay area; the National AIDS hotline; or Asians Together in Washington, DC. Do not disclose the same-gender relationships to other family members. Due to recent changes in law, gay or same-sex marriages have become legal in India, however, social stigma persists.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">At work, Hindus adopt American practices and cultural habits. Hierarchies of age, gender, and caste prescribe transactions among Hindus. At work, relationships are a reproduction of the authority-dependence characteristic of family and social relationships.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In seeking to establish a personal and benevolent relationship, Hindus may be seen as too eager to please, ingratiating, or docile, all antithetical to the task of assertion and independence. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the value of assertiveness expected of all health-care providers in the American workforce.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Punctuality may not be considered important. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the necessity of timeliness in the American workforce.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Similar trends may be noted among American Sikhs. Practicing Sikhs may be seen wearing turbans (head covers) and iron bracelets in dominant hand, even at work.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Indian diversity of physical types can be divided into three general groups according to the color of their skin: white in the north and northwest, yellow in areas bordering Tibet and Assam, and black in the south.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Indids</emphasis> (whites) have a light-brown skin color, wavy black hair, dark- or light-brown eyes; are tall or of medium height; and are either dolichocephalic (long-headed) or brachycephalic (short-headed).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Melanids</emphasis>, often referred to as the Dravidians, are the population of southern India and have dark skin ranging from light brown to black, elongated heads, broad noses, thick lips, and black, wavy hair. They are usually shorter than 5 ft. 6 in. tall.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Pallor in brown-skinned patients presents as a yellowish-brown tinge to the skin. Pallor in dark-skinned individuals is characterized by the absence of the underlying red tones in the skin. Jaundice may be observed in the sclera. The oral mucosa of dark-skinned individuals may have a normal freckling or pigmentation. Inspection of the nail beds, lips, palpebral conjunctiva, and palms of the hands and soles of the feet shows evidence of cyanosis.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0018s0001ta01">18.1</link>
                     </emphasis> lists commonly occurring health conditions for Hindus in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Be alert to possible signs and symptoms and risk factors associated with diseases linked to migration from India.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many individuals require lower doses of lithium, antidepressants, and neuroleptics, and they may experience side effects even with the lower doses. They also are more sensitive to the adverse effects of alcohol, resulting in marked facial flushing, palpitations, and tachycardia. <emphasis role="bold">Question therapeutic regimens that do not consider racial or ethnic differences.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0018s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 18.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Hindus</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Malaria</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Filariasis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tuberculosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pneumonia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cardiovascular diseases</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Rheumatic heart disease</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Sickle cell anemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dental diseases</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactose intolerance</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cancer of the cheek, nose, and mouth</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Breast cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ichthyosis vulgaris</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Beriberi</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Thiamine deficiency</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lathyrism</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Goiter</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Osteomalacia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Endemic dropsy</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stomach cancer</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Fluorosis</para>
              
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Alcoholism and cigarette smoking among Hindu Americans, especially among men, cause significant health problems. Sikhs are more prone to drinking problems, but refrain from smoking due to religious reasons. <emphasis role="bold">Refer to “stop smoking” clinics, and encourage low alcohol consumption. Partner with elementary school teachers to introduce anti-smoking at a young age.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Diabetes is becoming more common among Indian Americans due to genetic predisposition, dietary habits, and stressful lifestyle.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Beriberi is found in people coming from rice-growing areas, pellagra in maize-millet areas, and lathyrism in khesari-growing areas of Central India. Thiamine deficiency is common among people who are mostly dependent on rice. Thorough milling of rice, washing rice before cooking, and allowing the cooked rice to remain overnight before consumption the following day results in the loss of thiamine.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lathyrism is a crippling disease-causing paralysis of leg muscles; it occurs mostly in adults who consume large quantities of seeds of the pulse khesari, <emphasis>lathyrus sativus</emphasis>, over a long period.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Goiters are common along the sub-Himalayan tracts.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Osteomalacia is prevalent in northwest India.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Endemic dropsy is prevalent in west Bengal as a result of the use of mustard oil for cooking.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Cancers of the mouth and lip are common because of chewing <emphasis>pan</emphasis> and tobacco.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Fluorosis occurs in parts of Punjab, Haryana, Andhra Pradesh, and Karnataka, resulting from drinking water with large amounts of fluoride. Cancer is becoming increasingly common among North/Northwest Indians due to environmental changes, heavy use of pesticides for farming and food adulteration.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dietary habits are complex and regionally varied. Most believe that food was created by the Supreme Being for the benefit of man. The influence of religion is pervasive in food selection, customs, and preparation methods.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Classification of regional food habits can be twofold, based on the types of cereals and fresh foods consumed. In the first category are rice and bread eaters; in the second category are vegetarians and nonvegetarians. Vegetarianism is firmly rooted in culture; the term <emphasis>nonvegetarian</emphasis> is used to describe anyone who eats meat, eggs, poultry, fish, and sometimes cheese. Many Brahmins in North India consider eating meat to be religiously sanctioned. In some parts of India, eating fish is acceptable to Brahmins, whereas in other parts, eating meat is sacrilegious. Sikhs are primarily vegetarians, American Sikhs are more liberal and consume all variety of meats and animal products. Assess cultural food choices upon admission to the health-care facility.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dietary staples include rice, wheat, <emphasis>jowar, bajra</emphasis>, jute, oilseeds, peanuts, millet, maize, peas, sugarcane, coconut, and mustard. Cereals supply 70–90% of the total caloric requirements. A variety of pulses or lentils, cooked vegetables, meat, fish, eggs, and dairy products are also consumed. Heavily spiced (curry) dishes with vegetables, meat, fish, or eggs are favored, and hot pickles and condiments are common. Spice choices include garlic, ginger, turmeric, tamarind, cumin, coriander, and mustard seed. Vegetable choices include onions, tomatoes, potatoes, green leaves, okra, green beans, and root vegetables.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In North India wheat is the staple food. Other cereals are <emphasis>jowar</emphasis>, <emphasis>bajra</emphasis>, and <emphasis>ragi</emphasis>, consumed in porridges, gruels, and <emphasis>rotis</emphasis> (baked pancakes).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis>Bajra</emphasis>, a staple food in Maratha families, is not considered favorably in Uttar Pradesh. People from Punjab do not favor fish, and people from the south generally dislike the idea of meat of any kind. In Saurashtra in the south, fish, fowl, flesh, and eggs are taboo practically everywhere.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women generally serve the food but may eat separately from men. Women are not allowed to cook during their menstrual periods or have contact with other members of the family. In Sikhs culture is very liberal and women may join men during meals, very less restriction is seen for women related to menstruation and cooking.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assess food rituals practiced by Hindus and Sikhs in relation to meal times and food selections before attempting dietary counseling.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Foremost among the perceptions of Hindus and Sikhs is the belief that certain foods are “hot” and others are “cold” and therefore should only be eaten during certain seasons and not in combination. The geographic differences in the hot and cold perceptions are dramatic; many foods considered hot in the north are considered cold in the south. Such perceptions and distinctions are based on how specific foods are thought to affect body functions. The belief is that failure to observe rules related to the hot and cold theory of diseases results in illness. A more detailed description of the hot and cold theory of diseases is provided under Health-Care Practices. <emphasis role="bold">Given the diversity of Hindus in America, individually assess dietary practices and nutritional deficiencies of patients according to their ethnic origins and area of residence.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Birth control methods include intrauterine devices, condoms, and rhythm and withdrawal methods. <emphasis role="bold">Women may desire education in family planning from a same-sex health-care provider as well as assistance with delivery from female physicians, midwives, or female nurse practitioners.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Grandmothers, mothers, and mothers-in-law are considered to have expert knowledge in the use of home remedies during pregnancy and the postpartum period. Many older women frequently travel to the United States to assist new mothers in antenatal and postnatal care that is consistent with traditional customs.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The birth of a son is a blessing because the son carries the family name and takes care of the parents in their old age. The birth of a daughter is cause for worry and concern because of the traditions associated with dowry, a ritual that can impoverish the lives of those who are less affluent. With modernization, this thinking is changing and especially in urban areas, birth of daughter is welcomed.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0018s0001ta02">18.2</link>
                     </emphasis> describes various cultural practices related to pregnancy.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">No taboo against the father being in the delivery room exists, but men are usually not present during birthing. Instead, they tend to wait outside the delivery room and allow female relatives to support the pregnant mother during labor and delivery. <emphasis role="bold">Report labor progress to fathers who prefer to stay in the waiting room.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because self-control is valued, women suppress their feelings and emotions during labor and delivery. <emphasis role="bold">Closely observe nonverbal communication, such as a change in body posture, restlessness, and facial expressions during labor and provide assistance as necessary.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Beliefs and practices used during the postpartum period are discussed in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0018s0001ta03">18.3</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0018s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 18.2</emphasis> Practices during pregnancy</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Based on the hot and cold theory of disease, certain “hot” foods like eggs, jiggery (a course brown sugar), coconut, groundnut, maize, mango, papaya, fruit, and meat are avoided during pregnancy because of a fear of abortion caused by heating the body or inducing uterine hemorrhage</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Pregnancy is a time of increased body heat; hence “cold” foods such as milk, yogurt, and fruits are considered good. Buttermilk and green leafy vegetables are avoided because of the belief that these foods cause joint pain, body aches, and flatulence. Minor swelling of the hands and feet is thought to result from increased heat and is not of much concern</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Morning sickness is caused by an increase in body heat. Burning sensations during urination, scanty urine, or a white vaginal discharge are considered serious signs of significant overheating</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Overeating and consumption of high-protein foods, including milk, are avoided because such foods result in an exaggerated growth of the baby that may lead to a difficult delivery</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Anemia caused by iron deficiency is one of the nutritional disorders affecting women of childbearing age. This condition may be aggravated because of the practice of reducing the consumption of leafy vegetables to avoid producing a dark-skinned baby</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table id="ch0018s0001ta03">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 18.3</emphasis> Postpartum beliefs and practices</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• During the postpartum period, the mother remains in a warm room and often keeps the windows closed to protect her against cold drafts. Exposure to air conditioners and fans, even in warm weather, may be considered dangerous. Provide warm clothing and additional blankets for the mother and baby to keep them warm</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• After the birth, both the mother and the baby undergo purification rites on the 11th day. The postpartum mother is considered to be impure and is confined to a room. The pollution lasts for 10 days. This period of necessitated and mandatory confinement assists in bonding between the mother and the newborn and provides the mother with adequate rest and time to tend to the baby’s needs. The baby is officially named on the 11th day during the “cradle ceremony,” and several rituals are performed to protect the baby from evil spirits and to ensure longevity</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• A sponge bath for the newborn is recommended until the umbilical cord falls off</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Soft massage to the extremities is recommended before bathing the infant</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Washing the infant’s hair daily is believed to improve the quality of the hair</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• During the postpartum period, hot foods such as brinjals, drumsticks, dried fish, dhal, and greens are good for lactation. Cold foods are thought to produce diarrhea and indigestion in the infant. Cold foods such as buttermilk and curds, gourds, squashes, tomatoes, and potatoes are restricted because they produce gas. Such abstentions are primarily practiced for the baby’s health because harmful influences might be transmitted through the mother’s breast milk</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Some believe that colostrum is unsuited for infants. Most women think that the milk does not “descend to the breast” until their ritual bath on the third day and, as a result, newborns are fed sugar water or milk expressed from a lactating woman</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Breast milk is commonly supplemented with cow’s milk and diluted with sugar water. A child’s stomach is considered weak as a result of diarrhea; therefore, the child is given diluted milk</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Sources of protein such as eggs, curds, and meat are avoided because they might adversely affect the baby</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• The mother’s diet the first few days is restricted to liquids, rice, gruel, and bread</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Boiled rice, eggplant, curry, and tamarind juice are added to the diet between 6 months and a year after the birth of the baby</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Obtain dietary preferences and practices from the family before planning nutritional counseling</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A tenet of Hinduism is that the soul survives the death; death is a rebirth. Therefore, by performing a ritual bath, sprinkling holy river water over the body, covering the body with new clothes, daubing parts of the body with ghee, and chanting Vedic utterances, the deceased is considered purified and strengthened for the post-mortem journey.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hindus prefer to die at home. The eldest son is responsible for the funeral rites. In the absence of the oldest son, determine the spokesperson and decision maker for the family.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The death rite is called <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">antyesti</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">,</emphasis> or last rites. The priest pours water into the mouth of the deceased and blesses the body by tying a thread around the neck or wrist. The priest may anoint with water from the holy Ganges River or put the sacred leaf from the <emphasis>Tulsi</emphasis> plant in the mouth. The eldest son completes prayers for ancestral souls, but all male descendants perform the rites; each offers balls of rice on behalf of the deceased.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The body is usually cremated rather than interred. The ashes are immersed or sprinkled in the holy rivers. Such immersions are of great benefit to the souls of the dead. Hindus may save their family’s ashes to later scatter them in holy rivers when they return to their homeland.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women may respond to the death of a loved one with loud wailing, moaning, and beating their chests in front of the corpse, attesting their inability to bear the thought of being left behind to handle situations by themselves. <emphasis role="bold">Offer support and understanding with respect for death and grief behaviors.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death rituals in Sikhs are like Hindus. Corpse is given final bath before cremating the body, followed by pouring ghee into mouth of the corpse. After cremation, ashes are immersed in holy river followed by last prayer at the deceased’s home. Wake is usually observed for 3–5 days after death.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hinduism, the largest religion and oldest tradition practiced in India, represents a set of beliefs and a definite social organization. Hinduism denotes belief in the authority of Vedas and other sacred writings of the ancient sages, immortality of the soul and a future life, existence of a Supreme God, the theory of <emphasis role="bold">karma</emphasis> and rebirth, the theory of the four stages of life, and the theory of four <emphasis>Purusarthas</emphasis>, or ends of human endeavor. <emphasis>Karma</emphasis> stresses the individual’s responsibility for one’s actions and is interpreted in terms of past life. One’s present condition is seen as a result of one’s actions in a past life or lives.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sikhs believe in karma and reincarnation. However, they believe in one god and their holy book is Sri Guru Granth Sahib. Sikhs believe in hard work, sharing and meditation. Practicing Sikhs may also wear their five articles of faith which includes iron bracelet in dominant hand, small dagger for self-defense, long undergarment, small wooden comb and do not cut or shave hair from any part of their body.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Orthodox Hindus view society as divinely ordained on the basis of the four castes: (a) <emphasis>Brahmin</emphasis>, the highest caste, priests and scholars, emerged from the head of God; (b) <emphasis>Kshtriya</emphasis>, warriors, from the arms; (c) <emphasis>Vaisya</emphasis>, merchants, from the waist; and (d) <emphasis>Sudra</emphasis>, menials, from the feet of God. The four-fold caste system is a theoretical division of society to which tribes, clans, and family groups are affiliated. Although religion does not bestow the caste system with a religious sanction, the great Hindu legal codes are based on the caste system. <emphasis role="bold">Identify Hindu religious beliefs and practices, and incorporate these beliefs into patients’ care. Respectfully ask Sikh patients if they would like to take off their articles of faith and get consent before cutting or shaving hair from any body part.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Assess the extent to which religion is a part of the individual’s life, how religious beliefs are related to the individual’s perception of health and illness, and the individual’s daily religious practices. Assessing spiritual life is essential for identifying resources and solutions for therapy.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women often fast one day a week or for a lunar month to fulfill a vow made to a deity in supplication for a particular blessing. Sikh men/women do not believe in fasting.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Shrines may be set up in the living room or the dining room but are most often located in a back room or in a closet. The shrine typically contains representations or symbols of one or more deities. Sikh shrines/temples usually have holy sculptures to read from, Sikhs do not worship idols or photos.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Physical examinations are especially traumatic to women who may not have experienced or heard about Pap tests and mammography examinations. <emphasis role="bold">Provide female health-care providers for intimate care.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most believe that illnesses attack an individual through the mind, body, and soul.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some believe that excessive consumption of sweets may cause roundworms and that too much sexual activity and worry are associated with tuberculosis. Others believe that diarrhea and cholera are caused by a variety of improper eating habits. <emphasis role="bold">Explain factual information about parasitic and infectious diseases.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Suffering of any kind produces hope, which is essential to life. To maintain harmony between self and the supernatural world, the belief that one can do little to restore health by oneself provides a basis for ceremonies and rituals.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Worshiping goddesses, pilgrimages to holy places, and pouring water at the roots of sacred trees are believed to have medicinal effects in healing the sick person and in appeasing the planets to help prevent illnesses and misfortunes. Sikhs may believe in consuming holy water or pouring holy water on affected organ/body part to heal.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In <emphasis>Ayurveda</emphasis>, the traditional system of medicine in India, the primary emphasis is on the prevention of illnesses. Individuals have to be aware of their own health needs. One of the principles of Ayurveda includes the art of living and proper health care, advocating that one’s health is a personal responsibility. The key to health is an orderly daily life in which personal hygiene, diet, work, and sleep and rest patterns are regulated. A daily routine has to be established and changed according to the season.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A common health problem is self-medication. Those migrating to America are accustomed to self-medicating and may bring medications with them or obtain medications through relatives and friends. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically ask patients about folk practices, use of over-the-counter medicines, and medicines brought from India.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The traditional healers, <emphasis>nattuvaidhyars</emphasis>, use Ayurvedic, Siddha, and Unani medical systems. These systems are all based on the Tridosha theory. The Ayurvedic system uses herbs and roots; the Siddha system, practiced mainly in the southern part of India, uses medicines; and the Unani system, similar to the Siddha, is practiced by Muslims.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">According to the Tridosha theory, the body is made up of modifications of the five elements: air, space, fire, water, and earth. These modifications are formed from food and must be maintained within proper proportions for health. A balance among three elements, or humors—phlegm or mucus, bile or gall, and wind—corresponds to three different types of food required by the body. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0018s0001ta04">18.4</link>
                     </emphasis> presents the three types of foods and the allopathic equivalents of diseases associated with them.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because of their religious beliefs of karma, Hindus may attempt to be stoic and may not exhibit symptoms of pain. Pain is attributed to God’s will, the wrath of God, or a punishment from God and is to be borne with courage. <emphasis role="bold">Because of stoicism, rely on nonverbal manifestations as well as verbal expressions when assessing pain.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families tend to be protective of ill members. They may not want to disclose the gravity of an illness to the patient or discuss impending disability or death for fear of the patient’s vulnerability and loss of hope, resulting in death. <emphasis role="bold">The conflict between medical ethics and patients’ values may pose a problem for health-care providers, who need to be cognizant of the importance of the family members’ wishes and values regarding the care of their loved ones.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The sick role is assumed without any feeling of guilt or ineptness in doing one’s tasks. The individual is cared for and relieved of responsibilities for that time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Psychological distress may be demonstrated through somatization, which is common, especially in women. The symptoms may be expressed as headaches, a burning sensation in the soles of the feet or in the forehead, and tingling pain in the lower extremities. Because of the stigma attached to seeking professional psychiatric help, many do not access the health-care system for mental health problems. Mental illness is considered to be God’s will. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose to outsiders that patients are receiving mental health counseling.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">No Hindu policy exists that prevents receiving blood or blood products. Donating and receiving organs are acceptable.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0018s0001ta04">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 18.4</emphasis> Bodily manifestations of various foods</title>
               <tgroup cols="1">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Heat-producing foods: <emphasis>Brinjals</emphasis>, dried fish, green chilies, raw rice, and eggs. <emphasis>Pittham</emphasis> foods include cluster beans, cowgram, groundnuts (peanuts), almonds, millet, oil, and runner beans. Allopathic equivalents of <emphasis>sudu</emphasis> diseases include diarrhea, dysentery, abdominal pain, and scabies. Allopathic equivalents of <emphasis>pittham</emphasis> diseases include vomiting, jaundice, and anemia</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Cooling foods: Tomatoes, pumpkin, kul, gourds, greens, oranges, sweet limes, carrots, radishes, barley, and buttermilk. Cold, headache, chill, fever, malaria, and typhoid are allopathic equivalents of cool diseases</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Gas-producing foods: Root vegetables such as potato, sweet potato, and elephant yam; plantain; and drumstick. Joint pains, paralysis, stroke, and polio are disorders related to gas-producing foods</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                
                           <para role="SimplePara">• Heating and cooling effects are produced in the body and hence are not related to the temperature or spiciness of foods. An imbalance leads to disease. If too much heat is in the body from consuming heat-producing foods, then cold foods need to be eaten to restore balance</para>
              
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0018s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">18.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although Hindus in general have a favorable attitude toward American physicians and the quality of medical care received in the United States, relatives and friends are usually consulted before health-care providers.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Physicians are considered omnipotent because God grants cures through physicians. Patients tend to be subservient and may not openly question physicians’ behavior or treatment. If they are not pleased with the treatment, they just change physicians. However, they tend to be appreciative of the information that physicians provide about their illness. <emphasis role="bold">Provide factual information about diseases and illnesses. Explain the dangers of “shopping around” for health-care providers.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The physician is also viewed like an older person in the family; a protective, authoritative, and responsible relationship; a parent–child relationship; and a <emphasis>guru-chela</emphasis> (teacher-disciple) relationship. <emphasis role="bold">Patients expect physicians to teach them about the disease and how to get cured in a friend-to-friend relationship.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">In mental health, traditional healers, such as <emphasis>Vaids</emphasis>, practice an empirical system of indigenous medicine; <emphasis>mantarwadis</emphasis> cure through astrology and charms; and <emphasis>patris</emphasis> act as mediums for spirits and demons. <emphasis role="bold">Specifically ask patients if they are using folk health-care providers and what treatments have been prescribed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women are especially modest, generally seeking female health-care providers for gynecologic examinations. <emphasis role="bold">Respect modesty by providing adequate privacy and assigning same-gender caregivers whenever possible.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
            
                     <emphasis role="bold">Explain the procedures, provide privacy, and assign a female health-care provider to decrease the stress and discomfort associated with a pelvic examination.</emphasis>
          
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
