<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0002s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1 </emphasis> The Purnell Model</title>
         <para role="Para">The Purnell Model for Cultural Competence and its organizing framework can be used in all practice settings and by all health-care providers. Moreover, it has been classified a holographic and complexity grand theory. In fact, even mediators with the American Bar Association have found the model valuable. The model is a circle, with an outlying rim representing global society, a second rim representing community, a third rim representing family, and an inner rim representing the person (Fig. <emphasis role="InternalRef">
               <link linkend="ch0002s0001fg01">2.1</link>
            </emphasis>). The interior of the circle is divided into 12 pie-shaped wedges depicting cultural domains (constructs) and their associated concepts. The dark center of the circle represents unknown phenomena. Along the bottom of the model is a jagged line representing the nonlinear concept of cultural consciousness. The 12 cultural domains and their concepts provide the organizing framework. Each domain includes concepts that need to be addressed when assessing patients in various settings. Moreover, health-care providers can use these same concepts to better understand their own cultural beliefs, attitudes, values, practices, and behaviors. An important concept to understand is that no single domain stands alone; they are all interconnected. The 12 domains are overview/heritage, communications, family roles and organization, workforce issues, biocultural ecology, high-risk health behaviors, nutrition, pregnancy and the childbearing family, death rituals, spirituality, health-care practices, and health-care practitioners.</para>
         <figure float="0" id="ch0002s0001fg01" role="Figure">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Fig. 2.1</emphasis> The Purnell model for cultural competence</title>
            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="Ch0002f01.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>
         <sect2 id="ch0002s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.1 </emphasis> Assessment Guide</title>
            <para role="Para">Following each of the domains and concepts is a box that includes suggested questions to ask and observations to make when assessing patients from a cultural perspective. It is recognized that clinicians are not able to complete a thorough cultural assessment for every patient. The list of questions is extensive; thus, the clinician must determine which questions to ask according to the patient’s presenting symptoms, teaching needs, and the potential impact of culture. Furthermore, cultural values and beliefs might change over time.</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0002s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2 </emphasis> Domains and Concepts</title>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s01" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the country of origin and current residence; the effects of the topography of the country of origin and the current residence on health, economics, politics, reasons for migration, educational status, and occupations both present and past. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s02" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.2 </emphasis> Communications</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the dominant language, dialects, and the contextual use of the language; paralanguage variations such as voice volume, tone, intonations, inflections, and willingness to share thoughts and feelings; nonverbal communications such as eye contact, gesturing and facial expressions, use of touch, body language, spatial distancing practices, and acceptable greetings; temporality in terms of past, present, and future orientation of worldview; clock versus social time; and the amount of formality in use of names. Differences between the language spoken by the health-care provider and the patient, educational level, and health literacy are additional communication add to the communication difficulties. Effective communication is the first and probably the most important aspect of obtaining an accurate assessment. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s03" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.3 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes concepts related to the head of the household, gender roles (a product of biology and culture), family goals and priorities, developmental tasks of children and adolescents, roles of the aged and extended family, individual and family social status in the community, and acceptance of alternative lifestyles such as single parenting, same sex partnerships and marriage, childless marriages, and divorce. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s04" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.4 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes concepts related to autonomy, acculturation, assimilation, gender roles, ethnic communication styles, and health-care practices of the country of origin. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s05" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.5 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes physical, biological, and physiological variations among ethnic and racial groups such as skin color (the most evident) and physical differences in body habitus; genetic, hereditary, endemic, and topographical diseases; psychological makeup of individuals; and the physiological differences that affect the way drugs are metabolized by the body. In general, most diseases and illnesses can be divided into three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics.</para>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis>Lifestyle</emphasis> causes include cultural practices and behaviors that can generally be controlled: for example, smoking, diet, and stress.</para>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis>Environment</emphasis> causes refer to the external environment (e.g., air and water pollution) and situations over which the individual has little or no control (e.g., presence of malarial mosquitos, exposure to chemicals and pesticides, access to care, and associated diseases and illnesses). See table below.</para>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis>Genetic</emphasis> conditions are caused by genes.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s06" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.6 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes substance use and misuse of tobacco, alcohol, and recreational drugs; lack of physical activity; increased calorie consumption; nonuse of safety measures such as seat belts, helmets, and safe driving practices; and not taking safety measures to prevent contracting HIV and sexually transmitted infections. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s07" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.7 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes the meaning of food, common foods and rituals, nutritional deficiencies and food limitations, and the use of food for health promotion and wellness, and illness and disease prevention. Multiple diseases and illnesses are a consequence of this major cultural component. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s08" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.8 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes culturally sanctioned and unsanctioned fertility practices; views on pregnancy; and prescriptive, restrictive, and taboo practices related to pregnancy, birthing, the postpartum period, and family involvement. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s09" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.9 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes how the individual and the society view death and euthanasia, rituals to prepare for death, burial practices, and bereavement behaviors. Death rituals are slow to change. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s10" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.10 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes formal religious beliefs related to faith and affiliation and the use of prayer; behavior practices that give meaning to life; and individual sources of strength. See the following table.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s11" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes the focus of health care (acute versus preventive); traditional, magico-religious, and biomedical beliefs and practices; individual responsibility for health; self-medicating practices; views on mental illness, chronicity, and rehabilitation; acceptance of blood and blood products; and organ donation and transplantation. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0001s0002s12" role="Heading">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">2.1.2.12 </emphasis> Health-Care Practitioners</title>
               <para role="Para">Includes the status, use, and perceptions of traditional; magico-religious, and biomedical health-care providers; and the gender of the health-care provider. See table below.</para>
            </sect3>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
