<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0029s0001" role="Heading">
         <title>
            <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1 </emphasis> Overview and Heritage</title>
         <para role="Para">The Island of Puerto Rico is home to a population of approximately 3.5 million persons. The Puerto Rican community, comprising over 5.5 million individuals, represents the second largest demographic group in the continental United States accounting for nearly 10% of the Hispanic communities. They self-identify as <emphasis>Puertorri-queños</emphasis> or <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">Boricua</emphasis>
            </emphasis> (the Taíno Indian word for Puerto Rican) or <emphasis>
               <emphasis role="bold">Niuyoricans</emphasis>
            </emphasis> for those born in New York. Diversity among Puerto Ricans includes assimilation, individuality, and the variant characteristics of culture as presented in Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
               <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                  <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
               </ulink>
            </emphasis>.</para>
         <para role="Para">Puerto Rico is a commonwealth of the US Citizenship status, which has created a controversial <emphasis>va y ven</emphasis> (go and come) circular migration in which individuals and families are often caught in a reverse cycle of immigration, alternately living a few months or years in the United States and then returning to Puerto Rico. Some Puerto Ricans fear that the dominant American culture is a potential threat to the Puerto Rican culture, language, and future.</para>
         <para role="Para">Although the educational system in Puerto Rico is similar to that in the United States, when children emigrate from Puerto Rico to the mainland United States, many educational organizations place them one grade below their previous academic year, sometimes due to language barriers.</para>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.1 </emphasis> Communications</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">English and Spanish are both official languages.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans speak with a melodic, high-pitched, fast rhythm maintained when speaking English. <emphasis role="bold">Avoid making comments about accent, use caution when interpreting voice pitch, and seek clarification when in doubt about the content and nature of a conversation that may seem confrontational.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many prefer to read or share sensitive information, options, and decisions with close family members. Some obtain assistance from extended family or community members knowledgeable in health matters. <emphasis role="bold">Seek clarification of the information provided, ask for language preference in verbal and written communication, and allow time to exchange information with questions and answers when critical decisions need to be made.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Great value is placed on interpersonal interactions such as <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">simpatía</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> when an individual is perceived as likable, attractive, and fun-loving.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals enjoy sharing information about their families, heritage, thoughts, and feelings and expect the healthcare provider to exchange personal information when beginning a professional relationship.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">confianza</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (trust) is established, healthcare providers can establish open communication channels with individuals and families.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans readily express their physical ailments and discomforts, except for sexuality, which is often considered taboo. <emphasis role="bold">Set boundaries with discretion, emphasizing personal rather than impersonal and bureaucratic relationships.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among younger generations and those born in the United States, eye contact is maintained and is often encouraged, with the more traditional, limited eye contact being a sign of respect, especially toward older people.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The culture of Puerto Rico places significant importance on the values of reverence and nurturing toward the elderly population. <emphasis role="bold">Clinicians need to acknowledge and attend to the concerns and preferences of elderly patients while recognizing the significance of involving family members in the decision-making process and incorporating them into healthcare discussions when suitable</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Hand, leg, head, and body gestures are commonly used to augment messages expressed by words. Feelings and emotions are also expressed through touch.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Gesturing includes an affirmative nod with an “Aha!” response which does not necessarily mean agreement or understanding related to the conversation.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women greet each other with a robust and familiar hug, and if among family or close friends, a kiss is included. Young women may take offense to verbal and nonverbal communications that portray women as non-assertive and passive. Men may greet other men with a firm handshake and a left hand stroking the greeter’s shoulder.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Greet Puerto Ricans formally or with a friendly handshake.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most individuals are present-oriented, having a relativistic and serene view and way of life.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Carefully explain appointment times and time limits at the beginning of an interview.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Respect is reflected in how children talk, look, and refer to adults and older people. Rather than <emphasis>Señora</emphasis> (Mrs.) and <emphasis>Señor</emphasis> (Mr.), children and adults are expected to use the terms <emphasis>Doña</emphasis> (Mrs.) and <emphasis>Don</emphasis> (Mr.) for most adults. Aunts and uncles have their names preceded by <emphasis>tití</emphasis> or <emphasis>tío</emphasis> (auntie/uncle) and <emphasis>madrina</emphasis> or <emphasis>padrino</emphasis> (godmother or godfather).</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Address Puerto Ricans as</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Sr.</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">,</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Sra</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">.,</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Don</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">, and</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Doña</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A single woman may use her name as Sonia López Mendoza, with López being her father’s surname and Mendoza her mother’s. When she is married, the husband’s last name, Pérez, is added with the word <emphasis>de</emphasis> to reflect that she is married. This woman’s married name would be Sonia López de Pérez; the mother’s surname is eliminated. In business and health-care organizations, Señora López de Pérez is the correct formal title for promoting conversation or building relationships. <emphasis role="bold">Ask patients their complete name as well as their legal name.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some parents, hailing from conservative backgrounds, believe that children do not have to engage in conversations about sex with them. Some women perceive parents lacked awareness of children’s sexual activity during adolescence or before marriage.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sometimes, parents may struggle to initiate open and candid conversations regarding sexual matters with their children due to cultural norms that deem discussions about sex taboo within the household. Information about sex is predominantly facilitated through the educational system, with teachers and peers playing a crucial role in the education of young individuals. Involving Puerto Rican parents in conversations regarding sexual health education can pose specific difficulties attributed to potential unease surrounding the subject matter. <emphasis role="bold">Establish trust and cultivate an environment conducive to open communication. Offer guidance on engaging in conversations with children about safe sexual practices. Educate against sexually transmitted infections (STIs) and unintended pregnancies while underscoring the importance of privacy and consent</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">Ensure that their children’s health information is kept confidential</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">When language becomes a barrier, it is advisable to use interpreters to facilitate clear communication</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.2 </emphasis> Family Roles and Organization</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional families may view women as lenient, submissive, and wanting to please men. <emphasis role="bold">Accept family decision-making styles without judgment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional cultural norms discourage an overt sexual-being image for women, but many of these conventional values disappear with family assimilation. <emphasis role="bold">Topics such as sex, sexually transmitted infections, or other infections establish an environment built on</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">confianza</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">and</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">personalismo</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">. Employ culturally sensitive terminology and refrain from presumptions or imposing your views. Promote an environment conducive to open communication where clients are encouraged to articulate their opinions and share their concerns. Refer patients to specialty care or community support groups with specialized expertise in working within the Puerto Rican cultural context</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most families expect their children to stay home until they get married or pursue a college education. The mother is expected to actively discipline, guide, and advise children. Most fathers expect to be consulted but mainly see themselves as financial providers. <emphasis role="bold">Address family conflict within the context of the family to promote adolescents’ mental health issues rather than using individual approaches.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many traditional families socialize male children to be robust.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Female children are socialized with a focus on home economics, family dynamics, and motherhood.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Puerto Rican mothers use threats of punishment, guilt, and discipline, which can create stress and difficulties for adolescents as they struggle with the more permissive cultural patterns of the United States such as dating. <emphasis role="bold">Provide counseling and explain US child abuse laws.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The family structure may be nuclear or extended. Family members include grandparents, great-grandparents, married children, aunts, uncles, cousins, and even divorced families with their children.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Dependent older people are expected to live with their children and be cared for. Placements in nursing homes and extended-care facilities may be considered inconsiderate and cause family members to feel guilty and experience depression and distress. <emphasis role="bold">Explore alternatives for long-term care and provide information to all family members involved in this decision-making process—address discharge planning and hospice and palliative care. Develop strategies for providing emotional support and assistance to family members caring for older adults.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A family member is expected to be at the sick person’s bedside. <emphasis role="bold">Ask for the name of the family spokesperson and document it in the patient’s chart.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some families may have difficulty educating young women about sexuality and reproductive health. Thus, adolescents depend on educational organizations to learn about sexual health, including body changes such as menstruation and the reproductive system. <emphasis role="bold">Educating the family about sexuality issues gains respect and entrance into the trusted family environment.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Homosexuality is predominantly a taboo topic that carries a tremendous cultural stigma among most Puerto Ricans. Some men may perceive sexual intercourse with men as a sign of virility and sexual power rather than homosexual behavior. <emphasis role="bold">Do not disclose same-sex relationships without the patient’s consent. When providing care for individuals who identify as lesbian, gay, bisexual, or transgender, it is vital to inquire about their sexual orientation status, specifically whether they have openly shared this information (disclosed) or have chosen to keep it private (undisclosed)</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.3 </emphasis> Workforce Issues</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some have a relativistic view of time and may not value regular attendance and punctuality in the workforce. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the timeliness requirement in the dominant American (and other countries) workforce and any repercussions for chronic tardiness.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans value personal relationships at work. Work is perceived as a place for social and cultural interactions, including listening to background music while performing job activities. This practice may lead to loud, cheerful, and noisy conversations requiring the employer’s attention. <emphasis role="bold">Explain the culture of the dominant American workforce etiquette and the allowable noise level.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">For many women, family responsibilities, pregnancy, and the health of their children and other family members are prioritized over work. <emphasis role="bold">Negotiate flexible work hours when possible.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although most Puerto Ricans are bilingual, some speak broken or street English, such as <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Spanglish</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">Communicate composed and articulately, employing straightforward vocabulary and expressions that can aid in promoting comprehension</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among younger generations and those born in the mainland United States, eye contact is maintained and is often encouraged. With the more traditional, limited eye contact is a sign of respect, especially with older people. <emphasis role="bold">Ask questions and do not assume that the lack of eye contact means the person is not listening, caring, or being less than truthful.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0004" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.4 </emphasis> Biocultural Ecology</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The Puerto Rican population displays diverse skin tones, encompassing individuals with fair, olive, and darker complexions. The diversity observed can be attributed to the prevailing ancestral influences characterized by European, Spanish, African, and Native American physical traits.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">The facial features of individuals of Puerto Rican descent exhibit considerable diversity due to their varied ancestral backgrounds.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0029s0001ta01">29.1</link>
                     </emphasis> presents commonly occurring health conditions and diseases for Puerto Ricans in three categories: lifestyle, environment, and genetics. See Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0002#ch0002">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">2</emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Advise patients and families traveling to Puerto Rico to avoid exposure to endemic areas and always to use mosquito repellent and protective clothing. Become familiar with dengue fever’s signs, symptoms, and treatment recommendations.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0029s0001ta01">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 29.1</emphasis> Health conditions common to Puerto Ricans</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health conditions</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Causes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Heart disease</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lung cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Ovarian and cervical cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Asthma</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Prostate cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stomach and esophageal cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pancreatic cancer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diabetes mellitus</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Genetic, environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dengue fever</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Environment, lifestyle</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0005" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.5 </emphasis> High-Risk Health Behaviors</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Ricans have shown high rates of alcoholism. <emphasis role="bold">Use validated screening tools such as the brief version of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT), to assess individuals for alcohol misuse. Recommend patients to specialized treatment programs, such as outpatient counseling, inpatient rehabilitation, or mutual support groups. Conduct evaluations on patients to ascertain the coexistence of comorbid mental health disorders that commonly co-occur with alcoholism such as depression or anxiety. Develop a regular schedule of consecutive sessions to methodically assess the progress of the individual, address any potential relapses, and make adjustments to treatment</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Rican men and women have a high smoking prevalence. <emphasis role="bold">Assess smoking habits and promote programs aimed at helping individuals to quit smoking. It is beneficial for young children and adolescents to establish networks with schools, beginning in elementary school, to support healthy behaviors.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Lack of condom use may be a significant risk behavior. Some men fear that if they use condoms, they portray a less macho image, have decreased sexual satisfaction, or portray that they have a sexually transmitted infection or HIV. Some women may refuse a condom, believing the man thinks she is “dirty.” <emphasis role="bold">Provide choices such as contraceptive methods or pharmaceutical interventions</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0006" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.6 </emphasis> Nutrition</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Ricans celebrate, mourn, and socialize around food. Food is used (a) to honor and recognize visitors, friends, family members, and health-care providers, (b) as an escape from everyday pressures, problems, and challenges, and (c) to prevent and treat illnesses. Patients may bring homemade goods to healthcare providers to express appreciation, respect, and gratitude for services rendered. <emphasis role="bold">Refusing food offerings may be interpreted as a personal rejection.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Being overweight is a sign of health and wealth. Some individuals eat to excess, believing that if they eat more, their health will be better. <emphasis role="bold">Educate and negotiate a healthy weight with patients.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Diets include roots called <emphasis>viandas</emphasis>, vitamin-rich vegetables, and starches. The most common are celery roots, sweet potatoes, dasheens, yams, breadfruit, breadnuts, green and ripe plantains, green bananas, tanniers, cassava, and chayote squash or christophines. The dietary habits of Puerto Ricans often consist of processed foods while lacking in fresh fruits, vegetables, and whole foods. This dietary pattern may contribute to the development of many health disorders, including obesity, heart disease, and diabetes. In turn, it is crucial to evaluate Puerto Ricans’ access to nutritious food options and consider providing referrals to social workers to address this issue. <emphasis role="bold">Familiarize with some traditional foods and their nutritional content to assist families with dietary practices that integrate their conventional or preferred food selections.</emphasis> Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0029s0001ta02">29.2</link>
                     </emphasis> lists a variety of typical Puerto Rican food and ingredients.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many families believe a healthy child is <emphasis>gordita</emphasis> or <emphasis>llenito</emphasis> (diminutive for fat or overweight) and has red cheeks. <emphasis role="bold">Educate mothers and other family members about healthy nutrition and the health risks for children who are overweight.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A traditional breakfast includes hot cereal such as oatmeal, cornmeal, or rice and wheat cereal cooked with vanilla, cinnamon, sugar, salt, and milk. Although less common, many eat corn pancakes or fritters for breakfast. Lunch is served by noon, followed by dinner at around 5 or 6 p.m.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Rice and stew <emphasis>habichuelas</emphasis> (beans) are the main dishes. Rice may be served plain or cooked with many starch-rich side dishes. Rice cooked with vegetables or meat is considered a complete meal. <emphasis>Arroz guisado</emphasis> (rice stew) is seasoned with <emphasis>sofrito</emphasis>, a blend of spices such as cilantro, <emphasis>recao</emphasis> (a type of cilantro), onions, green peppers, and other nonspicy ingredients. Rice is cooked with chicken, pork, sausages, codfish, calamari, or shrimp. It is also cooked with corn, several beans, and <emphasis>gandules</emphasis> (green pigeon peas), a Puerto Rican bean rich in iron and protein.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Various pastas, breads, crackers, vegetables, and fruits are eaten. Fritters are also common foods. Fried green or ripe plantains are a favorite side dish.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many ascribe to the hot–cold classifications of foods for nutritional balance and dietary practices during menstruation, pregnancy, the postpartum period, infant feeding, lactation, and aging. Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0029s0001ta03">29.3</link>
                     </emphasis> identifies many of the foods that are considered either “hot” or “cold.” <emphasis role="bold">Becoming familiar with dietary practices facilitates the provision of expert recommendations for developing culturally sensitive food alternatives.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Understanding that iron is considered a “hot” food not usually taken during pregnancy can help healthcare providers negotiate approval. <emphasis role="bold">Educate women about the importance of adhering to iron recommendations, even during pregnancy and lactation. Demonstrate recognition and reverence toward these beliefs while delivering evidence-based knowledge regarding the significance of sufficient iron consumption and viable avenues for obtaining iron-rich dietary options. Participating in inclusive and culturally aware dialogues can facilitate the reconciliation of disparities between cultural values and medical recommendations.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A summary of food habits, reasons for practices, and recommendations for health-care providers during such developmental stages is included in Table <emphasis role="InternalRef">
                        <link linkend="ch0029s0001ta04">29.4</link>
                     </emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Black cohosh, evening primrose, St. John’s wort, ginkgo, ginseng, valerian root, sarsaparilla, chamomile, red clover, linden leaves, and passionflower are the most common herbs. <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the safety and efficacy of the most frequently used alternatives. Include the use of complementary and alternative therapies in routine health assessments.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">If the individual is believed to have low blood pressure and is weak or tired, brandy may be added to black coffee to enhance the work of “an old heart.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Exercise sensitivity toward folk practices as they can discourage patients from seeking further medical care and undermine their trust and confidence. This inquiry pertains to nutritional practices, focusing on integrating culturally sensitive meal choices or non-conflicting behaviors into dietary regimens.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">During illness, chicken soups and <emphasis>caldos</emphasis> (broth) are used as a hot meal to provide essential nutrients.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A honey, lemon, and rum mixture is used as an expectorant and antitussive. A malt drink, <emphasis>malta</emphasis> (grape juice), or milk is often added to an egg yolk mixed with sugar to increase the hemoglobin level. Ulcers, acid indigestion, and stomach discomfort are treated with warm milk, with or without sugar.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Herbal teas are used to treat illnesses and to promote health. Most herbal teas do not interfere with medical prescriptions. <emphasis role="bold">Incorporating herbal tea with traditional Western medicine may enhance treatment compliance.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <table id="ch0029s0001ta02">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 29.2</emphasis> Common Puerto Rican meals and fritters</title>
               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Puerto Rican meal</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">English translation</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Alcapurrias</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Green plantain fritters filled with meat or crab</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Arepas de maíz y queso</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cornmeal and cheese fritters</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Arroz con pollo</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Rice with chicken</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Arroz con gandules</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Rice with pigeon peas</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Arroz blanco (con aceite)</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Plain rice (with oil)</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Arroz guisado básico</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Plain stewed rice</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Asopao de pollo</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Soupy rice with chicken</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Bacalaitos</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Codfish fritters</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Bocadillo</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Grilled sandwich</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Mondongo</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Tripe stew</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Lechon</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Roasted pig</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Paella de mariscos</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Seafood paella</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Pastelillos de carne, queso o pasta de guayaba</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Turnovers filled with meat, cheese, or guava paste</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Pasteles</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Traditional dish mainly served during the Christmas season</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Pollo en fricase con papas</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Stewed chicken with potatoes</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Relleno de papa</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Potato ball filled with meat</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Sancocho</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Viandas and meat stew</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Sofrito</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Condiment (1 tbsp)</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">
                              <emphasis>Surullo de queso</emphasis>
                           </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cornmeal fritters filled with cheese</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table id="ch0029s0001ta03">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 29.3</emphasis> Puerto Rican hot–cold classification of health-illness status, medications, herbs, and selected foods</title>
               <tgroup cols="5">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
                  <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
                  <colspec colname="c5" colnum="5"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hot–cold classification</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health/illness status</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Western medications</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Traditional herbs</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Foods</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hot</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">G. I. illnesses (constipation, diarrhea, Crohn’s colitis, ulcer bleeding)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Gynecologic issues (pregnancy, menopause)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Skin disorders (rashes, acne)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Neurological disorders (headache)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Heart disease</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Urologic illnesses</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Syrups</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dark-colored pills</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Aspirin</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Anti-inflammatory agents</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Prednisone</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Antihypertensives</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Castor oil</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cinnamon</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Vitamins (iron)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Antibiotics</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Teas:</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cinnamon</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dark-leaf teas</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cocoa products</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Alcoholic beverages</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Caffeine products</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Hot cereals (wheat, corn)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Salt</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Spices and condiments</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Beans</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Nuts and seeds</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cold</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Osteomuscular illnesses (arthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis)</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Menstruation</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Respiratory illnesses</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Diuretics</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Bicarbonate of soda</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Antacids</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Milk of magnesia</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Teas:</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Orange-lemon, chamomile</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Linden</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Anise</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Rice</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Rice and barley water</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Milk</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Sugar and sugar products</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Mint</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Root vegetables</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Avocado</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Fruits</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Vegetables</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">White meat</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Honey</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Onions</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
            <table id="ch0029s0001ta04">
               <title>
                  <emphasis role="CaptionNumber">Table 29.4</emphasis> Puerto Rican cultural nutrition and health beliefs and practices during health stages</title>
               <tgroup cols="4">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1"/>
                  <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2"/>
                  <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3"/>
                  <colspec colname="c4" colnum="4"/>
                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Behavioral period</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Dietary and health practices</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cultural justification</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Recommendation for health-care providers</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry morerows="2">
                           <para role="SimplePara">Menstruation</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food taboos: Avoid spices, cold beverages, acidic citric fruits and substances, chocolate, and coffee</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">It may induce cramps, hemorrhage clots, and physical imbalance. It may produce acne during menstruation</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Assess individual beliefs and acknowledge them. Incorporate traditional beliefs with treatments as required in nonsteroidal anti-inflammatories for dysmenorrhea</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Foods encouraged: Plenty of hot fluids such as cinnamon tea and milk with cinnamon and sugar. Teas such as chamomile, anise seed, linden tea, mint leaves</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Fluids encourage body cleaning of impurities. Hot beverages promote circulation and reduce abdominal colic, cramps, and pain. Teas are soothing to all body systems</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Encourage passive exercise. Provide information about the role of exercise in the reduction of menstrual pain. Support other practices</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health practices: Avoid exercise and practice good hygiene. Do not walk barefoot. Avoid wind and rain. Stay as warm as possible</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Exercise may increase pain and bleeding. Good hygiene is important for health. Walking barefoot during menstruation may cause rheumatoid arthritis and other inflammatory diseases. Warm temperatures promote circulation and the health of the reproductive system, as well as prevent cramps</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry morerows="2">
                           <para role="SimplePara">Pregnancy</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food taboos: Hot foods, sauces, condiments, chocolate products, coffee, beans, pork, fritters, oily foods, and citric products</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">It may cause excess flatus, acid indigestion, bulging, and constipation. Chocolate and coffee may cause darker skin in the fetus. Some believe citric products may be abortive</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Encourage healthy food habits. Provide information about chocolate and coffee myths. Encourage fruits</para>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Discourage the use of raw eggs in beverages because of the possibility of salmonella poisoning</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food encouraged: Milk, beef, chicken, vegetables, fruits, and ponches</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Considered healthy and nutritious. Increase hemoglobin and strengthen and promote good labor</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Encourage the use of food recommended for pregnancy. Provide information about sexual activity</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health practices: Rest and get plenty of sleep. Eat plenty of food. Follow diet cautiously. Many avoid sexual intercourse early in pregnancy. Practice good hygiene and take warm showers</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">It enhances health and prevents problems during birth. Sex may cause issues with the baby or preterm labor</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Encourage a balanced plan of exercise with emphasis on weight control and the health of the baby</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry morerows="2">
                           <para role="SimplePara">Lactation</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food taboos: Avoid beans, cabbages, lettuce, seeds, nuts, pork, chocolate, coffee, and hot food items at all times</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">These foods cause stomach illnesses for the infant and mother, including baby colic, diarrhea, and flatus</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Include a dietary plan that is balanced with substitute food items. Clarify any myths about infant diarrhea, colic, and flatus</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food encouraged: Milk, water, ponches, chicken soup, chicken, beef, pastas, and hot cereals</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Improve health and increase hemoglobin and essential vitamins. Protect mother and infant from illnesses. Fluids and ponches increase milk supply. Red meats reduce cravings</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">As above with raw eggs. Provide information about reasons for stroke and facial paralysis. Provide time to ask questions and reduce anxiety during winter season deliveries</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health practices: Avoid cold temperatures and wind. A few may avoid showering for several days after birth. Great attention is paid to health of the mother</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Cold temperatures and winds are believed to cause stroke and facial paralysis in a new mother. Showering may cause respiratory diseases. Mother is believed to be at risk and fragile</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry/>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry morerows="2">
                           <para role="SimplePara">Infant feeding</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Food taboos: Beans, too much rice, and uncooked vegetables</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">It is believed to cause stomach colic, flatus, and distended abdomen. Too much rice causes constipation</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Provide information about appropriate dietary patterns for infant</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Foods encouraged: Hot cereals, ponches, chicken broth, or <emphasis>caldos</emphasis>. Fresh fruits, cooked vegetables, <emphasis>viandas</emphasis> (raw eggs, cereals, baby food in milk bottles). Fresh fruit juices. Mint, chamomile, and anise tea. Sugar and honey used for hiccups</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Believed to be nutritious, healthy, and to decrease hunger. <emphasis>Caldos</emphasis> are fortifying and preventing illness. Cooked vegetables are healthy and avoid constipation. Bottle food fills the baby. Fresh juices and fruits refresh the stomach. Teas help babies sleep and cure flatus. Sugar and honey have curing properties</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Instruct about infant diet and timely introduction of food items to diet. Explain the consequences of excessive weight in infants. Discourage food in a bottle to prevent choking. Discourage raw eggs because of the risk of salmonella and egg allergies and the use of honey because of the risk of botulism. Teas are harmless and provide additional fluid when used in moderation without sugar</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health practices: Keep baby warm while feeding</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Warm babies eat, chew, and digest food better, and choking is decreased</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Provide information about choking and babies</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Physical discomfort or illness</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Health practices: Some persons may believe they can alleviate discomfort by relying on faith and engaging in prayer</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Praying or invoking the Christian God to seek relief from physical discomfort or illness</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                           <para role="SimplePara">Evaluate dietary practices, including habits. Encourage prayer if it brings comfort and peace, emphasize medical treatment’s significance, and respect individuals’ beliefs. Puerto Ricans’ beliefs around worship have the potential to offer emotional and psychological benefits, which can have an indirect positive impact on their overall Well-being</para>
                        </entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0007" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.7 </emphasis> Pregnancy and Childbearing Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Due to the Catholic Church’s endorsement of “natural” family planning methods and sexual abstinence, women often refrain from using contraceptives such as foams, creams, and diaphragms, as they are regarded as morally objectionable. Historically, abortion has been predominantly seen as unacceptable, with limited exceptions granted when the mother’s life is at risk. However, it is worth noting that this perspective is shifting, with an increasing number of women embracing this option.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many women tend to initiate prenatal treatment later in their pregnancies. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage early prenatal visits and explain their importance in having a healthy pregnancy and newborn.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men are socialized to be tolerant, understanding, and patient regarding pregnant women and their preferences. Women are encouraged to rest, consume large quantities of food, and carefully watch what they eat. Some individuals expect women to “get fat” and place little emphasis on weight control. Strenuous physical activity and exercise are discouraged, and lifting heavy objects is prohibited.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many women refrain from <emphasis>tener relaciones</emphasis> (having sexual intercourse) after the first trimester to avoid hurting the fetus or causing preterm labor.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Loud and verbally expressive behaviors are culturally accepted and encouraged to cope with pain and discomfort. Pain medications are welcomed. Most women oppose having a cesarean section because it portrays a “weak woman.” <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the possibility of a cesarean section early in the pregnancy. Explain reasons for the necessity of invasive interventions during labor. Encourage using social support networks comprised of mothers who have undergone comparable experiences.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Women are encouraged to avoid exposure to wind and night lower temperatures, not to lift heavy objects, and not to do housework for 40 days after delivery. Some traditional women do not wash their hair during this time.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Mothers are encouraged to drink fluids such as milk and chicken soup if breastfeeding. They drink milk or fresh juices mixed with raw egg yolk and sugar if they feel weak or tired. Hot foods such as chocolate, beans, lentils, and coffee are discouraged because they are believed to cause stomach irritability, flatus, and colic for the mother and infant.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some women believe that breastfeeding increases their weight, disfigures their breasts, and makes them less sexually attractive and undervalue the benefits of breastfeeding. Puerto Rican women exhibit inferior evidence in several health habits and outcomes, such as lower exclusive breastfeeding rates.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide information about breastfeeding practices and educate women about myths and misconceptions. The inclusion of grandmothers and significant others in breastfeeding programs is encouraged due to their impact on breastfeeding practices.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0008" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.8 </emphasis> Death Rituals</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Death is perceived as a time of crisis. The body is considered sacred and is guarded with great respect.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Give news about the deceased to the head of the family first, usually the oldest daughter or son. <emphasis role="bold">Use a private room to communicate such notice and have clergy or ministers present when the news is disclosed. Allow time for the family to view, touch, and stay with the body before it is removed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Burial rituals may be delayed until all close family members can be present. Cremation is rarely practiced.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Among Catholics, religious ceremonies such as praying, <emphasis>velorio</emphasis> (wake), novenas, and 9 days of saying the rosary follow the death.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Families freely express themselves through loud crying and verbal expressions of grief. Some may talk in a thunderous way to God. Others may express their sorrow through sensitive but continuous crying or sobbing. Some believe that not expressing their feelings could mean a lack of love and respect for the deceased. Some develop psychosomatic symptoms; others may experience nausea, vomiting, or fainting spells due to an <emphasis>ataque de nervios</emphasis> (nervous attack). <emphasis role="bold">Be nonjudgmental with patients’ expressions of grief. Provide a private environment to help minimize interruptions.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0009" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.9 </emphasis> Spirituality</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans are Catholic; however, many have joined Evangelical churches because they offer a more personal spiritual approach. Many individuals who adhere to religious beliefs often rely on the concept of a higher power and miracles to overcome challenging circumstances.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">A few individuals practice <emphasis>espiritismo</emphasis>, a blend of Native Indian, African, and Catholic beliefs that deal with rituals related to spiritual communications with spirits and evil forces. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Espiritistas</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (individuals who communicate with spirits) may be consulted to promote spiritual wellness and treat mental illnesses. <emphasis>Espiritistas</emphasis> are often consulted to determine folk remedies compatible with Western medical treatments.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because older persons may consider illness a result of sins, a cure should be sought through prayer or by the “laying on of hands.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Inquire about the family’s wishes regarding the Sacrament of the Sick. Clergy are a resource for spiritual wisdom and help with various spiritual needs.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Although amulets have lost their popularity, some still use them. An <emphasis>azabache</emphasis> (tiny black fist) or a rabbit’s foot might be used for good luck, to drive away evil spirits, and to protect a child’s health. Rosary beads and patron saint figures may be placed at the head or side of the bed or on the patient to protect them from outside evil sources. <emphasis role="bold">Ask permission before removing, cleaning, or moving amulets. A benediction may be requested before removing amulets or religious objects, giving the Sacrament of the Sick, or providing spiritual support.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0010" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.10 </emphasis> Health-Care Practices</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many Puerto Ricans underuse health promotion and preventive services such as regular dental or physical examinations and Pap smears. The variant characteristics of culture (see Chap. <emphasis role="ExternalRef">
                        <ulink url="ch0001#ch0001">
                           <emphasis role="RefSource">1</emphasis>
                        </ulink>
                     </emphasis>) influence health-seeking beliefs and behaviors.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Integrate individual, family, and community resources to encourage a focus on health promotion and enhance early health screening and disease prevention. Offering weekend, evening, and late-night healthcare services increases the use of preventive services.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans believe in “family care” rather than self-care. Women are considered the primary caregivers and promoters of family health and are the source of spiritual and physical strength. The involvement of the family in the provision of care for individuals who are sick is a crucial aspect to consider. Given the cultural values held by Puerto Ricans, which prioritize the significance of family, faith, and religious practices, healthcare providers should exercise care when contemplating the possibility of referring families to social support services. <emphasis role="bold">Acknowledge the importance of family in healthcare-related matters. Involve family members in discussions and decision-making processes.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Natural herbs, teas, and over-the-counter medications are often used as initial interventions for symptoms of illness.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Patients who use folk practices visit <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">botánicas</emphasis>
                     </emphasis> (folk religious stores) and use natural herbs, aromatic incense, special bathing herbs, prayer books, prayers, and figurines for treating illness and promoting good health. <emphasis role="bold">Refrain from making prejudicial comments that may inhibit collaboration with folk healers.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most families prefer to keep chronically or terminally ill family members at home.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some place a damp cloth on the forehead to refresh the “hot” inside the body and relieve nausea. Some put the head between the legs to stop vomiting. Mint, orange, or lemon-tree leaves are boiled and used as tea to relieve nausea and vomiting.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Barriers to using healthcare services include poor English language skills, low socioeconomic status, lack of insurance, and lack of transportation. Many individuals experience apprehension when requesting time off from their employment concern for childcare.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Provide interpreters and offer social work or transportation services if needed.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Rican males may experience stigma and unease when engaging in open discussions about sexual health, primarily due to cultural norms and societal expectations. Consequently, individuals may exhibit more remarkable reticence and less inclination to pursue knowledge and assistance about matters of sexual health. <emphasis role="bold">Foster an environment that is inclusive and free from bias. Certain healthcare providers specialize in sexual health that can result in a higher level of expertise and sensitivity while engaging in discussions about sex-related matters.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Most Puerto Ricans tend to be loud and outspoken in expressing pain. Some prefer oral or intravenous medications for pain relief rather than intramuscular injections or rectal medications. Herbal teas, heat, and prayer are often used to manage pain.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Do not censure the expression of pain or judge it as an exaggeration. This expressive behavior is a socially learned mechanism to cope with pain.</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">¡Ay bendito!</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">is a common verbal moaning expression for</emphasis>
                     <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">dolor</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>
                     <emphasis role="bold">(pain).</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Rural elderly individuals might have difficulty interpreting and quantifying pain. The</emphasis> use of numerical pain-identifying scales may be inappropriate.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Because mental illness carries a stigma, obtaining information or talking about mental illness may be difficult. Some families might not disclose the presence or history of mental illnesses, even in a trusting environment. They might use phrases like “ <emphasis>estar bajoneado/</emphasis>a” (feeling down) or “ <emphasis>tener los nervios mal o de punta</emphasis>” (having bad nerves) as indirect ways to refer to these conditions. However, it’s important to note that this changes as mental health awareness grows and more people openly discuss these issues. <emphasis role="bold">Monitor the psychological well-being considering family dynamics and refer patients to support services as appropriate.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Symptoms of mental illness are often perceived as the result of <emphasis>nervios</emphasis> (nerves), having done something wrong, or failing God’s commandments. When someone is anxious or overcome with emotions or problems, they are just <emphasis>nervioso</emphasis>. Similarly, someone experiencing a mental health concern such as melancholy, anxiety, or lack of sleep may be <emphasis>nervioso(a)</emphasis> or suffering from an <emphasis>ataque de nervios</emphasis> (nervous attack) rather than clinically depressed or mentally ill. <emphasis role="bold">Demonstrate empathy and respect toward the individual’s beliefs. Recognize and validate the cultural perspective of the individual while acknowledging and affirming their emotional state and worries. Communicate by adapting to the cultural understanding of the listener. Refrain from using technical terminology commonly used in the medical field. Provide psychoeducational information regarding mental health disorders, emphasizing the multifactorial etiology of these problems, such as biological, psychological, and sociocultural elements</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Acknowledge confidentiality when obtaining healthcare history. If trust is built, health-care providers may get a more accurate response to their questions</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Promote physical and mental health by encouraging the active involvement of community-based churches, schools, or childcare centers</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Organ donation is considered an act of goodwill and a gift of life. Autopsy may be regarded as a violation of the body. <emphasis role="bold">When discussions regarding autopsies and organ donations are necessary, proceed patiently and provide precise and straightforward information. A priest or minister is often helpful and may be expected to be present at the time of death.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Many individuals are reluctant to receive or donate blood for fear of contracting HIV.</para>
                  <para role="Para ParaOneEmphasisChild">
                     <emphasis role="bold">Explore beliefs about blood donation and transfusions to dispel myths.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0029s0001s0011" role="Heading">
            <title>
               <emphasis role="HeadingNumber">29.1.11 </emphasis> Health-Care Providers</title>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Ricans hold healthcare providers in high regard. Distrust may develop if the healthcare provider (a) lacks respect for issues related to traditional health practices, (b) ignores <emphasis>personalism</emphasis> in the relationship, (c) does not use advanced technological assessment tools, and (d) has a physical or personal image that differs from the traditional “well-groomed white attire” image.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Puerto Ricans may use traditional and folk healers such as <emphasis>espiritistas</emphasis> and <emphasis>santeros</emphasis> with Western healthcare providers. Some <emphasis>espiritismo</emphasis> practices are used to deal with the power of good and evil spirits in the physical and emotional development of the individual. <emphasis>
                        <emphasis role="bold">Santeros</emphasis>
                     </emphasis>, individuals prepared to practice <emphasis>santería</emphasis>, are consulted in matters related to the belief of object intrusion, diseases caused by evil spirits, the loss of the soul, the insertion of a spirit, or the anger of God.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Traditional therapeutic practices like <emphasis>curanderismo</emphasis>, which mix herbal medicine, spiritual healing, and energy therapy, are just one example. Natural treatments, such as herbs and plants, are part of the healing practices employed by <emphasis>curanderos</emphasis> and <emphasis>curanderas</emphasis>. Another way that people deal with the disease is through the spiritual cleansing practice. Many Puerto Ricans put faith in the healing powers of spiritual purification. This may include using holy water or smudging negative energy away with herbs like sage or palo santo. <emphasis role="bold">Encourage patients to disclose any herbal remedies they are using alongside conventional treatments. Monitor the use of herbal remedies. Some herbs or vitamins may interact with prescribed medications or cause side effects: healthcare providers monitoring their use is essential for patient safety.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Men prefer male physicians and may feel embarrassed and uncomfortable with a female physician.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Sometimes, individuals may discount female physicians’ academic and intellectual competencies and distrust their judgment and treatment.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some women feel uncomfortable with a male physician; a few prefer a male doctor.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Older people may prefer more aged healthcare providers because they are considered wise and mature in health, life experiences, and folk practices.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Some people experience adverse societal perceptions when seeking help for mental health issues. <emphasis role="bold">Create a clinical environment that promotes support and inclusivity, acknowledging and valuing Puerto Ricans’ unique characteristics and cultural diversity</emphasis>. <emphasis role="bold">Use a systematic approach for facilitating appropriate referrals within mental healthcare. Integrate comprehensive health education initiatives that promote the normalization of mental healthcare and well-being, emphasizing the importance of seeking help when experiencing negative emotions</emphasis>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
