<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0004" label="4"><title>4. Patients Matter</title><sect1 id="ch0004s0012"><title>4. Patients Matter</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_4">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_4</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0004">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Patients, Healthcare organizations, Nurse, Patient-centered healthcare</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0004s0001"><title>4. Patients Matter</title><sidebar id="ch0004s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Describe the origin of the word patient.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explain how healthcare organizations facilitate the initiation of healthcare for patients entering their systems.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the role of the nurse as the protector of the patient.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Examine the importance of patient-centered healthcare.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0002" role="Heading"><title>Introduction</title><para role="Para">According to medical sociologist, the assuming of the role of patient involves the forfeiting of certain freedoms. Personal clothing is replaced with a hospital gown referred to as a “johnny” that allows for immediate access to the human body by healthcare workers and providers for physical examinations, assessments, placement of intravenous (IV) access for delivery of IV fluids and medications, and diagnostic tests (e.g., X-rays, ultrasounds, PET scans, etc.). Persons assume the role of “patient” after accepting that something is potentially not physically or emotionally well within themselves (Frank, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib04">2013</link></emphasis>; Parsons, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib09">1951</link></emphasis>; Schipke, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib12">2021</link></emphasis>).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0003" role="Heading"><title>Patients</title><para role="Para">The word <emphasis role="bold">patient</emphasis> originates from the Latin <emphasis>patiens</emphasis> or <emphasis>patior</emphasis> meaning one who bears or suffers (Neuberger, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib07">1999</link></emphasis>). Historically, the role of patient is one of passivity. Illness, mental and physical, happens to the patient and is uninvited. The unpredictability of the sick role experience is what has linked the patient role not with empowerment within the healthcare system but dependence and vulnerability. However, just because one adapts to their surroundings’ use of language (e.g., medical terminology), dress, and conduct does not mean that they are disempowered. Adaptation for functionality does not always equate to lack of access or knowledge of one’s illness state. It is also important to note that not all patients enter healthcare systems ill but for wellness checks to maintain health.</para><para role="Para">The vulnerability of patients occurs when there is no inquiry involved in their interfacing with the healthcare system. When information about illness and diseases one is diagnosed with is not provided by healthcare workers or healthcare providers, it is then that the patient role becomes one that is at risk for poor treatment and health outcomes. Hence, health disparities can occur within the patient role related to language barriers, race, socioeconomics, gender, ability to read and comprehend the medical information, sex, and other factors (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib05">2021</link></emphasis>).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0004" role="Heading"><title>Healthcare Organizations</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Healthcare organizations</emphasis> are structurally designed systems that are built with the intent to provide healthcare services in designated locations with varied populations. Healthcare organizations can include a physician group practice associated with a hospital system, clinics, hospitals, a host of different types of healthcare disciplines (e.g., nurses, physical therapists, respiratory therapists, physicians, etc.), third-party payers, the insured, specialty boards, and medical specialty groups (Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib02">2023</link></emphasis>). Additional services provided by healthcare organizations are home care, subacute care (e.g., skilled nursing facilities), acute care, hospice, and palliative care.</para><para role="Para">Healthcare organizations have become larger in size and have been purchasing multiple hospitals and building several clinics and urgent care facilities to address outpatient service public demands. When healthcare organizations are associated with academic institutions, research and evidenced-based practice are emphasized as being integrated into projected health outcomes for patient populations treated within the organizations. In order for populations residing in communities surrounding healthcare organizations to have their healthcare needs adequately met, healthcare organizations must invest in the investigation of risk factors associated with mortality and morbidity.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0005" role="Heading"><title>Patient-Centered Healthcare</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Patient-centered healthcare</emphasis> involves putting the patient and their physiological, psychological, and spiritual needs first. By embracing the patient first approach, all environmental and policy decisions related to patients are a priority. With the patient-centered care approach, theoretically, health systems exist solely to meet the needs of men, women, infants, and children who enter and exit the doors of their facilities. According to Santana et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib11">2018</link></emphasis>), patient-centered care itself is conceptually a holistic approach that is inclusive, empowering, individualized, and respectful of all persons. Caregiver leaders within healthcare organizations place their own personal relationship with patients as a priority, especially when planning and delivering patient health care.</para><para role="Para">Healthcare workers enter the field of healthcare to contribute to the identification, diagnosis, and implementation of care for ill patients. Ill patients drive the dedicated healthcare worker to make a difference not only in their lives but in the lives of others. Hence, patient-centered care is not a formidable task but a natural occurrence for healthcare workers, such as nurses who have made the conscious decision to enter professions providing care to persons suffering from physical and mental illnesses.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0006" role="Heading"><title>The Assumption of Sick Role</title><para role="Para">Talcott Parsons, a sociologist practicing within the United States, developed the theory of social systems. The social systems theory (Parsons, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib09">1951</link></emphasis>) explores the various roles held in society and the expectations placed on these roles and the persons who assume them in varied situations. The <emphasis>sick role</emphasis>, one of the roles identified by Parsons (Parsons, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib10">1975</link></emphasis>), is assumed by persons once labeled with an illness or diagnosis.</para><para role="Para">The assumption of the sick role often begins by the person acknowledging that their health status has changed. Physical and or mental symptomatology overcomes the affected person’s mind and body. The affected person will either present to a healthcare facility such as an urgent care center, a doctor’s office, community-based clinic, or emergency department within an acute care hospital setting to seek help.</para><para role="Para">Stripped of one’s own clothing, the sick person is welcomed into the health system with the changing into a disposable or cloth gown. The gown allows for ease of access for healthcare providers and healthcare workers to examine and assess the sick person using devices such as a stethoscope, the accessing of the veins (or arteries) to obtain blood specimens, ultrasounds, X-rays, or computed tomography (CT) scans. The process of diagnosis ensues as data is gathered via procedures, assessments, and evaluations. Ultimately, with critical analysis of gathered historical and past medical and surgical information, a diagnosis or diagnoses are made.</para><para role="Para">Lastly, with a known cause of illness or disease origination, the person in the sick role either accepts the proposed treatment or denies help. The engagement or disengagement with the healthcare system is the choice of the affected person. Their decision can have either lifesaving results, stabilization with cure, or the acceptance of a poor prognosis depending upon the diagnostic outcome projection made by healthcare providers, hence, the acceptance of death.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0007" role="Heading"><title>Nurses and Patients</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Nurses</emphasis> exhibit caritas toward their patients by meeting their physical, emotional, and spiritual needs. The assessment, diagnosis, planning, interventions, and evaluations performed by nurses for their patients literally stabilize disease processes, contribute to the diagnostic process, and save lives. The therapeutic foundations of the nurse-patient relationship develop with the initial communication of greeting and nurses’ introduction of themselves and their role in the provision of care to the patient. In academic nursing programs, nursing students are introduced to the concept of communication as a means to share and exchange information while transmitting and generating meaning. The latter occurs between two or more persons (Taylor et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib13">2023</link></emphasis>).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0008" role="Heading"><title>Forms of Communication</title><para role="Para">Communication involves the sending and receiving of both verbal and nonverbal communication by nurses and the patients in their care. Within verbal communication, language must be interpreted if the two persons do not share the same cultural and or geographic background. For nonverbal communication, the concepts of time and space will vary among persons of different cultures. Additionally, the way one moves their body, makes eye contact, and maintains boundaries are all impacted by their personal life experiences, culture, and any deficits in kinesthetic, auditory, or visual transmission (Andrews et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib03">2020</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">In the process of applying the <emphasis>nursing process</emphasis> to clinical practice, nurses are taught during their undergraduate education to formulate patient care plans. One of the tools used in several academic settings is the nursing diagnosis applying the North American Nursing Diagnosis Association-International (NANDA-I). The NANDA-I provides a formal definition and defining characteristics of identified patient’s risk factors (Ackley et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib01">2022</link></emphasis>), related factors, potential outcomes, and evidenced-based and clinically appropriate nursing interventions with rationales that support the reason for and necessity of implementation of interventions in the provision of quality and safe nursing care.</para><para role="Para">Current communication nursing diagnoses include communication and communication problems that are defined based upon specific patient needs, deficits, and disease factors or illnesses contributing to lack of communication or an inability to communicate suggestive of an impairment. The latter is determined by the clinical and critical thinking of the nursing professional, in the context of exercising clinical judgment. The following are two areas of communication to be addressed:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Impaired verbal communication.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Readiness for enhanced communication.</para></listitem></orderedlist><para role="Para">Readiness for enhanced communication involves the verbal exchange of information with others. The exchange of information includes comprehension of another’s thoughts, feelings, and objectives in the message they are delivering to another person. Communication, in absence of a language barrier or speech impediment, is understood by both parties. Impaired verbal communication is the absence, delay, or decrease in an individual’s ability to use a system of symbols, transmit, receive, or process information. Characteristically, examples of impairment in verbal communication can include slurred speech associated with a brain injury, stroke, facial paralysis, selective inattention, absence of eye contact, hearing impairment, or muteness (Ackley et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib01">2022</link></emphasis>; Newton &amp; Shah, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib08">2013</link></emphasis>).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0009" role="Heading"><title>Interpersonal Theory</title><para role="Para">Peplau (1952) examined the nurse-patient relationship with regard to the importance of the effectiveness of that which is being communicated and the clarity of the communication.</para><sect2 id="ch0004s0009s0001" role="Heading"><title>The Value of Effective Communication</title><para role="Para">Effective communication is invaluable because it constitutes the mutual listening, comprehension, and understanding of another person. Nurses, in their communication with patients, must demonstrate professionalism but most importantly, empathy and respect while nonjudgmentally gathering healthcare history and performing an assessment on their patients. Communication is necessary in the formation of therapeutic nurse-patient alliances that lead to diagnostic collaborations with healthcare providers and other disciplines in ensuring that patients are accurately diagnosed.</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0004s0009s0002" role="Heading"><title>The Angry Patient</title><para role="Para">Patients enter healthcare environments under duress. Unexpected illnesses that require the intervention of healthcare workers place ill persons in a position of vulnerability and powerlessness as they wait in waiting rooms to be evaluated and undergo diagnostic tests. Patients are also asked to tell their “health decline” stories over and over again the moment they enter healthcare environments. While it is imperative that patients’ past health histories be known in order for disease processes and illnesses to be identified, the repetition of “health decline” stories can heighten anxiety, increase fear, and frustrate patients. As a result of the latter, patients can become angry in their communications with nurses and other healthcare workers and professionals.</para><para role="Para">Workplace violence involving nurses is often perpetuated against them by patients, their families, or significant others. According to Lim et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib06">2022</link></emphasis>), violence in the workplace can include threats and acts of violence such as harassment, verbal abuse, physical assault, homicide, or bullying. Physical violence incurred in the workplace can include slapping, kicking, gun violence, biting, stabbing, and pushing. Harassment is used as a way to verbally insult, bully, irritate, humiliate, intimidate, and degrade another person, while psychological violence involves the targeted use of power and threat of physical harm to impair the social, spiritual, physical, moral, and mental development of another person or persons. Approximately 73% of nonfatal illnesses and injuries in the workplace occurred due to workplace violence (United States Bureau of Labor Statistics, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib14">2018</link></emphasis>). Over the course of their careers, 8–38% of healthcare workers are likely to experience physical violence (World Health Organization, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0004s0011bib15">2022</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0010" role="Heading"><title>Summary</title><para role="Para">Because of the strong likelihood that working as a nurse interfacing with persons under duress, workplace violence can be encountered, the use of therapeutic nurse-patient communication is imperative. Maintaining space and boundaries, listening intently, avoiding prejudgments, and being respectful to all persons are necessary to the prevention of violence. Nurses must also be aware of protecting themselves in workplace situations that place them at risk for harm such as patients intoxicated with alcohol or under the influence of substances or involved in domestic violence or criminal acts in the community.</para><figure id="ch0004s0010fg01" role="Figure"><title>Delicate Beauty</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="Ch0004f01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></sect1><sect1 id="ch0004s0011" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0004s0011bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib01">Ackley, B. J., Ladwig, G. B., Flynn Makic, M. B., Martinez-Kratz, M., &amp; Zanotti, M. (2022). Nursing diagnosis handbook: An evidenced-based guide to planning care (12th ed.). Elsevier.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib02">Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. (2023). Defining health systems. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ahrq.gov/chsp/defining-health-systems/index.html"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ahrq.gov/chsp/defining-health-systems/index.html</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib03">Andrews, M., Boyle, J. S., &amp; Collins, J. (2020). Transcultural concepts in nursing care (8th ed.). Wolters Kluwer.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib04">Frank, A. W. (2013). From sick role to practices of health and illness. Medical Education, 47(1), 18–25. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2923.2012.04298.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2923.2012.04298.x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2923.2012.04298.x">https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2923.2012.04298.x</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=23278821">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib05">Green, C. (2021). Examining and solving health disparities in the United States: Emerging research and opportunities. ISBN13: 9781799838746.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-7998-3874-6">https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-7998-3874-6</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-7998-3874-6">https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-7998-3874-6</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib06">Lim, M. C., Jeffree, M. S., Saupin, S. S., Giloi, N., &amp; Lukman, K. A. (2022). Workplace violence in healthcare settings: The risk factors, implications and collaborative preventive measures. Annals of Medicine and Surgery, 78. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/annals-of-medicine-and-surgery/fulltext/2022/06000/workplace_violence_in_healthcare_settings__the.29.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/annals-of-medicine-and-surgery/fulltext/2022/06000/workplace_violence_in_healthcare_settings__the.29.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib07">Neuberger, J. (1999). Let’s do away with “patients”. British Medical Journal, 318(7200), 1756–1758. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.318.7200.1756">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.318.7200.1756</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.318.7200.1756">https://doi.org/10.1136/bmj.318.7200.1756</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=10381717">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib08">Newton, V. E., &amp; Shah, S. R. (2013). Improving communication with patients with a hearing impairment. Community Eye Health, 26(81), 6–7. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3678307/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3678307/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=23840079">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3678307">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib09">Parsons, T. (1951). The social system. Tavistock Publications.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib10">Parsons, T. (1975). The sick role and the role of the physician reconsidered. The milbank memorial fund quarterly. Health and Society, 53, 257–278. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.2307/3349493">https://doi.org/10.2307/3349493</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib11">Santana, M. J., Manalili, K., Jolley, R. J., Zelinsky, S., Quan, H., &amp; Lu, M. (2018). How to practice person-centred care: A conceptual framework. Health Expectations, 21(2), 429–440. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12640">https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12640</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12640">https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12640</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=29151269">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib12">Schipke, T. (2021). The chronic sick role: Its time has come. Omega: Journal of Death &amp; Dying, 83(3), 470–486. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222819852848">https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222819852848</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222819852848">https://doi.org/10.1177/0030222819852848</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib13">Taylor, C., Lynn, P., &amp; Barlett, J. L. (2023). Fundamentals of nursing: The art and science of person-centered care (10th ed.). Wolters Kluwer.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib14">U. S. Bureau of Labour Statistics (USBLS). (2018). Workplace violence in healthcare. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.bls.gov/iif/oshwc/cfoi/workplace-violence-healthcare-2018.htm"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.bls.gov/iif/oshwc/cfoi/workplace-violence-healthcare-2018.htm</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0004s0011bib15">World Health Organization (WHO). (2022). Preventing violence against health workers. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.who.int/activities/preventing-violence-against-health-workers"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.who.int/activities/preventing-violence-against-health-workers</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
