<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0003" label="3">
  <title>3. Structured Workplace Chaos</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0014">
    <title>3. Structured Workplace Chaos</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_3">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_3</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0003">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para>
    <para role="keywords">Groupthink, Structured workplace chaos, Sabotage, Incivility, Unaffected bystander vulnerability</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0003s0001">
    <title>3. Structured Workplace Chaos</title>
    <sidebar id="ch0003s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Explain how structured workplace chaos can negatively impact workplace cultures if unaddressed by organizations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Describe how employees can become advocates for change in dysfunctional workplaces.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Decipher ways in which nurses affected by structured workplace chaos can maintain professional and emotional integrity.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0002" role="Heading">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para role="Para">Dysfunction is defined two ways by the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary: as an actual impairment in abnormal functioning and a person or persons unhealthy interaction(s) within a group or interpersonal behavior(s) (Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib06">2024</link></emphasis>). When bullying is ignored within the workplace environment, a healthy environment of collegiality and mutual respect cannot be maintained. Under the hidden guise of smiles at a team meeting lie hidden inappropriate temperaments, fabrication of information, and low-level sarcasm. The response of the closed-off and dysfunctional team dynamic is silence. An occasional question that may challenge the abnormal is met with dismissal by the bully or bullies within the group.</para>
    <para role="Para">Workplace dysfunction is able to permeate workplaces when leadership is afraid or consciously decides not to address their bullying problem. Unfortunately, organizations will be impacted by the bullying via turnover intentions, reduced productivity, and lawsuits. Employees can be proactive in the promotion of change, but many in the protection of their own health and wellness make the healthy decision to leave their dysfunctional workplaces.</para>
    <para role="Para">This dysfunction within workplace teams does not happen overnight but has been sustained for years to decades because anyone who challenges the dysfunction is met with actual roadblocks occurring within multiple levels within the organization. Interestingly enough, some workplaces choose to intentionally maintain dysfunction because it does not have to make progressive changes for its customers or workers. Of concern is that this level of dysfunction in healthcare environments can lead to patients dying and no one taking accountability as families mourn and healthcare workers with a conscious who care about positive and progressive change, leave their jobs. Hence, the cycle continues.</para>
    <para role="Para">Dysfunctional units, divisions, schools, and departments can exist in any workplace environment. Dysfunction is the lived experience of confusion, disruption, corruption, lies, thievery, and selective self-righteousness that seeks to destroy one, a few, or many for the sole purpose of gaining power. Hence, when dysfunction arises in workplaces, the only solution to end the dysfunction is to expose it and those that perpetrate its delusion. Dysfunction will only persist to exist when ignored and accepted as being a reality, and not fallacy.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0003" role="Heading">
    <title>Hypothetical Case Study: “That Is Not True!”</title>
    <para role="Para">Another dysfunctional staff meeting. An agenda focused on upholding fallacy. Sally was the type of person who had a difficult time acknowledging her weaknesses and failures. Errors would never be acknowledged but blamed on other colleagues. Trudy listened to Sally’s words and watched her in disbelief. Sally’s mouth curved and twisted and she stated angrily, “That is not true!” Then, as if well-rehearsed within a theatre class, Sally began to cry in absence of tears.</para>
    <para role="Para">Trudy thought to herself, “I cannot be the only one that sees that Sally’s behavior is unprofessional and that she has once again got away with blaming her poor work performance on others.” Trudy searched the room, curious if her colleagues had just heard and saw what Sally had just verbalized. Her colleagues’ eyes, as they met hers, trailed off looking out windows, staring down at the ground, or pretending to read an empty page of notes. One colleague shook their head in total disbelief and then shrugged her shoulders in silence.</para>
    <para role="Para">When the meeting ended, no one said anything to Trudy; it was as if nothing had occurred. One staff member went to console Sally. It was all so surreal. Only three people appeared in Trudy’s office after the staff meeting to acknowledge the truth of what had occurred. Thirty healthcare professionals had been present at the meeting.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0004" role="Heading">
    <title>Groupthink</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Groupthink</emphasis> occurs when people collaborate to reach a consensus on a specific subject matter(s). When groupthink occurs within workplace settings, individual creativity and ideas are not recognized. Persons find it easier or less stressful to agree with a group of people, rather than debate specific ideology brought forth by individuals that are a part of the group itself (Cha et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib01">2020</link></emphasis>). Groupthink played a part in Trudy’s colleagues not responding to the dysfunction that they had chosen to not address. In this case, the “group” decided that by not addressing the issue, they avoided becoming a part of the problem.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0005" role="Heading">
    <title>Territorialism</title>
    <para role="Para">Green and Dimino Luong (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib03">2023</link></emphasis>), in discussing the concept of territorialism, noted that both formal and informal leaders within organizations that have exhibited bullying behaviors often have historically done so and use their knowledge of the organization to positively and negatively impact others. The fear of loss of perceived power and loss of control drives the employees who embody territorialism to bully others. In order to disrupt the bully who uses territorialism to stand their ground in their familiar department or unit, changing their environment and co-workers can be the start of the end of their reign.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0006" role="Heading">
    <title>Sabotage</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Sabotage</emphasis> is a well-planned conspiracy theory practiced and executed for the sole purpose of physically attacking or emotionally harming another. Nurses can observe workplace dysfunction when communicating with co-workers who bully, patients, other healthcare workers, and patient’s families. However, the direct observation of bullying does not mean that the observance will translate to action to prevent the bullying from occurring. The latter requires nurses to address their own fears of retaliation by the bully or bullies and to confidently go against the normal comfort zone of groupthink.</para>
    <para role="Para">Interestingly, a room filled with nurses who have at one point in their careers cared and advocated for their fellow human beings (patients/clients), and yet in the presence of a bullying mob of colleagues, choose to be powerless in helping one another. The decision to be motionless and silent when witnessing bullying perpetuates dysfunction. The latter empowers bullies and worsens the toxicity in the workplace.</para>
    <para role="Para">An example of sabotage in practice:</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0007" role="Heading">
    <title>The Depleted Nurse</title>
    <para role="Para">Baffled by their own inability to speak up at times when confronted with workplace bullying, nurses, in the course of their education to become nurses, become embattled and fatigued. Nurses must learn to become “highly skilled health care workers” in a matter of a few years. Be it a 1-, 2-, 3- or 4-year program of academic study and clinical practice exposure, the ever-growing content of healthcare seems endless, and prelicensure nurses are overwhelmed. Nurses therefore enter the nursing profession emotionally depleted. Depleted of energy and at times fearful of the next challenge, it can seem easier for nurses to ignore dysfunction within their work environments than to speak up and help make positive changes.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0008" role="Heading">
    <title>Can’t Do It</title>
    <para role="Para">When working in a workplace that does not permit individual thriving and professional growth, change can feel unachievable. Employees become frustrated because of perceived challenges related to the resistance of change within workplaces they are employed. The status quo is quickly adopted within these work environments, and purposeful dysfunction develops. New ideology is dismissed, in favor of maintaining the status quo. In absence of productive and innovative change within work cultures, the emergence of toxic workplace environments can begin.</para>
    <para role="Para">When highly motivated persons enter the workplace environment that has adapted to the status quo, they may attempt to introduce innovation and promote change. It is often these highly motivated individuals that are targeted by bullies who are fearful of change and intimidated by the persons that they perceive have become a disruption. Toxicity ensues as the employees who bully attempt to exert their perceived power in the workplace with the goal of discrediting another person.</para>
    <para role="Para">For the person experiencing The Hollow, they tend to represent the highly motivated employee that is desirous of change and innovation. The latter is counterintuitive to the toxic work environment where there is often a power imbalance. As a result, the bully or bullies will utilize coercion skills like that of groupthink to dismantle any perceived power the employee desiring change has.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0009" role="Heading">
    <title>Structural Chaos in the Workplace</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Structural chaos</emphasis> in the workplace is the planned constructed attempt to discredit and or minimize another’s accomplishments. Structured chaos is created by the bully via lying, gossiping, and devaluing of another’s creative works and or intellectual property. In addressing structural chaos, it is imperative that employees and leadership listen to affected persons to develop a clear timeline of when the structured chaos plan began and the attempt to discredit the affected person emerged. By identifying the timeline, key players of the bullying can be identified.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0010" role="Heading">
    <title>Structural Empowerment</title>
    <para role="Para">Employees in the workplace can be empowered to voice their concerns or desire for proactive environmental and structural change through structured empowerment. <emphasis role="bold">Structural empowerment</emphasis> is a theory that explores both informal and formal allegiances between subordinates and superiors and networks of peer groups as means to influence positive changes in work culture and the organization. Employees that have formal power within an organization have roles that are aligned with organizational vision and mission statements that are flexible. Informal power roles are held by employees that maintain interpersonal relationships with employees at all levels within the organization, while themselves not holding a formal leadership position of formal power. Kanter (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib04">1977</link></emphasis>) noted that employees that are committed to the success of the organization seek for opportunities to grow professionally and have job satisfaction and will thrive in workplaces that support structural empowerment (Laschinger et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib05">2001</link></emphasis>).</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0011" role="Heading">
    <title>Incivility</title>
    <para role="Para">Uncivil conduct in the academic and workplace environments occurs when employees experience the negative behaviors of a bully or group of bullies. The bully or group of bullies may be a co-worker, supervisor, administrator, or an employee at any level within the hierarchy of the organization. The uncivil conduct manifests itself as incivility. <emphasis role="bold">Incivility</emphasis> is demonstrated by discourteousness, rude behaviors directed at others for the primary purpose of humiliation and disruption of a person or persons’ lives. According to Einarsen et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0003s0013bib02">2009</link></emphasis>) person-related incivility, physical intimidation, and work-related incivility are the three most common types of incivility. The complexity of incivility in its manifestation of lying, gossiping, belittlement, gaslighting, intimidation, and many other negative manipulative behaviors is that unaddressed, an unhealthy environment is left to proliferate. Hence, bullying worsens, and affected and unaffected bystanders who witness the incivility feel unsupported and vulnerable.</para>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Unaffected bystander vulnerability</emphasis> in witnessed incivility is the result of persons who witness co-worker(s) (or fellow student(s)) being bullied and consciously decide not to intervene for fear of becoming a victim of the bully or bullies themselves. The unaffected bystander’s fear leads them to deny the existence of the occurrence(s) of incivility though witnessed by them. As a result, unaffected bystanders reject or avoid the person or persons being bullied. The unaffected bystander may also deny the existence of bullying behaviors actually occurring to managers, administrators, and Human Resource Department representatives. The sole purpose of the behavior of the unaffected bystander is self-protection. The unaffected bystander is afraid of becoming a victim themselves, of the bully or bullies.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0012" role="Heading">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para role="Para">There are several factors impacting employees and their co-worker relationships within the workplace. Healthy workplaces welcome new ideas and the employees who share them. The maintaining of the status quo is not as important as innovation and change, because the organizational goal is productivity. Toxic workplaces can impair productivity because groupthink or individual control is prioritized over individual thought and willpower. In the support of healthy workplaces and employees, structured workplace chaos must be disarmed and ended. Failure to do so will result in employee burnout and increased turnover intentions.</para>
    <sidebar id="ch0003s0012ad02">
      <title>Examples of Structured Workplace Chaos</title>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each of the two structured workplace chaos case studies and discuss what in the case studies points to negative behaviors that have been permitted to flourish within the work environment.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Case Study 1 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Mitchell never says hello when he enters the office. His office colleagues have to await to determine how his mood is and if it’s “safe” to share a greeting. It is clearly understood by everyone that it is wise to use caution before initiating a conversation. Awaiting for Mitchell to talk is always the “best” move.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Case Study 2 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Margaret never meets deadlines, so none of the teams at work want to work with her. Margaret is known to “never carry her load.” Kevin, Margaret’s boss, is aware of Margaret’s poor work performance but does nothing to address her less than desirable work habits. Lately, Margaret’s co-workers have been discussing their lack of motivation to “work well and with purpose” given that low performance is acceptable in their workplace.</para>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0003s0012ad03">
      <title>Activity: Identification of Bully Roles and Hidden Agendas in the Workplace Environment</title>
      <bridgehead>Workplace Scenarios</bridgehead>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each scenario and determine what is the strategic role of the bully and the bully’s hidden agenda within the workplace. Determine the role of witnesses to the acts of bullying when applicable to the scenario, as well. Circle the answer. Discuss with peers why you selected your answer before discussing the correct answer.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 1 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Adam was quiet as he sat in the staff lounge eating his lunch overhearing Michael and Benjamin barrage Franklin. Franklin had recently received an award for his excellence in the delivery of patient care and recognition of subtle signs and symptoms of patients’ condition deterioration and his active participation in rapid responses that led to the saving of the lives of at least six patients in the past 8 months. Franklin, a medical-surgical nurse, had aspirations to become a nurse anesthetist, and his next career move within the coming year was to transfer to a critical care unit.</para>
      <para role="Para">The barrage that Adam witnessed his colleague Franklin receive was nearly unbearable to watch. Michael and Benjamin cursed at him, called him a “suck up,” a “failure as a nurse,” “disliked by most co-workers,” and proceeded to pour their cups of coffee over his sandwich and salad that he was having for lunch. Adam stood up from a chair he was sitting in finishing up his own lunch, made minimal eye contact with Franklin, and, in silence, walked away. On the clinical unit, when Franklin returned to resume the care of his patients, he was visibly shaken and had a difficult time concentrating. While Adam felt bad about what he had witnessed happen to Franklin, he in no way wanted to be involved. So, Adam decided not to discuss the incident with Franklin or anyone else.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 1 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Discussion: Let’s talk about this…</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>The strategic role of the bullies and their hidden agenda in Scenario 1 was to demean the achievements of another person through sharing falsehoods and discredit the person’s accomplishments.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Adam’s response was no response. Adam intentionally made the decision to not get involved and, instead, watched Franklin be bullied. Adam acted in fear. His fear was of becoming a victim himself of bullying, if he involved himself in the situation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Michael and Benjamin likely have been bullying others for quite some time. Their responses exhibit confidence and clarity in their expression of dislike for their target—Franklin.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Franklin feels exposed as he notices Adam is present in the staff lounge. Franklin’s response is the internalization of words and actions that are emotionally hurtful and targeted toward him by Michael and Benjamin. The exposure of being bullied can be crippling as the affected person can feel helpless and hopeless in their situation. Bodily, they are fatigued and lack energy in other areas of their lives because being bullied is emotionally draining.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 1 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Questions:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Should Adam have attempted to engage Franklin in a conversation to remove him from the bullying situation?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Did Adam make the right decision to not talk to Michael or Benjamin about their negative interaction with Franklin?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Is it difficult to observe another person be treated unfairly by someone else?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>If you were Adam, what would be your next steps after returning to the clinical unit to resume your work?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 2 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Jessica had changed jobs to spend more time with her family and at home resting. The last 5 months had been difficult because she had to take a leave of absence to take care of her husband who was dying of lung cancer. Jessica felt depressed and isolated. She had been married to her husband for 25 years and was now left to raise their 10-year-old son alone.</para>
      <para role="Para">Jessica was well-known in her company as a “fixer.” Fixers are synonymous with repairing dysfunctional workplace environments once recognized by administration as being problematic. Examples of dysfunctional workplace environments that a “fixer” would be requested to implement change within include those work environments having decreased productivity, high turnover intentions, and poor patient health outcomes. Jessica’s reputation as a “fixer” had led to her quickly rising to the level of Executive Director within 3 years of working within the company after entering the health system in the role of clinical nurse specialist.</para>
      <para role="Para">Jessica was kind and considerate to her co-workers and a strong advocate for patients entering the health system to receive care. When Jessica returned to work, she took the position of a part-time 24-h staff nurse on a stroke rehabilitation unit. Jessica took the part-time nursing position to ensure that she was available to be home with her son in the evening to support him with homework and maintain a regular schedule of family time together. Jessica enjoyed working as a bedside nurse leader and was excited to be involved in the day-to-day care of patients and educating patients and their families about various medications, conditions, and disease processes.</para>
      <para role="Para">Melinda was a night shift nurse who recently changed her alternating work weekends and weekly schedule to accommodate her return to graduate school. Melinda instantly recognized Jessica as being the Executive Director who had thwarted her plans to return to graduate school 2 years ago. Melinda approached Jessica angrily and said, “Oh, it’s you. Whose life are you trying to mess up now?” Jessica, who encountered many nurses in her role as a nurse leader, did not recognize Melinda at all. Jessica, looking at Melinda with a smirk on her face, stated, “Am I supposed to know you?”</para>
      <para role="Para">Melinda shared with peers her interaction with Jessica and her previous role within the organization. Melinda and her co-workers, some who also had negative experiences with Jessica in her nurse leader role, began to sabotage her work, spread rumors, and would not assist her when she required help in the provision of care to her patients. Jessica, realizing that she had become a target of bullying in the workplace, met with her manager to complain and report Melinda as the primary perpetrator.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 2 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Discussion: Let’s talk about this…</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Jessica’s transition to a direct care position provided additional family time with her 10-year-old son. The career transition occurred around Jessica becoming a widow. Life transitions can be both positive and negative. Because this was the loss of a spouse that then led to a career change and self-demotion, it is likely that Jessica may be experiencing multiple losses.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Sometimes after significant losses, the affected person(s) may desire to be “unseen.” To be “unseen” is to be unrecognizable and to “fly below the radar.” Jessica’s decision to return to bedside nursing provided a way to leave behind the demands of an Executive Director position and focus on physical and emotional healing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Melinda’s recognition of Jessica as the person who had disrupted her academic studies while she was actively pursuing a graduate degree likely brought about feelings of frustration, anger, and betrayal.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Melinda, seeing that her former boss was now a co-worker, decidedly took action to bully Jessica to seek revenge.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 2 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Questions</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Why did Jessica make the decision to demote herself at work?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What was Melinda’s history with Jessica?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Did Jessica’s response to Melinda warrant the bullying?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Could the entire situation have been avoided?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What can the manager of the unit do to remedy this situation?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Can bullying be passed on as a behavior that is reciprocal when more than one party is injured?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>In the case of Jessica and Melinda, are both persons equally at fault of unprofessional conduct within the workplace?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Should Melinda be disciplined?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Should Jessica be held accountable for her past actions, all be it in a different role, within the organization?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Should organizational standards of conduct be reinforced by the unit manager?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 3 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Michael was both a scoundrel and a gentleman. He knew when to schmooze and when to lay low. None of the team trusted him. Michael was known to lie and align with anyone who could possibly bring him accolades with minimal effort on his part. Hence, Michael had a keen eye for talent that made him shine brightly in the eyes of administration.</para>
      <para role="Para">When Florence joined Michael’s team of clinical outcome leaders, she had already been a well-established administrator for 25 years and a statistician for 15 years. Florence simply wanted to retire in 4 years without the burden of “work being taken home.” Michael met with Florence and gave her one project to initiate unto completion. The project examined the surgical outcomes of cardiac transplant patients regarding complications of surgical site infections within 30 days of the procedure.</para>
      <para role="Para">Florence was excited to begin the project. The project lasted 10 weeks, and an additional 4 weeks were taken to tabulate and examine the statistical evidence. Florence presented the project results to Michael and other key stakeholders within the organization. Michael then asked Florence to begin writing the manuscript describing the project’s purpose, process, and outcome for submission to journals. When the manuscript was completed, Florence submitted the manuscript to Michael for review.</para>
      <para role="Para">After having the manuscript for 6 weeks, Florence asked to return it to her so she can begin submitting the manuscript. Michael shared that he had submitted the manuscript to a journal 5-weeks ago and would be likely hearing from the journal in another 5 weeks, on the status of the manuscript. Florence was disappointed and hurt. However, Florence also felt that as a team member, Michael’s submission of the project ultimately was for the benefit of the organization and all those who participated in the project: patients, physicians, patient care associates (e.g., nurse assistants), nursing staff, and surgical technicians.</para>
      <para role="Para">Fast forward 4 weeks later, the manuscript was accepted by a cardiology journal. When published 3 months later, the publication’s sole author was Michael. Florence, the Principal Investigator and her many Co-investigators of physicians, nurses, patient care associates (e.g., nurse assistants), and surgical technicians were not given credit for their work. Their names were excluded from the manuscript. Florence had the difficult task of explaining to her research team, how their hard work was not given credit as promised.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 3 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Discussion: Let’s talk about this…</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Michael’s history of dishonesty was seemingly ignored by Florence. Perhaps she desired to give him a chance to prove himself different despite of what was rumored and discussed about him by his colleagues within the organization.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Florence and her fellow research team members’ talents were exploited.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Taking credit for another’s work benefits no one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Scenario 3 </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Questions</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Why was Florence assigned the research project by Michael?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Should Michael apologize to Florence and the research team?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Did Michael plagiarize by not giving credit to other’s work? If yes, could disciplinary action be taken against him?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>What was the sole purpose of Michael’s actions?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0003s0012ad04">
      <title>Activities Acknowledging Workplace Ingenuity</title>
      <bridgehead>Recognizing Healthy and Not So Healthy Workplace Communication Responses</bridgehead>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read the following ten examples of workplace communications, and determine which are healthy communications and unhealthy communications.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“I thought what you said was not very clear. You just seemed very uncomfortable.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Your oral skills need some work. You do a lot of repeating of the same information when you are nervous.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“The flow of your paper requires some revising. Have you considered hiring an Editor?”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“The ideas you come up with are really off the mark. I think we should meet to get you back on the right track.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Let’s have a vote. Who thought Sarah’s speech was good?”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“What you just said makes no sense?”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“We will be taking over the project anyway.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“An excellent idea. Let’s get together to develop it further as a team.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Wow, it is evident that you have been working really hard on this project Bob.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“You have been eating up a lot of company time Judy. Why is this job seemingly so hard for you?”</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0003s0012ad05">
      <title>Answers</title>
      <bridgehead>Recognizing Healthy and Not So Healthy Workplace Communication Responses</bridgehead>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read the following ten examples of workplace communications, and determine which are healthy communications and unhealthy communications.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“I thought what you said was not very clear. You just seemed very uncomfortable.” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Your oral skills need some work. You do a lot of repeating of the same information when you are nervous.” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“The flow of your paper requires some revising. Have you considered hiring an Editor?” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“The ideas you come up with are really off the mark. I think we should meet to get you back on the right track.” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Let’s have a vote. Who thought Sarah’s speech was good?” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“What you just said makes no sense?” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“We will be taking over the project anyway.” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“An excellent idea. Let’s get together to develop it further as a team.” <emphasis role="bold">healthy communications</emphasis> or unhealthy communications</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“Wow, it is evident that you have been working really hard on this project Bob.” <emphasis role="bold">healthy communications</emphasis> or unhealthy communications</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>“You have been eating up a lot of company time Judy. Why is this job seemingly so hard for you?” healthy communications or <emphasis role="bold">unhealthy communications.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
    <figure id="ch0003s0012fg01">
      <title>Activity</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="Ch0003f01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0003s0013" role="bibliography">
    <title>References</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0003s0013bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib01">Cha, N., Hwang, J., &amp; Kim, E. (2020). The optimal knowledge creation strategy of organizations in groupthink situations. Computational &amp; Mathematical Organization Theory, 26(2), 207–235. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1007/s10588-020-09313-w"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.1007/s10588-020-09313-w</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10588-020-09313-w">https://doi.org/10.1007/s10588-020-09313-w</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib02">Einarsen, S., Hoel, H., &amp; Notelaers, G. (2009). Measuring exposure to bullying and harassment at work: Validity, factor structure and psychometric properties of the negative acts questionnaire—Revised. Work &amp; Stress: An International Journal of Work, Health &amp; Organisations, 23(1), 24–44. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/02678370902815673">https://doi.org/10.1080/02678370902815673</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1080/02678370902815673">https://doi.org/10.1080/02678370902815673</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib03">Green, C., &amp; Dimino Luong, A. (2023). Bullied: Exploring the concepts of territorialism and groupthink involvement in workplace bullying. Nursing Open, 10(10), 6777–6781. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.1938">https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.1938</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.1938">https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.1938</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=37483110">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10495714">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib04">Kanter, R. (1977). Men and women of the corporation. Basic Books.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib05">Laschinger, H. K. S., Finegan, J. M., Shamian, J., &amp; Wilk, P. (2001). Impact of structural and psychological empowerment on job strain in nursing work settings: Expanding Kanter’s model. Journal of Nursing Administration, 31(5), 260–272. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/00005110-200105000-00006">https://doi.org/10.1097/00005110-200105000-00006</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/00005110-200105000-00006">https://doi.org/10.1097/00005110-200105000-00006</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=11388162">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0003s0013bib06">Merriam Webster Online Dictionary. (2024). Dysfunction. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/dysfunction"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/dysfunction</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
