<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0007" label="7"><title>7. The Depths of Forgetfulness</title><sect1 id="ch0007s0009"><title>7. The Depths of Forgetfulness</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_7">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_7</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0007">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Forgetfulness, Forgiveness, Emotional injury, Quiet quitting</para></sect1><sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0007s0001"><title>7. The Depths of Forgetfulness</title><sidebar id="ch0007s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3"><title>Learning Objectives</title><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Explain how forgetting when wronged by someone can be difficult.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss the necessity of forgiveness in moving beyond experiences of workplace bullying and incivility.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Discuss how continual exposure to work environments that permit the emergence of symptomatology surrounding The Hollow can impact affected nurses psychologically and physically.</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0002" role="Heading"><title>Forgetfulness</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Forgetfulness</emphasis> is the state of being unable to recall an event. Forgetfulness warrants that something that was to be remembered is not easily recalled. However, the pain and recall of a traumatic event provide an opportunity for those who were hurt to remember, reflect, and heal.</para><para role="Para">The Merriam -Webster Dictionary defines the word <emphasis role="bold">forgetfulness</emphasis> as inducing oblivion (forgetful sleep), being likely to be forgetful, and the characterization of being neglectful related to a failure to remember (Merriam-Webster Dictionary, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib17">2024</link></emphasis>). The complexity of the word forgetfulness materializes in the discussion of The Hollow Theory because when someone experiences physical harm or emotional abuse, it is the mental replay (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib10">2019</link></emphasis>) of the actual incident of bullying and incivility that paralyzes them. The repetition of the traumatizing memory can become incapacitating affecting sleep, appetite, the ability to concentrate, and trust and engagement with others.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0003" role="Heading"><title>Forgiveness</title><para role="Para">Forgiveness is the only means by which the mental replay of the traumatizing event can be redefined in the mind of persons affected by The Hollow. While the ability for a human being to forget traumatic events may not always occur, the pain generated from emotionally laden experiences can cause persons with The Hollow, to feel empty, unloved, not cared for, and isolated. These false narratives unaddressed by counseling and support both inside and outside the work environment, can lead to disturbances in mental health.</para><para role="Para">The American Psychological Association (APA) defines <emphasis role="bold">forgiveness</emphasis> as the decision to willfully put aside resentment toward someone who has been hurtful, harmed you, been unfair, or wronged you (APA, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib03">2024</link></emphasis>). The act of forgiveness is transformative. In order to fully forgive another person that has harmed you, resentment is no longer the focus nor is anger. The person who forgives exhibits generosity and compassion toward the person who harmed them (APA, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib03">2024</link></emphasis>). While not easily obtained, forgiveness releases the wronged person from the restrictive bondage of anger and hatred toward the person that harmed them and allows them to move forward in their lives toward happiness and positive productivity.</para><para role="Para">From a scriptural perspective, the forgiveness of others is healing. Below are some scriptural references about forgiving others (Holy Bible, New International Version, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib12">1984</link></emphasis>).</para><itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone"><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">2 Corinthians 2: 7–8.</emphasis> Now, instead, you ought to forgive and comfort him, so that he will not be overwhelmed by excessive sorrow. I urge you, therefore, to reaffirm your love for him.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Matthew 6:12.</emphasis> Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Ephesians 4:31–32.</emphasis> Get rid of all bitterness, rage and anger, brawling and slander, along with every form of malice. Be kind and compassionate to one another, forgiving each other, just as in Christ God forgive you.</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Luke 17: 3–4</emphasis> If your brother sins, rebuke him, and if he repents, forgive him. If he sins against you seven times in a day, and seven times comes back to you and says, “I repent, forgive him.”</para></listitem><listitem><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Matthew 6:14–15.</emphasis> If you forgive men when they sin against you, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. But if you do not forgive men their sins, your Father will not forgive your sins.</para></listitem></itemizedlist><para role="Para">Being bullied is difficult. The affected person feels that they have literally loss control of their own lives and the outcome of their future selves. However, the latter is a lie of which the bully or bullies wish to bestow or feed to the mind of the person(s) they are bulling to gain control. Power is a perception only, and not all perceptions are based on reality. For the person experiencing The Hollow, forgiveness can be their greatest asset in terms of self-protection against incivility and bullying. Rationally, the conscious decision to forgive persons who have wronged you releases you from their perceived power to enter a new journey and adventure in your life whereby the wrong behaviors that were used against you are subdued and rendered useless. You are free!</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0004" role="Heading"><title>The Danger of Workplace Bullying</title><para role="Para">Workplace bullying is dangerous to affected persons because the emotionally injured person is not within a silo. The bullied person leaves work and returns to a family, friendships, church, marriages, intimate relationships, other jobs, and activities of daily living (e.g., going to the bank or grocery shopping). Hence, the bullied person reciprocally interacts with society and the organization in which the bullying is occurring (Tuckey &amp; Neall, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib20">2014</link></emphasis>). <emphasis role="bold">Emotional injury</emphasis> occurs when someone has been repeatedly attacked verbally and either withdraws or projects their suppressed feelings on others in their immediate environments and within random encounters. Emotionally injured persons may verbally abuse others or could potentially physically harm another, as suppressed anger, hostility, and a perceived need to protect oneself from bullying, envelopes the affected person.</para><para role="Para">For nurses working within healthcare organizations, the immediate environment constitutes the healthcare environment and the patients to whom they are providing nursing care. Because the patient is the primary focus of nurses in their work within healthcare organizations, it is the patient(s) that can become the unintended target of the bullied nurses’ emotional injury. Therefore, verbal abuse, being ignored, speaking abruptly and walking away, and making medication or treatment errors may occur to patients being cared for by bullied nurses.</para><para role="Para">According to Johnson and Benham-Hutchins (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib13">2020</link></emphasis>), nursing errors are more likely to occur within the context of bullying. Arnetz et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib05">2020</link></emphasis>) found that nurse work environments that were associated with poor nurse health and bullying could result in adverse patient events (e.g., central-line associated bloodstream infections). Therefore, workplaces that permit or choose to ignore occurrences and reports of bullying may have more errors impacting patients. It is important to note that nursing teams where bullying is allowed will likely have impaired communication barriers amongst team members because the team consists of nurses who bully and nurses who are recipients of their uncivil conduct.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0005" role="Heading"><title>Quiet Quitting</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Quiet Quitting</emphasis> occurs when an employee who is dissatisfied with their employer begins to gradually reduce their work productivity and overall performance, rather than submitting a resignation letter. During the coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19) pandemic, employees took to social media platforms such as TikTok to share how they were quietly quitting their jobs (Harter, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link></emphasis>; Lord, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib15">2022</link></emphasis>; Scheyett, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib19">2022</link></emphasis>). Debatably, quiet quitting is believed not to be a new phenomenon, but one that has been practiced in industry for several years (Lord, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib15">2022</link></emphasis>). Harter (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link></emphasis>), upon review of US Gallup noted that it is estimated that at least 50% of workers make up “quiet quitters.” Engaged workers make up (Harter, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib11">2023</link></emphasis>) 32% with 18% of employees actively disengaging. In healthcare settings, studies on quiet quitting have found that over 50% of healthcare employees engage in quiet quitting (Galanis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib06">2023</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib07">2024a</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">Nurses who experience The Hollow have experienced bullying. Bullying is a type of workplace violence. Nurses subjected to bullying, unless provided support at the unit level from peers and managers, will likely leave their jobs. Experiencing post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), physical health problems, stress, anxiety, decrease in work productivity and work quality, depression, burnout, low self-esteem, and job dissatisfaction, nurses’ turnover intentions increase (Al Muharraq et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib02">2022</link></emphasis>; Galanis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib08">2024b</link></emphasis>; Goh et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib09">2022</link></emphasis>; Karatuna et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib14">2020</link></emphasis>). Younger and older nurses are impacted by bullying. However, it is often the newer nurse that receives the unhealthy initiation of bullying and dysfunctional behaviors associated with bullying (Anusiewicz et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib04">2019</link></emphasis>; Karatuna et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib14">2020</link></emphasis>) from the experienced nurse(s).</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0006" role="Heading"><title>Wronged</title><para role="Para">There is a sense, a feeling of having been wronged when bullying occurs in the workplace. The intent of the bully or bullies is to set the other person(s) up to be harmed in some way. Bullies may use attacks of character, lying, and sabotaging of one’s work, all underhanded attempts at casting the affected person in a shadow of being questionably a troublemaker. When a person experiences The Hollow at work and at home in their personal life, the duality of the stress and simultaneous abuse warrants immediate therapeutic intervention. Bitterness, anger, frustration, and distrust (Lutzer, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib16">2007</link></emphasis>) can envelope the affected person and will eventually impede their personal and professional lives. In this case, professional counseling should be sought in order for distinct patterns of behavioral reactions to bullies and the action of bullying to be addressed successfully. Sometimes insight into why one allows certain personality types and behavioral patterns to persist in their lives can bring resolution to the bullying problem as the affected person recognizes unhealthy people in their lives and begins to set boundaries regarding what they will and will not tolerate.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0007" role="Heading"><title>Summary: Unearthing Forgetfulness</title><para role="Para">In order for healthcare organizations to end bullying and retain nurses, training must be initiated at the staff level all the way up to managerial, administrative, and senior level leadership on the dangers of ignoring bullying. Current research (and articles) on workplace bullying has shown that patients’ health outcomes are impacted and affected nurses’ mental and physical health, and nurse suicide (Ahc Media, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib01">2020</link></emphasis>; Mental Health Practice, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0007s0008bib18">2018</link></emphasis>) can occur as a result of prolonged exposure to toxic workplaces. While organizations would like to forget that bullying has occurred because acknowledgment of bullying behaviors is viewed as bad publicity, the bullied nurse suffers alone in isolation and their patients are unintentionally harmed.</para><sidebar id="ch0007s0007ad02"><title>Putting Forgiveness into Practice</title><bridgehead>A Personal Activity</bridgehead><bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Forgiveness is a process. Sometimes in relationships, only one party forgives the other. And, sometimes, forgiveness can occur between two or more persons, resulting in peace and complete resolution of the problem. In the latter case, persons can walk away without bitterness. It is important to remember that forgiveness is an individual process that allows those impacted by negative situations, to positively move forward in absence of the burden of unforgiveness. In this activity, select and discuss a personal action that involves forgiveness. Consider how your personal reaction may impact the situation.</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #1 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A co-worker constantly interrupts you during meetings when you are contributing to a group discussion. Does this warrant a one-to-one conversation, or should the co-worker’s behavior be dismissed and forgiven?</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #2 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">A manager steals your ideas and presents them as their own during a corporate presentation. Taken aback, you feel hurt and betrayed and decide to leave the meeting early. As you return to your office, your manager requests you to return to the meeting immediately because they would like one of your ideas “explained in more detail to the team.” You pause and decide to return to the meeting. The manager acknowledges your presence and kindly asks you to share your ideas.</para><para role="Para">Did this manager betray you? Are the manager’s actions forgivable?</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #3 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">You are at a corporate compliance training event with colleagues. The lead trainer provides the opportunity for participants to take a 50-min break to eat their lunch. During lunch, two co-workers from another department sit at the table that you have already begun to eat lunch at with two other colleagues. As a friendly conversation ensues, one of the colleagues from a different department states directly to you, “You are really nice. You are nothing like we heard you were.” Unsure as to what this meant, you continue to eat your lunch quietly. Should you address this comment after the training event? Ignore the comment? Or inquire, why the comment was asked and who shared that you were difficult to communicate with?</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #4 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Loneliness is isolating, makes a person feel depressed, and have a yearning to belong. As a young biracial executive who practices Judaism, I have openly experienced discrimination within the workplace. My director is aware and has said very little to my co-workers, or supported me. It has been 1 year since my employment in my current position. I am not quite certain how to address my co-workers’ and director’s intentional disregard for discrimination in the workplace. Should I report what is happening to Human Resources or the Vice President of the division? Or, both?</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #5 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">The bullying has impacted my life negatively, more than I care to admit. Most days I do not want to go to work. I feel alone, sad, detached, and cry most of the work day intermittently. I am not certain what my next steps should be because I have been working in this environment for 8 years, and it appears to only be getting worse. My personality has changed. I am not as confident as I use to be and I know it. I need to make a change, but I am not certain of what my next steps should be and where I should go after so many years working at the same company. What should I do? How should I proceed?</para><bridgehead role="Heading"> Personal Activity #6 </bridgehead><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Lately, I have been just thinking about ending my life. I have gone to Human Resources and spoken numerous times with my manager and director, and nothing has improved in my work situation. The bullying has worsened. Sometimes I wake up and dread going to work. I argue with family members over very simple things and isolate myself when I am at work. I am starting to have thoughts of just ending it all. I am just not happy with my life. What should I do? Should I talk to someone? What should be my next steps?</para></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0007s0008" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0007s0008bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib01">Ahc Media. (2020). Research on nurses’ suicide risk reveals ethical concerns. Medical Ethics Advisor, 36(2), N. PAG.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib02">Al Muharraq, E. H., Baker, O. G., &amp; Alallah, S. M. (2022). The prevalence and the relationship of workplace bullying and nurses’ turnover intentions: A cross sectional study. SAGE Open Nursing, 24(8), 23779608221074655. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608221074655">https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608221074655</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608221074655">https://doi.org/10.1177/23779608221074655</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib03">American Psychological Association (APA). (2024). Forgiveness. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.apa.org/topics/forgiveness"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.apa.org/topics/forgiveness</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib04">Anusiewicz, C. V., Shirey, M. R., &amp; Patrician, P. A. (2019). Workplace bullying and newly licensed registered nurses: An evolutionary concept analysis. Workplace Health &amp; Safety, 67(5), 250–261. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/2165079919827046">https://doi.org/10.1177/2165079919827046</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/2165079919827046">https://doi.org/10.1177/2165079919827046</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib05">Arnetz, J. E., Neufcourt, L., Sudan, S., Arnetz, B. B., Maiti, T., &amp; Viens, F. (2020). Nurse-reported bullying and documented adverse patient events: An exploratory study in a US hospital. Journal of Nursing Care Quality, 35(3), 206–212. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/ncq.0000000000000442">https://doi.org/10.1097/ncq.0000000000000442</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/ncq.0000000000000442">https://doi.org/10.1097/ncq.0000000000000442</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32433142">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib06">Galanis, P., Katsiroumpa, A., Vraka, I., Siskou, O., Konstantakopoulou, O., Katsoulas, T., Moisoglou, I., Gallos, P., &amp; Kaitelidou, D. (2023). The influence of job burnout on quiet quitting among nurses: The mediating effect of job satisfaction. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/372094983_The_influence_of_job_burnout_on_quiet_quitting_among_nurses_the_mediating_effect_of_job_satisfaction"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/372094983_The_influence_of_job_burnout_on_quiet_quitting_among_nurses_the_mediating_effect_of_job_satisfaction</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib07">Galanis, P., Moisoglou, I., Malliarou, M., Papathanasiou, I. V., Katsiroumpa, A., Vraka, I., Siskou, O., Konstantakopoulou, O., &amp; Kaitelidou, D. (2024a). Quiet quitting among nurses increases their turnover intention: Evidence from Greece in the post-COVID-19 era. Healthcare, 12(1), 79. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12010079">https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12010079</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12010079">https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12010079</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib08">Galanis, P., Moisoglou, I., Katsiroumpa, A., &amp; Mastrogianni, M. (2024b). Association between workplace bullying, job stress, and professional quality of life in nurses: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Healthcare (Basel), 12(6), 623. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12060623">https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12060623</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12060623">https://doi.org/10.3390/healthcare12060623</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=38540587">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib09">Goh, H. S., Hosier, S., &amp; Zhang, H. (2022). Prevalence, antecedents, and consequences of workplace bullying among nurses – A summary of reviews. International Journal of Environmental Research &amp; Public Health, 19(14), 8256. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19148256">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19148256</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19148256">https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph19148256</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib10">Green, C. (2019). Incivility among nursing professionals in clinical and academic environments: Emerging research and opportunities. IGI Global.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8">https://doi.org/10.4018/978-1-5225-7341-8</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib11">Harter, J. (2023). Is quiet quitting real? Workplace. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.gallup.com/workplace/398306/quiet-quitting-real.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.gallup.com/workplace/398306/quiet-quitting-real.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib12">International Bible Society. (1984). Holy bible (New International Version). Zondervan Publishing House.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib13">Johnson, A. H., &amp; Benham-Hutchins, M. (2020). The influence of bullying on nursing practice errors: A systematic review. Association of Perioperative Registered Nurses Journal, 111(2), 199–210. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/aorn.12923">https://doi.org/10.1002/aorn.12923</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/aorn.12923">https://doi.org/10.1002/aorn.12923</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib14">Karatuna, I., Jönsson, S., &amp; Muhonen, T. (2020). Workplace bullying in the nursing profession: A cross-cultural scoping review. International Journal of Nursing Studies, 111, 103628. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103628">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103628</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103628">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2020.103628</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32932063">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib15">Lord, J. (2022). Quiet quitting is a new name for an old method of industrial action. The Conversation. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/363415148_Quiet_quitting_is_a_new_name_for_an_old_method_of_industrial_action"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/363415148_Quiet_quitting_is_a_new_name_for_an_old_method_of_industrial_action</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib16">Lutzer, E. W. (2007). When you’ve been wronged: Moving from bitterness to forgiveness. Moody Publishers.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib17">Merriam-Webster Dictionary. (2024). Forgetful.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/forgetfulness"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/forgetfulness</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib18">Nurse took her own life after being “bullied” at work. (2018). Mental Health Practice, 21(9), 6. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.7748/mhp.21.9.6.s3"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://doi-org.acu.idm.oclc.org/10.7748/mhp.21.9.6.s 3</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib19">Scheyett, A. (2022). Quiet quitting. Social Work, 68, 5–7. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/sw/swac051">https://doi.org/10.1093/sw/swac051</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1093/sw/swac051">https://doi.org/10.1093/sw/swac051</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=36409998">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0007s0008bib20">Tuckey, M. R., &amp; Neall, A. M. (2014). Workplace bullying erodes job and personal resources: Between- and within-person perspectives. Journal of Occupational Health Psychology, 19(4), 413–424. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037728">https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037728</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037728">https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037728</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=25151461">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
