<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0001" label="1"><title>1. Dysfunction Within a Profession of Caritas</title><sect1 id="ch0001s0006"><title>1. Dysfunction Within a Profession of Caritas</title><para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para><para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para><para role="ContextInformationBookTitles"><emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis></para><para role="ChapterDOI"><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_1">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_1</ulink></para><para role="AuthorGroup"><emphasis role="Author"><emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis><superscript><link linkend="ch0001">1</link></superscript></emphasis></para><para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para><para role="keywords">Caritas, Nurses, Dysfunction, Nurse suicides</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0001" role="Heading"><title>Introduction</title><para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Caritas</emphasis> subjectively, is the individual’s personal drive to provide and exhibit care to others. The care exhibited by the individual can be emotional, physical, and spiritual in nature. The Theory of Human Caring was developed by Jean Watson (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib14">2008</link></emphasis>). The Theory of Human Caring is a framework for the delivery of nursing care to patients that focuses upon the nurse-patient therapeutic relationship (Watson, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib15">2009</link></emphasis>). The nurse in the role of a caring and compassionate healthcare professional uses this healing relationship to promote caritas during a time in life when patients/clients are most vulnerable, either physiologically or psychologically.</para></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0002" role="Heading"><title>Therapeutic Communication</title><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0001" role="Heading"><title>Dysfunction</title><para role="Para">The premise of <emphasis role="bold">dysfunction</emphasis> is the absence of order. Chaos is a distractor. Amidst noise, subtle complaints, frustrations, and anger, persons acting as <emphasis>disruptors</emphasis> within the work environment seek to lie and undermine their fellow workers, often without provocation. Compartmentally, units, departments, schools, and other organizationally defined teams can either thrive, survive, or slowly disintegrate under the weight of denigration perpetuated by persons or a person who bullies.</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0002" role="Heading"><title>A Systemic Problem</title><para role="Para">According to Edmonson and Zelonka (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib04">2019</link></emphasis>), bullying behaviors have been found to exist before nursing school and persist throughout a nurse’s careers. Nurse bullying quickly becomes a systematic problem because financially, organizations are impacted. Patient satisfaction scores are lower (Hospital Consumer Assessment of Healthcare Providers and Systems [HCAPS]) because patients are treated within environments of high nursing stress whereby there may be a higher likelihood of nursing errors, and there is a pattern of nursing turnover. Hence, each time a nurse leaves their position related to bullying, the bottom-line costs for hospitals are impacted. While bullied nurses can be any age, turnover is seen more often within nurses in their first job which is often that of a bedside nurse.</para><para role="Para">Turnover of bedside nurses is of particular concern. The current estimated cost of a nurse leaving the bedside increased by 20.7% and is $56,300.00 per nurse. Statistically, on average, hospitals within the United States are losing $3.9 to $5.8 million dollars annually (Nursing Solutions Inc., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib10">2024</link></emphasis>). If hospitals are able to significantly decrease their nurse turnover, a savings/cost of $262,500 annually could be obtained. Given that it can take 3 months or more to recruit nurses with clinical practice experience, the vacancy for registered nurses is nationally 9.9% and the RN Recruitment Difficulty Index averages a total of 86 days (Nursing Solutions Inc., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib10">2024</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0003" role="Heading"><title>Bullying Manifestation</title><para role="Para">Manifestations of bullying behaviors can be subtle or direct. For example, a bully may lie, attempt to discredit someone through distorting what they say or do, or spread rumors. Other bullying can be based on identity-based hate (e.g., racism, religion, gender, etc.). Bullies may overtly yell at, ignore, or embarrass the person they are targeting as a means to gain power over them. Remember, bullies are often very insecure and fearful of coworkers that are more knowledgeable than themselves, happy, or accomplished in their specialty areas.</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0004" role="Heading"><title>Direct Harm</title><para role="Para">Direct harm in bullying tends to be openly done in the presence of others, openly humiliating someone with their co-workers being present, silencing or pretending the targeted person did not say anything. Hostile and antagonistic body language, blaming and shaming, yelling, punching and pushing, emailing, texting, or writing angry messages are behaviors that are more direct. With direct harm, the bully has reached the point of comfort. Hence the bully’s behavior has gone unchecked or corrected by the organization, so the bully or bullies openly express their dislike of their target(s) without retribution (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib11">2022</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0005" role="Heading"><title>Indirect Harm</title><para role="Para">When a person is indirectly harmed during bullying, persons may experience less than adequate transfer of information from colleagues in order to perform their jobs; shared information with vital gaps, hence, occurs, with the goal of sabotaging. Bullied persons can also experience circumvention of information and spreading of rumors (Edmonson &amp; Zelonka, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib04">2019</link></emphasis>; Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib11">2022</link></emphasis>). Ultimately, the bully or bullies are focused upon the failure of the affected person in their ability to do and successfully complete their work. Within the workplace, an employer that is intuitively tracking these behaviors after an initial incident should involve a human resource representative to investigate all future events to rule out patterns of lying and sabotage. However, in absence of actual disciplinary action of the bully or bullies, once patterns have been identified, behaviors will continue. The affected nurse, if resilient, can with ease, address what they know to be false information. However, not all nurses are comfortable in doing so, and hence, affected nurses may begin to feel helpless and hopeless within the situation.</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0006" role="Heading"><title>Nurse Suicide</title><para role="Para">Historically, the profession of nursing has been wrought with staff division, emotionally embattled nurses, and physically ill nurses because of a long-standing bullying problem within the profession. Suicides committed by nurses who hurt (Davis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib02">2021</link></emphasis>; Lee &amp; Friese, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib06">2021</link></emphasis>; Stephenson, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib12">2018</link></emphasis>) have occurred within the context of nurses being bullied by fellow nurses in the workplace and the day-to-day stress of delivering healthcare to patients in a fast-paced environment. Davidson et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib03">2018</link></emphasis>) in a discussion paper to raise awareness about the problem of <emphasis role="bold">nurse suicides</emphasis> for the National Academies of Medicine shared that there had been minimal tracking of nurse suicides and organizational responses to help nurses in comparison to physicians and other professions (e.g., police officers, educators, firefighters, and military personnel). Davidson et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib03">2018</link></emphasis>) noted that compassion and caring can take a toll on nurses. Ethical issues at work, lateral violence, staffing shortages, moral distress (nurse is prevented from doing what the nurse knows is right to do), blame, medical and medication errors, near misses and omissions in the care of patients/clients, and inappropriate treatment are just a few examples of what practicing nurses must deal with while delivering healthcare. Collective risk factors for nurse suicide include the knowledge of how to use toxic substances and lethal doses of medications, personal and work-related stressors, smoking, depression and undertreatment of depression, and substance abuse (Davidson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib03">2018</link></emphasis>; Lee &amp; Friese, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib06">2021</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">Between the years 2017 and 2018, it is estimated that 729 nurses within the United States ended their lives by suicide (Davis et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib02">2021</link></emphasis>). According to the National Academy of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib07">2019</link></emphasis>), burnout of healthcare clinicians threatens the quality of patient care delivered. Hence it is imperative that health systems’ organizational leadership act to address their workers’ stress. Limited human resources, equitable workload challenges, improvement in documentation and administrative processes, and assignment of non-nursing duties to nursing staff must be readily addressed. The National Academy of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib07">2019</link></emphasis>) recommends that healthcare organizations and systems senior leadership be held accountable for nurses’ safety and partner with nurses to create healthier work environments. Other recommendations to address nurse suicide include the American Rescue Plan Act of 2021 (<emphasis role="ExternalRef"><ulink url="http://congress.gov"><emphasis role="RefSource">Congress.gov</emphasis></ulink></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib01">2021</link></emphasis>–2022) that has allotted monies to promote mental healthcare for healthcare professionals, implementation of the Healer Education Assessment and Referral (HEAR) suicide prevention program in some organizations (Davidson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib03">2018</link></emphasis>), emphasis on self-care (Zhang et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib16">2020</link></emphasis>), and the potential implementation of a socio-ecological framework to decrease nurse suicides at a societal level through policy development, changes in the working environment, and practice changes (Wasserman et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib13">2020</link></emphasis>).</para></sect2><sect2 id="ch0001s0002s0007" role="Heading"><title>Lamenting</title><para role="Para">To <emphasis role="bold">lament</emphasis> is to experience a deep sadness over an event that occurred in one’s life. The death of spouse or child or the loss of something or someone of great significance in one’s life can cause sorrow, grief, and regret. When nurses experience The Hollow, bewilderment as to why the bullying or gaslighting is occurring to them can be a precipitant to their lamenting. As the mind recalls story after story of situations whereby bullying or gaslighting was the theme of conversational content or physical actions directed toward them, nurses begin to feel anxious. Their overwhelming anxiety disturbingly leading to feelings of hopelessness and helplessness as they mentally fight to differentiate what they perceive versus what is actually happening to them.</para><para role="Para">Lamenting actually occurs as a result of the recall of times of peace and happiness in the workplace that is remembered by the affected nurse. The bewilderment, the affected nurse asking themselves, “How and why is this occurring? Why is this happening to me?” Shrouded by either an environment that either supports the nurse(s) with their bullying situation or a workplace that decidedly ignores bullying, choosing to view the nurse or nurses’ situation as an individual problem only and not potentially an organizational issue, The Hollow will either continue to grow or be intervened upon and ended abruptly. Whatever the organization’s decision, human lives are impacted both on the part of the nurse and the patients that the lamenting nurse provides care to as he or she is experiencing workplace bullying. Distracted, unfulfilled, anxious, fearful, worried, and scattered in their ability to thoroughly exercise clinical judgment and critical thinking, nurses affected by The Hollow, although historically good nurses, may not perform well in their delivery of healthcare to the public (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib11">2022</link></emphasis>; NSI, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib08">2018</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib09">2023</link></emphasis>, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib10">2024</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">The healthy side of lamenting is its necessity. Human beings must have periods of grief and sorrow in order to process life events. In absence of the ability to process a harm that is mental, physical, or spiritual, persons are left vulnerable because they are unable to protect themselves from the event occurring again in their lives. Lamenting provides a life lesson. The life lesson of lamenting is that a person or persons can survive difficult situations and do well in their lives. Losses experienced through The Hollow can include self-esteem, insecurity with one’s previously mastered skills, self-hatred, and a general feeling of awkwardness and not belonging. Unfortunately, the latter feelings not only manifest themselves in the workplace environment of origination but also impact the private life of the nurse or nurses affected, hence the risk for the development of mental illness (e.g., depression, anxiety, etc.) and physical illness. Of even more concern, the nurse may have accompanied sleep deprivation, decrease or increase in appetite, and a decrease in the ability to concentrate. Physical and mental vulnerabilities can also increase the potential for the development of suicidal ideation and lead to an actual suicide attempt (Halter, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0001s0005bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para><para role="Para">The result of successful lamenting is the realization that life is filled with imperfection and that we ourselves are imperfect. Because we must daily interact with imperfection, we must learn to be kind to ourselves in every situation. Being kind to ourselves gives us permission to recognize and act on the correction of the negative behaviors of others toward us. We do not have to tolerate the dysfunction of other people in our lives, nor do others have to tolerate our negative behaviors in their lives.</para></sect2></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0003" role="Heading"><title>Wilderness Stories</title><sidebar id="ch0001s0003ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle1"><title>Directions</title><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Wilderness stories are stories told by nurses that have experienced bullying and share how it has impacted their lives. Please read each of the ten short stories and discuss with another person or within a group of peers how each situation may have impacted the lives of the affected nurses. These are hypothetical stories written for the purpose of educating others about the short-term and long-term effects of bullying:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>I could not believe that she thought it was o.k. to yell at me at a staff meeting. My boss said absolutely nothing. It is as if the yelling episode never happened. I cannot understand how being inappropriate in a professional work environment is tolerated.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>I am done with being treated like an ignorant child by my preceptor. My preceptor and I have met four times with the manager. The first time we met with the manager, it was 2 weeks into my 8-week orientation. My preceptor shared with a patient’s wife that she had to watch everything I did to ensure I did not make an error and “kill someone.” I have been a nurse for 10 years. What a ridiculous and extremely rude thing to say. I am done with my preceptor and this place!</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Who would have thought I would be bullied by a 22-year-old with less than 1 year of clinical nursing experience? I am 62 years old and I have a “kid” lying and trying to set me up. Trying to explain this nonsense to a Human Resource representative is even more hilarious. No support, absolutely no support.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>We do not know quite how to react when we observe Mike get teased and belittled by our director. Mike is a really nice guy and a hard worker. I just do not understand why our director is unnecessarily hard on him. Should we come to Mike’s defense? He is starting to look very depressed and tired of the director’s behavior.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>I vomit before and after I have to deal with them. They are like wolves, travelling in a pack. No one takes responsibility for the acknowledgement of the negative behaviors the three of these women bring to the workplace. I don’t know how much longer I will be at this place. And to think, I planned to advance my career and, eventually, retire from this job.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Craig is so comfortable lying. It is as if his defamation of other’s character and stealing of their ideas bring no regret nor discomfort to his consciousness. How can persons affected pretend no damage has been done. How do people sell their own souls and identity to stay in the good graces of a person that has absolutely no respect for them?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Lately, I have been having thoughts of just ending it all. I just cannot take being bullied anymore at work. I am depressed and feel hopeless and helpless.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>I feel paranoid sometimes. Being gaslighted was tough. I just do not trust people and I am not sure if I ever will. Should I see a therapist or counselor? I am not sure how to move forward.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>My stomach hurts and I have a headache. I have always put a job…a career before family and everything else. When you go through harassment in the workplace for nothing you personally did, you question who you are and who you abandoned for a job. Family, friends, a husband, a child…all of these are priceless. To think, I put a job before all that mattered most. The harassment I experienced on the job is proof that a job is never important than those you love.</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Pushed and shoved in silence. A smirk and then laughter. Belittled in front of others. I am much more than how a bully perceives me. I am loved by others and valued. I will move on and be just fine.</para></listitem></orderedlist><figure id="ch0001s0003fg01" role="Figure"><title>Brush in Spring Time</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="Ch0001f01.jpg" width="100%" scalefit="1"/></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0004" role="Heading"><title>Questions to Contemplate: Let’s Get to Work!</title><sidebar id="ch0001s0004ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle1"><title>Directions</title><para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read and discuss the following questions about dysfunction within the profession of nursing. Consider what you can do to help improve work environments for nurses. Contemplate immediate reparative responses that can be made by nurses, professional organizations, and the healthcare systems and organizations which employee nurses:</para><orderedlist><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Why would a profession based on caritas be so stressful?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>How early should nurse bullying be intervened upon?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is there a pattern of bullying within the nursing profession?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Can nurses be given support earlier by their organizations with bullying prevention?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Should nursing leadership be held responsible for knowingly allowing bullying to occur in the workplace?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Should human resources be held accountable if consistent patterns of bullying on a particular clinical unit or other healthcare workplace setting are permitted or not addressed directly at all?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is it possible for nurses to be insulated from factors contributing to nurse suicide?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What other actions could be taken to address nurse suicide?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>Is nurse suicide a public health issue?</para></listitem><listitem role="ListItem"><para>What does it mean to the nursing profession to experience another nursing death by suicide? What are the implications?</para></listitem></orderedlist></sidebar></sect1><sect1 id="ch0001s0005" role="bibliography"><title>References</title><para></para><bibliography id="ch0001s0005bib0001"><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib01">American Rescue Plan Act of 2021, Pub. L. No. H. R. 1319. (2021). Congress.gov. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-bill/1319/text"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.congress.gov/bill/117th-congress/house-bill/1319/text</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib02">Davis, M. A., Cher, B. A. Y, Friese, C. R., Bynum, J. P. W. (2021). Association of US nurse and physician occupation with risk of suicide. JAMA Psychiatry, 78(6):651–658. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2021.0154">https://doi.org/10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2021.0154</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib03">Davidson, J., Mendis, J., Stuck, A. R., De Michele, G., &amp; Zisook, S. (2018). Nurse suicide: Breaking the silence. National Academy of Medicine. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://nam.edu/nurse-suicide-breaking-the-silence/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://nam.edu/nurse-suicide-breaking-the-silence/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib04">Edmonson, C., &amp; Zelonka, C. (2019). Our own worst enemies. The nurse bullying academic. Nursing Administration Quarterly, 43(3), 274–279. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://journals.lww.com/naqjournal/fulltext/2019/07000/our_own_worst_enemies__the_nurse_bullying_epidemic.12.aspx"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://journals.lww.com/naqjournal/fulltext/2019/07000/our_own_worst_enemies__the_nurse_bullying_epidemic.12.aspx</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/NAQ.0000000000000353">https://doi.org/10.1097/NAQ.0000000000000353</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=31162347">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6716575">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib05">Halter, M. J. (2022). Varcarolis’ foundations of psychiatric-mental health nursing: A clinical approach (9th ed.). Elsevier.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib06">Lee, K. A., &amp; Friese, C. R. (2021). Deaths by suicide among nurses: A rapid response call. Journal of Psychosocial Nursing and Mental Health Services, 59(8), 3–4. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3928/02793695-20210625-01">https://doi.org/10.3928/02793695-20210625-01</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.3928/02793695-20210625-01">https://doi.org/10.3928/02793695-20210625-01</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=34343054">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8344804">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib07">National Academy of Sciences Engineering and Medicine. (2019). Taking-action against clinician burnout: A systems approach to professional Well-being. The National Academies Press. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.17226/25521">https://doi.org/10.17226/25521</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.17226/25521">https://doi.org/10.17226/25521</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib08">Nursing Solutions Inc. (2018). 2018 National health care retention &amp; RN staffing report. <bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/files/assets/library/retention-institute/nationalhealthcarernretentionreport2018.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">http://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/files/assets/library/retention-institute/nationalhealthcarernretentionreport2018.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib09">Nursing Solutions Inc. (2023). 2023 National health care retention &amp; RN staffing report. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/Documents/Library/NSI_National_Health_Care_Retention_Report.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/Documents/Library/NSI_National_Health_Care_Retention_Report.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib10">Nursing Solutions Inc. (2024). 2024 NSI national health care retention &amp; RN Staffing Report. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/documents/library/nsi_national_health_care_retention_report.pdf"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.nsinursingsolutions.com/documents/library/nsi_national_health_care_retention_report.pdf</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib11">Praslova, L. N., Carucci, R., &amp; Stokes, C. (2022). How bullying manifests at work—And how to stop it. Harvard Business Review. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib12">Stephenson, J. (2018). Nursing director to meet family of nurse who said she was bullied before taking own life. Nursing Times, 114(8), 131. ISSN: 0954-7762.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib13">Wasserman, D., Iosue, M., Wuestefeld, A., &amp; Carli, V. (2020). Adaptation of evidence-based suicide prevention strategies during and after the COVID-19 pandemic. World Psychiatry: Official Journal of the World Psychiatric Association, 19(3), 294–306. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/wps.20801">https://doi.org/10.1002/wps.20801</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/wps.20801">https://doi.org/10.1002/wps.20801</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib14">Watson, J. (2008). Nursing the philosophy and science of caring (Revised ed.). University Press of Colorado.</bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib15">Watson, J. (2009, Spring). Caring science and human caring theory: Transforming personal and professional practices of nursing and healthcare. Journal of Health and Human Services Administration, 31, 466–482. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19385422/"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/19385422/</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed><bibliomixed id="ch0001s0005bib16">Zhang, X.-J., Song, Y., Jiang, T., Ding, N., &amp; Shi, T.-Y. (2020). Interventions to reduce burnout of physicians and nurses: An overview of systematic reviews and meta-analyses. Medicine, 99(26), e20992. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000020992">https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000020992</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000020992">https://doi.org/10.1097/MD.0000000000020992</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=32590814">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7328917">PubMedCentral</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed></bibliography></sect1></chapter>
