<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0005" label="5">
  <title>5. Unprovoked</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0012">
    <title>5. Unprovoked</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_5">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_5</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0005">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para>
    <para role="keywords">Unprovoked, Harming others, Heal thyself, Moving forward</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0005s0001">
    <title>5. Unprovoked</title>
    <sidebar id="ch0005s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Explain what it means to be involved in an unprovoked situation.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Discuss the effects of harming others, both intentionally and unintentionally.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Determine the potential benefits of healing oneself and discuss if healing oneself is possible.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Discuss how moving forward can bring closure.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0002" role="Heading">
    <title>Unprovoked</title>
    <para role="Para">To be <emphasis role="bold">unprovoked</emphasis> in the workplace setting is to be involved in situations whereby there was seemingly no cause for what reportedly occurred to be validated or be reality-based. Hence, with regard to the bullying experience of The Hollow Theory, the bullied nurse is harassed without identifiable cause. And upon investigation the behaviors demonstrated by the bully or bullies is unjustifiable.</para>
    <para role="Para">It is the unprovoked component of being bullied that confuses persons affected and targeted by the actual act of bullying. For persons experiencing The Hollow, it is the question of “Why this is happening to me?” that is ruminated upon both internally by the conscious and externally, verbally, as the person attempts to explain to others their encounters with the bully or bullies. The latter is why persons who are bullied, regardless of their level of intelligence, years of work experience, or accomplishments, tend to isolate and not share with others that they are being bullied, often waiting until the bullying has impacted their physical and emotional health and well-being.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0003" role="Heading">
    <title>Harming Others</title>
    <para role="Para">Bullying harms others. While the bully or bullies have an intentional plan or purpose in the harming of their target(s), it is the unprovoked component of the bullying process that bewilders the affected person. Bullies are reliant upon their targets’ response of bewilderment because it further arms them with the ability to harass inconspicuously. The <emphasis role="bold">harming of others</emphasis> is perpetuated when the bully or bullies seek to disarm others by verbally or physically targeting them within the work environment.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0004" role="Heading">
    <title>The Bewilderment of Gaslighting</title>
    <para role="Para">The term <emphasis>gaslighting</emphasis> comes from a 1938 play entitled, “Angel Street” that was set in the year 1880 in London. The play was written by the playwright and British novelist, Patrick Hamilton. In the play, a married man uses subtle tricks to make his new wife gradually feel like she is going insane (Hamilton, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib06">1966</link></emphasis>). The namesake of the tormenting trickery used by the spouse originates as he gradually dims the lights in their home that were “gas-fueled,” hence, the origin of the term “gaslighting.” The unsuspecting wife initially notices that the lights in the home have become dim, but as her seemingly innocent and well-intended husband denies that the gas-fueled lights have not dimmed, the wife begins to think she is losing her mind. Ironically, the story takes place on a street called Angel Street, which further alludes to the innocence and trust in angelic heavenly beings. Metaphorically, the person who gaslights is one who appears innocent and caring to others, while those that are being tricked by them are unaware of the gaslighter’s trickery.</para>
    <para role="Para">According to Feilding-Singh and Dmowska (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib04">2022</link></emphasis>), the goal of the gaslighter is to gradually cause the person they are targeting to develop self-doubt. The act of perpetuating self-doubt is implemented by the gaslighter through carefully crafting stories about the person that they are targeting that undermine their skillset and ability to perform their job. For example, a supervisor who is a gaslighter may say to an employee who has been excelling within their position at work, “I was talking to some of your peers and one of them said that your performance on the last project was not up to par like it has been in the past. Is something going on with you at home or work?” The gaslighter’s inquiry about the target’s personal and professional life is inappropriate and has no basis. However, the gaslighter uses this type of inquiry to create doubt and to cause the target to share private information that the gaslighter can strategically use to further undermine the target’s performance at work.</para>
    <para role="Para">The more frequent the incidences of gaslighting, the more the targeted person is psychologically impacted and begins to question their own abilities. However, targeted persons can experience a one-time incident with a gaslighter and be impacted (Johnson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib07">2021</link></emphasis>). The good news is that once the targeted person can recognize that they are being gaslighted, healing can begin.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0005" role="Heading">
    <title>Dominance</title>
    <para role="Para">Dominance over the target is a win for the gaslighter. Gaslighters are believed to diagnostically exhibit the characteristics of a person with narcissistic personality disorder (Boring, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib02">2020</link></emphasis>). The following is the diagnostic criteria for narcissistic personality disorder from the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders Fifth Edition (DSM-5):</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0006" role="Heading">
    <title>Narcissistic Personality Disorder 301.81 (F60.81)</title>
    <para role="Para">A pervasive pattern of grandiosity (in fantasy or behavior), need for admiration, and lack of empathy, beginning by early adulthood and present in a variety of contexts, as indicated by five (or more) of the following:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Has a grandiose sense of self-importance (e.g., exaggerates achievements and talents, expects to be recognized as superior without commensurate achievements).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Is preoccupied with fantasies of unlimited success, power, brilliance, beauty, or ideal love.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Believes that he or she is “special” and unique and can only be understood by, or should associate with, other special or high-status people (or institutions).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Requires excessive admiration.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Has a sense of entitlement (i.e., unreasonable expectations of especially favorable treatment or automatic compliance with his or her expectations).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Is interpersonally exploitative (i.e., takes advantage of others to achieve his or her own ends).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Lacks empathy: is unwilling to recognize or identify with the feelings and needs of others.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Is often envious of others or believes that others are envious of him or her.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Shows arrogant, haughty behaviors or attitudes. (American Psychiatric Association,<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib01">2013</link></emphasis>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0007" role="Heading">
    <title>Gaslighting in the Workplace</title>
    <para role="Para">When gaslighting goes undetected within the workplace, persons that have done nothing wrong, can be labeled and lied about by persons who gaslight. Therefore, it is imperative that leadership within organizations be educated on techniques used by bullies and divisive personalities that are disruptive to the work environment. Persons who gaslight are trying to gain control and manipulate another person for personal gain and perceived power. Characteristically, the gaslighter has low self-esteem and self-worth, and there is an attempt to hide their own insecurities by talking negatively about others. Gaslighters are highly manipulative and have difficulty navigating their personal and workplace roles when they feel they are without power. In absence of their ability to psychologically manipulate others, they themselves experience a heightened anxiety of being discovered of how little they may actually know and how disempowered they truly feel. Gaslighters are in fact victims of their own deception as they reside in a world crafted of their own lies.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0008" role="Heading">
    <title>Heal Thyself</title>
    <para role="Para">The Cambridge Dictionary defines a <emphasis>healer</emphasis> as “a person who has the power to cure ill people without using ordinary medicines: a spiritual healer” and also as “a person or thing that heals: time is a great healer” (Cambridge Dictionary, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib03">2023</link></emphasis>). Traditionally, nursing has had a historical background of religious and spiritual connections. During the pre-Christian era, the care of the ill was associated with the ability to nourish the souls of others with prayer and was a noble act (Timmins &amp; Mc Sherry, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib08">2012</link></emphasis>). The embodiment of the spiritual is how nursing was viewed in Celtic ancient writings, and the nurse was referred to as a “soul friend” to the ill to whom they provided care to, or “anam cara” (Grove &amp; Klauser, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0005s0011bib05">2005</link></emphasis>). Foundationally, nursing is a profession of faith and carries with it the foundational belief that healing is a gift of compassion directed toward others who are in need of nurses’ delivery of physical, emotional, and spiritual healing.</para>
    <para role="Para">Nurses are professional healers. Nurses learn to heal through the recognition of symptomatology associated with different disease processes. However, for nurses when scars turn inward, the nurse as healer experiences emotional wounds that unattended to, manifest as physical and mental illness. To heal thyself is often not possible. Therefore, nurses will require someone to listen, maintaining confidentiality, to their story and situation related to bullying and help them to identify, processes, develop, and plan approaches to heal their pain so that they can move toward action and, ultimately, forgiveness. Because in absence of forgiveness, nurses affected by The Hollow give power to those who bully.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0009" role="Heading">
    <title>Moving Forward</title>
    <para role="Para">The purpose of “moving forward” in name, theme, and goal is to inspire others who have encountered bullying and thrived. Mental health, spiritual wellness, and physical heath are protective factors against bullying. When one maintains a work-life balance, they are already proactive in their understanding of the importance of health maintenance and wellness promotion.</para>
    <para role="Para">The next steps in the acceleration of health and wellness “moving forward” are the following:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Acknowledgment that bullying can be an emotional and physical insult to one’s body and mind.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>The spiritual health of persons who are bullied is challenged when the act of harming another mentally and physically is intentionally ignored by others in an attempt to provide an image of unity and belonging.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Supporting of plans of change at the micro- and macro-system level in promoting nursing wellness and addressing incivility and bullying within the workplace can easily become stagnant when organizations fear a “reveal” of employees sharing their discontentment with the status quo.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem role="ListItem">
        <para>Positive change can occur within any work environment. All that is needed is the empowerment of all nursing staff to correct that which is dysfunctional in environments that have historically tolerated bullying and incivility.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para role="Para">Bullying is a painful, often unprovoked act of treating a person unjustly and without cause. For the bully or bullies, they believe that their intentional actions taken to shame, lie, cause doubt, and physically or emotionally harm their targets are warranted because of their own need to self-protect. Bullies view their targets as a potential or actual threat to the exposure of their own deficits. Hence, when exposed by their targets, bullies may attempt to either increase their attack or retreat in fear. The process of the target making the decision to move forward beyond the experience of the bully or bullies is a conscious one that can only be empowered with a counter move to expose the act of incivility and the perpetrators involved.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0010" role="Heading">
    <title>Summary</title>
    <para role="Para">Moving forward for the nurse affected by The Hollow is the process of exposing the acts of the bully and making the conscious decision to forgive and resume their own lives before the bully existed. The positive event that occurs post the exposure of the bully or bullies and their acts of incivility is that the affected nurse emerges stronger in character, moral clarity, and an undefeatable resolve. The process of moving forward is one of rebuilding.</para>
    <sidebar id="ch0005s0010ad02">
      <title>Activity</title>
      <bridgehead>Adult Drawing for Healing and Clarity of Situation</bridgehead>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Drawing pictures and coloring can be very relaxing and also thought provoking for adults. When a person draws a picture of how they are feeling, of someone close to them, or a picture of their immediate environment, both consciously and unconsciously, the person(s) is sharing how they are feeling about a particular situation and how they perceive what is occurring. Draw a picture that describes your feelings as you are presently experiencing them now and when recalling an event.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of yourself.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a part of your body that you are pleased with.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Write two words that describe what makes you happy. Draw a picture representing the two words.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your family.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your best friend.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of how you feel working as a nurse on a good day.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of how you feel working in another role (e.g., mother, wife, son, brother, daughter, etc.).</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your face as you prepare to go to work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your face upon arrival to work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your face when interacting with patients.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your face and body when interacting with family members.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of your face and body when interacting with your co-workers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of yourself if you have ever experienced bullying.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Draw a picture of yourself free from the hold of The Hollow.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para role="Para">Upon completion of the drawing activity, consider this:</para>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">After completing your drawings, examine them closely.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Are you surprised at how your drawings look?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">What do your drawings reveal about you and your current life situation?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">If there is an area in need of improvement, what will be your next steps?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Identify a person or person (e.g., disclosure to a friend, co-worker, manager, director, spouse, counselor, or therapist) that can help you with you next steps.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0005s0010ad03">
      <title>Activity</title>
      <bridgehead>The Act of Moving Forward</bridgehead>
      <para role="Para">The act of moving forward is an exercise in accepting the past and the future to come, as being negotiable. The negotiability is either positive or negative. The decision to no longer be stagnant but to change one’s position in life warrants that one be presented with options. With this activity, participants will be asked to “move forward” when they perceive that there is no threat to their safety; physically, emotionally, or spiritually.</para>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Moving Forward Scenarios </bridgehead>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>You are invited to meet with a co-work and another peer. No agenda has been provided. Would you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis>? Yes or No. What is the reason for the rationale you provided?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>A colleague during a work-related meeting makes a side comment to another colleague about how you handled a situation. What would you do? Should you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> with initiating a conversation about what was said or ignore the conversation as ridiculous and nonsensible?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>If your story is true, then no one can argue with you about your story not being true. To do the latter means that the person in which you are engaged in a conversation with is lying. What would you do if someone is obviously lying about you in front of others. Do you remain quiet or <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> and address the person or persons engaged in the act of lying?</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>To be kind involves being genuine of heart. Knowingly and respectfully acknowledging one’s truth or the truth of another. How would you <emphasis role="bold">move forward</emphasis> knowing that the standard of organizational acceptance is not being kind nor genuine? Should you consider leaving the organization or help promote change by increasing awareness?</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0005s0011" role="bibliography">
    <title>References</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0005s0011bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib01">American Psychiatric Association. (2013). Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders fifth edition (DSM-5). American Psychiatric Publishing.<bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596">https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib02">Boring, R. L. (2020). Implications of narcissistic personality disorder on organizational resilience. In P. Arezes &amp; R. Boring (Eds.), Advances in safety management and human performance (AHFE 2020. Advances in intelligent systems and computing) (Vol. 1204, pp. 259–266). Springer. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-50946-0_35"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-50946-0_35</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-50946-0_35">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-50946-0_35</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib03">Cambridge Dictionary. (2023). Healer. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/healer"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://dictionary.cambridge.org/us/dictionary/english/healer</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib04">Feilding-Singh, P., &amp; Dmowska, A. (2022). Obstetric gaslighting and the denial of mothers’ realities. Social Science &amp; Medicine, 301. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114938">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.socscimed.2022.114938</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib05">Grove, R. F., &amp; Klauser, H. A. (2005). The American book of the dying: Lessons in healing spiritual pain. Celestial Arts.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib06">Hamilton, P. (1966). Angel street: A Victorian thriller in three acts. Samuel French Inc. Plays.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib07">Johnson, V. E., Nadal, K. L., Gina Sissoko, D. R., &amp; King, R. (2021). “It’s not in your head:” Gaslighting, splaining, victim blaming, and other harmful reactions to microaggressions. Perspectives on Psychological Science: A Journal of the Association of Psychological Science, 16(5), 1024–1036. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916211011963">https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916211011963</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916211011963">https://doi.org/10.1177/17456916211011963</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0005s0011bib08">Timmins, F., &amp; Mc Sherry, W. (2012). Spirituality: The holy grail of contemporary nursing practice. Journal of Nursing Management, 20(8), 951–957. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12038">https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12038</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12038">https://doi.org/10.1111/jonm.12038</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=Retrieve&amp;db=PubMed&amp;dopt=Abstract&amp;list_uids=23151097">PubMed</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
