<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<chapter id="ch0006" label="6">
  <title>6. Shallow</title>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0013">
    <title>6. Shallow</title>
    <para role="ChapterCopyright">© The Author(s), under exclusive license to Springer Nature Switzerland AG 2025</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationAuthorEditorNames">C. Green</para>
    <para role="ContextInformationBookTitles">
      <emphasis role="BookTitle">How Can Nurses Survive Bullying Environments?</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="ChapterDOI">
      <ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_6">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-86617-3_6</ulink>
    </para>
    <para role="AuthorGroup">
      <emphasis role="Author">
        <emphasis role="AuthorName">Cheryl Green</emphasis>
        <superscript>
          <link linkend="ch0006">1</link>
        </superscript>
      </emphasis>
    </para>
    <para role="AffiliationText">Abilene Christian University, Abilene, TX, USA</para>
    <para role="keywords">Shallow, Difficult conversations, Forgiveness</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 role="auto-generated" id="ch0006s0001">
    <title>6. Shallow</title>
    <sidebar id="ch0006s0001ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
      <title>Learning Objectives</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Explain how the perception of feeling unsupported can impact nurses experiencing The Hollow.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Discuss how difficult conversations can facilitate positive change in the work environment.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Discuss how continual exposure to work environments that permit incivility can be emotionally and physically damaging to affected nurses.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0002" role="Heading">
    <title>Shallow</title>
    <para role="Para">The Merriam-Webster Dictionary (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib03">2024</link></emphasis>) defines the word <emphasis role="bold">shallow</emphasis> as breathing with minimal depth, moving minimal air in the lungs; lack of knowledge in feelings, thoughts, and depths; reaching only the easily perceived; having little extension backward or inward; and having no depth, such as shallow water. The absence of depth can coincide with risks of harm. For example, diving into shallow water can lead to bodily harm, and shallow breathing can lead to retention of carbon dioxide. And a person who verbally expresses shallow thoughts and feelings usually has no desire to develop a strong bond to those who they are engaging in conversation with or building a relationship. Shallow communication is superficial.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0003" role="Heading">
    <title>Treading Water</title>
    <para role="Para">Nurses in the midst of a bullying experience can feel as if they are treading water. Nurse leaders are often reluctant themselves in addressing the bullying. The nurse leader may not want to be perceived by their fellow nurse leaders as aligning with a subordinate. Or the nurse leader may not feel comfortable engaging in what they perceive will be difficult conversations around the bullying the affected nurse is experiencing. As a result, the affected nurse may feel unsupported because they have been intentionally silenced by their manager in attempt to avoid conflict with others involved in the bullying process. Additionally, by silencing the affected nurse, the manager avoids the perception by their director, vice president of nursing, or chief nursing officer, of weakness and an inability to effectively manage their unit and staff.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0004" role="Heading">
    <title>Difficult Conversations</title>
    <para role="Para"><emphasis role="bold">Difficult conversations</emphasis> occur when a conscious decision is made by two different parties to engage in resolution to an identified problem. Both parties must be willing to maintain honesty and respectfully acknowledge when they are “wrong” and take feedback to correct their actions. Unwillingness to respectfully listen to one another does not bring about healing, nor repair broken lines of communication.</para>
    <para role="Para">According to Patterson et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib04">2012</link></emphasis>), crucial conversations are necessary when stakes are high. For example, a relationship may be affected, a job loss could occur, a financial transaction may be disrupted, and a business deal upended. Current research supports that when organizations create cultures whereby crucial conversations are embraced, more patient lives are saved within hospitals, financial institutions gain loyal customers and have more financial gains, technology firms can with ease enhance functionalities internationally, and nuclear power plants operate safely (Patterson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib04">2012</link></emphasis>). Crucial conversations will involve high stakes, opposing opinions, and strong emotions.</para>
    <para role="Para">When facing crucial conversations, participatory parties may choose to avoid engaging in an open conversation to address the issue(s) at hand, or engage within the conversation but not explore the issues at all. From a positive productivity perspective, participatory parties can decide to face the issues at hand and work toward resolution. The decision to walk away from crucial conversations can be one that may bring regret or inadvertently aid in the maintenance of cultural dysfunction within an organization. The choice is there and awaiting a healthy and empowering decision by each individual.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0005" role="Heading">
    <title>Hidden Conflict</title>
    <para role="Para">Shallow motives bring about moments of physical and emotional injury, as the affected nurse attempts to navigate their own perceived truth of the bullying experience while maintaining composure as the bully or bullies decidedly choose to lie. An internal conflict is felt as the belly tightens, heart beats quickly, and the body overheats. Our body reacts to the bully’s lies in total disbelief and attempts to reorganize the mind to truly hear and process what has been said. The bully hopes that his or her statements are off putting and uses this strategy as a means to attempt to overpower the other person.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0006" role="Heading">
    <title>The Maintenance of Truth</title>
    <para role="Para">The closure to most dilemmas ends with the disclosure of truth. If the person or persons affected by bullying has done nothing wrong, there is no need to exhaust themselves and place their own mental and physical health at risk if they are being lied about. What does it prove? Speak the truth and move forward. It is then up to the organization in which the employees are employed to thoroughly investigate the transaction. If the organization fails to investigate the allegations, and the bullying worsens, it is then that the affected person’s health is at greater risk, and an employment lawyer may need to be consulted. The employment attorney should be a last resort. If conflicts, both provoked and unprovoked, can be civilly dealt with within the organizational structure via open and honest communication, it is best to do so. Remember, ultimately, those who have a record of historically distorting the truth will eventually be exposed.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0007" role="Heading">
    <title>Overexposed</title>
    <para role="Para">Overexposure to workplaces that ignore bullying can be dangerous to one’s health. When bullying is accepted and ignored, organizations leave themselves open to lawsuits. Nurses are more at risk for physical and mental illness development after days, weeks, months, and years of dealing with toxic workplace interactions. Of concern is that organizations are often well aware that there is a problem with bullying but fear having to change a culture. This can be a large undertaking, and to do so requires the organization to admit to its employees that a problem exists.</para>
    <para role="Para">The public admission of a bullying problem is a brave undertaking which employers believe will leave them legally vulnerable to employees that have had past complaints of experiencing bullying and incivility in the workplace. To the contrary, the admittance of a problem and the resolution to identify and address the problems at hand can also absolve the company of being known for acceptance of “bad” behaviors in the workplace and not responding to employees’ complaints. In essence, proof of attempting to absolve the culture of bullying is better than having not tried to at all.</para>
    <para role="Para">It may bring some comfort to organizations experiencing employee bullying within the workplace that the problem of bullying is international. Germany reports having 17% of their workforce report bullying. In the United States, 30% of the workforce report having experienced bullying; 30% translates to an estimation of 48.6 million working adults. India has an estimated 46% to 55% of workplace bullying (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib05">2022</link></emphasis>).</para>
    <para role="Para">Creating a work environment that not only educates its employees about bullying but discusses the consequences of intentionally physically and mentally harming a fellow employee such as progressive action (verbal and written) discipline that can lead to termination of employment is imperative. Workplaces that demonstrate the valuing of each employee and focus on employee safety are more likely to be healthier places to work. The latter are also workplaces that are less likely to demonize and then ostracize the person reporting having experienced bullying within the organization.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0008" role="Heading">
    <title>Not an Option</title>
    <para role="Para">When does the continued acceptance of bullying workplace behaviors become too extreme? Should it be after an employee is openly verbally accosted in front of their fellow employees? Or a physical assault occurs after numerous reports of witnessed verbal bullying and “light shoves” in the hallway while the bully passes by the affected person. When a person or persons submit a notice of resignation to their employer after weeks, months, or years of experiencing workplace bullying? Or, Perhaps it is when an actual suicide has occurred after the person affected by workplace bullying just could not tolerate another day, hour, minute, or second with being bullied. The affected person in the case of a suicide feels helpless and hopeless after being unheard and ignored by their employer and fellow employees (Howard et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib02">2021</link></emphasis>).</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0009" role="Heading">
    <title>The Workplace</title>
    <para role="Para">Organizational interest in their employees’ well-being has historically been a focus because of increased productivity and decrease of turnover intentions. For organizations, in order to maintain a culture whereby bullying is not acceptable behavior and awareness of the effects of bullying, such as depression, gastrointestinal problems, and suicide exists, employers must be openly willing to discuss observations and reports of bullying by employees without judgment. Raycha and Almoula (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib06">2023</link></emphasis>) studied how organizational cultures are impacted when bullying is allowed to remain without intervention. Productivity and profitability are important elements of success for organizations, but neither can occur when employees are allowed to bully their fellow employees. The mission, vision, and values of the organization are shattered as wounded workers infuse the workplace and bullying behaviors are permitted to proliferate. Ultimately, these organizations will encounter financial problems and difficulty in the achievement and sustainability of success within their industries.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0010" role="Heading">
    <title>Exit, Voice, Loyalty, and Neglect</title>
    <para role="Para">The Exit, Voice, Loyalty, and Neglect (EVLN) Model (Hirshman, <emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib01">1970</link></emphasis>) examines how intent to leave an organization or stay is based upon the organizational culture and how employees take cues from the culture in determining their decisions. Employees who encounter difficult situations (e.g., bullying) within the workplace and desire a change in position may make the decision to either transfer to a different department or resign and <emphasis role="bold">exit</emphasis> the organization. Some employees may choose to <emphasis role="bold">voice</emphasis> their concerns to the organization about dissatisfying situations in the workplace like bullying, while others decide that silence is the only option to survive and remain in their current position. Employees’ <emphasis role="bold">loyalty</emphasis> to their organizations ultimately will drive their decision to resign or remain in workplace situations that may be unhealthy. Lastly, the <emphasis role="bold">neglecting</emphasis> of workplace incidences that are uncivil and result in the continuation of bullying may temporarily lead to employee retention. However, it is the ongoing interface with dysfunctional work environments that will impact productivity and profitability and lead to the decision of employees to decide that in order to maintain physical and mental health, that resignation is their best option.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0011" role="Heading">
    <title>Summary: Depth</title>
    <para role="Para">The unknown depth of dark waters can be unnerving. Of concern, is when someone is in dark waters, the depth cannot be determined and drowning can occur. Nurse-to-nurse bullying and incivility are metaphorically representative of dark waters and the unsafe nature of swimming in potentially dangerous waters. Nurses can drown within workplace environments that are isolating and unsupportive.</para>
    <sidebar id="ch0006s0011ad02">
      <title>Activity</title>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each workplace scenario. Applying Hirshman’s (<emphasis role="CitationRef"><link linkend="ch0006s0012bib01">1970</link></emphasis>) Exit, Voice, Loyalty, and Neglect (EVLN) Model, select which of the four areas fit the best.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Marie felt she had come to a dead end. She had reported her co-worker’s argumentative behaviors in staff meetings several times as a concern. Her co-worker consistently sought ways in which she could interrupt or embarrass Marie whenever she spoke during staff meetings. Marie’s peers would offer support but only at the end of the meeting, walking quietly in her office and closing the door. The manager and peers all seemed afraid of the bully. Marie made an appointment with her manager and entered the meeting with a resignation letter. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Marie’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Bob was angry. He had difficulty hiding his frustration. His face was beet red, and now, his blood pressure had become chronically elevated. Bob was one of those employees who always put his job first and family second. As a senior administrator at work, he had anticipated that when the position of president became available, his education and vast experience at the company meant that he was the ideal candidate. Bob was deeply hurt when his long-term career goal was disrupted and the company hired a person from outside of the state and requested that Bob train the new President. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Bob’s current workplace situation and his reaction to not being promoted? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Sherry was usually silent in team meetings, but when her boss demanded to know if she was up to completing an assignment that she had successfully completed the work for the last 15 years, Sherry was in disbelief. Sherry shared, “I have been at this company for 20 years and worked on this assignment for the last 15 years. I have received numerous awards and accolades for my work. Why am I now being questioned as to my ability to do the work?” <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Sherry’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>Jose frequently communicated his concern that there were problems with a new robotic device used for surgeries in the operating room. The hospital had recently changed vendors. While the cost was substantially lower than the previous vendor, the quality of the product was in question. After communicating his concern to his nurse manager and director, at least six times, Jose became frustrated and decided to say nothing anymore after the nurse manager and director informed him during a meeting that they “Did not appreciate being told (by Jose) how to handle their responsibilities.” As a result, Jose isolated himself and chose to use silence as a means to cope with being unheard and, in his perception, disrespected. Three months after the new robotic device was introduced, the device malfunctioned during a procedure causing significant burns to a patient and nurse. Jose decided to report his prior complaints to his nurse manager and director to the chief nursing officer and vice president of operations. After his report, he received minimal communication or support. Jose then documented his concerns and shared them with the Department of Public Health (DPH) and the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA). An investigation is currently in process regarding Jose’s shared concerns about device safety. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Jose’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Answers </bridgehead>
      <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Question 1: (a); Exit</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Question 2: (g); Loyalty</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Question 3: (j); Voice</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para role="Para">Question 4: (d); Neglect</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sidebar>
    <sidebar id="ch0006s0011ad03">
      <title>Activity</title>
      <bridgehead>Depth or No Depth: Shallow</bridgehead>
      <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
      <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each statement and identify whether the statement has depth or no depth (is shallow). Circle depth or no depth after each statement.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>1. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth.</emphasis> “I am not sure just how smart she really is, but I do know that I have a lot more know how.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>2. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “I like to listen to him. He offers wisdom and insight.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>3. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “We can solve this problem together.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>4. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “We should pull together and see if we can take over the situation. Autonomy is not needed in this situation. Who cares about what they think.”</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem role="ListItem">
          <para>5. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “If we work as a team, we can succeed together.”</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sidebar>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="ch0006s0012" role="bibliography">
    <title>References</title>
    <para/>
    <bibliography id="ch0006s0012bib0001">
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib01">Hirschman, A. O. (1970). Exit, voice, and loyalty: Responses to decline in firms, organizations, and states. Harvard University Press.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib02">Howard, M. C., Follmer, K. B., Smith, M. B., Tucker, R. P., &amp; Van Zandt, E. C. (2021). Work and suicide: An interdisciplinary systematic literature review. Journal of Organizational Behavior, 43(2), 260–285. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/job.2519">https://doi.org/10.1002/job.2519</ulink></bibliomisc><bibliomisc><ulink url="https://doi.org/10.1002/job.2519">https://doi.org/10.1002/job.2519</ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib03">Merriam-Webster Dictionary. (2024). Shallow. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/shallow"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/shallow</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib04">Patterson, K., Grenny, J., Mc Millan, R., &amp; Switzler, A. (2012). Crucial conversations: Tools for talking when stakes are high. Mc Graw Hill.</bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib05">Praslova, L. N., Carucci, R., &amp; Stokes, C. (2022). How bullying manifests at work—And how to stop it. Harvard Business Review. <bibliomisc><ulink url="https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it"><emphasis role="RefSource">https://hbr.org/2022/11/how-bullying-manifests-at-work-and-how-to-stop-it</emphasis></ulink></bibliomisc></bibliomixed>
      <bibliomixed id="ch0006s0012bib06">Raycha, B. P., &amp; Almoula, T. S. (2023). Sustaining organizational culture amid workplace bullying: A review of employee responses using EVLN model. IUP Journal of Organizational Behavior, 22(3), 87–109.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
