<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0002s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>What Is The Hollow Theory?</title>
         <para role="Para">The <emphasis role="bold">Hollow Theory</emphasis> is the manifestation of emotional and physical symptomatology related to stress that nurses encounter in workplace settings whereby bullying and incivility are permitted to flourish unabated. Feelings associated with The Hollow include sadness, embittered, feeling hurt, and misunderstood by others. Additionally, affected persons perseverate on incidences of negative behaviors experienced by them from the perpetrator of the act(s) of bullying. Sustained, persons experiencing The Hollow can become physically and mentally ill. Lack of energy, focus, and enthusiasm emerge as part of the perseveration component of The Hollow, whereby affected persons play and replay incidences of bullying. For nurses, and other affected persons, the replaying of incidences of bullying in their minds makes them feel vulnerable, frustrated, and anxious. Accompanied by intermittent tearfulness, productivity in the workplace can ultimately be impacted (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link>
            </emphasis>; Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib02">2020</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0002s0003ad02" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle3">
            <title>Nursing Profession Nursing is a profession whereby the ability to think analytically, think critically, and exercise clinical judgment in the care of acute and chronically ill patients is a daily expectation. For nurses who experience The Hollow, their ability to concentrate can be affected. Hence, patient safety and the quality in the delivery of nursing care may be compromised.</title>
            <para role="Para">Nurses that are impacted by The Hollow may make the decision to seek mediation from a nurse manager or a Human Resources representative. Counseling support can be beneficial in helping nurses cope with their anxiety, worry, and perseveration on recalled events of bullying. Counseling can be accessed through the Employee Assistance Program (EAP) through their employer or nurses may seek a private therapist. Licensed mental health professionals can be helpful in helping affected nurses process their bullying experience and maintain their emotional health as affected nurses decide on their next actions in dealing with their unhealthy work situation.</para>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
