<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0005s0006" role="Heading">
         <title>Narcissistic Personality Disorder 301.81 (F60.81)</title>
         <para role="Para">A pervasive pattern of grandiosity (in fantasy or behavior), need for admiration, and lack of empathy, beginning by early adulthood and present in a variety of contexts, as indicated by five (or more) of the following:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Has a grandiose sense of self-importance (e.g., exaggerates achievements and talents, expects to be recognized as superior without commensurate achievements).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Is preoccupied with fantasies of unlimited success, power, brilliance, beauty, or ideal love.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Believes that he or she is “special” and unique and can only be understood by, or should associate with, other special or high-status people (or institutions).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Requires excessive admiration.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Has a sense of entitlement (i.e., unreasonable expectations of especially favorable treatment or automatic compliance with his or her expectations).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Is interpersonally exploitative (i.e., takes advantage of others to achieve his or her own ends).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Lacks empathy: is unwilling to recognize or identify with the feelings and needs of others.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Is often envious of others or believes that others are envious of him or her.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Shows arrogant, haughty behaviors or attitudes. (American Psychiatric Association,<emphasis role="CitationRef">
                     <link linkend="ch0005s0011bib01">2013</link>
                  </emphasis>)</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
      </sect1>
      
