<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0008s0007" role="Heading">
         <title>The Emotional Voice</title>
         <para role="Para">The emotional voice (EV) is either a voice of reason and sound rationale or of confusion and intentionally remiss of truth versus evil. Be it the voice of a co-worker, boss, supervisor, president, chief officer, manager, a family member, close friend, spouse, or significant other, the speech with emotional expressions and vocalizations (Pell et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib10">2022</link>
            </emphasis>) brings context to the communication being shared between people. For example, if a person is raising the tone of their voice and crying uncontrollably, they may be perceived as being weak and vulnerable by onlookers. The face of the crying person is sad and remorseful and can appear indecisive.</para>
         <para role="Para">Within the context of bullying and persons experiencing The Hollow, the person who bullies will use their observation of EV to determine how, when, and what words and situations they can use to manipulate the person or persons they are targeting. According to Giordano et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib07">2021</link>
            </emphasis>), affective science theories have examined continuous dimensional attributes such as negative vocal emotions and intense vocalizations and perceptions of emotional stimuli such as a voice that sounds angry. Perceptions of emotions are not always based on reality. Emotional perceptions observed or heard by different persons may produce varied thoughts of personal threat—harm to self or harm to others.</para>
         <para role="Para">An example of the perception of the emotional voice as angry has been linked to different people groups. For example, some ethnic groups have been perceived to be louder or more emotional than others (Cowen et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib06">2019</link>
            </emphasis>). The angry Black woman or the loud Italian. While these perceptions are not 100% accurate, they breed racism and misunderstanding. While, acoustically, there are some variations among different people from varied cultural backgrounds, this does not account for individual personalities and life experiences.</para>
      </sect1>
      
