<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0009s0006" role="Heading">
         <title>Workplace Norms</title>
         <para role="Para">The Hollow challenges workplace norms that perpetuate self-destruction and the destruction of others. The nurturing workplace is one that seeks to resolve conflict, bring forth solutions, and sustain healthy work environments. Workplace norms that set forth the expectation of gratitude, supporting one another, and the importance of truth-telling are not representative of an idealistic Utopia but can easily be made a reality. Examples of workplace norms include the following:</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkBullet">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Zero tolerance for defamation of character in writing or orally.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Affected parties and non-affected parties of bullying are provided the opportunity to confidentially express their experiences working within a toxic work environment.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Ambiguous platitudes of others’ character are thoroughly investigated to substantiate accuracy.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Patterns of possible discrimination are investigated thoroughly by the organization.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Annually, classes are provided on bullying prevention and reporting of toxic workplace experiences at identified system levels; employees to managers to directors to administrators and administrative teams and board members are treated as equal occurrences by the organizations, because all employees and persons that work, receive care, or interface with the organization have value.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Progressive disciplinary action will be taken against repeat offenders and will include termination if no change in behaviors or actions occurs.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">Policies are reviewed annually to determine if an update is required for continual support and protection of all employees against The Hollow.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">By upholding workplace norms, employees and employers have a contractual dialogue and agreement to maintain healthy workplace environments.</para>
      </sect1>
      
