<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0009s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>Simplifying Life</title>
         <para role="Para">The <emphasis role="bold">simplification of one’s life involves the recognition of the brevity of life and that the circumstantiality of negative behaviors and outcomes persist for a season only</emphasis>. In other words, change, no matter how difficult the situation, can occur. It is the realization that it is the moment-to-moment glimpses of peace and tranquility that can bring about hope for the future.</para>
         <para role="Para">Below are ten tips for simplifying one’s life:</para>
         <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Kiss a person you love each day and tell them you appreciate them.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Make healthy food selections to nourish your body and mind, and prepare your body to conquer stress and disease.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Remove yourself from toxic situations both at work and at home. If a person is physically or verbally abusive toward you, even if you love the person, give yourself permission to set limits and depart from the situation.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Take short vacations to regroup throughout the year and designate time for a longer vacation during the year.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Avoid patterns of volatile arguments from persons who are preoccupied with their own emotions and peace, and not yours.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Exercise daily. Even a short walk around the block or in nature, lifting weights, or stretching can help build balance and strength.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Have faith that you are not alone in this world or universe. Explore spirituality and your belief in God.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Understand that your beauty is both inward and outward. If you are content with a new hairstyle or outfit and others do not like your outfit or hairstyle, own what you like and love it. Consciously decide to just be you.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Leave work on time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem role="ListItem">
               <para>Let no one define your worth both at work or home.</para>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>
         <para role="Para">While this is by no means an exhaustive list of ways to simplify one’s life, it is a start. The tips are free and most can be completed with minimal to no monetary amounts. Remember, taking a vacation at home with time off from work can be gratifying. Or taking a day off to explore the beach or experiment with new hairstyles or clothing or obtaining a massage can be relaxing. The key is to find something that is relaxing and people who bring “life to your life” through positivity and genuine care that is unconditional.</para>
      </sect1>
      
