<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0008s0008" role="Heading">
         <title>Regret in the Workplace: Why Is This Unhealthy Behavior Tolerated Anyway</title>
         <para role="Para">Unhealthy workplaces are unfortunately a common occurrence. A workplace survey taken by the American Psychological Association entitled <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib03">2024</link>
            </emphasis>
            <emphasis>Work in America Survey</emphasis>, noted that 59% of employees think that their employers believe their workplace to be healthier than it actually is in reality. The APA survey found that 39% of employees believe that if they shared with their employer that they were experiencing a mental health condition, this would not have a positive impact on their career.</para>
         <para role="Para">Resignations can occur in the workplace for a variety of reasons including that of employee relocation, corporate restructuring, job instability, promotion to a higher-level position, or general unhappiness with the type of work the employee is doing. Sull et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib12">2022</link>
            </emphasis>) in an article written within the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) Sloan Management Review implemented research that investigated why people leave their jobs and analyzed over 170 organizational cultural issues that can impact employee attrition. Sull et al.’s (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib12">2022</link>
            </emphasis>) research occurred during the months of April through September 2021, during the global pandemic of the coronavirus 2019 (COVID-19). Culture 500 companies were included in the study. Culture 500 companies are companies that excel in these nine areas: performance, innovation, respect, integrity, customer orientation, agility, diversity, and collaboration (Sull &amp; Sull, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0008s0010bib11">2020</link>
            </emphasis>). The five top predictors of attrition identified were:</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Poor response to COVID-19:</emphasis> 1.8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Failure to recognize employee performance</emphasis>: 2.9</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">High levels of innovation</emphasis>: 3.2</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Job insecurity and reorganization</emphasis>: 3.5</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Toxic corporate culture</emphasis>: 10.4</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">Interestingly, despite having otherwise healthy cultures, these top-performing Culture 500 companies shared in common the existence of toxic corporate cultures. Hence, toxic work environments can exist anywhere and are by no means a reflection of company failure. Instead, companies can take the approach of maintaining or establishing healthy work environments, by acknowledging the need for their existence and then actively and unashamedly, pursuing change.</para>
      </sect1>
      
