<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0001s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>Wilderness Stories</title>
         <sidebar id="ch0001s0003ad01" role="FormalPara FormalParaRenderingStyle1">
            <title>Directions</title>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Wilderness stories are stories told by nurses that have experienced bullying and share how it has impacted their lives. Please read each of the ten short stories and discuss with another person or within a group of peers how each situation may have impacted the lives of the affected nurses. These are hypothetical stories written for the purpose of educating others about the short-term and long-term effects of bullying:</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>I could not believe that she thought it was o.k. to yell at me at a staff meeting. My boss said absolutely nothing. It is as if the yelling episode never happened. I cannot understand how being inappropriate in a professional work environment is tolerated.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>I am done with being treated like an ignorant child by my preceptor. My preceptor and I have met four times with the manager. The first time we met with the manager, it was 2 weeks into my 8-week orientation. My preceptor shared with a patient’s wife that she had to watch everything I did to ensure I did not make an error and “kill someone.” I have been a nurse for 10 years. What a ridiculous and extremely rude thing to say. I am done with my preceptor and this place!</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Who would have thought I would be bullied by a 22-year-old with less than 1 year of clinical nursing experience? I am 62 years old and I have a “kid” lying and trying to set me up. Trying to explain this nonsense to a Human Resource representative is even more hilarious. No support, absolutely no support.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>We do not know quite how to react when we observe Mike get teased and belittled by our director. Mike is a really nice guy and a hard worker. I just do not understand why our director is unnecessarily hard on him. Should we come to Mike’s defense? He is starting to look very depressed and tired of the director’s behavior.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>I vomit before and after I have to deal with them. They are like wolves, travelling in a pack. No one takes responsibility for the acknowledgement of the negative behaviors the three of these women bring to the workplace. I don’t know how much longer I will be at this place. And to think, I planned to advance my career and, eventually, retire from this job.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Craig is so comfortable lying. It is as if his defamation of other’s character and stealing of their ideas bring no regret nor discomfort to his consciousness. How can persons affected pretend no damage has been done. How do people sell their own souls and identity to stay in the good graces of a person that has absolutely no respect for them?</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Lately, I have been having thoughts of just ending it all. I just cannot take being bullied anymore at work. I am depressed and feel hopeless and helpless.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>I feel paranoid sometimes. Being gaslighted was tough. I just do not trust people and I am not sure if I ever will. Should I see a therapist or counselor? I am not sure how to move forward.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>My stomach hurts and I have a headache. I have always put a job…a career before family and everything else. When you go through harassment in the workplace for nothing you personally did, you question who you are and who you abandoned for a job. Family, friends, a husband, a child…all of these are priceless. To think, I put a job before all that mattered most. The harassment I experienced on the job is proof that a job is never important than those you love.</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Pushed and shoved in silence. A smirk and then laughter. Belittled in front of others. I am much more than how a bully perceives me. I am loved by others and valued. I will move on and be just fine.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <figure float="0" id="ch0001s0003fg01" role="Figure">
               <title>Brush in Spring Time</title>
               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata fileref="Ch0001f01.jpg" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
