<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0004" role="Heading">
         <title>Difficult Conversations</title>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Difficult conversations</emphasis> occur when a conscious decision is made by two different parties to engage in resolution to an identified problem. Both parties must be willing to maintain honesty and respectfully acknowledge when they are “wrong” and take feedback to correct their actions. Unwillingness to respectfully listen to one another does not bring about healing, nor repair broken lines of communication.</para>
         <para role="Para">According to Patterson et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0006s0012bib04">2012</link>
            </emphasis>), crucial conversations are necessary when stakes are high. For example, a relationship may be affected, a job loss could occur, a financial transaction may be disrupted, and a business deal upended. Current research supports that when organizations create cultures whereby crucial conversations are embraced, more patient lives are saved within hospitals, financial institutions gain loyal customers and have more financial gains, technology firms can with ease enhance functionalities internationally, and nuclear power plants operate safely (Patterson et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0006s0012bib04">2012</link>
            </emphasis>). Crucial conversations will involve high stakes, opposing opinions, and strong emotions.</para>
         <para role="Para">When facing crucial conversations, participatory parties may choose to avoid engaging in an open conversation to address the issue(s) at hand, or engage within the conversation but not explore the issues at all. From a positive productivity perspective, participatory parties can decide to face the issues at hand and work toward resolution. The decision to walk away from crucial conversations can be one that may bring regret or inadvertently aid in the maintenance of cultural dysfunction within an organization. The choice is there and awaiting a healthy and empowering decision by each individual.</para>
      </sect1>
      
