<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0002s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0001" role="Heading">
            <title>Bullying Characteristics</title>
            <para role="Para">
               <emphasis role="bold">Bullying</emphasis> is the action(s) taken by a person or group of people toward another person(s) with the intent of producing physical or emotional harm. In the study of different ways that nurses bully one another, the literature identifies behaviors such as cyberbullying (Park &amp; Choi, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib04">2019</link>
               </emphasis>), with bullying occurring on Internet platforms. Additionally, nurse-to-nurse bullying can consist of mobbing (groups of individuals who are jealous of another person’s skill level in the workplace bully and attempt to intimidate the person; Valclavikova &amp; Kozakova, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib08">2022</link>
               </emphasis>), rudeness, lying, gossip, singling out (not being invited to work events fellow employees are all participating within), attempting to attack one’s character, name-calling, sabotaging of another’s work, and joy-stealing (Heinrich, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib03">2007</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
            <sect3 id="ch0002s0002s0001s01" role="Heading">
               <title>Rude Boy, Rude Girl</title>
               <para role="Para">In the West Indian culture, a “rude boy or rude girl” was someone within the subculture that was involved in gangster activities or spent time on street corners attempting to make a living, as they were unable to secure work. The rude boy and rude girl were usually unemployed and had difficulty surviving because of their financial and social isolation. Historically, the terms rude boy and rude girl originated in shanty towns within the West Indies. Shanty towns are lower-income areas on the island (The Guardian, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                     <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib06">2014</link>
                  </emphasis>; Underground, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                     <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib07">2021</link>
                  </emphasis>).</para>
               <para role="Para">Changes in cultures arise in difficult life situations. In organizations, organizational cultures can shift with changes in employees that bring either negative or positive behaviors to the workplace based upon their own life experiences. Rude boys and rude girls were in fact poor persons who had difficulty finding employment during the 1960s. However, with pride intact, they dressed nicely and moved in the music scene but yet maintained a gangster element.</para>
               <para role="Para">With regard to “The Hollow,” the bully or bullies inflate their own value due to their own insecurities that they make a distinct point of hiding from others. Instead, the bully or bullies project their own frustrations with themselves and their life situations on others. Like the rude boy or rude girl, the bully emerges from complicated life circumstances but makes the wrong decisions in how they view and interact with others who they interact with in “their world” (the world of the bully).</para>
            </sect3>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0002" role="Heading">
            <title>Bullying Target Types</title>
            <para role="Para">There are approximately four bullying target types. The bullying target types include <emphasis>downward, horizontal, upward, and mixed</emphasis>. Downward bullying involves persons in organizational leadership positions whereby they directly supervise and have employees to whom they provide oversight of their work. Bullying that occurs horizontally is lateral, and typically involves coworkers or peers. Upward bullying within the workplace involves subordinates, while mixed bullying usually consists of a workplace clique comprised of subordinates and supervisors. With mixed bullying, the bully or bullies approach their targets directionally, using any of the targeting types of bullying (Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
         </sect2>
         <sect2 id="ch0002s0002s0003" role="Heading">
            <title>Personal Losses Endured by Bullied Persons</title>
            <para role="Para">The losses that persons affected by bully endure can be devastating to their mental and physical health. All areas of their lives are affected. Psychologically, persons may experience posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), loss of confidence, nightmares, anxiety, suicidal ideation, insomnia, and depression. Persons may experience a decline in their physical health and have several different physiological problems such as gastrointestinal issues, palpitations, or severe headaches. Additionally, persons with physical health changes may experience burnout and disability with worsening illnesses associated with stress such as an elevated blood pressure or the overuse of drugs or alcohol to self-medicate their trauma (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link>
               </emphasis>; Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
            <para role="Para">Socially, persons affected by bullying may lose their professional networks as bullies lie and attempt to attack their character. Friendships are impacted and some persons may experience a loss in their reputation. The person affected by bullying may decide to leave their job, and income or promotion may be given up in order to maintain physical and mental health (Green, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib01">2019</link>
               </emphasis>; Praslova et al., <emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0002s0006bib05">2022</link>
               </emphasis>).</para>
         </sect2>
      </sect1>
      
