<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0006s0011" role="Heading">
         <title>Summary: Depth</title>
         <para role="Para">The unknown depth of dark waters can be unnerving. Of concern, is when someone is in dark waters, the depth cannot be determined and drowning can occur. Nurse-to-nurse bullying and incivility are metaphorically representative of dark waters and the unsafe nature of swimming in potentially dangerous waters. Nurses can drown within workplace environments that are isolating and unsupportive.</para>
         <sidebar id="ch0006s0011ad02">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each workplace scenario. Applying Hirshman’s (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
                  <link linkend="ch0006s0012bib01">1970</link>
               </emphasis>) Exit, Voice, Loyalty, and Neglect (EVLN) Model, select which of the four areas fit the best.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Marie felt she had come to a dead end. She had reported her co-worker’s argumentative behaviors in staff meetings several times as a concern. Her co-worker consistently sought ways in which she could interrupt or embarrass Marie whenever she spoke during staff meetings. Marie’s peers would offer support but only at the end of the meeting, walking quietly in her office and closing the door. The manager and peers all seemed afraid of the bully. Marie made an appointment with her manager and entered the meeting with a resignation letter. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Marie’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Bob was angry. He had difficulty hiding his frustration. His face was beet red, and now, his blood pressure had become chronically elevated. Bob was one of those employees who always put his job first and family second. As a senior administrator at work, he had anticipated that when the position of president became available, his education and vast experience at the company meant that he was the ideal candidate. Bob was deeply hurt when his long-term career goal was disrupted and the company hired a person from outside of the state and requested that Bob train the new President. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Bob’s current workplace situation and his reaction to not being promoted? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Sherry was usually silent in team meetings, but when her boss demanded to know if she was up to completing an assignment that she had successfully completed the work for the last 15 years, Sherry was in disbelief. Sherry shared, “I have been at this company for 20 years and worked on this assignment for the last 15 years. I have received numerous awards and accolades for my work. Why am I now being questioned as to my ability to do the work?” <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Sherry’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>Jose frequently communicated his concern that there were problems with a new robotic device used for surgeries in the operating room. The hospital had recently changed vendors. While the cost was substantially lower than the previous vendor, the quality of the product was in question. After communicating his concern to his nurse manager and director, at least six times, Jose became frustrated and decided to say nothing anymore after the nurse manager and director informed him during a meeting that they “Did not appreciate being told (by Jose) how to handle their responsibilities.” As a result, Jose isolated himself and chose to use silence as a means to cope with being unheard and, in his perception, disrespected. Three months after the new robotic device was introduced, the device malfunctioned during a procedure causing significant burns to a patient and nurse. Jose decided to report his prior complaints to his nurse manager and director to the chief nursing officer and vice president of operations. After his report, he received minimal communication or support. Jose then documented his concerns and shared them with the Department of Public Health (DPH) and the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA). An investigation is currently in process regarding Jose’s shared concerns about device safety. <emphasis role="bold">Question:</emphasis> Which of the four EVLN Model selections best fit Jose’s current workplace situation? <emphasis role="bold">Discuss the progression of the situation and the eventual outcome.</emphasis>
                  </para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Answers </bridgehead>
            <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Question 1: (a); Exit</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Question 2: (g); Loyalty</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Question 3: (j); Voice</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem>
                  <para role="Para">Question 4: (d); Neglect</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
         </sidebar>
         <sidebar id="ch0006s0011ad03">
            <title>Activity</title>
            <bridgehead>Depth or No Depth: Shallow</bridgehead>
            <bridgehead role="Heading"> Directions </bridgehead>
            <para role="Para FirstParaInFormalPara">Read each statement and identify whether the statement has depth or no depth (is shallow). Circle depth or no depth after each statement.</para>
            <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore">
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>1. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth.</emphasis> “I am not sure just how smart she really is, but I do know that I have a lot more know how.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>2. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “I like to listen to him. He offers wisdom and insight.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>3. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “We can solve this problem together.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>4. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “We should pull together and see if we can take over the situation. Autonomy is not needed in this situation. Who cares about what they think.”</para>
               </listitem>
               <listitem role="ListItem">
                  <para>5. <emphasis role="bold">Circle Depth or No Depth</emphasis>. “If we work as a team, we can succeed together.”</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </sidebar>
      </sect1>
      
