<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0003s0011" role="Heading">
         <title>Incivility</title>
         <para role="Para">Uncivil conduct in the academic and workplace environments occurs when employees experience the negative behaviors of a bully or group of bullies. The bully or group of bullies may be a co-worker, supervisor, administrator, or an employee at any level within the hierarchy of the organization. The uncivil conduct manifests itself as incivility. <emphasis role="bold">Incivility</emphasis> is demonstrated by discourteousness, rude behaviors directed at others for the primary purpose of humiliation and disruption of a person or persons’ lives. According to Einarsen et al. (<emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0003s0013bib02">2009</link>
            </emphasis>) person-related incivility, physical intimidation, and work-related incivility are the three most common types of incivility. The complexity of incivility in its manifestation of lying, gossiping, belittlement, gaslighting, intimidation, and many other negative manipulative behaviors is that unaddressed, an unhealthy environment is left to proliferate. Hence, bullying worsens, and affected and unaffected bystanders who witness the incivility feel unsupported and vulnerable.</para>
         <para role="Para">
            <emphasis role="bold">Unaffected bystander vulnerability</emphasis> in witnessed incivility is the result of persons who witness co-worker(s) (or fellow student(s)) being bullied and consciously decide not to intervene for fear of becoming a victim of the bully or bullies themselves. The unaffected bystander’s fear leads them to deny the existence of the occurrence(s) of incivility though witnessed by them. As a result, unaffected bystanders reject or avoid the person or persons being bullied. The unaffected bystander may also deny the existence of bullying behaviors actually occurring to managers, administrators, and Human Resource Department representatives. The sole purpose of the behavior of the unaffected bystander is self-protection. The unaffected bystander is afraid of becoming a victim themselves, of the bully or bullies.</para>
      </sect1>
      
