<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0003s0002" role="Heading">
         <title>Introduction</title>
         <para role="Para">Dysfunction is defined two ways by the Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary: as an actual impairment in abnormal functioning and a person or persons unhealthy interaction(s) within a group or interpersonal behavior(s) (Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0003s0013bib06">2024</link>
            </emphasis>). When bullying is ignored within the workplace environment, a healthy environment of collegiality and mutual respect cannot be maintained. Under the hidden guise of smiles at a team meeting lie hidden inappropriate temperaments, fabrication of information, and low-level sarcasm. The response of the closed-off and dysfunctional team dynamic is silence. An occasional question that may challenge the abnormal is met with dismissal by the bully or bullies within the group.</para>
         <para role="Para">Workplace dysfunction is able to permeate workplaces when leadership is afraid or consciously decides not to address their bullying problem. Unfortunately, organizations will be impacted by the bullying via turnover intentions, reduced productivity, and lawsuits. Employees can be proactive in the promotion of change, but many in the protection of their own health and wellness make the healthy decision to leave their dysfunctional workplaces.</para>
         <para role="Para">This dysfunction within workplace teams does not happen overnight but has been sustained for years to decades because anyone who challenges the dysfunction is met with actual roadblocks occurring within multiple levels within the organization. Interestingly enough, some workplaces choose to intentionally maintain dysfunction because it does not have to make progressive changes for its customers or workers. Of concern is that this level of dysfunction in healthcare environments can lead to patients dying and no one taking accountability as families mourn and healthcare workers with a conscious who care about positive and progressive change, leave their jobs. Hence, the cycle continues.</para>
         <para role="Para">Dysfunctional units, divisions, schools, and departments can exist in any workplace environment. Dysfunction is the lived experience of confusion, disruption, corruption, lies, thievery, and selective self-righteousness that seeks to destroy one, a few, or many for the sole purpose of gaining power. Hence, when dysfunction arises in workplaces, the only solution to end the dysfunction is to expose it and those that perpetrate its delusion. Dysfunction will only persist to exist when ignored and accepted as being a reality, and not fallacy.</para>
      </sect1>
      
