<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<sect1 id="ch0007s0003" role="Heading">
         <title>Forgiveness</title>
         <para role="Para">Forgiveness is the only means by which the mental replay of the traumatizing event can be redefined in the mind of persons affected by The Hollow. While the ability for a human being to forget traumatic events may not always occur, the pain generated from emotionally laden experiences can cause persons with The Hollow, to feel empty, unloved, not cared for, and isolated. These false narratives unaddressed by counseling and support both inside and outside the work environment, can lead to disturbances in mental health.</para>
         <para role="Para">The American Psychological Association (APA) defines <emphasis role="bold">forgiveness</emphasis> as the decision to willfully put aside resentment toward someone who has been hurtful, harmed you, been unfair, or wronged you (APA, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib03">2024</link>
            </emphasis>). The act of forgiveness is transformative. In order to fully forgive another person that has harmed you, resentment is no longer the focus nor is anger. The person who forgives exhibits generosity and compassion toward the person who harmed them (APA, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib03">2024</link>
            </emphasis>). While not easily obtained, forgiveness releases the wronged person from the restrictive bondage of anger and hatred toward the person that harmed them and allows them to move forward in their lives toward happiness and positive productivity.</para>
         <para role="Para">From a scriptural perspective, the forgiveness of others is healing. Below are some scriptural references about forgiving others (Holy Bible, New International Version, <emphasis role="CitationRef">
               <link linkend="ch0007s0008bib12">1984</link>
            </emphasis>).</para>
         <itemizedlist role="UnorderedListMarkNone">
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">2 Corinthians 2: 7–8.</emphasis> Now, instead, you ought to forgive and comfort him, so that he will not be overwhelmed by excessive sorrow. I urge you, therefore, to reaffirm your love for him.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Matthew 6:12.</emphasis> Forgive us our debts, as we also have forgiven our debtors.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Ephesians 4:31–32.</emphasis> Get rid of all bitterness, rage and anger, brawling and slander, along with every form of malice. Be kind and compassionate to one another, forgiving each other, just as in Christ God forgive you.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Luke 17: 3–4</emphasis> If your brother sins, rebuke him, and if he repents, forgive him. If he sins against you seven times in a day, and seven times comes back to you and says, “I repent, forgive him.”</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para role="Para">
                  <emphasis role="bold">Matthew 6:14–15.</emphasis> If you forgive men when they sin against you, your heavenly Father will also forgive you. But if you do not forgive men their sins, your Father will not forgive your sins.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para role="Para">Being bullied is difficult. The affected person feels that they have literally loss control of their own lives and the outcome of their future selves. However, the latter is a lie of which the bully or bullies wish to bestow or feed to the mind of the person(s) they are bulling to gain control. Power is a perception only, and not all perceptions are based on reality. For the person experiencing The Hollow, forgiveness can be their greatest asset in terms of self-protection against incivility and bullying. Rationally, the conscious decision to forgive persons who have wronged you releases you from their perceived power to enter a new journey and adventure in your life whereby the wrong behaviors that were used against you are subdued and rendered useless. You are free!</para>
      </sect1>
      
